<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
 <idno>011-02</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">Blake</hi>: AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>[Contributors]</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <name>Raymond Deck</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Drrbecker</name>
              <name>Brice Farwell</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Katharyn R. Gabriella</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Claude Marie Senninger</name>
              <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <front>
      <pb id="p11-69-70" n="69-70"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.011.02.bqscan" rend="file">
          <figTranscr>Blake<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY 42<lb/>
            VOLUME ELEVEN<lb/>
            NUMBER TWO<lb/>
            FALL NINETEEN SEVENTY-SEVEN</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0001">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">CONTENTS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <table id="contents" rows="17" cols="3">
          <row>
            <cell>BLAKE &amp; ZOROASTRIANISM</cell>
            <cell>72</cell>
            <cell>Mary V. Jackson</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>MORE THAN MUSIC COMPOSED AFTER BLAKE BY ARTHUR FARWELL</cell>
            <cell>86</cell>
            <cell>Brice Farwell</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">CHECKLIST</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>RECENT BLAKE SCHOLARSHIP 1976-1977</cell>
            <cell>104</cell>
            <cell>Thomas L. Minnick with Detlef W. Doerrbecker</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>THE BLAKE EXHIBITION AT ADELPHI UNIVERSITY</cell>
            <cell>110</cell>
            <cell>Ruth Fine</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>SUSAN FOX’S <hi rend="i">POETIC FORM IN BLAKE’S MILTON</hi></cell>
            <cell>114</cell>
            <cell>Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>CLARK STEWART’S DRAWINGS FOR <hi rend="i">THE MARRIAGE</hi></cell>
            <cell>117</cell>
            <cell>Judith L. Ott</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">POUR LES SEXES: LES GRILLES DE PARADISE</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>119</cell>
            <cell>From <hi rend="i">Les Nouvelles Littéraires</hi></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>BLAKE’S "WARRING ANGELS"</cell>
            <cell>120</cell>
            <cell>Frances Carey</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>MR. RUDALL THE FLAUTIST</cell>
            <cell>123</cell>
            <cell>Raymond G. Deck, Jr.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>JEAN PAUL RICHTER &amp; BLAKE’S <hi rend="i">NIGHT THOUGHTS</hi></cell>
            <cell>124</cell>
            <cell>Detlef W. Doerrbecker</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>BLAKE’S ILLUSTRATION OF THE 3RD TEMPTATION IN <hi rend="i">PARADISE REGAINED</hi></cell>
            <cell>126</cell>
            <cell>Robert F. Gleckner</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><hi rend="i">CUMBERLAND BIBLIOGRAPHY</hi> ADDENDA</cell>
            <cell>128</cell>
            <cell>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Mark Schorer 1908-1977, Blake at Tate Gallery, "Warring Angels," Mrs. Blake &amp; <hi rend="i">Faerie Queene</hi>, Blake on Thames TV, Correction, <hi rend="i">The Song of Milos</hi>, Fitzwilliam Withdraws Blake, Works by and about Blake, Golgonooza Bestiary, <hi rend="i">Prose Studies 1800-1900, CLQ</hi> Blake Issue, Lavater, Taurus Press <hi rend="i">America</hi></cell>
            <cell>129</cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>THE COVER &amp; INSIDE COVERS: xerox images by Michael Hays</p>
        <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">Copyright © 1977 by Morris Eaves &amp; Morton D. Paley</note>
        <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER is 0006-453X. Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly is INDEXED in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language &amp; Literature, <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>’ annual Romantic bibliography, and ARTbibliographies MODERN, EDITORIAL ASSISTANTS, Marietta Barnes &amp; Michael Hays, Univ. of New Mexico. CIRCULATION MANAGER: Jane Welford, Univ. of New Mexico. DESIGN for this issue: Chris Merwin, Washington Univ., St. Louis.</note>
        <pb id="p11-71" n="71"/>
        <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">
          <hi rend="b">EDITORS MORRIS EAVES &amp; MORTON D. PALEY · BIBLIOGRAPHER THOMAS L. MINNICK · ASSOCIATE EDITOR FRANCES A. CAREY Production Office Morris Eaves Department of English University of New Mexico Albuquerque New Mexico 87131 Telephone 505/277-3103 · Morton D. Paley Department of English University of California Berkeley California 94720 · Thomas L. Minnick University College Ohio State University 1050 Carmack Road Columbus Ohio 43210 · Frances A. Carey Department of Prints &amp; Drawings British Museum Great Russell Street London WC1B 3DG England.</hi>
        </note>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., (University of Toronto) is also the author of books on Flaxman and Blake, of which the most current are <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Critical Heritage</hi> (1975), <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Writings</hi> (2 vols., announced for 1977).</p>
        <p>Frances A. Carey is our Associate Editor for Great Britain.</p>
        <p>Raymond Deck is at Brandeis University finishing a dissertation and beginning to write a book about Blake and Swedenborg. His note will also appear in <hi rend="i">Rudall Newsletter</hi>, as "William Blake, the Poet: An Authentic Rudall Anecdote."</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker is a graduate student at the Johann Wolfgang Goethe University in Frankfurt. Originally he wanted to be a rock-and-roll hero but is now trying hard to become an art historian. He recently finished a study of Los’s Mathematic Power in the pencil drawing for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 51.</p>
        <p>Brice Farwell, the eldest of Arthur Farwell’s children, born 1918, has held administrative and editorial assignments at the research laboratory of IBM, in Yorktown Heights, New York. From 1951 to 1956 he was on the staff of <hi rend="i">McGall’s</hi> and <hi rend="i">Better Living</hi> magazines. Assembling, cataloguing, and microfilming his father’s work, which has become a full time hobby, began in the mid-1960s with the aid of most of his brothers and sisters.</p>
        <p>Ruth E. Fine is National Gallery of Art Curator for Alverthorpe Gallery, which houses the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection. In addition to the checklist of the Blake material in that collection (<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 35), she has written about 19th and 20th century prints and drawings.</p>
        <p>Katharyn R. Gabriella frequently calls our attention to items on Blake from Continental newspapers and journals. She is the author of <hi rend="i">The Imagination of the Resurrection: The Poetic Continuity of a Religious Motif in Donne, Blake, and Yeats.</hi></p>
        <p>Robert F. Gleckner (Professor of English, University of California, Riverside) is the author of <hi rend="i">The Piper and the Bard: A Study of William Blake</hi> and <hi rend="i">Byron and the Ruins of Paradise.</hi></p>
        <p>Mary V. Jackson is an Assistant Professor of English at the City College of New York and author of several articles on Blake.</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Minnick, of Ohio State University, is our Bibliographer. He is already at work on next year’s Annual Checklist of Blake Scholarship. He is also preparing a Norton Critical Edition on Coleridge.</p>
        <p>Judith Ott is a doctoral candidate in the History of Art at Ohio State University. She is presently working on a dissertation concerning the iconographical sources of the illustrations to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and their meanings in Blake’s system.</p>
        <p>Claude Marie Senninger, who translated the review from <hi rend="i">Les Nouvelles Littéraires</hi>, is Professor of Modern and Classical Languages at the University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. (Professor of English at the University of Maryland, College Park, and this year Visiting Professor at Brown University), is the author of <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of Milton</hi> (1975) and of <hi rend="i">Visionary Poetics: Milton’s Tradition and His Legacy</hi> (forthcoming from Huntington Library, 1978).</p>
        <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY is published under the sponsorship of the Department of English, University of New Mexico. SUBSCRIPTIONS are $7 for 1 year, 1 volume, 4 issues. Special rate for individuals, $6, surface mail. $10 for subscribers overseas who prefer air mail. U.S. currency or international money order if possible. Make checks payable to Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly. Address all subscription orders &amp; related communications to the Circulation Mgr., Jane Welford, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Dept. of English, Univ. of New Mexico, Albuquerque NM 87131 USA. Some BACK ISSUES are available. Address Jane Welford. Prices: whole numbers 1-8 (bound together), #9-13 (bound together), $5 each (individuals, $4). #22-present, $2 each, except #35 (Checklist of Blake Material in Rosenwald Collection, ed. Ruth Fine Lehrer), $3. #14-21 are out of print. MANUSCRIPTS are welcome. Send 2 typed copies to either of the editors. PHOTOGRAPHIC CREDITS usually appear in the captions. Others are: pp. 74-75, 82-83 (illus. 13-14), Raymond Jackson; pp. 86-99, the estate of Arthur Farwell; pp. 106-09, George H. Meyer, Westbury NY; pp. 113-15, reprinted courtesy of Clark Stewart; pp. 116-19, Thos. Agnew &amp; Sons, Ltd.; p. 123, courtesy of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. The INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER of Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</note>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <pb id="p11-72" n="72"/>
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND ZOROASTRIANISM</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>MARY <name>JACKSON</name></docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>There is considerable evidence that Blake was influenced by Zoroastrian and Mithraic iconography in several illuminations for his and other’s poetry. When one compares the figures of god and <hi rend="i">daeva</hi> with Blake’s drawings and engravings, the sheer number of parallels argues convincingly for some form of influence. Were there no other data than this to prove that Blake may have incorporated elements of representations of the bull-slaying ritual, of Arimanes or Ahriman, god of dark, and Ormazd, god of light, into his visual art, the evidence would seem persuasive. Fortunately, there is a good deal of external evidence to substantiate the case for direct sources. To begin with, we have Blake’s own testimony in <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809. In his discussion of the spiritual form of Pitt guiding Behemoth, Blake asserts:
<q>
These two pictures of Nelson and Pitt are compositions of a mythological cast, similar to those Apotheoses of Persian, Hindoo and Egyptian antiquity which are still preserved on rude monuments, being copies from some stupendous originals now lost or perhaps buried till some happier age. The artist having been taken in vision to those wonderful republics . . . has seen those wonderful Originals . . . some of them were one hundred feet in height; some were painted as pictures, and some carved as basso relievos, and some as groupes of statues, all containing mythological and recondite meaning, where more is meant than meets the eye. (Keynes, 565-66; Erdman, 521-22.)
</q>
Several things are suggested: first, that Blake actually saw representations of ancient Persian and other compositions, for he asserts that they <hi rend="i">are</hi> preserved on rude monuments and are but copies of the originals; second, that Blake’s imagination was keenly touched by what he saw, as his visionary journey to view the originals attests; third, that he obviously considered his two paintings to resemble Persian design, the most likely element being the snake enfolding portions of creation. Blake’s words and the often stunning similarity of his illuminations and "copies" of Ahriman and Ormazd require careful consideration of these analogues and possible direct sources of the Persian or so-called Zoroastrian.</p>
        <p>The evidence is corroborated by the existence of a large and diverse body of literature on Zoroaster, which was often accompanied by drawings and engravings, and some of which we know Blake saw. That this material usually contained information on and designs of the cult of Mithras—the religion popular among Roman legions and thus spread even to Britain—is of no real importance, for writers frequently confused the two. Religious and secular commentators contributed volume after volume on the subject. Travelers’ accounts of voyages to the East were popular and numerous after mid-seventeenth century and continued to interest philosophers and mythologists in the eighteenth century. These books only occasionally added any really fresh information to what was already known from ancient Greek and Roman sources and from medieval writers, but they sometimes contained line engravings of ruins, temples, rituals, and the like.<ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> (Although many travelers were themselves clergymen, they by no means unanimously approved of Persian religion and culture.) To some, the praise of Zoroastrian monotheism and spiritual enlightenment smacked of a heretical failure to appreciate the uniqueness of Christianity’s divinely revealed truth. This priestly perception fueled many a dispute, eventually involving
<pb id="p11-73" n="73"/><figure><head>3 "Tornado," published state, from Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden.</hi></head><figDesc>Robert N. Essick Collection.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-74" n="74"/>
even the philosophes, notably Diderot and Voltaire, who wished to discredit the idea that Christianity was the sole possessor of Truth, which could be discovered, they argued, by man in a natural and reasonable fashion, unaided by the "light of Revelation."<ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Both groups of partisans entertained hopes that the explorations of a young Frenchman in India would settle the battle in their favor; both were rather disappointed, for the scrupulously non-partisan researcher declined to enter the lists. Interest in Zoroastrianism was greatly stimulated, nonetheless, in 1771 upon the publication of his work, <hi rend="i">Zend Avesta, Ouvrages du Zoroastre.</hi><note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Mandelslo, du Mans, Le Bruyn, Wheeler, Hanaway and Kaempfer, for example, are among those traveler-journalists cited, with some engravings reproduced, in Jacob Bryant, <hi rend="i">A New System</hi> (1774-76). See also J. Bidez and F. Cumont, <hi rend="i">Les Mages Hellénisés</hi> (Paris, 1938); F. Cumont, <hi rend="i">Textes et monuments figurés relatif aux mystères de Mithra</hi> (Paris, 1902); J. Duchesne-Guillemin, <hi rend="i">The Western Response to Zoroaster</hi> (Oxford, 1958); and A. V. W. Jackson, <hi rend="i">Zoroaster, the Prophet of Ancient Iran</hi> (New York, 1898, 1928).</note><note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Duchesne-Guillemin, pp. 2-10, 12-15.</note></p>
        <p>Anquetil du Perron had spent eight years in India in Pahlavi or Parsee communities learning ancient and modern Persian, Arabic and Sanskrit. During these years he also meticulously copied and collated numerous volumes of sacred works, and collected many texts and sorely needed dictionaries in these languages. His two-volume translation, with a lengthy account of his voyage and a seventy page "Vie de Zoroastre," was received with much excitement in Germany and France, where scholars agreed that it superseded all other works. Although English academics knew of du Perron’s finds before they were published, for he had visited London and Oxford University before returning to France (<hi rend="i">Tome</hi> I, cccclviij-ccccxviij), they were slower to accept the Continental judgment. Indeed, du Perron’s splendid achievement had little if any effect on English mythologists before 1830: studies continued to pour out and most, like John Bell’s <hi rend="i">New Pantheon, or Historical Dictionary of the Gods</hi> (1790), rehearsed the established errors and clichés. In addition to such "new" efforts, earlier popular works were readily available. Pierre Bayle’s <hi rend="i">Dictionnaire historique et critique</hi>, for example, went through four editions in England between 1710 and 1826.</p>
        <p>Two volumes contain crucial evidence about Blake’s possible sources. The first is familiar to Blake critics. Jacob Bryant’s <hi rend="i">A New System, an Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi> (1774-1776) contains several fine line engravings of Ormazd, the god of light, and Mithraic devices. The plates were engraved in Basire’s shop while Blake was an apprentice there, as is well known. Almost certainly, they are a direct source for one of Blake’s most important illuminations. The second work may have been seen by Blake, though it is impossible to be certain. Prior to 1771 (and long after in England) the treatise on the Persian religion most widely known and influential was by the English scholar Thomas Hyde, whose <hi rend="i">Historica Religionis Veterum Persarum</hi> [sic] was first published in 1700 and reissued in a second edition, which I have used, in 1760. On the continent it had been the subject of heated debate and controversy because of the English cleric’s high esteem for the Zoroastrian religion. In England it remained a major source for "speculative mythologists," like Jacob Bryant, as his numerous references to it in <hi rend="i">A New System</hi> reveal.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Historica Persarum</hi> contains several reproductions, including a four-panelled tauroctone (illus. 1), which is from the 1760 edition. The progress of the panels is from the lower left, where the stage is set for the sacrifice; to the upper left, where the key characters are positioned (Mithra, the bull, Cautes, Cautopates, dog, sun, moon, snake and scorpion); to the upper right, in which the arrows, whip and stylized thunderbolts indicate the world turbulence the sacrifice will rectify; to the lower right panel, where the bull’s blood and semen are shed, and, though they try, neither scorpion nor snake will steal the precious life-renewing fluids. Located between the two right panels is a minute particular which, if Blake saw this book, he might not have overlooked. Illustration 2 is an enlargement of the center right scene. Between the Apollo-like figure guiding four horses (which resembles the upper left hand figure in <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, plate 11) and the chariot of seven fire altars drawn by two horses, there are two figures of special interest. The main, winged one is serpent entwined and holds a sceptre in his left hand. This small engraving of Ahriman, taken from a gem-stone carving, is accompanied by another, less frequently seen version of the god or <hi rend="i">daeva</hi>, one which depicts him without lion features and wings, as an entirely human form which is serpent encoiled.</p>
        <p>In this illustration from the 1760 work much alluded to by Bryant we find two major elements which are paralleled in Blake drawings and engravings: first, those in the tauroctone in which Mithra sacrifices the sacred bull; second, the winged, serpent-bound god, Ahriman, ruler of the corporeal world and guardian of the means of ingress and egress. There is little difficulty tracing sources for the bull-slaying scene, which was frequently described and illustrated. Examples of the Mithraic ritual, identical in the main to its Zoroastrian counterpart, are housed in museums throughout Britain. Some were imported, like the magnificent marble statue of the sacrifice in the British Museum (#1720), taken to England from Rome in 1815 by one C. Standish, Esq. But in reality that was a case of coals-to-Newcastle, for the country was dotted by archaeological sites containing tauroctones and a number of these were reported in "Transactions of the Philosophical Society," starting as early as 1743.<ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> The representation of Ahriman, however, is rarer. These two figures in Hyde are the only possible direct links I have yet discovered between Blake and images of the Mithraic god who is the Zoroastrian devil, except for Fuseli’s drawing of Tornado, which we know only through Blake’s engraving (illus. 3). While it cannot be stated unequivocally that the figures in <hi rend="i">Historica</hi> constitute a direct influence, it can justly be said that Blake at least could have known through Bryant of this widely influential work. I suggest that these minute particulars are very possible sources and that such close analogues may in fact indicate direct influence, especially in the light of Blake’s own comments in <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue.</hi><note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Leroy A. Campbell, <hi rend="i">Mithraic Iconography and Ideology</hi> (London, 1968). Prof. and Mrs. T. J. King verified data on the holdings in the British Museum.</note></p>
        <p>The figure of Ahriman in Hyde contains all the vital components commonly found in representations of the god except one, the lion’s head. Curiously, Blake’s engraving of "Tornado" after Fuseli, depicting
<pb id="p11-75" n="75"/><figure><head>1 Tauroctone.</head><figDesc>Hyde’s <hi rend="i">Historica.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure><head>2 Enlargement of right center panel.</head></figure><pb id="p11-76" n="76"/><figure><head>4 Mithraic God (190 AD), Vatican Museum.</head><figDesc>Alinari 35666.</figDesc></figure><figure><head>5 Mithraic God (c. 2nd C.), Vatican Museum.</head><figDesc>Alinari 35667.</figDesc></figure>
a lion-headed, winged demon, is both an analogue to the tradition and evidence of a direct source. We do not have the original drawing and cannot guess how Blake may have treated its contents. But his engraving for the third edition of Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> (1795) bears a great mechanical resemblance to more often seen versions of the god, the human face being a late development. Both forms were accessible in Europe during the eighteenth century. Though strikingly alike, the engraving does not precisely reproduce the symbolic features of the Mithraic god. For one thing, Tornado is encircled by a dragon with bat-like wings and a snaky body and tail; the wings are not his own. However, the leonine head is notable as are the flashes of lightning which recall the Mithraic tradition in which Ahriman’s two keys frame a thunderbolt, an emblem associated with Jupiter. Perhaps the interesting parallels in the plate raise questions less about Blake than about what Fuseli might have seen, or about what he actually drew, for that matter. For we do not know what details, if any, Blake added or altered. The most we can say is that the engraving is significant because it points to a now lost source which, in some respects was like the more widely available representations of the lion-headed, winged god holding his sceptre.</p>
        <p>I have included examples of statues and bas-reliefs of the two main Mithraic traditions without intending to suggest, naturally, that they are to be used for anything other than comparisons. As striking as some of the correspondences are, there is no reason to believe they are more than coincidence. To facilitate the discussion, I offer a brief account of the major Ahrimanic visual traits and their symbolism.</p>
        <p>In the statues, "basso-relievos," and gem-stone engravings, Ahriman is most frequently depicted as having the body of a man, the head of a lion, and one or two sets of wings (illus. 4, 5, and 6). His body is entwined by a serpent—usually in two to three or five to seven coils—whose head rests on the crown of the god’s head. In Mithraism, the serpent represents the world serpent believed to have been coiled around the body of the cosmos. The four wings attached at the shoulders and hips (broken in illus. 4 but clearly visible in 6) represent the
<pb id="p11-77" n="77"/><figure><head>6 Eone, Villa Albani, Rome.</head><figDesc>Alinari 27619.</figDesc></figure><figure><head>7 Deus Arimanius (c. 2nd C.), Florence.</head><figDesc>Courtesy of E.J. Brill, Leiden.</figDesc></figure>
winds of the four seasons and are "symbols of Pneuma, the hot breath that rules the seasons of life." In his aspect as <hi rend="i">Deus aeternus</hi>, Ahriman holds two keys (illus. 4 and 5), or less frequently one (illus. 6), emblems of his cosmic powers in his role as demi-urge or creator of the natural world and lord of men’s fortunes. He is not merely prince of <hi rend="i">this</hi> world, for the keys unlock one of the seven doors barring the soul’s path to heaven. His rod or sceptre usually held in the left hand (illus. 4 and 6) is another emblem of his sovereignty over this world, as is the globe on which his feet rest. The zodiacal and planetary signs on the body of the god (illus. 5) or surrounding him (illus. 10) became increasingly popular and had important implications. Whether in his role as <hi rend="i">daeva</hi> or <hi rend="i">Deus aeternus</hi>, Ahriman is thus shown to have control over the cycle of the months as well as the movements of planets and other heavenly bodies.<ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref><note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Campbell, pp. 211, 300-03, 348, 353. Cumont <hi rend="i">Les Mages</hi>, I, 12, 59, 67; II, 145. R. C. Zaehner, <hi rend="i">The Dawn and Twilight of Zoroastrianism</hi> (London, 1961), pp. 129-30.</note></p>
        <p>Although there is a good deal of variety in the representations of the god, most of them contain the symbolic elements described, with two noteworthy exceptions. There is a not very common tradition in which Ahriman is depicted solely as a serpent encircled human figure, with none of the features usually given him. Second, many of the standard traits appear in illus. 7, as well as another unusual, intriguing detail. To the lower left, attached to the lowest two coils of the serpent, is what appears to be a cocoon-like structure with the head and shoulders of a tiny human form breaking through its top. The cocoon is similar to the design in the center of the god’s chest in illus. 4. Its progress down the snake’s body toward its tail suggests the movement of the soul toward material or bodily existence. This appears to be a symbol of creation specifically as a fall into the mortal world.<ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref><note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Campbell, p. 350. Note that the cocoon-like encasing of the human form is analogous to the Frontispiece, "What is Man?", <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi> and to the ambiguously infantile worm, Plate III, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi></note></p>
        <p>There are numerous Blake illuminations which closely parallel these versions of Ahriman’s form and meaning in Mithraism and Zoroastrianism. Perhaps the most well known are the variants of plate 6 of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi> In copy D in the Fitzwilliam, a single serpent entwined human figure is shown falling, head downwards, arms in a cruciform position. The more frequently published version of that detail contains two additional snake-coiled figures on either
<pb id="p11-78" n="78"/><figure><head>8 Elohim Creating Adam.</head><figDesc>Courtesy Tate Gallery.</figDesc></figure>
side.<ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Blake has clearly incorporated his own recondite mythological meaning. The cruciform male with his falling companions simultaneously fore-shadows and parodies Christ’s crucifixion, an inevitable though distant consequence of Urizen’s error, which leads to fallenness or creation. But also the falling, serpent-bound bodies are symbolic forms being thrown headlong toward the abyss or, more mercifully, toward the fixed forms that will limit their fallen condition, which may then be temporary. Although the cruciform position of the figure is unique, I think, to <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, the motive is certainly utilized increasingly in Blake’s visual art after 1795, paralleling perhaps his growing view of the peril and horror of corporeality, despite its merciful quality or even its beauty. Examples abound, from the detail in plate 13 of the early prophetic book, <hi rend="i">America</hi>, to major individual creations such as "The Spiritual Form of Nelson Guiding Leviathan, "Laocoon," or "A Vision of the Last Judgment." <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Where it is feasible, I refer readers to published plates, as in this case; see the Micromethods filmstrips for the Fitzwilliam variant. See also David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City, N. Y., 1974), p. 188.</note></p>
        <p>Blake’s "Elohim Creating Adam" (1795) is a richly imaginative analogue to the icons of Ahriman, despite, or perhaps because of, the fact that the critical elements—wings, lion’s head, man’s naked body, and serpent—are dispersed, so to speak, divided between the two figures (illus. 8). God or the Elohim is given the wings (which closely resemble those of Ahriman in illus. 4) and a lion-like face with flowing, mane-like hair. Adam’s body, serpent encoiled, is being created, given fixed form. The
<pb id="p11-79" n="79"/><figure><head>9 Satan Watching the Caresses of Adam and Eve.</head><figDesc>Courtesy the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-80" n="80"/><figure><head>10 Deus Arimanius (c. 3rd C.), Modena.</head><figDesc>Courtesy E.J. Brill, Leiden.</figDesc></figure>
snake encircles the lower half of his body, as God’s hands reach out to touch or gesture over Adam’s head; and Adam’s feet (less completely articulated or metamorphosed than his head and torso?) seem to blend or bend into the last two coils of the snake’s body. Blake may have intended to suggest in vision that Adam was created out of the serpent’s body—the serpent symbolizing the senses, corporeality, and nature. The wings no less than the serpent suggest to me the ambiguity of this scene, for wings recall the immortal psyche, but also angels who are often representatives of mistaken or fallen vision (and at least one important devil, as we shall see). The four parallel forms, the wings, God’s and Adam’s and the snake’s bodies, emphasize the paradox, as do the mirrorings in the plate. The curling of the serpent’s tail above Adam’s lower legs mirrors the swirling robe of God, and the facial expressions, particularly the somberness and the open mouths, are deliberate visual echoes designed to shadow forth the truth that Creator and created are inescapably bound together in this paradoxical moment: the momentous beginning is an end to eternal life; creation is fall. The senses are vital in corporeal existence but simultaneously signal the closing off of the soul from immortality. The vision records the moment and the shape of the process that are both profoundly sad and merciful. Blake’s illumination calls to mind the statue (illus. 6) in which the tiny human form in the cocoon progresses down the snake’s body toward existence in this world.<ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref><note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Blake’s "With Dreams upon my bed thou scarest me," Plate XI of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, is indeed a horrific and intensely ironic analogue to his "Elohim Creating Adam." See S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> (New York, 1969).</note></p>
        <p>Ahriman was an ambiguous figure partly because of his innately paradoxical attributes and partly because of the early confusion of two discrete traditions. In Mithraism he was a <hi rend="i">deus</hi> whose awesome powers necessitated supplicating him for release from earthly existence and safe passage to heaven; in Zoroastrianism he was a <hi rend="i">daeva</hi> (diabolical spirit) with a ferocity, cruelty, and fondness for wantonly destroying men’s fortunes and spiritual hopes. This latter tradition predominated in Western culture, where he was identified with Baal, Pluto, the anti-Christ and Satan.<ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> Blake’s watercolor, "Satan Watching the Caresses of Adam and Eve" (1808) for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (illus. 9), is part of that tradition, to the extent that we can allow that he was influenced by representations of Ahriman. It is also an analogue to a late Roman visual development. The transformation in the bas-relief (illus. 10) represents a late trend in which Ahriman has fully human features, though the symbolic lion is retained, appearing on his chest. As in the other icons, he is serpent entwined and bears the sceptre of sovereignty in his left hand. Signs of the zodiac adorn the ovular frame of the relief, and that structure is echoed by the egg—note its flaming halves at his feet and above his head—from which the god is born.
<figure><head>11 Satan’s and Raphael’s Entries into Paradise.</head><figDesc>Courtesy the Huntington Library, San Marino, Calif.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-81" n="81"/>
Blake’s Satan, winged and serpent bound like the god, also has fully human features. In the foliage just left of and slightly above Eve’s right wrist, however, one may see a shape created by the configuration of the leaves, flame-like leaves, which suggests perhaps the head of a lion. It is coincidence un-doubtedly that there is so great a similarity between the drawing and bas-relief so removed from each other in time and place. Yet the resemblance is even more striking in "Satan’s and Raphael’s Entries into Paradise" (1807) for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (illus. 11). One can only marvel at what appears to be one of those fortuitous similarities whose exactness is suggestive of the powerful, universal appeal of certain visual symbols. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> F. Cumont, <hi rend="i">The Oriental Religions in Roman Paganism</hi> (New York, 1956), pp. 153-54; and <hi rend="i">Les Mages</hi>, I, 12, 59. Campbell, p. 353.</note></p>
        <p>Examples abound of Blake’s incorporation of two Ahrimanic details, perhaps from Hyde and certainly from Fuseli, into his own visual symbolism, bat-like wings and serpent-encoiled forms. Any one even a little familiar with his illuminations and paintings can call to mind an impressive number of serpent-bound bodies, emblematic of Blake’s vision of the paradox of corporeal existence. Though essential to life and often the portals of joy, the senses, especially touch, are perilous and can easily become a bog in which mortals flounder and are lost. They are simultaneously the tangible, outward bound of the process by which the spirit is benighted and the mode in this life of experiencing potentially redemptive bliss. Touch (particularly sexuality), the most threatening of all, is appropriately symbolized by the serpent. And, though the condition of being either female or male bespeaks to Blake the spirit’s descent and diminution, sexual delight is a reflection, if only a pale one, of the imagination’s delight which is Eternity. As such it lies at the heart of the dilemma of mortality—the unavoidable need to surrender to that which in Eternity is horrific because in corporeality it is a staff of life to the soul.</p>
        <p>In few instances indeed does Blake’s pictorial imagery more succinctly delineate this quandary than in "Comus with the Lady Spellbound" for <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> (illus. 12). The patterns on the chair to which the enchanted Lady is riveted are unique adaptations of the serpent-bound Ahriman, with and without wings. The two wingless figures decorating the legs of the chair and the winged one on its back are women, not girls, as their full breasts indicate. Unlike the Lady, whose hands fold protectively across her breasts, the winged, serpent-coiled female’s arms are raised, perhaps suggesting her openness to experience, as in plate 99 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The sinuous coils of the serpents are rigidly circumscribed by the moldings of the chair, a potently compressed metaphor of the Lady’s condition as she confronts the problem of successfully negotiating her way from childhood to a womanhood which includes wholesome sexuality. The nightmare enchantment, the phallic threatening Comus, and the serpent-dominated females who are further imprisoned in the frame represent the Lady’s own spiritual state as she approaches and resists adult sexuality. The
<figure><head>12 Comus with the Lady Spellbound at the Banquet.</head><figDesc>Courtesy the Huntington Library, San Marino, Calif.</figDesc></figure>
tension between living, flowing line and the inanimate, geometric one underscores the virgin’s perplexity: budding desire hemmed in, repressed, and thus distorted by her mingled fear and shame. The bestialized serpent coils belong within the rigid, wooden frame, for together they symbolize obverse sides of a fundamental process, the impulse-repression mechanism of her mind. Once the Lady can forgive and accept her own sensuality, she will transcend the entrapping process and no longer see sex as bestial. The wings and uplifted arms of one of the females suggest that she shall succeed.<ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref><note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> And she does, as Irene Tayler so cogently argues in "Say First! What Mov’d Blake? Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>," [S. Curran and J. A. Wittreich, Jr., eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi> (Madison, Wisconsin, 1973), pp. 233-581.</note></p>
        <p>We have examined at some length the ambiguities of the serpent, but wings too have their paradoxical emblematic value. They may be those of the eagle who is strong enough to fly near the sun, emblem of the life of the imagination which is Eternity; or those of the bat, symbol of the long night of the soul and dormancy of the imagination. But both are after all wings, where withal for passage from one point or state to another, image of the capability during the season of mortal existence of transforming consciousness into either the divinely human state of Man that approaches eternal bliss or the sub-human, visionless state of misery that Blake called Satan. So consistently did Blake use the bat-like dragon wings of his Tornado engraving that they constitute a visual code for destructive fallenness or demonic vision. With a few exceptions (like the early, ironic use of the emblem in some copies of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, plate 10, where a devil-liberator attempts
<pb id="p11-82" n="82"/>
to instruct the human from the bible of Hell) the bat wings signify vision so narrow as to constitute evil, the hindrance of life. In plate 11 of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>; plate 19 of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, added after 1815, when <hi rend="i">For the Children</hi> was enlarged and renamed, according to Erdman (<hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose</hi>, p. 734); in several illustrations for the <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy; Job</hi> engravings and paintings, and "Sullen Moloch" for <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity</hi>, we have instances of the adaptation from Fuseli of Ahriman’s demon wings to Blake’s own symbolic cosmos.<ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref><note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> The Illuminated Blake</hi>, pp. 169, 279; Albert S. Roe, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine Comedy</hi> (Princeton, 1953); Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job.</hi> "Sullen Moloch" is reproduced in Ruthven Todd’s <hi rend="i">William Blake The Artist</hi> (London, 1971).</note></p>
        <p>I wish to call attention briefly to three last motives from Zoroastrian and Mithraic statuary and bas-reliefs which may have influenced Blake’s illuminations of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The first we have already examined in the reproduction from Hyde’s <hi rend="i">Historica</hi> (illus. 1), but as I pointed out, tauroctones were frequently unearthed in, and even brought to, England during the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. The bull slaying, sacred to Zoroaster and Mithras, is analogous to plates 25, 69, and 85 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Of course, Blake’s symbolism stresses the cruelty and dubious value of the living sacrifice. The second feature, noticed originally by Anthony Blunt, is the near mirroring in what he calls Blake’s "human-headed bulls" in plate 41 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> of an engraving
<figure><head>13 Ormazd and the priest, engraving for <hi rend="i">A New System.</hi></head></figure>
from <hi rend="i">Ouseley’s Travels.</hi><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> I think Erdman’s idea that they are "ox-hooved, lion-maned, man-headed unicorns" is convincing.<ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Although I have not found any source to which Blake may have had access, I have recently come across examples from Susa of the winged bull figure, single-horned like the fabulous unicorn. In some cases such figures have even been called sphinxes, perhaps in acknowledgement of their likeness to the human-headed offspring of Chimaera, herself part serpent and lion. In any event, the similarity between Blake’s beasts in harness and the Persepolis reliefs is so great that it hardly seems accidental, especially since the figure in <hi rend="i">Ouseley</hi> is also reproduced in <hi rend="i">A New System</hi>, source for the final device in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that I wish to discuss. <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> The Illuminated Blake</hi>, pp. 304, 348, 364. <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 22, Vol. 6, no. 2 (Fall, 1972) note by Deirdre Toomey on the states of Plate 25.</note><note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Anthony Blunt, "Blake’s Pictorial Imagination," <hi rend="i">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</hi>, 6 (1943), 205; and <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake</hi> (New York, [1959]), p. 38, Plates 50a, b.</note><note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> The Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 320.</note></p>
        <p>The Zoroastrian god of light, Ormazd, was frequently represented on temples and state buildings in "basso relievos," and copies of them were available in travel accounts and books on mythology. Illustration 13 is taken from an 1807 edition of the second volume of <hi rend="i">A New System.</hi> Because of Blake’s relationship to Bryant, it is one quite important example of the readily accessible reproductions of Ormazd. In addition to the staple elements, such as the sun and fire altar, we see here the priest and Ormazd looking amazingly like in features and
<pb id="p11-83" n="83"/><figure><head>14 Enlarged engravings of Ormazd, <hi rend="i">A New System.</hi></head></figure><figure><head>15 The Palace Doorway of Darius the Great, Persepolis.</head><figDesc>Alinari MW207.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-84" n="84"/>
clothing (Bryant, II, plate XI). The god floats above his priest in clouds which fan out to either side; he holds a circlet or ring which is symbolic of the sun, the universe, and his eternal realm beyond this life. Scroll- or ribbon-like streamers unfold beneath the clouds to either side of the rather ragged skirt of the god’s gown. There are more accurate engravings of this motive in the same volume. A stylized drawing of the god’s wings (left, illus. 14) also contains the traditional curving, serpentine appendages below (Bryant, II, plate VIII). The line engraving to the right is a fine reproduction of a portion of the ruins at Persepolis, taken from a travel account as is its fellow. Eagle-like wings, the god’s perched hat, the symbolic ring, and—most notably—the circle or cincture, which encloses the god’s waist, with its curving lower arms or appendages, are faithfully copied as we can see by comparing the engravings to two photographs of the ruins. The first is the palace doorway of Darius the Great (illus. 15); the second is an earlier, better preserved example from the same ruin (enlarged detail, illus. 16).</p>
        <p>I particularly wish to call attention, again, to the cincture about the waist of Ormazd and its two swirling appendages, for there is a precise analogue to this structure in plate 100 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> I believe Ruthven Todd was the first to notice that the serpent temple, in front of which we see Los or Urthone, his Spectre and Emanation (illus. 17), is quite similar to a drawing of a Druid temple at Averbury, reproduced (or "reconstructed") in Stukeley’s <hi rend="i">Abury, A British Druid Temple</hi> (1743).<ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Surely it is also clear that we have here another direct influence, for Blake’s serpent temple is exactly like Ormazd’s serpentine girdle, as it is shown in Bryant and in the photographs of the ruins of Persepolis. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Ruthven Todd, <hi rend="i">Tracks in the Snow</hi> (London, 1946), pp. 31 ff.</note></p>
        <p>Analogues can be vexing, for once they have been produced they sometimes seem little more than curiosities. With Blake, however, it is usually true that they are integral both to his aesthetics and to the practice of his own art, because of his interpretations of the artist, be he poet or painter, and of human nature, which he believed to be a miracle of infinite variety founded on primal, universal patterns and processes. Thus, as we know, it was his conviction that the truth and beauty the artist creates are in a very real sense "discovered." For they represent that rare state of grace in which the artist is in touch with the source of his own being, which is itself a reflection of the soul of the Eternal Man who is the cosmos. And thus whatever an arttist produces can be and almost always has been discovered by others before him, with a greater or lesser accuracy and fullness depending upon the freedom from fetters of individual poetic genius and the sureness of individual craft. The existence, for example, of the coincidences we have discussed would only prove to Blake that his beliefs about art, vision and human nature are right. It is accurate though tautological to observe that for him the abundance of correspondences of ideas and visual forms in art and architecture <hi rend="i">demands</hi> his theory of poetic genius as a guide to Truth (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, plate 11), which in turn sensitizes one to perceive still more of these fortunate affinities: Ahriman’s and Tornado’s wings and those of the Elohim and Raphael, of Satan and Moloch; Ahriman’s serpent coiling, awesome symbol of the power and terror of corporeality and touch, and the falling soul’s taking on a body or Adam and the Lady emerging; the mistaken attempts at a <hi rend="i">natural</hi> renovation of the world through the bull slaying, the Druids’ human sacrifices, and the sacrifice of Albion in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 25; Ahura Mazda’s fiery serpentine girdle, Abury’s Druid temple, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s serpent temple—these must have been to Blake a wondrous concordance, proof of the sublime unity and universality of genuine myth or vision, the golden string threaded mercifully through the labyrinth.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p11-85" n="85"/>
      <figure>
        <head>16 Enlargment of Ormazd, Persepolis.</head>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <head>17 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 100.</head>
        <figDesc>From the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon.</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <pb id="p11-86" n="86"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">MORE THAN MUSIC COMPOSED AFTER BLAKE BY ARTHUR FARWELL</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>BRICE <name>FARWELL</name></docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>"Blake is right, ‘One thought fills immensity,’" wrote composer Arthur Farwell in the 1940s about the power of Blake’s imagery and intuitive quest for "unlimited mental expansion."<ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref><note id="n0">For further information about Farwell’s music or writings, <hi rend="i">a Guide to the Music of Arthur Farwell and to the Microfilm Collection of His Work,</hi> 1972, is available at music libraries or from the publisher, Brice Farwell, 5 Deer Trail, Briarcliff Manor, New York 10510. In the present essay, numbers in parentheses following opus numbers refer to their arrangement in the <hi rend="i">Guide.</hi> In 1975 the entire lifework archive was micropublished. Several major music libraries have acquired the collection; for information, address Brice Farwell as above.</note> Farwell is another composer who contributed to the music on Blake’s verse, but he did not stop there. He was influenced not only by the lyrical and beautiful (the strong symbolic and philosophical inventiveness of Blake’s expression) but was also intensely interested in Blake’s creative processes and in what Blake told about them. Like Blake, Farwell recorded an inner consciousness of his own that was possessed with vivid intuitive images, not only of musical ideas but also of both spontaneous and consciously-induced flashes of pictorial or visionary insight, which he was able to illustrate in a somewhat Blakean fashion decades later.</p>
        <p>The intuitive process, in Blake, in others and in his own experience, became an object of lifelong study by the composer, my father (trained in electrical engineering, B.S.E.E., M.I.T., 1893) before he embarked on his musical craeer. In his investigations he sought to objectify the role of intuitive phenomena in his own life and to understand the psychological principles in the general operation of intuition. He developed his work into a practical discipline whereby one might achieve purposeful, directed expansion of consciousness for artistic creation.</p>
        <p>In his record of the results of these studies, entitled in manuscript <hi rend="i">Intuition in the World-Making</hi>, Farwell explores the insights of numerous creative giants in the history of art, science and thought. Of Blake he concludes, "In the history and on the stage of intuition in art, Blake is surely the protagonist"; the thrust of this interpretation of Blake is presented in excerpts following this article.</p>
        <p>We may presume Arthur Farwell’s musical treatment of Blake’s verse to be among many unpublished or unsung Blake settings which no doubt exist. It is not surprising that they did not appear in the article on and checklist of musical settings of Blake’s poetry by Peter Roberts (<hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> 28, Spring 1974). There is no more reason for Peter Roberts, or anyone, to know Farwell’s Blake music today than for anyone beyond a small circle to have known of Blake the artist before Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Pictor-Ignatus</hi> in 1863. Upon Roberts’ invitation for assistance from readers, we introduce below five Blake poems Arthur Farwell set into song.</p>
        <p>Farwell, 1872-1952, was a composer better known for his music on American Indian themes than for his Blake settings, and for his efforts on behalf of his colleagues in the early part of this century (see the recent re-issue in 5 volumes of his music and writings from the Wa-Wan Press, edited by Vera B. Lawrence and published by Arno Press in 1970). In order of their composition, his Blake works are settings of <hi rend="i">Love’s Secret, The Wild Flower’s Song, The Lamb</hi>, a version of <hi rend="i">A Cradle Song</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi>, the first of which was published by the Wa-Wan Press in 1903. The next Blake poem was not set until after World War I.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">The Lamb, The Tyger</hi>, and <hi rend="i">A Cradle Song</hi> were done in the early 1930s, when Farwell was beginning to draft his notes for the text on intuition. <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi> exists only in manuscript, but the other two were published in a curiously Blakean fashion by the composer himself, who learned offset lithography for the purpose, drew the music and title designs on tracing paper, hand coated and exposed the zinc
<pb id="p11-87" n="87"/><figure><head>Blake songs in hand-made editions announced by the composer.</head><figDesc>In explaining the venture, Farwell said (on verso), "The present is, generally, a time of mass-thought and mass-action. However desirable or necessary this may be in certain fields, it is nevertheless directly against the spirit of art, which must remain a matter peculiarly individual."</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-88" n="88"/>
plates and operated the press himself. (A photo of him engaged in this activity, shown here, is reproduced in Percy Scholes’ <hi rend="i">Oxford Companion to Music.</hi>) Editions and distribution of the settings were naturally quite limited. Proper bibliographic references are as follows:
<q>
Op. 14 (25): No. 2.—(1) <hi rend="i">Love’s Secret</hi>, 1903, published by Wa-Wan Press, Newton Center, Mass., 1903.<lb/><lb/>
Op. 54 (74): <hi rend="i">Three Songs for Medium Voice</hi>: No. 2. <hi rend="i">The Wild Flower’s Song</hi>, 1919, published by John Church, New York, 1920.<lb/><lb/>
Op. 88 (114): Two Songs on Poems by William Blake, for medium voice and piano: No. 1. <hi rend="i">The Lamb</hi>, 1930, published privately, East Lansing, Mich., 1935.<lb/>
No. 2. <hi rend="i">A Cradle Song</hi>, 1930, published privately, East Lansing, Mich., 1935.<lb/><lb/>
Op. 98 (128): <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi>, for medium voice and piano, 1934, ms. only.
</q></p>
        <p>From the earliest setting the music is sensitive to the color, form, mood and meaning of Blake’s poetry: <hi rend="i">The Lamb</hi> is simple and lyrical, <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi> is quite stormy, and <hi rend="i">A Cradle Song</hi> has characteristics of both. The harmonic characteristics of all three are romantic and somewhat "modern" but not avantgarde for the 1930s. These and the early <hi rend="i">Love’s Secret</hi> were heard on 3 March 1976 in a musical program at the conference on "Blake in the Art of His Time," sponsored by the Departments of Art and English at the University of California at Santa Barbara. Local reviewer Richard Ames considered the Farwell songs the "most subtle settings of the evening." Another piece, without text, composed at about the same time, also printed at Farwell’s hand press at East Lansing, was inspired by Blake’s visionary mythology: Op. 91 (116), <hi rend="i">Vale of Enitharmon</hi>, piano, 1930, published 1935.</p>
        <p>Like Blake, Farwell was practically as well as philosophically anti-establishment, which is seen as one motif in his hand-crafted do-it-yourself publishing venture. His choice and treatment of these selections was styled more to seek a working response from devoted amateurs than to serve a virtuoso elite. And, like the poet, he also sought symbolic meanings. He introduced these publications with examples from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Experience.</hi> In his own way, Farwell may have borrowed an aspect of Blake’s symbolic concepts to subtly represent his own sense of an eternal and revolutionary rejuvenation (akin to what he had found deeply in Boehme) in Blake’s mythology and prophecy. Something vital, human and universal governed the function of music for Farwell and colored his musical expression of his inner vision.</p>
        <p>He had been driven in this quest since his early student days when he began to experience visionary phenomena, later recorded in drawings (the Blakean influence of which is suggested in the accompanying illustrations). He had also been a very public man in the first half of his musical career and quite a fighter for the independence of American music. As a music student he immersed himself in the romantic, bohemian ideas of his day, having spent two years in Europe under Humperdinck, Pfitzner and Guilmant. In the Wa-Wan venture he travelled the country, lecturing with the aid of a piano, and energetically organizing music clubs. Coming to New York in 1909, he joined the editorial staff of <hi rend="i">Musical America</hi> and became Supervisor of Municipal Concerts. He wrote numerous civic pageants and masques, including "Caliban" for the Shakespeare Tercentenary, with Percy MacKaye. During World War I he was a leader in the community singing movement.</p>
        <p>When he went west in 1918 with the beginnings of a family, he left behind much of his public life. He turned to formal teaching, at Berkeley and at Pasadena, and later at East Lansing, where he taught composition at Michigan State until his retirement in 1939. Although he continued with further interpretations of Indian themes into the 1940s, by the California years he had turned substantially toward his own musical ideas, trying to create an identifiably American music. He remained deliberately and constitutionally opposed to the zeitgeist of his day. Some of his work received public performance, such as the orchestral <hi rend="i">Symbolistic Study No. 3</hi> Op. 18 (68), on Walt Whitman’s "Once I passed through a populous city" and the <hi rend="i">Gods of the Mountain</hi> suite, Op. 52 (68). His <hi rend="i">Symbolistic Study No. 6, Mountain Vision</hi>, Op. 37 (52), earned a national broadcast in a 1939 competition, the year he retired to New York City. During the 1940s his most advanced American Indian works were heard in the concert repertoire of pianist John Kirkpatrick and the <hi rend="i">a capella</hi> choral tours of the Westminster Choir School.</p>
        <p>Musicians today, beginning to examine the compositions of Farwell’s later years, are finding of interest works which are said to show inventive musical experimentation and growth. Though these works are still only in manuscript (except for the few works of his hand-press venture) several posthumous premieres in the last three years have introduced his <hi rend="i">Piano Sonata</hi>, Op. 113 (161), <hi rend="i">Sonata for ‘Cello and Piano</hi>, Op. 116 (163), <hi rend="i">Quintet in E</hi><pb id="p11-89" n="89"/><figure><head>Cover design, in red and black, for two Blake songs, the first issue of Arthur Farwell’s hand press.</head><figDesc>The cover for his Blake-inspired piano work <hi rend="i">Vale of Enitharmon</hi> (see ff. pp.) was illustrated with an angelic figure, vignetted in radiant color, reproduced from an original drawing by Irish poet George Russell (A.E.), given to Farwell at an earlier time.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-90" n="90"/><pb id="p11-91" n="91"/><figure><head>Page 91 (opposite): sketch in pencil and crayon of "Spirit refusing to reincarnate in such a body," given to Arthur Farwell about 1903.</head><figDesc>According to a note in Farwell’s hand on the back of the drawing, it was given to him by Charles Johnston, who told him it was by the poet A.E. But when A.E. paid a visit to Farwell in 1938, "He couldn’t remember, said it could be either by him or Jack Yeats."</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-92" n="92"/><figure><head>Page 92: cover for <hi rend="i">Vale of Enitharmon</hi>, using the sketch.</head></figure><pb id="p11-93" n="93"/><figure><head>Page 93: first page of <hi rend="i">Vale of Enitharmon</hi>, 1935.</head><figDesc>On the back of this page is the following explanation:</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-94" n="94"/><figure><head>Pages 94-95: <hi rend="i">The Lamb</hi>, first publication of Arthur Farwell’s hand press.</head><figDesc>For uniformity he hand-whittled a cherrywood stamp for the note heads, which he applied on tracing paper using an india-ink stamp pad. Note stems were made with a draftsman’s ruling pen.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-95" n="95"/><pb id="p11-96" n="96"/><figure><head>Pages 96-97: Farwell’s music hand, as shown on a manuscript page of <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi>, compared with his hand-copied opening page of the published version of <hi rend="i">A Cradle Song.</hi></head></figure><pb id="p11-97" n="97"/><pb id="p11-98" n="98"/><hi rend="i">Minor</hi>, piano and strings, Op. 103 (136) and <hi rend="i">What’s In an Octave?</hi> Op. 84 (111) for piano. Perhaps his most characteristic works have been his many settings of poems by Emily Dickinson, another individualist and spirited American mystic. These were written from the time of the later Blake settings on through the 1940s and until the end of his life. Farwell worked at the manuscript of his study of intuition and the illustrations of his visionary experience throughout this period. He published several articles on his views of intuition and gave lectures illustrated with slides of his drawings (like those here reproduced) along with some done in water colors.</p>
        <p>Farwell asserts that any individual can bring the infinite resources of his own intuitive faculty to bear on any problem, if he will learn meditatively to let the force of universal principles flow and work. From fleeting hunches to visions of "cosmic import," a whole spectrum of inner experience lies along the axis from the particular to the universal. In art, Farwell perceived Blake’s visionary experiences to fully embody this process in which Blake "set forth his symbolic dreams in their entirety, just as they came to him." Farwell held that in this portion of Blake’s work the direct recording of visionary symbolism accounted for much of what he termed the "unique and problematic place Blake has so long held in the world of art." Farwell was of course unaware of the recent scholarship that has shown Blake’s graphic work to be readily understandable in the context of other work in his time. But at any rate Farwell was more interested in the working of Blake’s creative mind and its influence on the larger meaning of the work than in particulars per se.</p>
        <p>The captioned illustrations in these pages suggest a Blakean influence on several levels in Farwell’s work, which exemplify an awareness of craft, a naive artistic style and some analogue of universal intuition furnished in part by his exposure to the inspiration of Blake. Arthur Farwell’s contributions have not as yet found a Gilchrist; they may never. Though his name is listed in the musical encyclopedias, most of his works lay undisturbed until his seven children<ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> were able to find ways to make them accessible beginning in 1972, his centennial year.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">ARTHUR FARWELL ON BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Excerpted from his book manuscript <hi rend="i">Intuition in the World-Making</hi>, drafted over the years from about 1933 through 1948 and illustrated by the author with his sketches of symbolic images from his inner experiences, Arthur Farwell dwells on the meaning of Blake’s inner experiences for Blake’s art.</p>
          <p>Each chapter, broadly titled as shown in these pages, is given an analytical list of contents. For Chapter Six, containing Farwell’s principal examination of Blake and entitled <hi rend="i">Artistic Inspiration as Intuition</hi>, these topics are:
<q>
Relation of the artistic to the spiritual. Example of musical intuition. Richard Strauss’ testimony. Schubert’s phenomenal intuition. Composition in hypontic state. Composition in semi-trance. Unconscious practice of "consciously induced" intuition. Asking the "infinite" for musical themes. Application of Criteria and Law. Wagner’s striking testimony. Transference of artistic intuitive power to life-problems. Artists’ lack of understanding of intuition. Testimony of writers. Identity of principle of intuition in all fields, including the spiritual. Testimony of painters. Blake’s singular position. Vision as abstract art. Vision vs. dream in painting. Relation of conscious and subconscious minds to imagination. Artistic functioning as field for psychological study. Man’s four basic faculties. Intuition and "inspiration." Genius. Despiritualization of art. A new artistic teaching. Potential height of subconscious response.
</q>
Farwell’s development of Blake’s "singular position" is excerpted below, slightly condensed, following these brief opening words in his Introduction, given here to set the author’s tone and perspective.
<q>
This book, on its first level, is a direct and unqualified account of the experience of myself and others with intuition, and, on my own part, with its conscious control and use. As such, it is a recital of adventure and observation in a region of perception beyond that of reason, though not without a recognition of the organic relation of that region to the total human consciousness, in which reason plays its proper part.<lb/><lb/>
On its second level it presents a formulation of certain principles and laws of intuition and its use, and a record of thoughts, conclusions and outlooks born of this adventure and observation. On its third level it pictures the result upon human life, the larger meanings for the individual and the race, of the full development and use of the intuitive faculty.<lb/><lb/>
The present work in no way seeks to alter or oppose the current general idea of what
<pb id="p11-99" n="99"/><figure><head>Title and Table of Contents of Arthur Farwell’s discourse on his investigation of intuition.</head><figDesc>Farwell went on to examine this process, tame it, reduce it to practice and study its context and range of meaning in human experience. Farwell illustrated his treatise with his hand sketches from memory of both his spontaneous visionary experiences and also with some of those he consciously induced. He turned to Blake as a key example of intuition and vision in art; he concluded the study by picturing, narrating and interpreting a vision-like experience which he likens to Blake’s visions. Two of his sketches for this example are shown here.</figDesc></figure>
intuition is. But this idea is so . . . narrow and limited . . . that it has become outworn as an aid to the further development of this faculty, with its limitless latent powers of illumination . . . and of creative inspiration. . . . This popular attitude is further devoid of any sense of the spiritual and cosmic implications of the intuitive faculty, and of its immense significance for the future, in human evolution. . . .<lb/><lb/>
Intuition, then, will embrace the commonly understood idea of intuition (inclusive of what is popularly known as the "hunch"), the artistic, scientific, philosophical or spiritual inspiration, in fact all creative revelation in any sphere, the symbolic dream, the vision, and other related subconscious phenomena of a revelatory nature, and all of these reason-transcending illuminations as experienced both in their spontaneous, unexpected manner, and also as the result of the conscious and purposeful inducing of them. The name of none of these so different appearing phenomena, other than "intuition" itself, may suitably be used to include them all.<lb/><lb/>
The present work aims to make progress in laying the foundations of a Science of Intuition.
</q></p>
          <p>Leaping from here into the framework of his Chapter Six, as given above, we read of Blake in Arthur Farwell’s thought thus:
<q>
William Blake’s is the name most usually brought forward in connection with the idea of artistic inspiration as intuition, but without the bearing which I shall indicate. His pictorial work, along the line of cleavage which I am considering, divides itself into two classes: one being the work in which he exercised his creative capacities in the usual manner of artist, whether or not intuition played a part; the other being that in which he set forth his symbolic dreams and vision in their entirety, exactly as they came to him, with nothing added from his conscious mind. . . .<lb/><lb/>
In the extensive portion of Blake’s art which is a direct and exclusive presentation of that which the subconscious mind puts forth, he was more completely a medium of intuitive revelations than were the other artists mentioned
<pb id="p11-100" n="100"/>
here. Pure intuition is pure truth, clearly revealing itself and readily graspable as such, when not sullied or distorted by . . . the darkness and error to which the objective mind is all too susceptible. Its immediate expression in artistic terms, with no such interferences . . . introduced, will reflect that truth in equal purity. The result of this cosmically involved act of the direct revelation of truth [is] a picture of most decisive outline, authoritative, absolutely irrefutable, and commanding acceptance. And it is precisely these qualities that mark the character of Blake’s genuine vision pictures. Blake, quite naturally, is not always at this height.<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/><lb/>
It is this giving straight out of his intuitive visions as they came to him, instead of merely availing himself of the aid of occasional intuitions in the execution of a consciously conceived picture, that accounts for the unique and problematical place which Blake has so long held, and still holds [1948], in the world of art. The many works in which he has followed this course do not appear to reveal a man’s conscious devising faculties at play, but rather a superhuman power, as from without, working through the artist’s hand. Of these Blake writes, "And though I call them mine, I know they are not mine."<lb/><lb/><figure><head>Two of the six somewhat Blake-inspired drawings by the composer illustrating his narration, recorded and drawn in the 1930s from his memory of an experience in the night of 28 December 1905, which he interpreted at length in the final chapter of his book ms.</head><figDesc>on intuition; "‘The Vision of The Great City,’ in its most general sense, is a picture of regeneration and reconstruction in its widest human bearings. It is revealed in a five-fold cycle—the end of a certain phase of consciousness with its attendant human order, cataclysm and change, ascent to a higher level, passage through darkness leading to mystical experience, and establishment of a new human order on a higher ground. With the momentary exclusion [1948 writing] of the more obscure fourth phase, it will, I believe, be generally admitted that these are, or contain, issues of first importance to the world today. They are certainly vastly more to the fore now than they were at the time the vision occured." Farwell’s use and illustrations of this experience are a personal example of the sort of occurence he ascribes to Blake in regard to Blake’s more visionary art.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-101" n="101"/><figure><head><hi rend="i">Humanity at a Standstill</hi>—Opening scene in Farwell’s 1905 "Vision of the Great City."</head><figDesc>" . . . stood an immense multitude of people, waiting, with dread . . . An age had ended, civilisation collapsed—everything had stopped. Mankind, with its dream—at last—thwarted—beaten. Something must happen, and happen quickly, or the race itself would be at an end."</figDesc></figure><pb id="p11-102" n="102"/><figure/><pb id="p11-103" n="103"/>
This is to me the <hi rend="i">real</hi> abstract art, as conveying human and cosmic meanings which seldom appear in the art of the day bearing that designation. While we shall probably never do without pictorial art produced in the usual manner, . . . [yet] "without a vision the people perish" is a truth for tomorrow as well as for yesterday. A function hitherto observed chiefly in spiritual seers may very possibly appear and find increasing activity in the sphere of pictorial art. So much did his visions mean to Blake, that when they failed to appear he went to his knees and prayed for them, a quite sufficient testimony to the spiritual character of the man. . . .<lb/>
In the exercise of imagination without the intuitive possibility, I would merely be fishing around for images in a mind of which I ought to be thoroughly tired. But in the request for intuitive revelations I would be offering myself as a candidate for unlimited mental expansion. Blake was evidently continually tired of what he knew his conscious mind to contain, and so was frequently praying for more visions. The continuous revelation of continually new images of truth is undoubtedly what he justifiably thought of and so greatly exalted as "imagination," and not the former limited and wearying procedure. Hence the amazing divergence and variety of his designs. . . . Blake is right, "One thought fills immensity." . . .<lb/><lb/>
. . . Certain . . . famous painters . . . have had virtually only one pictorial idea or image in their heads. . . . They appear to have spent the best part of their lives seeking to paint this image continually better . . . . We doubtless have some of our most perfect specimens of art from such. . . . Blake’s mind, on the other hand, was in this respect a <hi rend="i">tabula rasa</hi>, ready for the impress of any sort of image whatsoever, of any aspect of the universal diversity. . . . The major attitude and trend, indeed the prayerful urge, of his mind was . . . toward universal imagination—necessarily something beyond his conscious conceptive power. Images from such a super-personal sphere can be communicated to the individual in no other way than through intuition. What comes through intuition <hi rend="i">lives.</hi> Thus Blake’s art has remained vital, in essential respects "modern," and even prophetic, for a century and a half. In the history, and on the stage, of intuition in art, Blake is surely the protagonist.
</q></p>
          <figure>
            <head><hi rend="i">Cataclysm</hi>—The second vista in Farwell’s "Vision of The Great City."</head>
            <figDesc>In the picture the figures in the foreground he said were himself and "one who was my mother." "It was a period of upheaval and dire events. Occupations had been swept away, and the people thronged the hills. . . . Suddenly there came a great earthquake . . . I and those around me were hurled helplessly about." After a quiet, "Again a mighty earthquake shook and split the earth . . . until in the midst of the convulsions the hills gave way and sank, and mountains rose up from the low places.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p11-104" n="104"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0004">
        <byline><docAuthor>THOMAS L. <name>MINNICK</name></docAuthor> WITH THE ASSISTANCE OF DETLEF W. DOERRBECKER</byline>
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">A CHECKLIST OF RECENT BLAKE SCHOLARSHIP 1976-1977</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p>This issue of the annual checklist of Blake scholarship differs from previous ones in two significant ways. First, through the assistance of Detlef W. Dörrbecker, who has sifted through European publications, the checklist covers current continental scholarship on Blake and his contemporaries for the first time. Second, we have included a number of Blake references, mostly European, that have not hitherto been recorded either in the annual checklists or in such other bibliographies as those by Keynes, Bentley and Nurmi, or Schiff. These retrospective items, also contributed by Dörrbecker, are marked with an asterisk.</p>
        <p>We are grateful to many people for helping with the checklist this year: Ms. Susan A. Hoyt, of Columbus, Ohio, who helped with art history items; Mrs. Aasta Fischer (Prestel-Verlag), Dr. Niehaus (Verlag Freies Geistesleben), and other German and Swiss publishers who were most helpful and cooperative in compiling materials for the reviews section; and the authors and editors who thoughtfully sent along notes and offprints to call to our attention items that might otherwise have gone unrecorded.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">BIBLIOGRAPHIES, BIBLIOGRAPHICAL ESSAYS, EXHIBITION CATALOGUES</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Allen, Robert R., ed. "The Eighteenth Century. A Current Bibliography for 1974." Philological Quarterly, 54 (1975), no. 4. [Blake items are listed with annotations and brief reviews on pp. 901-910.]</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. A Bibliography of George Cumberland (1754-1848). New York and London: Garland Publishing, Inc., 1975. $18.00</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. Blake Books: Annotated Catalogues of William Blake’s Writings, Designs, Engravings, Books He Owned, and Scholarly and Critical Works About Him. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977. $88.00. [A revised and considerably expanded edition of Bentley and Nurmi’s <hi rend="i">Blake Bibliography.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., ed., with the assistance of Robert R. Mollenauer and James S. Patty. "The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography for 1975." English Language Notes, 14 (1976), supplement to no. 1.</p>
          <p>Gleeson, Larry, ed. Followers of Blake. Santa Barbara, Calif.: Santa Barbara Museum of Art, 1976. [Catalogue of an exhibition of the Shoreham Group mounted by the Santa Barbara Museum of Art in conjunction with the conference, "Blake in the Art of His Time."]</p>
          <p>Goff, Phyllis, comp. William Blake. Catalogue of the Preston Blake Library Presented by Kerrison Preston. Cumulative Supplement to the Printed Catalogue of 1969. London: Westminster City Libraries, 1976. [Adds 322 items to the catalogue of 1969, including those in the supplement of 1972 "which is consequently now superseded."]</p>
          <p>*Gradmann, Erwin. Schweizer Graphik von Urs Graf bis Hodler. Zurich: no publisher, n.d. (196?). [Exhibition catalogue of a travelling exhibition organized by the Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule for the Pro-Helvetia Foundation. See pp. 9-10 and catalogue nos. 106-115 for information about Fuseli. Not listed in the bibliography by Schiff.]</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn. "Choosing Textbooks for Blake Courses: a Survey &amp; Checklist." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 8-26. [An extensive review essay. Appendixes include lists of out-of-print items, works in progress, and addresses of publishers.]</p>
          <p>Jordan, John E. "Recent Studies in the Nineteenth Century." Studies in English Literature 1500-1900, 15 (1975), 671-694. [Includes reviews of recent books about Blake.]</p>
          <p>Lemaitre, Henri. "Etat présent des études blakiennes." études Anglaises, 28, no. 4 (1975), 439-443.</p>
          <p>Minnick, Thomas L. "A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship." Blake Newsletter, 10 (Fall 1976), 59-62.</p>
          <p>Robinson, K.E. "The Eighteenth Century" in James Redmond, ed., The Year’s Work in English Studies, 55 (1974). [For reviews of recent books about Blake, see pp. 334-337.]</p>
          <p>Schiff, Gert, et al. Johann Heinrich Füssli 1741-1825, ed. Werner Hofmann. Kunst im 1800. Munich: Prestel-Verlag, 1974. [Exhibition catalogue of the Hamburger Kunsthalle.]</p>
          <p>Schiff, Gert, et al. Henry Fuseli 1741-1825, ed. Sir Norman Reid, trans. Sarah Twohig. London: The Tate Gallery Publications Department, 1975. [Exhibition catalogue of the Tate Gallery, translated into English from the original Hamburg catalogue with some revision and rearrangement.]</p>
          <pb id="p11-105" n="105"/>
          <p>Schiff, Gert, et al. Johann Heinrich Füssli 1741-1825, ed. Adeline Cacan, trans. Martine Perrel, Christine Casler, and Jacques Chavy. Paris: Les Presses Artistiques, 1975. [Exhibition catalogue of the Musée du Petit Palais, translated into French from the original Hamburg catalogue, with some rearrangement and revision.]</p>
          <p>Walker, Corlette Rossiter, et al. William Blake in the Art of His Time. Santa Barbara: University of California, Santa Barbara, 1976. [Catalogue of an exhibition held at the University Art Galleries, University of California, Santa Barbara, 24 February to 28 March 1976.]</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">EDITIONS, TRANSLATIONS, FACSIMILES, REPRODUCTIONS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr., ed. William Blake’s Writings. 2 vols. Oxford English Texts. Oxford: The Clarendon Press, 1976. $83.60. [Volume I: Engraved and Etched Writings. Volume II: Writings in Conventional Typography and in Manuscript.]</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, and Deirdre Toomey, eds. The Complete Engravings of William Blake. Forthcoming from Thames and Hudson.</p>
          <p>Bircher, Martin, and Karl S. Guthke, eds. Johann Heinrich Füssli: Sämtliche Gedichte. Nobile Turegum: Zürcher Drucke des 16. bis 19. Jahrhunderts. Zürich: Orell Füssli Verlag, 1973. [The first complete edition of Fuseli’s poetry, with his German poems in German, his English poems in English. Edition limited to 1000 copies.]</p>
          <p>*Blake, William. "Das Buch Los," trans. Joachim Uhlmann. Die Neue Rundschau, 73(1962), 678-683.</p>
          <p>*Blake, William. "Gedichte," trans. Georg von der Vring. Insel-Almanach auf das Jahr 1958. Wiesbaden: Insel-Verlag, 1957. Pp. 95-97. [Translations of seven short poems, included in Vring’s edition of the following year.]</p>
          <p>*Blake, William. "Der Geist des Abel; Eine Offenbarunq aus den Visionen Jehovas, gesehen von William Blake (1822)," trans. Wolfgang Martin Schede. Antaios, 3 (1961), 65-67.</p>
          <p>*Blake, William. Le Marriage du ciel et de l’enfer, trans. André Gide. Paris: Charlot, 1947. [In the series, "poésie et théâtre," edited by Albert Camus.]</p>
          <p>*Blake, William. Sprüche der Hölle. n.p. (Frankfurt am Main?): 1963-64. [The "Proverbs of Hell" privately printed in a small edition intended as a New Year’s gift.]</p>
          <p>*Blake, William. Unschuld und Erfahrung: Die beiden Kontraste der Menschenseele; Gedichte, trans. and ed., Kaethe Wolf-Gumpold. Vienna: Europäischer Verlag, 1966. [Includes <hi rend="i">Songs, Thel.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Blake, William. The Wood Engravings of William Blake. Introduction by Andrew Wilton, preface by Kenneth Clark. London: British Museum Publications Ltd., 1977. £300. [Printed from the original blocks held by the British Museum, the edition is limited to 150 copies of which 135 are for sale.]</p>
          <p>Crehan, A.S., ed. William Blake. Pergamon English Literature. New York: Pergamon, 1976. $3.50.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., ed. The Selected Poetry of Blake. Bergenfield, N.J.: New American Library, 1976. $2.50.</p>
          <p>Flaxman, John. Receuil de ses compositions gravées au trait (1836). Paris and Brussels, 1974. [A facsimile of the Reveil edition.]</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. The Book of Los. London: The Trianon Press for the William Blake Trust, 1976.</p>
          <p>*Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. William Blake: Dichter, Drucker, Prophet; Eine Studie über die Illuminierten Bücher, trans. Marguerite Schlüter. Wiesbaden: Limes Verlag, in association with the Trianon Press, 1965.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. William Blake’s Laocoön. A Last Testament. With Related Works: <hi rend="i">On Homer’s Poetry</hi> and <hi rend="i">On Virgil, The Ghost of Abel.</hi> London: The Trianon Press for the William Blake Trust, 1976. $65.00. ["This volume completes the series begun by the William Blake Trust in 1951 with its first publication, a facsimile of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> . . . . Following this volume the Trust will, from time to time, publish further titles, including <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations for the Book of Job, Blake’s Engravings for Dante’s Divine Comedy</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Portraits of William and Catherine Blake.</hi>" This edition limited to 380 copies.]</p>
          <p>*Longstreet, Stephen, ed. The Drawings of Fuseli. Master Draughtsman Series. Alhambra, Calif.: Borden Publishing Co., 1969. [Reproduces 62 drawings.]</p>
          <p>Thorpe, James Ernest, ed. William Blake: Songs of Innocence and of Experience: Selected Plates Reproduced in Facsimile from Originals in the Huntington Library. San Marino, Calif.: Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1975.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">CRITICAL STUDIES</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Abel, Elizabeth Frances. "The Married Arts: Poetry and Painting in Blake and Baudelaire." Diss. Princeton, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 290-A.</p>
          <p>*Adams, Hazard. "Reading Blake’s Lyrics: ‘The Tyger’," in Willi Erzgräber, ed., Englische Lyrik von Shakespeare bis Dylan Thomas. Ars interpretandi, vol. 1. Darmstadt: Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft, 1969. [Reprinted from Texas Studies in Literature and Language, 2 (1960).]</p>
          <p>Adlard, John. "Bawdy Blake." English Studies, 56 (1975), 320-321.</p>
          <p>*Adlard, John. "Blake and ‘Electrical Magic’." Neophilogus, 53 (1969), 422-23.</p>
          <p>Adlard, John. "Blake, Thel and ‘The Wisdom of Angels’." Studia neophilologica, 46 (1974), 172-74.</p>
          <p>*Adlard, John. "The Cock, the Lion, and the Spectres in Blake." Archiv fur das Studium der Neueren Sprachen und Literaturen, 204 (1968), 432 f.</p>
          <p>Adlard, John. "Fields from Islington to Marybone." Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 120.</p>
          <p>Ahmad, Iqbal. "Northrop Frye’s Theoretical Criticism." Diss. York University, 1974. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36 (1975-76), 6667-A. [Chapter One treats Blake’s influence on Frye.]</p>
          <p>Allan, David. "The Progress of Human Culture and Knowledge, Part II." Connoisseur, 188 (1975), 98-107. [On paintings by James Barry.]</p>
          <p>Antal, Frederick. Füssli Studien, trans Eva Schumann. Neue Bibiothek der Kunst- und Kulturgeschichte. Dresden: VEB Verlag der Kunst, 1973. [German edition of Antal’s Fuseli Studies (1956).]</p>
          <p>Ault, Donald. Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton. 1974; rpt. Midway Reprint Series, 1976. $7.25.</p>
          <p>Ba-Han, Maung. William Blake: His Mysticism. 1924; rpt. Norwood, Pa.: Norwood Editions, 1976. [Limited to 100 copies.]</p>
          <p>Baine, Rodney M. and Mary R. Baine. "Blake’s Inflammable Gass." Blake Newsletter, 10 (Fall 1976), 51-52.</p>
          <p>Baine, Rodney M., and Mary R. Baine. "Blake’s Sketch for <hi rend="i">Hamlet.</hi>" Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 117-119.</p>
          <p>Baine, Rodney M., and Mary R. Baine. "Then Mars thou wast our center." English Language Notes, 13 (1975), 14-18. [Swedenborg and <hi rend="i">America</hi> 5, <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 19.]</p>
          <p>*Bataille, Georges. "William Blake." Die Neue Rundschau, 73 (1962), 684-702.</p>
          <p>Beaucamp, Eduard. "Blake oder der Ausstieg aus der Geschichte" in Das Dilemma der Avantgarde; Aufsätze zur bildenden Kunst. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp Verlag, 1976. Pp. 44-49.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. "The Vicissitudes of Vision: The First Account of William Blake in Russian." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 112-114.</p>
          <p>*Berefelt, Gunnar. Philipp Otto Runge: Zwischen Aufbruch und Opposition 1777-1802. Acta Universitatis Stockholmiensis—Stockholm Studies in History of Art, vol. 7. Stockholm, Göteborg and Uppsala: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1961. [Includes numerous references to Blake’s art and art theory.]</p>
          <p>*Bernus, Alexander von. "Dem Gedächtnis William Blakes." Ruperto-Carola, Mitteilungen der Vereinigung der Freunde der Studentenschaft der Universität Heidelberg, 9 (1957), 86-88. [Includes Blake poems in German translation from Bernus’s edition.]</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. "An Announcement." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 70. [Announces the rediscovery of an impression of the Laocoön last recorded in 1938 and includes a photograph.]</p>
          <p>*Bloch, Ernst. "Milde und ‘Licht seiner Wut’ (William Blake)" in Atheismus im Christentum; zur Religion des Exodus und des Reichs. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp Verlag, 1968. [The eminent German philosopher, Ernst Bloch, mentions Blake’s eschatological ideas in various works.]</p>
          <p>Bloxham, Laura Jeanne. "William Blake and Visionary Poetry in the Twentieth Century." Diss. Washington State University, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36 (1975-76), 5275-A.</p>
          <p>Blunt, Anthony. "Des origines de la critique et de l’histoire de l’art en Angleterre." Revue de l’art, 30 (1975), 5-16.</p>
          <p>Bogan, James. "Vampire Bats &amp; Blake’s Spectre." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 32-33.</p>
          <pb id="p11-106" n="106"/>
          <p>Bohrer, Karl-Heinz. "William Blake (1757-1827): Maler, Dichter, Visionär—‘Eschatologisches Zeitalter’ und industrielle Revolution." [Radio broadcast.] Kulturelles Wort, Abendstudio-Feature. Hessischer-Rundfunk, Frankfurt am Main: 30 July 1973.</p>
          <p>*Bölker, Uwe. "Lyrik der englischen Romantik" in K.H. Göller, ed., Epochen der englischen Romantik. Düsseldorf: August Bagel Verlag, 1970. Pp. 152-181.</p>
          <p>Bonham, Ronald Allen. "Hart Crane’s ‘Mystical-Empirical’ Poetry and Its Relation to Nineteenth Century Traditions." Diss. University of British Columbia, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 4350-A. [Chapters two through five discuss Crane’s relationship to British Romantics, including Blake.]</p>
          <p>Briganti, Guiliano. Phantastische Malerei im 19 Jahrhundert. Munich: Schuler Verlagsgesellschaft, 1974. [First published in Italy by Fratelli Fabbri Editori, this work reproduces six works by Blake and a number by Fuseli.]</p>
          <p>Bronowski, Jacob. Der Aufstieg des Menschen, trans. Gustav Kemperdick. Frankfurt am Main, [West] Berlin, and Vienna: Ullstein Verlag, 1976. [The German edition of The Ascent of Man.]</p>
          <p>*Bullough, Geoffrey. "William Blake: ‘The Book of Thel’" in T.A. Riese and D. Riesner, Versdichtung der englische Romantik; Interpretationen. Berlin: Erich Schmidt Verlag, 1968. Pp. 108-123.</p>
          <p>Burke, Joseph. English Art 1714-1800. Oxford History of English Art, Vol. 9. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1976. £12.50.</p>
          <p>Butler, Gerald J. "Conflict Between Levels in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>" Recovering Literature, 5 (1976), 39-49.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. "The Rediscovery of an Artist: James Jefferys 1751-1784." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 123-124.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. "‘The Very William Blake of Living Landscape Painters.’" Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 33-34.</p>
          <p>Chesterton, Gilbert Keith. William Blake. 1910; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1976.</p>
          <p>Clark, R. "Samuel Palmer et la peinture visionaire." Revue de l’art, 30 (1975), 55-60.</p>
          <p>Cox, Stephen D. "‘The Stranger Within Thee’: The Self in British Literature of the Later Eighteenth Century." Diss. University of California, Los Angeles, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 2193-A. [Discusses Richardson, Gray, Chatterton, Cowper, and Blake.]</p>
          <p>Dargan, Tom. "Blake and Hayley in Wittreich’s <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse.</hi>" Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 130-135.</p>
          <p>Davidson, C. "Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> and ‘Rebel Nature’." Research Studies, 44 (1976), 35-41.</p>
          <p>Dobai, Johannes. Die Kunstliteratur des Klassizismus und der Romantik in England. Vol. I. Bern: Benteli, 1974. [At least four volumes are planned for this monumental study.]</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr. "Unnoticed Printings of Blake’s Poems, 1825-1851." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 125.</p>
          <p>Dembo, Pamela. "William Blake and Rabindranath Tagore." UNISA [University of South Africa] English Studies, 14 (1976), 52-55.</p>
          <p>Dennis, Rodney G. "Flaxman’s Answers to Klopstock." Harvard Library Bulletin, 24 (1976), 197-203.</p>
          <p>Diffey, T.J. "Morality and Literary Criticism." Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism, 33 (1975), 443-454. [Includes examples from Blake.]</p>
          <p>DiSalvo, Jackie. "Blake Encountering Milton: Politics and the Family in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>" in Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., ed., Milton and the Line of Vision. Madison, Wisconsin: University of Wisconsin Press, 1975. Pp. 143-184.</p>
          <p>Donaldson, Ian. "The Satirists’ London." Essays in Criticism, 25 (1975), 101-122. [Mentions Blake on London.]</p>
          <p>*Draper, R.P. "Blake’s Early Poems: Experiments in Romantic Style." Revue des langues vivantes, 32 (1966), 587-597.</p>
          <p>Dupperay, Max. "A la source de la ville fantastique: ‘London’ de William Blake." études Anglaises, 28 (1975), 385-397.</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris. An Index to Damon’s Blake Dictionary. Providence: Brown University Press, forthcoming.</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris. "Postscript: Blake’s Abnormal Psychology." Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 121-122.</p>
          <p>Edwards, Thomas R. "Blake: The Mythologist as Agitator" in Imagination and Power: A Study of Poetry on Public Themes. New York: Oxford University Press, 1971. Pp. 141-159.</p>
          <p>Epstein, E.L. "The Self-Reflexive Artefact: The Function of Mimesis in an Approach to a Theory of Value for Literature" in Roger Fowler, ed., Style and Structure in Linguistics: Essays in the New Stylistics. Oxford: Blackwell’s, 1975. Pp. 40-78. [Includes discussion of "The Tyger," pp. 60-78.]</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. "The Bravery of William Blake." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 27-31. [Reprinted from Erdman’s Signet Classic edition of <hi rend="i">The Selected Poetry of William Blake.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. "Blake in the Marketplace, 1974-75." Blake Newsletter, 10 (Fall 1976), 53-59.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N., and Morton D. Paley. "The Printings of Blake’s Designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi>" Book Collector, 24 (1975), 535-552. [The "1813 small paper folio" was printed in 1870.]</p>
          <p>Feaver, William. The Art of John Martin. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1975. £7.00.</p>
          <p>Ferber, Michael. "‘Thel’s Motto’: Likely and Unlikely Sources." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 36-38. [Discussion with Michael Tolley.]</p>
          <p>Firestone, E.R. "John Linnell: The Eve of the Deluge." Bulletin of the Cleveland Museum of Art, 62 (1975), 131-139. [13 illustrations.]</p>
          <p>Fleissner, Robert F. "William Blake, ‘The Little Black Boy’." Notes on Teaching English, 3 (1975), 8-9.</p>
          <p>Fox, Susan, Poetic Form in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1976. $13.50.</p>
          <p>Franson, J. Karl. "Christ on the Pinnacle: Interpretive Illustrations of the Crisis in <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained.</hi>" Milton Quarterly, 10, (1976), 48-53. [Discusses Blake’s illustration which is reproduced in color on the front cover of the issue.]</p>
          <p>*Frey, Dagobert. Englisches Wesen in der bildenden Kunst. Stuttgart and Berlin: W. Kohlhammer Verlag, 1942. [For an analysis of Blake’s pictorial style, see pp. 372-379.]</p>
          <p>Galbraith, Thomas William. "A ‘Fresher Morning’: Blake Labors to Awaken Man." Diss. University of Washington, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 984-A.</p>
          <p>*Gantner, Joseph, and Adolf Reinle. Kunstgeschichte der Schweiz. Vols. 3 and 4. Frauenfeld: Verlag von Huber &amp; Co., 1956, 1962. [For discussion of Fuseli, see vol. 3, pp. 368, 396-399; vol. 4, pp. 134, 161, 187, 301. For discussion of Blake, see vol. 3, pp. 398-399.]</p>
          <p>Glozer, Laszlo. "Johann Heinrich Füssli." in Kunstkritiken, Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp Verlag, 1974. Pp. 82-87. [Originally published as a review essay on the Zurich Fuseli exhibition of 1969 in Süddeutsche Zeitung (Munich), 28/29 June 1969.]</p>
          <p>*Göller, Karl Heinz. "William Blake: ‘Songs of Innocence, Introduction’" in K.H. Göller, ed., Die englische Lyrik; Von der Renaissance bis zur Gegenwart. Düsseldorf: August Bagel Verlag, 1968. Vol. 1, pp. 301-308.</p>
          <p>Goyder, George. "An Unpublished Poem about Blake by William Bell Scott." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 125. ["On seeing again after many years William Blake’s designs for ‘the Grave’."]</p>
          <p>*Graberg, Marie-Louise von. Die Nibelungen-Illustrationen von Johann Heinrich Füssli und Peter Cornelius. [West] Berlin: printed for the author, 1970. [Ph.D. thesis.]</p>
          <p>*Grant, John E. "William Blakes ‘The Fly’" in Willi Erzgräber, ed., and Regine Wolf, trans., Interpretationen 8; Englische Literatur von William Blake bis Thomas Hardy. Frankfurt am Main and Hamburg: Fischer Bücherei, 1970. Pp. 9-37. [Reprinted from Bulletin of the New York Public Library, 1963.]</p>
          <p>Grant, Philip Bernard. "A Possible Source for a Blake Sketch and Drawing." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 85-87.</p>
          <p>Grant, Philip Bernard. "Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi>: An Edition and Study." Diss. University of Pennsylvania, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 4366-A.</p>
          <p>Greenberg, Mark. "The Canterbury Pilgrims by Stothard and Blake: An Account with Reproductions in ‘The Architect’." Notes and Queries, n.s. 23 (1976), 401-402.</p>
          <p>*Hartmann, Wolfgang. Die Wiederentdeckung Dantes in der deutschen Kunst: J.H. Füssli, A.J. Carstens, J.A. Koch. Bonn: printed for the author (at the University Press), 1969. [Ph.D. thesis.]</p>
          <p>Haworth, Helen E. "‘A Milk-White Lamb That Bleats’? Some Stereo-types of Women in Romantic Literature." Humanities Associattion Review, 24 (1973), 277-293. [Includes discussion of Blake.]</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher. "Notes on Some Items in the Blake Collection at McGill with a Few Speculations around William Roscoe." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 100-108.</p>
          <p>*Hermand, Jost, ed. Jugendstil. Wege der Forschung, vol. 110. Darmstadt: Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft, 1971. [For discussion of Blake and art nouveau, see pp. 81, 278-279, 298, 300, 302, 305.]</p>
          <p>*Hönnighausen, Lothar. "Aspekte des Blake-Verständnisses in der ästhetik des neunzehnten Jahrhunderts—Blake und die Präraphaeliten." Zeitschrift für Kunstgeschichte, 33 (1970), 41-53.</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner. Das Irdische Paradies; Motive und Ideen des 19. Jahrhunderts. Munich: Prestel-Verlag, 1960. 2nd ed., 1974. [Blake is mentioned throughout, with added emphasis in the 2nd edition.]</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner. "Per Capire Blake." Bolaffiarte, 50 (1975), 21-24.</p>
          <pb id="p11-107" n="107"/>
          <p>[Hofmann, Werner.] "William Blake (1757-1827), Zeichnung." Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 10 December 1976, p. 23. [Notes the acquisition of a Blake drawing for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 51, now in the Kunsthalle Hamburg.]</p>
          <p>Hofstätter, Hans H. Geschichte der europäischen Jungendstilmalerei; Ein Entwurf. Cologne: Verlag M. Dumont Schauberg, 1963. Rev. 3rd ed., 1965. Rpt., 1972. [Discusses Blake and art nouveau on pp. 91, 108-111, 119 f.]</p>
          <p>Hofstätter, Hans H. Idealismus und Symbolismus. Aufbruch der Druckgraphik von der Romantik bis zur Gegenwart, vol. 2. Vienna and Munich: Schroll Verlag, 1972. [Blake mentioned throughout.]</p>
          <p>Hofstätter, Hans H. Symbolismus und die Kunst der Jahrhundertwende. Cologne: Verlag M. Dumont Schauberg, 1965. 2nd ed., 1973. [Blake discussed as a source of symbolist art in the late nineteenth century. Fuseli and other contemporaries of Blake are also discussed.]</p>
          <p>*Hofstätter, Hans H., with Jaworska and S. Hofstätter. Jugendstil Druckkunst. Epochen der Druckkunst. Baden-Baden: Holle-Verlag, 1968. [Blake discussed as a forerunner of art nouveau.]</p>
          <p>Hofstätter, S. See Hofstätter, Hans H., Jugendstil Druckkunst.</p>
          <p>Holstein, Michael E. "Crooked Roads without Imporvement: Blake’s ‘Proverbs of Hell’." Genre, 8 (1975), 26-41.</p>
          <p>Howard, John. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: A Study in the Selfhood. Cranbury, N.J.: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 1976, $15.00.</p>
          <p>*Hume, Robert D. "The Development of Blake’s Psychology: The Quest for an Understanding of Man’s Position in the World." Revue des langues vivantes, 35 (1969), 240-258.</p>
          <p>Jaworska, W. See Hofstätter, Hans H., Jugendstil Druckkunst.</p>
          <p>Johnson-Grant, Mary Lynn. "Mapping Blake’s London." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 117-122. [Includes three maps by Karen McHaney: "Blake’s Britain," "The Holy Land," and "Blake’s London."]</p>
          <p>Jones, Edward Terry. "Another Look at the Structure of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>" Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 115-116.</p>
          <p>Kauvar, Elaine. "Los’s Messenger to Eden: Blake’s Wild Thyme." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 82-84.</p>
          <p>Keating, Ruth Aikman. "A Fourth Dimension in Word and Picture: William Blake’s Theory of Imagination." Diss. Texas Woman’s University, 1974. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36 (1975-76), 6115-A.</p>
          <p>Kegel-Brinkgreve, E. "Auguries of Innocence." Dutch Quarterly Review of Anglo-American Letters, 4 (1974), 111-119.</p>
          <p>*Kellner, Leon. "William Blake." Xenien, Monatsschrift für literarische ästhetik und Kritik, 2 (1909), 321-327. [An early reference to Blake not mentioned in the bibliographies by Keynes or Bentley and Nurmi.]</p>
          <p>*Kuczynski, Jürgen. Darstellung der Lage der Arbeiter in England von 1760 bis 1832. Die Geschichte der Lage der Arbeiter unter dem Kapitalismus, vol. 23. [East] Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 1964. [Blake cited as one who expressed through art and literature the social conditions of late eighteenth-century laborers.]</p>
          <p>*Kuczynski, Jürgen. "William Blake: Ein Romantiker besonderer Art" in Gestalten und Werke, vol. 2: Soziologische Studien zur englischsprachigen und französischen Literatur. [East] Berlin and Weimar: Aufbau-Verlag, 1971. Pp. 54-67. [An essay in much the same vein as Bronowski’s Man Without a Mask, Schorer’s Politics of Vision, and Erdman’s Prophet Against Empire.]</p>
          <p>*LeBreton, Georges. "William Blake et le néo-platonisme." Mercure de France, 7, no. 1197 (1963), 494-499.</p>
          <p>Liscombe, R.W. "The Commencement of Real Art." Apollo, 103 (1976), 34-39. [Traces the influence of the Parthenon friezes on English sculpture and painting of the early nineteenth century, including Flaxman.]</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. "Blake’s Appearance in a Textbook on Insanity." Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 120-121.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. "Calvert’s ‘Lady &amp; the Rooks’ &amp; Cornish Scenes." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 34.</p>
          <p>Loehrich, Rolf. Exercitium Cogitandi. 6 vols. London: Exercitia Publications, 1976. £46. [Vol. 6 includes "Menage a Trois/ Blake at a seminar, with the menage present among others." Vol. 6 alone, £8.50.]</p>
          <p>MacDonald, Greville. The Sanity of William Blake. 1908; rpt. Norwood, Pennsylvania: Norwood Library Editions, 1975.</p>
          <p>MacMillan, J.D. "The Illuminated Book and the History of Art." Apollo, 104 (1976), 142-143.</p>
          <p>Masterson, Donald Joseph. "The Method of Openness and the Theme of Love in the Early Poetry of William Blake." Diss. University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36 (1975-76), 6117-A.</p>
          <p>Matteson, Lynn Robert. "Apocalyptic Themes in British Romantic Landscape Painting." Diss. University of California, Berkeley, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 5-A. [On John Martin, Turner, Benjamin West, and Francis Danby.]</p>
          <p>McClellan, Jane Martha. "William Blake’s Concept of Man in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>" Diss. Florida State University, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 4371-A.</p>
          <p>McHaney, Karen. See Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant.</p>
          <p>*Mertner, Edgar. "Die ältere romantische Dichtung: Blake, Wordsworth, Coleridge" in Ewald Standop and Edgar Mertner, Englische Literaturgeschichte. Heidelberg: Quelle &amp; Meyer Verlag, 1967. Pp. 404-408.</p>
          <p>Metken, Günter. Die Präraffaeliten: Ethischer Realismus und Elfenbeinturm im 19. Jahrhundert. Cologne: Verlag M. DuMont Schauberg, 1974. [Includes remarks on Blake and the Pre-Raphaelites.]</p>
          <p>*Müller, Hermann Alexander, and Hans Wolfgang Singer, eds. Allgemeines Künstlerlexikon—Leben und Werke der berühmesten bildenden Künstler. 3rd rev. ed. Frankfurt am Main: Literarische Anstalt Rütten &amp; Loening, 1895. [Brief article on Blake on p. 132. This item is not listed in the bibliographies of Keynes or Bentley and Nurmi.]</p>
          <p>Murry, John Middleton. William Blake. 1933; rpt. Norwood, Pa.: Norwood Editions, 1976.</p>
          <p>*Muther, Richard. "Phantastik und Geschichtsmalerei" in Geschichte der englischen Malerei. Berlin: S. Fischer Verlag, 1903. Pp. 86-90. [This early essay on Blake, well-known in Germany, is not listed in the bibliographies of Keynes or Bentley and Nurmi. Muther discusses the "weaknesses" of Blake’s artistic execution but notes the parallels between Blake and William Morris and treats the dynamics of Blake’s flaming lines.]</p>
          <p>Nathan, Norman. Prince William B. The Philosophical Conceptions of William Blake. The Hague: Mouton, 1976. $14.50.</p>
          <p>Nelson, J. Walter. "Blake Anthologies." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 32.</p>
          <p>Nochimson, Martha. "Against the Limitations of Rationalism: Undercurrents in the Works of William Faulkner." Diss. City University of New York, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 1551-A ["Reinterpretations of <hi rend="i">The Sound and the Fury, Light in August</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Absalom, Absalom!</hi> in an anti-dualistic light, with the aid of Blake’s spectacles. . . ."]</p>
          <p>Nurmi, Martin K. William Blake. Kent, Ohio and London: Kent State University Press and Hutchinson &amp; Co. Ltd., 1976. $10.00.</p>
          <p>O’Hare, Susan Carol. "Going Wonder-Ways: Sacrality and Skepticism in British Romantic Poetry." Diss. Rice University, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1967-77), 2203-A. [Heirophany in Blake, Wordsworth, Shelley, and Keats.]</p>
          <p>Ott, Judith. "The Bird-Man of William Blake’s Jerusalem." Blake Newsletter, 10 (Fall 1976), 48-51.</p>
          <p>Owlett, F.C. Chatterton’s Apology: With a Short Essay on Blake and a Note on Cowper. 1930; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1976.</p>
          <p>Pache, Walter. "‘Blakes seltsame Poesien’. Bildzitat und Bildwirkung in Thomas Manns ‘Doktor Faustus’." Arcadia, Zeitschrift für vergleichende Literaturwissenschaft, 8 (1973), 138-155. [Discusses Blake’s influence on Thomas Mann, who used part of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in <hi rend="i">Doktor Faustus.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. "John Camden Hotten, A.C. Swinburne, and the Blake Facsimiles of 1868." Bulletin of the New York Public Library, 79 (1976), 259-296. [Includes 14 illustrations.]</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. See also Robert N. Essick.</p>
          <p>*Pauli, Gustav. Die Kunst des Klassizismus und der Romantik. Propyläen-Kunstgeschichte, 1st series, vol. 14. Berlin: Propyläen Verlag, 1925. [Discusses Blake on pp. 135f., 138 f., 481, 516.]</p>
          <p>Pressly, William Laurens, Jr. "The Life and Art of James Barry." Diss. New York University, 1974. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 1280-A.</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen. William Blake. Paris: Chêne, 1975. [French translation of the volume published by Thames and Hudson in 1970.]</p>
          <p>Reinli, Adolf. See Gantner, Joseph.</p>
          <p>Riede, David George. "Swinburne: A Study in Romantic Mythmaking." Diss. University of Virginia, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 2204-A. [Chapter two discusses Blake and Swinburne.]</p>
          <p>*Riese, Teut Andreas. "William Blake: ‘The Little Girl Lost’ und ‘The Little Girl Found’" in T.A. Riese and D. Riesner, eds., Versdichtung der englische Romantik; Interpretationen. Berlin: Erich Schmidt Verlag, 1968. Pp. 80-107.</p>
          <p>*Rønning, Helge. "The Poet as a Rebel—Blake’s and Shelley’s Views of Promethean Man" in Miscellanea; Essays . . . , A Tribute to Prof. Kristian Smidt on the Occasion of His 50th Birthday, 20 November 1966. Oslo: Universitetsforlaget, 1966. Pp. 44-49.</p>
          <pb id="p11-108" n="108"/>
          <p>Rosenblum, Joseph. "A Motley Web: A Study of Thomas Holcroft’s Dramatic Art." Diss. Duke University, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36 (1975-76), 6715-A.</p>
          <p>Rosenblum, Robert. Modern Painting and the Northern Tradition. Friedrich to Rothko. New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1975. [Pp. 41-64 include commentary on Blake and Palmer.]</p>
          <p>Ryan, Robert Emmett. "The Structure and Function of the Cosmogonic Myth in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>" Diss. Case Western Reserve University, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 339-A.</p>
          <p>Ryskamp, Charles. "A Blake Discovery." The Times Literary Supplement, 14 January 1977, pp. 40-41. [An extra-illustrated copy of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> (1830), now in the Pierpont Morgan Library, contains six posthumous impressions from Blake’s plates (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 2, 41, and 59; and <hi rend="i">America</hi> 12, 13, and 14), six contemporary impressions (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 28 [an unknown reworking] and 70; <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 3, 4, and title-page [an unknown reworking]; and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> 5); a variant of the plate "Gem Engraving" for Rees’s <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi>; and two letters about Blake, one by John Varley, the other by Bernard Barton quoting Charles Lamb on Blake and a previously unpublished poem by Barton on Blake.]</p>
          <p>*Schede, Wolfgang Martin. "‘Heilig ist, was lebt.’ William Blake und die schöpferische ‘Insanity’." Antaios, 3 (1961), 59-64.</p>
          <p>*Schiff, Gert. "Einige Bemerkungen über die künstlerischen Beziehungen zwischen Füssli und Blake." Kunstchronik, 15 (1962), 296-297. [Not noted in Schiff’s Fuseli bibliography.]</p>
          <p>*Schmutzler, Robert. Art Nouveau—Jugendstil. Stuttgart: Gerd Hatje Verlag, 1962. [Note especially "Ursprünge des Art Nouveau: William Blake’ (pp. 35-53) and "Die Wirkung William Blakes" (pp. 109-114) for discussions of Blake’s influence on Art Nouveau. Reproductions include 12 Blakes.]</p>
          <p>Schotz, Myra Glazer. "On the Frontispiece of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>" Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 126-127.</p>
          <p>Scrimbeour, J.R. "Great Example of Horror and Agony: A Comparison of Søren Kierkegaard’s Demoniacally Despairing Individual with William Blake’s Spectre of Urthona." Scandinavian Studies, 47 (1975), 36-41.</p>
          <p>Searle, Leroy F. "Anatomical Criticism and Value in Contemporary Art." Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism, 33 (1975), 393-402. [Includes references to Blake.]</p>
          <p>Signet, Charles J. "The Role of Christ in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>" Essays in Literature, 3 (1976), 167-180.</p>
          <p>Stempel, Daniel. "Angels of Reason: Science and Myth in the Enlightenment." Journal of the History of Ideas, 36 (1975), 63-78. [Includes discussion of Blake’s angels.]</p>
          <p>Stempel, Daniel. "Blake’s Monadology: The Universe of Perspectives." Mosaic, 8 (1975), 77-98.</p>
          <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie. "Blake’s News from Hell: <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and the Lucianic Tradition." ELH, 43 (1976), 74-99.</p>
          <p>Tayler, Irene. "Blake’s Laocoön." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 72-81.</p>
          <p>Tolley, Michael. "‘Thels’s Motto’: Likely &amp; Unlikely Sources." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 35-36. [Discussion with Michael Ferber.]</p>
          <p>Tomory, Peter A. "A Blake Sketch for Hayley’s Ballad ‘The Lion’ and a Connection with Fuseli." Burlington Magazine, 118 (1975), 377-378.</p>
          <p>Tomory, Peter A. Johann Heinrich Füssli, Leben und Werk, trans., Peter Hahlbrock. [West] Berlin: Propyläen Verlag, 1974. [The German edition of Tomory’s book, first published by Thames and Hudson (1972).]</p>
          <p>Torbruegge, Marilyn K. "‘Der grösste nach den Griechen’: Winckelmann and Fuseli in accord." Lessing Yearbook, 5 (1973), 186-197.</p>
          <p>Trent, Robert J. "The Case Against Death: Transformations of ‘Generation’ in the Writings of William Blake." Diss. New York University, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976-77), 1573-A.</p>
          <p>Twitchell, James B. "‘The Mental Traveller,’ Infinity and the ‘Arlington Court Picture’." Criticism, 17 (1975), 1-14.</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet. "Blake’s ‘Auguries of Innocence’." Colby Library Quarterly, 12 (1976), 126-138.</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet. "A Contemporary Reference to Blake." Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 122.</p>
          <p>Waxler, Robert Phillip. "William Blake: The Sexual Dynamics of his Early Illuminated Books." Diss. State University of New York, Stoney Brook, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37, (1976-77), 995-A.</p>
          <p>Weitzman, Arthur J. "Eighteenth-Century London: Urban Paradise or Fallen City?" Journal of the History of Ideas, 36 (1975), 469-480. ["Explains to some extent the cult of Blake in academic circles. . . ."]</p>
          <p>White, Harry. "Blake and the Mills of Induction." Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 109-112.</p>
          <p>Woodman, R.G. "Satan in the ‘Vale of Soulmaking’: A Survey from Blake to Ginsberg." Humanities Association Review, 25 (1974), 108-121.</p>
          <p>Worrall, David. "William Blake and Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden.</hi>" Bulletin of the New York Public Library, 78 (1975), 397-417.</p>
          <p>Wright, John W. "Blake’s Relief-Etching Method." Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 94-114.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Adams, Hazard. William Blake: A Reading of the Shorter Poems. Reviewed by Erich Zauner, Erasmus—speculum scientiarum, 22 (1970), cols. 545-546.</p>
          <p>Adlard, John. The Sports of Cruelty. Reviewed by F.W. Bateson, Notes and Queries, n.s. 22 (1975), 83-84.</p>
          <p>Ault, Donald D. Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton. Reviewed by J.D. North, Review of English Studies, 27 (1976), 517.</p>
          <p>Beer, John. Blake’s Visionary Universe. Reviewed by R.B. Kennedy, Notes and Queries, n.s. 22 (1975), 79-82.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. Blake Records. Reviewed by R.B. Kennedy, Notes and Queries, n.s. 22 (1975), 79-82.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr., ed. William Blake: The Critical Heritage. Reviewed by Suzanne Hoover, Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 89-90.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the Fitzwilliam Museum. Reviewed by Jacques Lethève Bulletin des bibliothèques de France, 17 (1972), 942.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. An Island in the Moon. Audio tape of a production for KPFK Pacifica, Pasadena, California. Produced by Everett C. Frost. Music by Edward Cansino. Reviewed by Martin K. Nurmi, Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 128-129.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Folcroft facsimile. Reviewed by Mary Ellen Reisner, Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 130.</p>
          <p>Blake exhibition, Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, Spring 1971. Reviewed by Günter Metken, Frankfurter Rundschau, 3 April 1971.</p>
          <p>Blake exhibition, Hamburg, 1975. Reviewed in a radio broadcast on Bayerischer Rundfunk [Munich], 6 November 1975.</p>
          <p>Blake exhibition, Hamburg and Frankfurt (1975), and David Bindman, et al., William Blake 1757-1827 (exhibition catalogue). Reviewed in Die Presse [Vienna], 9/10 August 1975; Gazette des Beaux Arts, September 1975; by Hans Theodor Flemming, Weltkunst, 45 (1975), 426-427; by Rolf Herzog, Neue Zürcher Zeitung, 1/2 August 1975; by Peter Sager, Buch und Bibliothek, no. 3 (1976), 192-93.</p>
          <p>Blake Newsletter. America, a Prophecy. Reviewed by David V. Erdman, Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 123-126.</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. The Anxiety of Influence. Reviewed by J.A. Appleyard, S.J., in Keats-Shelley Journal, 25 (1976), 188-190.</p>
          <p>Burke, Joseph. English Art 1714-1800. Reviewed by Hugh Honour, The Times Literary Supplement, 21 January 1977, pp. 63-64.</p>
          <p>Dorfman, Deborah. Blake in the Nineteenth Century. Reviewed by Margaret Bottrall, Studia neophilologica, 42 (1970), 237-239.</p>
          <p>Easson, Roger R., ed. America: A Prophecy. Reviewed by David V. Erdman, Blake Newsletter 9 (1976), 123-126.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. The Illuminated Blake. Reviewed by Kenneth Garlick, Notes and Queries, n.s. 23 (1976), 379; Leonard M. Trawick, Studies in Burke and His Time, 18 (1977), 57-60.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., with the assistance of Donald K. Moore, eds. The Notebook of William Blake. Reviewed by Gerald E. Bentley, Jr., JEGP, 75 (1976), 437-444; R.B. Kennedy, Notes and Queries, n.s. 22 (1975), 79-82.</p>
          <p>Feaver, William. The Art of John Martin. Reviewed by Peter Conrad, The Times Literary Supplement, 30 January 1976, pp. 111-112.</p>
          <p>Fox, Susan. Poetic Form in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Reviewed in Milton Quarterly, 10 (1976), 129; Mary Lynn Johnson, Milton and the Romantics, 2 (1976), 1-10.</p>
          <p>Frosch, Thomas R. The Awakening of Albion. Reviewed by Robert Brinkley, Kritikon litterarum, 3 (1974), 206-207.</p>
          <p>Johann Heinrich Füssli: Sämtliche Gedichte. Reviewed in Neue Zürcher Zeitung, 30 September 1973, in Schweizer Monatshefte, 9 (1973); Hermann Boeschenstein, Erasmus—speculum scientiarium, 26 (1974), 862-865; Friedhelm Kemp, Sliddeutsche Zeitung, 15 November 1973; Christoph Siegrist, Germanistik, 15 (1974), 633; Thomas Terry, Zuger Tagblatt, 29 November 1973 (the same review was also published in the Solathurner Zeitung, 1 December 1973; in Der Bund [Bern], 10 February
<pb id="p11-109" n="109"/>
1974; and in the Berner Tagblatt, 26 May 1974.)</p>
          <p>Gillham, D.G. William Blake. Reviewed by F.W. Bateson, Notes and Queries, n.s. 22 (1975), 83-84.</p>
          <p>Hartmann, Wolfgang. Die Wiederendeckung Dantes in der deutschen Kunst: J.H. Füssli, A.J. Carstens, J.A. Knoch. Reviewed by Christian Geelhaar, Pantheon, 28 (1970), 456-457.</p>
          <p>Howard, John. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: A Study in the Selfhood. Reviewed in Milton Quarterly, 10 (1970), 129.</p>
          <p>Keay, Carolyn, ed. William Blake Selected Engravings. Reviewed by Gerda Norvig and Myra Glazer Schotz, Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 90.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey L., ed. William Blake: Die Vermahlung von Himmel und Holle. Reviewed in Freie Presse/Prensa Libre [Buenos Aires], 8 January 1976; by E[duard] B[eaucamp], Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 8 August 1975; and in radio broadcasts by Bayerischer Rundfunk [Munich], 6 November 1975, and Osterreichischer Rundfunk, Studio Karnten, 15 December 1975.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey L., William Blake; Dichter, Drucker, Prophet. Reviewed in St. Galler Tagblatt, no. 438 (1965?); in Werk, Schweizer Monatschrift für Kunst, Architekur, Künsterlisches Gewerbe, 53 (1966); Curt Grützmacher, Die Kunst und das Schöne Heim, no. 1 (1966); Hans A. Halbey, Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 30 October 1965; Werner Helwig, Rheinische Post, 11 September 1965; Phillop Wolff-Windegg, Basler Nachrichten (1965?).</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. The Letters of Samuel Palmer. Reviewed by G. Reynolds in "Palmer as a Letter-Writer," Apollo, 102 (1975), 78-79; William Feaver, The Times Literary Supplement, 21 March 1975, 304.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. Samuel Palmer, A Biography. Reviewed by A.M. Smith, British Journal of Aesthetics, 16 (1976), 176-177; William Feaver, The Times Literary Supplement, 21 March 1975, 304; G. Reynolds, "Palmer as Letter-Writer," Apollo, 102 (1975), 78-79.</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. Blake’s Human Form Divine. Reviewed by Desiree Hirst, Review of English Studies, 27 (1976), 87-89.</p>
          <p>Miles, Josephine. Poetry and Change. Reviewed by Robert F. Gleckner, Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 133-136.</p>
          <p>Nurmi, Martin K. William Blake. Reviewed by Morton D. Paley in Review of English Studies, 27 (1976), 517.</p>
          <p>The Oothoon Dance Theatre. The Mental Traveller, a dance-drama based on the ballad by William Blake. Reviewed by Frank Parisi, Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 128-132. Includes six photographs and a scenario.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D., and Michael Phillips, eds. William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes. Reviewed by Stanley Gardner, Notes and Queries, n.s. 22 (1975), 82-83.</p>
          <p>Powell, Nicholas. Fuseli: The Nightmare. Reviewed by Heinfried Wischermann, Kunstchronik, 26 (1973), 181-184.</p>
          <p>Roberts, Mark. The Tradition of Romantic Morality. Reviewed by Leslie Tannenbaum, Blake Newsletter, 9 (1976), 126-128.</p>
          <p>Schiff, Gert. Johann Heinrich Füssli 1741-1825, OEuvrekatalog, 2 vols. Reviewed in Luzerner Tagblatt, 16 October 1973; Schaffhausener Nachrichten, 26 October 1973; The Times Literary Supplement, 24 May 1974; Eighteenth-Century Studies, 9 (1975), 270 ff.; by Herbert von Einem, Zeitschrift für Kunstgeschichte, 38 (1975), 320-324; Christiam Geelhaar, Neue Zürcher Zeitung, 10 November 1973; Laszlo Glozer, Süddeutsche Zeitung [Munich], 15 November 1973; Edwin Maria Landau, General-Anzeiger [Bonn], 28 November 1974 and on Radio Bremen, 8 December 1974; Klaus Lankheit, Kunstchronik, 27 (1974), 397-403; Norbert Miller, Die Zeit [Hamburg], 29 November 1974.</p>
          <p>Schiff, Gert, et al. Johann Heinrich Füssli 1741-1825, ed. Werner Hofmann [exhibition catalogue of the Hamburger Kunsthalle.] Reviewed in Saarbrückner Zeitung, 14/15 December 1974; Neue Zürcher Zeitung, 9 January 1975; by Eduard Beaucamp, Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 14 December 1974; by George Galweit, Schleswig-Holsteinische Landeszeitung [Rendsburg], 14 December 1974; by Gottfried Knapp, Süddeutsche Zeitung [Munich], 4/5/6 January 1975; by Peter Steinhart, Rheinische Post [Düsseldorf], 14 December 1974.</p>
          <p>Sellars, James. Samuel Palmer. Reviewed by William Feaver, The Times Literary Supplement, 21 March 1975, p. 304.</p>
          <p>Songs of William Blake and Music of Blake’s Time. [A concert at the University of California, Santa Barbara, 3 March 1976.] Reviewed by Martin K. Nurmi, Blake Newsletter, 10 (1977), 128-129.</p>
          <p>Wagenknecht, David. Blake’s Night. Reviewed by R.B. Kennedy, Notes and Queries, n.s. 22 (1975), 79-82.</p>
          <p>Weiskel, Thomas. The Romantic Sublime: Studies in the Structure and Psychology of Transcendence. Reviewed by Michael Fischer, Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 93-95.</p>
          <p>Wilner, Eleanor. Gathering the Winds: Visionary Imagination and Radical Transformation of Self and Society. Reviewed by Stephen C. Behrendt, Blake Newsletter, 10 (1976), 91-93.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. Angel of Apocalypse. Reviewed by Christopher Hill, Notes and Queries, n.s. 23 (1976), 69-71; Mary Lynn Johnson, Milton and the Romantics, 2 (1976), 1-10; Purvis E. Boyette, Blake Newsletter 10 (1976), 88-89; Brian Wilkie, English Language Notes, 14 (1976), 69-71.</p>
          <p>Wolf-Gumpold, Kaethe, William Blake—Versuch einer Einführung. Reviewed in Die Tat, 15 June 1965; in Der Staadtler-Brief, no. 12 (1965); in Neuer Bücherdunst, 13 (1966); in Badische Neueste Nachrichten, 1 June 1966; by Hans A. Halbey, Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 30 October 1965; and by R. Hootz, Der Literaturspiegel, no. 2 (1966).</p>
          <p>Wolf-Gumpold, Kaethe. William Blake; Painter: Poet: Visionary. Reviewed by John Tonge, The Press and Journal [Edinburgh], 25 October 1969.</p>
          <p>Wright, Andrew. Blake’s Job: A Commentary. Reviewed by Pamela Dunbar, Notes and Queries, n.s. 22 (1975), 85-86.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p11-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0005">
        <figure/>
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">William Blake: The Painter as Poet. An Exhibition Commemorating the 150th Anniversary of the Artist’s Death. March 19-May 29, 1977. Catalog by Donald A. Wolf, Tom Dargan, &amp; Erica Doctorow. Garden City, NY: Library Gallery, Adelphi University, 1977. 24 pp., 9 pls. (1 in color). $1.50.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Ruth</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Fine</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>As part of a University Blake Festival commemorating the 150th anniversary of the artist’s death, the exhibition <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter as Poet</hi> was held at the Swirbul Library Gallery, Adelphi University, Garden City, NY, from 19 March to 29 May. Donald A. Wolf, Chairman of Adelphi’s Department of English, Erica Doctorow, Head of the Fine Arts Library, and Tom Dargan, consultant from State University of New York, Stony Brook, organized the exhibition and wrote the accompanying illustrated catalogue. The catalogue is essentially a word-for-word record of the exhibition labels and other posted explanatory material, and I shall refer below either to labels or to catalogue entries depending upon the context. Either of the two designations may be assumed to describe both. The exhibition consisted of 41 objects—15 original Blake works borrowed from various collections as listed below, supplemented by facsimile items mainly drawn from the Swirbul Library’s Leipniker Blake Collection with loans from the Hofstra University Library and Lessing J. Rosenwald.</p>
          <p>The exhibition was housed in an entrance gallery space with standing cases along ore wall and table cases along a second. It was directed to the broad university audience, possibly serving as an introductory Blake experience for many. The cases were
<pb id="p11-111" n="111"/><figure/>
tightly filled but the installation was handsome; the works were placed upon felt and velvet of a brown-orange color similar to that used by Blake in surface printing, for example <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, Copy V or <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, Copy F.<ref target="n15" type="note">1</ref> Magnifying lenses permitted a clearer view of particular objects and the volumes rested on plexiglas cradles. Unfortunately, labels occasionally were placed so that a novice viewer might easily have been confused about which labels referred to which objects. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">1</hi> This color was used for the catalogue cover-stock, text, and illustrations as well as for printed material related to the other Blake Festival events—clearly an effort to visually emphasize for the public the relationship among the several activities. For the catalogue illustrations, the color is sympathetic to reproduction of Blake’s relief printed works, but the engravings and the drawing do suffer.</note></p>
          <p>According to the catalogue introduction, the exhibition (which was inclusive enough to indicate the rich texture of Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi> and the complexity of his mythology) "focuses on the ways in which art and poetry contribute to the totality of his vision; and in doing so it explores a central theme, the contraries of innocence and experience in his work." The introduction then provides Northrop Frye’s explanation of Blake’s contrary states of innocence and experience.<ref target="n16" type="note">2</ref> Lacking in both the catalogue introduction and the accumulated catalogue entries was a broad statement explaining the relationships between the particular exhibited works in the context of Blake’s contraries of innocence and experience. Also, given that the exhibition was directed to a non-specialist audience, it would have been helpful if some explanation of Blake’s total system (of which this pair of contraries was a part) had been offered in the descriptive material. For the books, a paragraph summarizing the essential bibliographical information and more importantly the content or themes of volumes, followed by brief explanatory labels for each plate, would have helped make the exhibition easier to grasp than the repetitive (especially with the bibliographical material), somewhat fragmented labels that were provided.<ref target="n17" type="note">3</ref> As this review is to be of both the exhibition and the catalogue (unpublished labels are not the same as a published catalogue, even if the material is identical), I feel obligated to make one initial distinction—the selection of objects (the exhibition) was much richer than the explanatory material (the catalogue), which was more spirited than informative. <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Northrop Frye, ed., <hi rend="i">Selected Poetry and Prose of</hi> [<hi rend="i">William</hi>] <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (New York: Random House, 1953), pp. xxv-xxvii.</note><note id="n17"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Summaries and explanatory material were inconsistent in quantity and quality. For example, no overall picture was presented for <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, while for <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, one was. In this regard, it is difficult to accept as explanation that "<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> is a feminist tragedy and something of a puzzle" (cat. 20). Interpretive entries at times lacked clarity. In some instances this results from the fragmentary presentation. For example, cat. 25 by implication refers back to cat. 24 in contrasting two "perspective(s)" on Urizen. Some entries are internally confusing, as in cat. 30, where in a description of plate 2 from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem, Milton</hi> is quoted without indicating the source. The entry is further unclear as to what a "labor hymn" is and whether the phrase refers to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the work being described, or <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, the work being quoted. Facts, too, sometimes require clarification. In cat. 38, while the inscription on plate 1 of <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> may indeed be read as "1828," one presumes this is an error for 1825.</note></p>
          <p>Along with one copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (Trianon facsimile) and one of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (Muir facsimile) were two copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (both Trianon); <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> presented in two copies (Trianon and Brown University Press facsimiles); <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> in three copies (two Trianon and one Hotten facsimile). <hi rend="i">America, A Prophecy</hi> was presented both in facsimile and
<pb id="p11-112" n="112"/>
the original; the facsimiles were two copies of the Trianon edition, and the electrotype made from the copperplate fragment of cancelled plate "a" (in copy a* not A* as in cat. 19) in the National Gallery of Art, Rosenwald Collection. Importantly, the exhibition included the hand colored <hi rend="i">America</hi> frontispiece from the Philip H. and A. S. W. Rosenbach Foundation. Also on loan from the Rosenbach Foundation were the title page and frontispiece from <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (Copy H) and the title page from <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi><ref target="n18" type="note">4</ref><hi rend="i">Visions</hi> was further presented in two facsimiles (Muir and Trianon), <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> in one (Trianon). <hi rend="i">Europe, A Prophecy</hi> was represented by the hand colored frontispiece "The Ancient of Days" from the Rosenbach Foundation and plate 11 (uncolored) on loan from the Philadelphia Museum of Art. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los, Milton, A Poem</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> were all shown in Trianon Press facsimiles. An impression of <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, on loan from the Philadelphia Museum of Art, further demonstrated Blake’s work in relief printing. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Editorial inconsistencies which affect the quality of the information occur throughout the catalogue. To cite one example, the Rosenbach <hi rend="i">America</hi> frontispiece (cat. 17) is described as "Relief etching printed in blue painted with tan and blue watercolors" while the Rosenbach <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> title page and frontispiece (cat. 20 and 22) are described as "Relief etching painted with watercolors." One might also note such editorial problems as the fact that both of Northrop Frye’s names are misspelled in the footnote to the Introduction.</note></p>
          <p>Blake as an engraver was seen in <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> on loan from Maxine S. Cronbach, <hi rend="i">Christ Trampling Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, the latter two lent by R. John Blackley, and from The Art Museum, Princeton University, four plates from <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, and restrikes from two of the seven (not six as stated in cat. 39) <hi rend="i">Illustrations of Dante</hi>, printed in 1968 from the engraved plates in the National Gallery of Art, Rosenwald Collection. The one drawing in the exhibition was one of the wash drawings from the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> series, "Tiriel Dead Before Hela" (lent anonymously).</p>
          <p>Because the exhibition in several instances included more than one facsimile of a given book, one was able to see several plates from one book, or, when different facsimile editions (from various copies) were used, to focus on the variations Blake made on one plate. While this aspect of Blake’s investigative spirit was both implied and demonstrated by the exhibition, it was not pointed out or discussed; neither were the very real differences between facsimiles and originals. Adelphi was fortunate in obtaining several significant originals which made these differences clear but they might not have been noted by the novice viewer. A most cogent demonstration of the differences in the tactile life of printed surfaces and their effects on one’s responses to works of art might have been made by comparing the Trianon copy of <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> with any of the original engravings on exhibition. Attention might well have been brought to this difference, as well as to the variations in the quality and character of the different facsimile editions. I don’t mean to suggest that this ought to have been a major concentration but, rather, that within the context of an exhibition these points are important if the viewer is to see the significance of the nuances in Blake’s visual art.</p>
          <p>The focus of the Adelphi exhibition was not one of art historical or bibliographical analysis or explication. The catalogue was undoubtedly published within a limited timespan and budget. It seems desirable, however, that certain basic information be included. To cite a few desiderata: one would like to have page or entry numbers throughout for references cited; would like to know that the impression of <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> was in the fourth state (cat. 1); that the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> drawing is one of 9 extant of a presumed series of 12, and something about the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> poem other than that it "is about an old man who was really dead before his day, a despairing wanderer who cursed his children" (cat. 11); that the 1868 (J. C., not T. C.) Hotten facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> was the first published facsimile of a Blake illuminated book (cat. 9); be assured that inscriptions are accurately quoted, as, for example, the ones from <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi> (cat. 34) and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi> (cat. 41) which are not;<ref target="n19" type="note">5</ref> "Experts" and "pupil" are best mentioned by name (because Keynes’ <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi> is cited, one assumes that reference is being made to Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Thomas Butts, Jr. or Sr., cat.26); and finally, I have reservations about the words and phrases quoted throughout without citation. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">5</hi> "printed &amp; sold by the Widow Spicer of Folkstone for the benefit of her orphans." should read "Printed for &amp; Sold by the Widow Spicer of Folkstone / for the Benefit of her Orphans / October 5, 1800" and "W Blake inv &amp; sc: A AE 1827." should read "W Blake inv &amp; sc: / A Æ 70 1827."</note></p>
          <p>Unfortunately, the catalogue perpetuates some fallacies. For example, to describe Blake in the introduction as having "found a way through his contemporary wasteland of indifference, ignorance and dullness" does a disservice to late 18th and early 19th century England.<ref target="n20" type="note">6</ref> To say that "Blake should be read with imagination. The reasoning intellect can tag along if it can keep up . . . " (cat. 1) does a disservice to Blake’s contraries of reason and imagination. While Blake’s process for applying his texts to metal plates and his relief printing techniques may remain "Blake’s secret(s)" (cat. 19), not mentioning some of the recent experiments and theories related to these methods does a disservice to contemporary artists and scholars.<ref target="n21" type="note">7</ref> Furthermore, it seems shortsighted to state (in the introduction) that Blake was "neglected, regarded as an eccentric or a madman" by his contemporaries.<ref target="n22" type="note">8</ref><note id="n20"><hi rend="s">6</hi> As a recent and convincing denial of this premise, one might note Corlette Rossiter Walker’s <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of His Time</hi>, the catalogue for an exhibition held at the University Art Galleries, University of California at Santa Barbara, 24 February to 28 March 1976.</note><note id="n21"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Robert N. Essick, ed., <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand: Essays for the Study of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics</hi> (Los Angeles: Hennessey &amp; Inqalls, 1973), Part I: "Blake’s Techniques of Relief Etching: Sources and Experiments," pp. 7-44 (includes Ruthven Todd’s essay "The Techniques of William Blake’s Illuminated Printing" originally published in <hi rend="i">The Print Collector’s Quarterly</hi>, 29 (Nov. 1948), here published with Todd’s revisions of the notes and new illustrations and (p. 44) the editor’s list of sources for other brief descriptions of the relief etching process); John W. Wright, "Blake’s Relief-Etching Method," <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 36(Spring 1976), pp. 94-114; Robert N. Essick, "William Blake as an Engraver and Etcher," pp. 16-17 in Walker, <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of His Time</hi>, op. cit.</note><note id="n22"><hi rend="s">8</hi> A less negative possibility is presented by Suzanne R. Hoover in her essay "William Blake in the Wilderness: A Closer Look at his Reputation, 1827-1863," published in Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips, eds., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973), pp. 310-48. While the essay attends to the period after Blake’s death, on p. 312 Hoover notes that "Of the seven obituaries that are known, one is derisive, but the others are appreciative."</note></p>
          <p>The Adelphi Swirbul Library exhibition brings into focus some problems facing Blake studies and also presents possibilities for future Blake exhibitions. While one laments the extensive use of facsimile objects (especially without adequate explanatory material), it has become clear that important unique Blake works (and one generally considers each copy of his books as unique) will be more and more difficult to obtain for other than major exhibitions (i.e., those that will both attract large audiences and make scholarly contributions via well-researched and imaginative catalogues). The organizers of the Adelphi exhibition indicated that institutions which in the past have been most generous in lending their other holdings for exhibitions were hesitant to release the Blake items. It is admirable that they organized their exhibition in spite of this obstacle. It seems that in the near future organizing an exhibition like <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Apocalyptic Vision</hi> held at Manhattanville College in Purchase, NY in 1974<ref target="n23" type="note">9</ref> will be difficult except in special circumstances. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">9</hi> This exhibition, also held at a small, not centrally located educational institution, included several very important Blake watercolors and drawings as well as superb plates from the illuminated books. It was accompanied by an illustrated catalogue.</note></p>
          <p>Since 1974 the number of requests to borrow Blake material for exhibitions has increased dramatically. Various factors make repeated lending a problem. The primary one is concern for the care and preservation of the objects; increasing knowledge in the field of paper conservation has made many of us alter
<pb id="p11-113" n="113"/><figure><head>Frontispiece and Titlepage, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter as Poet</hi>, catalogue of the Adelphi exhibition.</head></figure>
our long-range views about exhibitions. Also, Blake material is so extensively studied at home institutions (in itself a danger to the preservation of the objects) that one feels an obligation to try to have it available for persons who travel great distances and at great expense in anticipation of viewing particular works. From the standpoint of borrowing institutions, insurance costs have become prohibitive. One suspects, therefore, that many institutions may have to make use of facsimile material in organizing small instructional exhibitions such as this, which was reviewed at length by the press<ref target="n24" type="note">10</ref> and enthusiastically received by the University community. <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Garden City, N.Y., <hi rend="i">Newsday</hi>, 13 May 1977, p. 11a, and <hi rend="i">The New York Times</hi>, Long Island Supplement, 15 May 1977, p. 24.</note></p>
          <p>Adelphi’s Blake festival included several inter-disiplinary programs which took place concurrently with the exhibition—Tom Dargan’s illustrated talk, "Engraving Lessons from a Favorite Angel: William Blake’s Secret Printing Process;" "Eternity in an Hour" including "The Spoken Word," readings arranged and directed by Nancy Miller and read by the University’s Story Players, and "The Visual Image," a modern dance piece inspired by Blake’s poetry (with choreography by Norman Walker, music by Britten, lighting by Randy Klein, and costumes by Linda Cliggett) which was performed by the senior dance majors; and the world premiere of a structuralist opera, commissioned especially for the Blake Festival, "Willy" or "Auguries of Innocence." The opera was written and directed by Jacques Burdick and Thomas Vuozzo and performed by students in the Theatre Program. According to Mr. Burdick, Director of the Department of Performing Arts Theatre Program, the opera based on Blake’s life, times, visions, and works began as a class project in a Radical Theatre course concerned with the structuralist tenets of the French linguist Jacques Lacan. The particular problem was how to translate Blake’s vision to sound. When it became apparent that the project as envisioned would become a five or six hour trilogy, the group determined to concern itself, for the time, with only the first part, "Willy" (Blake’s use of his powers of sight in infancy and youth). The remaining two sections are conceived as "Will Blake" (youth and maturity) and "Mr. William Blake" (Blake’s prophetic powers in old age). Mr. Burdick noted in the program that the group was hoping for financial assistance to "stir up ‘Willy’ and allow him to spring, like the phoenix, into the triple flight of a complete realization of our project."</p>
          <p>A lighter facet of the Blake Festival was the production of Blake tee-shirts. Available from the same address as the catalogue, the tee-shirts bear Blake’s autograph (Berg Collection, New York Public Library), and come in sizes S, M, L, XL, in yellow, red, blue, white, royal and brown. The cost is $5 + .50 shipping. The University requests prepayment for the exhibition catalogue and the tee-shirts.</p>
          <pb id="p11-114" n="114"/>
          <p>The exhibition catalogue is available from the Fine Arts Library, Adelphi University, Garden City, NY 11530, for $1 + .50 shipping.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Poetic Form in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Susan Fox. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1976. 242 pp. $13.50.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Joseph Anthony</hi><name><hi rend="b">Wittreich</hi></name>, <hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Not so long ago, F. R. Leavis spurned Blake’s late prophecies as not worth reading and, because laden with obscurities, as neither intelligible nor interpretable. Subsequently, the <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> celebrated Leavis for setting forth an essential truth from which Blake studies might now proceed. Never before the subject of a book, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, it seemed, might not now elicit a book—at least not until there had been a major reversal in critical thinking. That reversal, however, was already under-way, with the epoch-making studies of Northrop Frye and Harold Bloom prompting David Erdman’s annotations for the <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> designs, together with the wonderfully incisive essays by E. J. Rose, W. J. T. Mitchell, and Florence Sandler. <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, despite Leavis, was drawing forth an important body of commentary that shortly would culminate in the publication of two books, within months of one another: one of them is by John Howard, and the other (here under review) by Susan Fox. Fox’s <hi rend="i">Poetic Form in Blake’s Milton</hi>, even if narrowly conceived, is an important addition to Blake studies: this is a splendidly perceptive book, which, nevertheless, is somewhat long on the minutiae of Blake’s poem and correspondingly short on a historical sense that might explain them; still, the book is prodigiously argued, keenly sensitive to Blake’s text, deft in dealing with its complexities, and (what today is rare) both lucidly and elegantly written. Whatever its defects, <hi rend="i">Poetic Form in Blake’s Milton</hi> has the virtue of illuminating the structure of one poem and, through that analysis, of shedding light on those formal features that come increasingly to govern Blake’s art.</p>
          <p>Fox’s commentary terminates in a question: "Why should Blake deliberately call two books twelve?" Then comes a declaration, "Whether that means he was . . . thinking about the structure of his poem, . . . or . . . not thinking about it all, seems to me moot." Declaration, in turn, yields to conjecture—"Perhaps Blake was merely enjoying some prophetic private joke"—followed by yet another question: "Do those ten unwritten books represent Blake’s ten lost tribes?" (p. 238). In this coda, we see at once the strengths and deficiencies of Fox’s study: it is everywhere imaginatively responsive to Blake’s art, always provocative—a question-asking, consciousness-raising book; yet the boundaries of its consciousness are set by Blake’s canon and so never extend outward
<pb id="p11-115" n="115"/><figure/>
to embrace those traditions that might help explain the puzzles created by a poem like <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> This study gives little attention to literary analogues, and none to literary models, except for John’s Book of Revelation, which it never really admits to be a model.</p>
          <p>Whether <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> should be called an epic is disputable; however, indisputably, the poem is lodged in the epic tradition, and that tradition historically has focused on the question of a book’s integrity. Homer did not, of course, divide his epics into books—the book divisions are instead the invention of his editors. And as Blake must have known, the problem of the "book" was very much on the mind of Spenser, Milton, and the critics of both poets. In his letter to Raleigh, Spenser promises an epic in twelve books but then delivers only six. Milton published <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> first in ten books but later revised the poem into a twelve-book structure. What to say of Blake’s proclaiming <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> to be a poem in twelve books is problematical in the extreme; but whatever <hi rend="i">is</hi> said, I suspect, must allow the convention of broken expectations and explore Blake’s strategy in terms of it, taking some hints from the tradition itself. <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi>, for example, may not issue forth in twelve books, but each book <hi rend="i">is</hi> composed of twelve cantos. By implication, we are thus dealing with six epic patterns, epic within epic, patterns that the poem’s outer structure conceals. By way of explaining Milton’s decision to change from a ten- to a twelve-book structure when <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> went into a second edition, it has been suggested that Milton was motivated by a fear that, unless presented in twelve books, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> would never be recognized for what it is. But such an explanation misses the central point: there are <hi rend="i">two</hi> traditions of epic, the one classical and the other Christian; and both these traditions progress by systematically reducing the number of books that constitute an epic. Thus we move, in one tradition, from Homer (24), to Virgil (12), to Spenser (6)—and in the other tradition from Dante (100), to Tasso (20), to Milton (10). What is curious about Milton’s modification of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>’s book-structure is that he dislodges his poem from the very tradition to which it belongs, lodging it instead in the tradition that <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> would subvert. There is special propriety in Milton’s strategy here, for in a poem that pits epic against prophecy, treating them as countergenres, it is appropriate for outer structure (mechanical form) to contend with inner form (the sevenfold pattern of prophecy).</p>
          <p>What are we to infer from all this: that calculated confusion over the number of books is a device for indicating the essential incompleteness of <hi rend="i">all</hi> epic poems? that playing with numbers evinces not only a profound consciousness of structure but a desire through numbers to discriminate outer structure from inner form? that numbers themselves symbolize other poems which the new poet would displace (Milton, the <hi rend="i">Aeneid</hi>; Blake, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>)? Are we to remember the principle of progression by systematic reduction, and thus the fact that the epic line moves from <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> (a poem in four books) to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (a poem in two)? Is it important that the outer structure of these two poems conceals, in each instance, a tripartite design? These are the kinds of questions that Fox’s book might have raised—but doesn’t. On the other hand, there are many questions that her book does raise and, what is more, pursues to intelligent resolution.</p>
          <p>Two lengthy, substantial chapters (ii and iii) elaborate the structural principles operative in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, elucidating the complex patterns those principles generate. Symmetry, elaborate parallelism, interruptions and revisions, manifold repetitions and layered organization, alternating perspectives, disrupted time-sequences—these are the devices, <hi rend="i">all of them</hi> hallmarks of prophetic literature it should have been noted, which are called upon to explain the peculiar features of Blake’s poetry, especially <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, a poem that is both "intricately and suggestively formed" (p. xiii). This poem’s structure, according to Fox, finds its prototype in <hi rend="i">Europe, a Prophecy</hi> (another poem marked by the principles of simultaneity and perspectivism) and its contrasting type in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, a poem, as Fox would have it, that, linear in design, is "plotted progressively" (p. 14). (On prototypical structures in Blake’s early poetry, William Halloran’s "Revelation’s ‘New’ Form" should have been mentioned; and on the structure of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Stuart Curran’s "The Structures of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>" might have been cited.) Perspectivism and simultaneity, however, are not represented as the ultimate controls of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>’s structure. Rather, the principle that organizes that poem
<pb id="p11-116" n="116"/>
is said to be parallelism: "Accruing definitions, simultaneity, multiple perspectives all are organized in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> by the elaborate system of parallels that is the poem’s basic framework" (p. 24). In these terms, Books I and II are shown to be correspondent and their various parts (each book is shown to be threefold in design) to be correspondent. Book I expounds the myth of which Book II is a personal realization; the poem begins by prophesying, through the voice of the Bard, the action that climaxes Book II. The structure of this second book, Fox argues, exactly parallels that of Book I: "Each has three major parts, a prologue of events leading to an act of union, a refracted account of that union, and an epilogue expanding upon a vision associated with that union" (p. 128). The argument is both tidy and convincing; and it is supported by a profusion of detail—is augmented by rich, impressive interpretations.</p>
          <p>Yet there are problems here: inconsistencies and even contradictions that go back to Fox’s early declaration that "the ‘epic’ structure of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is largely illusory, that Blake uses it only as a superficial organizing device and so undermines it" (p. 14 n.). What, in this context, are we to make of the fact that salient symmetries and balances, persistent parallels and repetitions (what Fox calls the primary organizational principles in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>) are historically the devices of the epic poet—and of the fact that the subsidiary devices of perspectivism and simultaneity are, again historically, the chief attributes of prophetic literature? By Fox’s own analysis, it is mechanical structure that here subdues living form, rather than the other way around; and by her own admission, this analysis has focused attention on the "illusory," "superficial" devices of epic—not, it would appear, on the real, central strategies of prophetic structuring.</p>
          <p>There are other problems besides, first of all with the book’s critical idiom. Its tendency is to eradicate rather than observe time-honored distinctions such as between form and structure, even as it fashions distinctions (between bardic and visionary techniques [p. 191], for instance), which confuse more than ‘they clarify. The former tendency is particularly regrettable, for the blurred distinction might have focused attention where it finally belongs—on the two contending structures in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> which derive from the poem’s countergenres, epic and prophecy. Correspondingly, where distinctions are drawn, as between visionary and narrative coherence (p. xi), Fox oddly reverses the meanings such terms have accrued. Thus, visionary coherence here refers to thematic structure and is to be distinguished from narrative, poetic, rhetorical structure (those terms are used interchangeably). Confusion reigns when structures are conflated and treated as if they were one. After all, Blake’s is a poetry not of one but of many structures.</p>
          <p>Most distressing, though, is the amount of waffling in this book—and waffling on crucial issues. The Preface, for example, quite rightly associates the structural devices of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> "with the visionary forms of Isaiah, Ezekiel, Daniel, and especially Revelation" (p. xii) and, I think mistakenly, enters a demurral when it comes to arguing "that Blake consciously devised the structure of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> according to the principles delineated in this study" (p. xiii). But in the course of this study, <hi rend="i">both</hi> these suppositions are reversed as we are told: "That St. John deliberately built his vision on these complex structural principles I do not propose. That Blake did . . . I am certain" (p. 187). And: "I do not mean . . . to imply that St. John was writing a Blakean poem . . . The design of the book of Revelation arises from far different conventions and necessities from those of early nineteenth-century England" (p. 186). That proposition requires an explanation that is never forthcoming. Is it important to know that through the ages John’s New Testament prophecy was always distinguished from Old Testament prophecies—on these grounds: in the Old, we are given the visions of Isaiah, Ezekiel, of Jeremiah and of Daniel; but in the New, we are given not the vision of John but the vision of Jesus Christ? Old Testament prophecy is thus the embodiment of impaired human vision, whereas the Apocalypse is an example of divine vision. Accordingly, the book of Revelation was exalted as a perfect pattern of prophecy, as <hi rend="i">the</hi> model for all aspiring prophets to observe. Authenticated by Christ himself, its structural conventions, its whole aesthetic, had very special authority for the Christian poet.</p>
          <p>More than any other scriptural book, the Apocalypse was thought to embody the great code of Christian art. One commentator may be cited by way of suggesting the pertinence of this whole tradition to a structural analysis of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Johann Bengel, in <hi rend="i">Bengelius’s Introduction to His Exposition of the Apocalypse</hi> (1757), speaks of "the exact coherent order" of the Apocalypse, which he proceeds to describe as being "like a piece of musick" all of whose parts "are beautifully interwoven; and like the pipes and stops of an Organ, at times some of them are silent, at others again all of them sound aloud together." And, says Bengel, "this very regularly disposed system brings it’s key along with it," its key being its structure and its structure being marked by these features:
<q>
(1) . . . elegant <hi rend="i">Simultaneum</hi> . . . by which . . . two things, that belong precisely to the same time, is often divided into two parts, and, as it were, split; and the other comes in unexpectedly between these two parts, as a parenthesis.<lb/><lb/>
(2) Wonderful, and very conspicuous in all this, is the Gradation in which the <hi rend="i">Evil</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Good</hi> always advance and increase, till they come to the utmost conflict with one another . . .
</q>
Aware that the number seven figures prominently in prophetic writing, Bengel nevertheless suggests that sevens are divided into fours and threes so that fours "are directed to the four Quarters of the world" and threes "relate in some measure to invisible things" (see pp. 65, 111-14, 115-16, 125-26). There is nothing new here-nothing that cannot be found treated more expansively in the work of David Pareus, Joseph Mede, Henry More, and Isaac Newton who together must be credited with unlocking the secrets of Revelation’s structure. Bengel introduces into his commentary, though, this observation: "the Revelation . . . is
<pb id="p11-117" n="117"/>
. . . so contrived that the other Prophets are not necessary for the understanding of it; but it is rather necessary for the understanding of them" (p. 65). That observation leaves us with this haunting question: if so, to what extent is a prophet like Blake dependent upon the book of Revelation; how important is an understanding of that prophecy to an understanding of his prophecies?</p>
          <p>Fox has answered that question in one way—"not very important at all"; but I think that students of Blake will eventually answer differently: "it is very important, indeed." The context of prophetic literature, missing from Fox’s book, would have saved her from exaggerated claims for Blake’s uniqueness. "The structure of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is unique" (p. 3), we are told; and its "uniqueness . . . is that in its controlling as well as in its underlying structures it seeks to tell the same story ‘in several ways at the same time and at several times in the same way.’" (p. 24). When we have come to know more about the tradition of Revelation commentary, we will come to realize that this is precisely the claim made for that book’s uniqueness of structure, which by Mede first, then by More, and finally by Newton is discussed under the rubric of <hi rend="i">synchronism.</hi></p>
          <p>These commentators, indeed, turn one of Fox’s offhand remarks into a question that future students of both Blake and romanticism will have to confront: Which supposition is nearer the truth—that biblical prophecy and romantic poetry arise from very different cultures, predications, needs, and aspirations; or, that biblical prophecy generates the poetic on which romantic poetry is founded and represents, finally, the ur-form of all romantic literature? That question cannot be answered satisfactorily until, like the poets they are studying, students go back to the Bible, to its commentators, to the very tradition of prophecy of which Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is a mighty emanation.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell. William Blake. Drawings by Clark Stewart: Knoxville, TN: Darkpool Press, 1972. 35 pp., 13 pls. $55. Order from F. Clark Stewart, Art Department, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN 37916. Edition of 100 copies, numbered and signed by the author.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Judith</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Ott</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Clark Stewart’s drawings for <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> will cause mixed reactions in many a Blake enthusiast. Intended as a personal response to Blake’s visionary cosmology, Stewart’s designs incorporate familiar Blakean motifs (mundane shell, batwinged spectre, and flocks of
<figure/>
sheep) with some wildly disparate ones (World War I and II planes and tanks, top hats and a jack-o-lantern). As a result, the combined images in these drawings create a simultaneous sensation of déjà vu and culture shock in the viewer. This kind of liberal play within the hallowed territory of Blake’s own illustrations may well be frowned upon by the Blake purist. However, seen as an extension of—rather than an intrusion upon—Blake’s designs, these drawings present a fresh interpretration of the artistpoet’s well-thumbed iconographical system.</p>
          <p>In style, Stewart’s drawings are of a gorgeously detailed, linear character not unlike the graphic works of Dürer. They display the variety of texture, depth of space, crinkled drapery patterns and tightly packed compositions that characterize works of the Northern Renaissance. Although Blake often borrowed from such engravings, he inevitably simplified the figures and flattened the spatial representations in his own work. Thus, with their Northern Renaissance flavor, Stewart’s illustrations resemble Blakean, sources more closely than Blake designs. Both Blake and Dürer were skilled at combining many different symbolic elements into a cohesive whole. Unfortunately, Stewart’s compositions lack this quality and too often appear overworked, disjointed or contrived e.g., pls. 7, 11, 13). The unifying device of a frame is only successful in some of the designs
<pb id="p11-118" n="118"/><figure/><pb id="p11-119" n="119"/><figure/>
(pls. 1, 3, 8, 10)—generally the compositions suffer from a non-integrated eclecticism.</p>
          <p>Iconographically, Stewart borrows much from Yeats and the Christian mystical-magical symbolism of the Rosicrucians (pls. 1, 4, 7, 9). The rose and other emblems like the stag and horned goat have a prominence in these drawings that is foreign to Blake. But Blake is certainly the main source of Stewart’s imagery and some of his drawings follow the text of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> closely. Plate 8 is clearly the "Printing House in Hell," complete with Dragon-Man, viper, eagle, lion (shown as a cat) and books "arranged in libraries" (Blake and Stewart’s books among them). Many of the other illustrations can be convincingly linked with a line from the text: plate 6 with the poet "sitting on a pleasant bank beside a river by moonlight"; plate 5 with "man [who] has closed himself up, till he sees all things thro’ narrow chinks of his cavern"l and plate 4 with " a mighty Devil folded in black clouds, hovering on the sides of a rock."</p>
          <p>There are other drawings by Stewart that owe more to Blake’s images than to his text. Plates 1 and 2 compare in theme with Blake’s title-page for <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> and plate 3 seems to elaborate on the image of "The Sick Rose" from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> Although there is much of Blake in these drawings, Stewart has not attempted to illustrate <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> literally. Each of his plates contain fresh and intriguing combinations of old and new motifs and this is their greatest strength. Significantly, Stewart is most successful in the few designs in which he goes beyond the text. For example, plate 12 represents the "cherub with flaming sword" with an intense visionary grandeur comparable to Blake’s own.</p>
          <p>In a well-bound, signed and limited edition, Clark Stewart’s illustrations for <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> should be of interest to any Blake admirer who has struggled with the poet-artist’s complex visions in the past, knows the joys born of careful thought and close observation, and is willing to apply these techniques to the work of another. As with Blake’s illustrations to the works of other poets, Stewart’s drawings inevitably reveal more about the illustrator than about the subject being illustrated. Those who would seek only an echo of Blake’s imagery should look elsewhere.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Raw Material [Matière Première] by Denis Roche, and For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise [Pour les Sexes: Les Grilles de Paradise] by William Blake. Paris: L’Energumène (31, Rue Victor-Duruy, 75015).</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">L’Energumène</hi>, a collection linked to the journal of the same name, presents a combined volume, unless it be only one book of mirrors and reflections. Denis Roche provides the reader with his translation of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> by William Blake. These are short poems which either frame a series of prints (run off by the poet on 17 May 1793), or provide them with a title.</p>
          <p>Denis Roche does not utilize the traditional preface or introduction. Instead, he makes use of an ensemble of poetry, narrative, and criticism which might be characterized as poetic fiction or creative reading. It should be noted that there is often little more than a slight phonetic slippage separating poetics from politics. This is made apparent to the reader by the appearance of Fourier, Herbért, Restif and Sade in the black romantic and red revolutionary landscape of William Blake’s time, or of Denis Roche’s inner realm.</p>
          <p>Denis Roche rereads Blake, follows him in his garden (where he and his wife played Adam and Eve), or into his studio in front of his plates, where he engraves his illuminations in the form of words and drawings. Denis Roche seeks out, brings to light, makes audible and visible that which constitutes for Blake (but also for himself, as author of <hi rend="i">Louve Basse</hi>) the raw material of writing—the bursting forth of words, images, and phantasms.</p>
          <p>Reprinted by permission from <hi rend="i">Les Nouvelles Littéraires</hi>, 26 May 1976, no. 2534, p. 32. Contributed by Katharyn R. Gabriella and translated by Claude-Marie Senninger of the University of New Mexico.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p11-120" n="120"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>BLAKE’S "WARRING ANGELS"</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Frances <name>Carey</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>A hitherto unknown drawing from the early part of Blake’s career appeared in a Christie’s sale on 3 August 1976, where it was purchased by Thos. Agnew and Sons, Ltd., who have included it in their 104th exhibition of watercolors and drawings (17 January-18 February 1977, cat. no. 11). The composition on the recto, <hi rend="i">Warring Angels</hi> (illus. 1), is one of three versions of this subject, the other two belonging to the Tonner Collection, now in the Philadelphia Museum (64-110-6), and to the Graham Robertson Collection (no. 97 in the sale catalogue of 1947). A fourth drawing of the same subject is to be found in the British Museum (1874-12-12-140, 141); this is much later in date and should be associated with Blake’s illustrations to Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> rather than his "juvenilia." Of the three early versions in question, Agnew’s drawing is the most fully developed composition and the Graham Robertson sketch, the most perfunctory. The subject matter is, itself, of interest, when seen in conjunction with a number of drawings from Lady Melchett’s collection (<hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Gods</hi>, Christie’s sale 9 November 1971, no. 78; <hi rend="i">Adam and Eve</hi>, Christie’s 9 November 1976, no. 78), which are proof of Blake’s intention to execute a series of Miltonic illustrations as early as c. 1780.</p>
          <figure>
            <head>1 Recto: Warring Angels c. 1780.</head>
            <figDesc>Pen, ink and wash. 238 × 330 mm.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p11-121" n="121"/>
          <figure/>
          <pb id="p11-122" n="122"/>
          <figure/>
          <pb id="p11-123" n="123"/>
          <figure>
            <head>2 Verso: Academic Studies.</head>
            <figDesc>Pencil.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>On the verso of the sheet are studies of a leg and foot (illus. 2) which probably relate to Blake’s student exercises at the Royal Academy, where he enrolled in 1779.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>MR. RUDALL, THE FLAUTIST: AN AUTHENTIC BLAKE ANECDOTE</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Raymond H. <name>Deck</name>, Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <q>
. . . when Mr. Rudall, the flautist, called upon him at his poor lodging near Clare Market, the mystic told his visitor that he had a palace of his own of great beauty and magnificence. On Mr. Rudall’s looking round the room for evidence, Blake remarked, "You don’t think I’m such a fool as to think this is it."
</q>
          <p>The residence in question is Blake’s apartment at 3 Fountain Court, where he lived from 1821 until his death; Clare Market, which has not survived into the twentieth century, is an extension of the Vere Street which lies at the extreme right center of that portion of Horwood’s <hi rend="i">Plan of the Cities of London and Westminster</hi> reproduced in Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Plate LIX, pp. 564-65). For a description of this apartment as it might have appeared to Mr. Rudall’s "corporeal eye," see Bentley’s "William Blake, Samuel Palmer, and George Richardson," <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 2 (Spring 1970), 43-48.</p>
          <p>Blake’s encounter with Mr. Rudall is reported by James Spilling, an English Swedenborgian, in "Blake the Visionary," <hi rend="i">New Church Magazine</hi>, 6 (1887), 209. Spilling explains that his source for the anecdote is J. J. Garth Wilkinson, the Swedenborgian who published the first letterpress edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in 1839. Spilling’s report begins: "He saw and drew his own residence at Felpham differently to what it appeared to anyone else. It was in this spirit that, as we are informed by Dr. Wilkinson, when Mr. Rudall, the flautist. . . . " Wilkinson in turn probably had his information from Charles Augustus Tulk, Blake’s Swedenborgian patron during the last decade of the poet’s life, who in 1838 introduced Wilkinson to Blake’s work and loaned him the copy of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> used as the copy text for the 1839 edition.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p11-124" n="124"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>JEAN PAUL FRIEDRICH RICHTER AND BLAKE’S <hi rend="i">NIGHT THOUGHTS</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Detlef W. <name>Dörrbecker</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Writing an essay which was later printed in the catalog of the Hamburg Blake exhibition, Werner Hofmann recently made a discovery in the field of early allusions to Blake.<ref target="n25" type="note">1</ref> Thus, he added another item to our Blake Records which hitherto obviously passed the eyes of Blake scholars unnoticed. This I thought important enough to be published in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, and thus to make it known to more than just the few German speaking Blakists who might read Hofmann’s article, and then go on to look up the original sources for themselves. <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Werner Hofmann, ‘Die Erfüllung der Zeit," in <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827</hi>, [Kunst um 1800], exhb. cat., ed. W. Hofmann (Munich: Prestel-Verlag, 1975); see p. 25 and notes 47, 48 and 52 on pg. 29.</note></p>
          <p>Hofmann pointed out that the <hi rend="i">Vorschule der ästhetik</hi> written by Jean Paul (who in English speaking countries is better known as Jean Paul Friedrich Richter), and first published in 1804, contains what is probably the first mention of Blake ever to appear in print in Germany. As early as 1801 a copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrated with Blake’s engravings was anonymously given to Jean Paul by Emil August, the Hereditary Prince of Gotha. On receiving this valuable present the German poet immediately referred to the book and Blake’s plates in two of his letters. Following Prof. Hofmann’s hint, I here quote the relevant passages in full. In the first of these letters (which is preserved in a contemporary [?] copy only) Jean Paul thanks the donor, whom he pretends not to know:
<q>
An Erbprinz Emil August von Gotha.<lb/>
[Meiningen, 20 November 1801]<lb/><lb/>
Vorgestern erhielt ich ein Geschenk, das mich zu einer Bitte nöthigt, deren Erfüllung das zweite ist. Youngs Nachtgedanken, die ich mit meinen eigenen vermehrte, um vergeblich zu errathen, welcher reichen Hand in der Wolke ich die Gabe verdanke. Wenn Sie, wie ich vermuthen kan, die Youngische Verklärung durch Blake—hier der englische Titel [The Complaint, and the Consolation; or Night Thoughts, by Edward Young, London 1797]—vielleicht gesehen: so finden Sie meinen Wunsch zu danken gewis gerecht und den Weg dazu verzeihlich.—Die metall[ische] und künst[erische] Kostbarkeit<ref target="n26" type="note">2</ref>—die Liebe gegen meine litterarischen Wasserschöslinge—seine schöne Schmeichelei meines Geschmacks—und der Ort der Aufgabe auf die Post (es ist Gotha, wie ich höre) lassen mich errathen, dass Sie gewis diesen Geber näher kennen als ich. Darf ich an Sie, da Sie seine Nachsicht vielleicht nicht ganz misbilligen, die Bitte wagen, Ihrem Freunde meinen Dank zu übergeben und so der chargé d’affaires meines Herzens zu werden? Sie werden diese Kühnheit mit meine Vertrauen und mit meiner Sehnsucht entschuldigen und ich verlasse mich auf die Fürsprache Ihres gleichges[inten] Freundes.<ref target="n27" type="note">3</ref><note id="n26"><hi rend="s">2</hi> This copy was in a very rich binding; see also the next quotation, below.</note><note id="n27"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Jean Paul [Friedrich Richter], <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Werke</hi>, Historisch-kritische Ausgabe, 3. Abt. (section 3): Briefe, Bd. 4 (vol. 4), ed. Eduard Berend (Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 1960), p. 117.</note></q>
In an abridged English translation the same text reads like this:
<q>
. . . Young’s Night Thoughts, to which I added my own when trying, in vain, to guess whose was the munificent hand in the cloud[s] to which I am indebted for this gift. If you, as I dare assume, have possibly seen Blake’s illuminated version of Young—here [I give you] the English title [The Complaint, and the Consolation; or Night Thoughts, by Edward Young, London 1797]—you will surely think my desire to express my gratitude not more than just . . . .—The metal-sheathed . . . artistic treasure— . . . make[s] me guess that doubtless you know this donor better than I do. . . .<ref target="n28" type="note">4</ref><note id="n28"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Since I could not trace an English translation of Richter’s collected letters, I had to translate this and the following quotation myself.</note></q>
In a second letter to a friend which was most probably written on the same day, but dated differently, we are given a more detailed description of the book and Richter’s reaction:
<q>
An Christian Otto. M[einingen] d. 21. Nov. 1801.<lb/><lb/>
. . . . —Vorgestern abends fand ich von der Post eine Folio-Kapsel, und darin eine englische Folio-Ausgabe von Young mit 20 oder 25 [sic] herlichen phantastischen Kupferstichen von Blake, englisch prächtig vergoldet und Saffian [und] Atlas und alles wieder in schwarzer L[eder] Hulse; eine achte Gold[kette] geendigt mit einer grossen Perle dient stat der Zwerg-Zettel die du in Bücher legst. Anonym kams, ist aber vom gothaischen Erbprinzen. Ich taxier’ es 15 Guineen. Die Kette bin ich gesonnen abzulösen und meiner Frau an den Hals zu henken. Es ist vielleicht nicht zweimal in Deutschland, was mir sehr bei dem Verkaufen einmal helfen kan.—<ref target="n29" type="note">5</ref><note id="n29"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Jean Paul, <hi rend="i">Briefe</hi>, vol. 4, pp. 118 f.</note></q>
This is how the same words might have sounded had they been written in English:
<q>
. . . —The day before yesterday in the evening I found [delivered] from the post office a folio-box, and in it an English folio edition of Young with 20 or 25 [sic] magnificent [and] phantastic copper engravings by Blake, pompously gilded in English style and morocco [and] sateen [-bound] and all that again in [a] black l[eather] case; a genuine gold [chain] terminating in a huge pearl is used instead of the dwarf-[paper]slips that you put into books. Anonymously it arrived, but it comes from the Hereditary Prince of Gotha. I tax [i.e. value] it at 15 guineas. The chain I am inclined to detach and hang around my wife’s neck. There is possibly no second copy [of the book] in Germany, [and] this sometime might help me a lot in selling it.—
</q>
These two letters reveal a rather materialistic attitude; mentioning the written and engraved contents of the volume in passing only—though respectfully and appreciatively—Jean Paul then goes on to describe the rich binding <hi rend="i">in extenso</hi>: and you can’t tell a book from looking at the cover, can you? But of course Jean Paul Richter was too much of a poet himself not to be perfectly aware of this. Obviously he decided at least not to sell the book with those "phantastic" illustrations too soon, and he remembered it when writing down his aesthetic
<pb id="p11-125" n="125"/>
theory in the <hi rend="i">Vorschule.</hi> There he still mentions Blake in passing only, but also shows that meanwhile he has opened the book and actually added his own "Night Thoughts." If we look up §73 (i.e. §79 of the second, revised, and enlarged edition published in May 1813) which deals with the representation of the human figure, we read as follows:
<q>
Ausser der äussern Bewegung giebt [2nd ed.: gibt] es noch eine höhere Malerin der Gestalt, die innere Bewegung. Unsere Phantasie malt nichts leichter nach als eine zweite. In einer Folio-Ausgabe von Youngs Nachtgedanken mit phantastischen Randzeichnungen von Blake ist z.B. auf dem Blatte, wo Träume gezeichnet werden [see <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> eng., p. 4; DWD], die Gestalt für mich fürchterlich, die [2nd ed.: welche] gekrümmt und schaudernd in ein Gebüsch starrt; denn ihr Sehen wird mir Gesicht. Um also unserm Geiste eine schöne Gestalt zu zeigen— —: [2nd ed.: punctuation reversed] zeigt ihm nur einen, der sie sieht; aber um wieder sein Sehen zu zeigen, müsst ihr irgend einen Körpertheil, und wär’ es ein blaues Auge, ja ein weisses grosses Augenlied, [2nd ed.: comma missing] mitbringen; dann ist alles gethan.<ref target="n30" type="note">6</ref><note id="n30"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Jean Paul [Friedrich Richter], <hi rend="i">Vorschule der Aesthetik, nebst einigen Vorlesungen in Leipzig über die Parteien der Zeit</hi> (Hamburg: Friedrich Perthes, 1804), pp. 476 f. The version of the text printed here is that of the first edition; in square brackets, however, I have recorded the few variants of the second edition; cf. Jean Paul [Friedrich Richter], <hi rend="i">Vorschule der Aesthetik; nebst einigen Vorlesungen in Leipzig über die Parteien der Zeit</hi>, Zweite, verbesserte und vermehrte Auflage [2nd ed.], 3 vols. (Stuttgart &amp; Tübingen: in der J. G. Cotta’schen Buchhandlung, 1813), pp. 628 f. (§79). See also the critical edition of Jean Paul’s works with a text based on the later editon: Jean Paul [Friedrich Richter], <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Werke</hi>, Historisch-kritische Ausgabe, 1. Abt. (section 1): Zu Lebzeiten des Dichters erschienene Werke, Bd. 11 (vol. 11), ed. Eduard Berend (Weimar: Hermann Böhlaus Nachfolger, 1935), p. 269 (facing p. 272 a detail from Blake’s design for p. 4 of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> is reproduced).</note></q>
The same paragraph in a modern translation based on Margaret Hale’s:
<q>
Besides external motion there is a still higher paintress of the figure: internal motion. We imagine nothing more easily than another’s imaginings. In a folio edition of Young’s Night Thoughts with fantastic marginal designs by Blake on the page where dreams are described [see <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> eng., p. 4; DWD], there is a figure terrifying to me, which stares, bent over and shuddering, into a bush; its seeing becomes vision for me. In order to show a beautiful figure to our minds, simply show someone who sees it; but to show his perception, you must accompany it with some part of the body, a blue eye or even a great white eyelid, and it will all be there.<ref target="n31" type="note">7</ref><note id="n31"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Margaret R. Hale, tr. &amp; ed., <hi rend="i">Horn of Oberon: Jean Paul Richter’s School for Aesthetics</hi> (Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 1973), p. 208. Margaret Hale translates the second edition (see p. lvii), and also provides the reader with an extensive introduction. My own version of the text differs from Hale’s in minute particulars only, where I thought a more literal translation necessary.</note></q>
Werner Hofmann suggested a full-length study comparing the metaphorical, political, and philosophical concepts of Blake and Jean Paul, which seem to be quite similar in some respects.<ref target="n32" type="note">8</ref> In the sentences quoted above, the author of <hi rend="i">Titan</hi> demonstrates how well he understood an artistic method used by Blake in more than one case; and it is remarkable that Richter manages to get along with Blake’s work without employing any pejorative terms. For him the word "phantastic" was still appropriate to describe the special quality of the engravings he wrote about. Only a few years later, when in 1811 Henry Crabb Robinson published his essay on Blake —which for other reasons of course is of more importance for us than Richter’s few lines—the artist’s reputation as a madman already interfered greatly with his critic’s view. Jean Paul, by the way, might have known Crabb Robinson’s article by the time he was revising his <hi rend="i">Preparatory School for Aesthetics</hi>; the publisher of the first edition, Friedrich Perthes in Hamburg, also printed the <hi rend="i">Vaterländisches Museum</hi> in 1811. Jean Paul originally intended to have Perthes publish the second edition of his book on aesthetics too; might not Perthes in their correspondence have told Richter about Robinson’s biographical sketch? This is mere guesswork at the moment, and after all Richter did <hi rend="i">not</hi> revise the section with his reference to Blake. We will have to wait for the study proposed by Prof. Hofmann before we can go on and speculate about what Jean Paul would have thought of the Lambeth books, and whether he would have seen Los as an image close to his Titan. Then also we might be able to answer a perhaps more important question, namely why the author of the <hi rend="i">Vorschule</hi> thought this "relatively insignificant detail" more important than the more sublime designs in Edwards’ edition of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi><ref target="n33" type="note">9</ref><note id="n32"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Hofmann, "Erfüllung," p. 29, n. 52.</note><note id="n33"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Hofmann, "Erfüllung," p. 25. About a month after I had finished the MS. for this note, the summer issue of <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> arrived and necessitated the addition of a few sentences at least. In a—generally most precarious—review of the series of Hamburg catalogs on art around 1800, John Gage refers his readers to Hofmann’s note on Jean Paul and Blake, which also served as the basis of the present article. Hofmann’s (and my own) surprise at finding Jean Paul selecting the detail on p. 4 of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> engravings in return seems to come as a surprise to that critic. For Gage obviously no problems arise: Jean Paul’s attitude is known "in criticism at least as far back as late antiquity." I do not think it all <hi rend="i">that</hi> simple. What about the effects of time and contemporary context on the "critical concepts and vocabulary" Gage is writing about? Of course it is not the relative originality of Richter’s aesthetic theory Hofmann and I are interested in, but rather the peculiar attitude of Richter towards Blake’s mode of thinking and creating. Still I firmly believe that only a thorough study comparing Richter’s and Blake’s thought in the larger context of their respective historical surroundings (inclusive of contemporary aesthetic theory) might furnish us with the basic pre-requisites for answering the questions sketched by Hofmann and above. —See John Gage, review of <hi rend="i">Kunst um 1800, SIR</hi>, XV, No. 3, Summer 1976, 482-89 (especially p. 483).</note></p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p11-126" n="126"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>BLAKE’S ILLUSTRATION OF THE THIRD TEMPTATION IN <hi rend="i">PARADISE REGAINED</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Robert F. <name>Gleckner</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In a recent note in the <hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi> (10 [1976], 48-53) J. Karl Franson compares a number of the illustrations by various artists to the temple spire scene in <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, concluding that "only one—William Blake—interprets the scene in close accord with the text of the entire poem." Further, his illustration "presents a perceptive and convincing interpretation of the crisis, and indeed of the whole work, that resolves much of the apparent ambiguity" in the episode that has made it one of the most perplexing cruxes in the poem (p. 48). More particularly, in contrast to the other Milton illustrators and to his commentators, Blake’s rendition "suggests neither a human balancing feat nor a miraculous intervention" (i.e. support for Christ by the angels), but rather "provocative evidence that Blake is proposing a third alternative, that Christ alone performs the miraculous stand,"<ref target="n34" type="note">1</ref> that, as Wittreich pointed out earlier, "Christ’s words [on the pinnacle] indicate his own coming to awareness; he now comprehends that which he did not know before."<ref target="n35" type="note">2</ref><note id="n34"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Franson, p. 51. He cites other passages in <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> (e.g. I, 11; IV, 535-36, 598, 601-03) and <hi rend="i">The Christian Doctrine</hi> as evidence of Milton’s intent. Blake’s illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> are available in a variety of publications: Darrell Figgis, <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake</hi> (London: E. Benn, 1925); Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Milton’s Poems in English</hi> (London: Nonesuch Press, 1926); David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Blake Collection of the Fitzwilliam Museum</hi> (Cambridge: Heffer, 1970); and J. A. Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Calm of Mind</hi> (Cleveland: Case Western Reserve, 1971). The issue of the <hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi> in which Franson’s note appears features the pinnacle illustration, in color, on its cover.</note><note id="n35"><hi rend="s">2</hi> "William Blake: Illustrator-Interpreter of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>," in <hi rend="i">Calm of Mind: Tercentenary Essays on Paradise Regained and Samson Agonistes</hi>, ed. Wittreich (Cleveland and London: Case Western Reserve University Press, 1971), p. 121.</note></p>
          <p>While there is little to quarrel with in this general view, there are some additional details that both strengthen Franson’s (and Wittreich’s) case and at the same time reveal a greater complexity in Blake’s illustration than he seems to see. For example, Psalm 91, which Satan refers to (<hi rend="i">PR</hi>, IV, 556-59), speaks of God’s angels being given "charge over" Christ, including the responsibility to "bear thee up in their hands, lest thou dash thy foot against a stone." Milton’s version, in Satan’s words, is: "in thir hands / They shall up lift thee" (IV, 557-58). But in fact it is Satan who lifts him up and bears him in his hands ("caught him up" and "There on the highest Pinnacle he set / The Son of God"—IV, 541, 549-50). Beyond this textual reinterpretation by Milton of the Biblical passage and Satan’s version of it,<ref target="n36" type="note">3</ref> Blake positions one of his three angels at Christ’s feet somewhat ambiguously. Is he indicating appropriate obeisance, or offering physical support as if in anticipation of a loss of balance, or calling attention to the lack of physical and divine aid, or gesturing to earth in invitation to the "flow’ry valley" in which they finally "set him down" for the feast of "Celestial Food, Divine, / Ambrosial" and "Ambrosial drink" (IV, 586-90) before Christ returns refreshed "to his Mother’s house" (639)? The answer seems to me a combination of all four, the second and third possibilities reiterating visually Franson’s point that neither physical support nor divine intervention is necessary to steady Christ no matter how "uneasy" his "station" (IV, 584), the "undoubtable ‘proof’ of his divine nature" (Franson, 51). <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">3</hi> It should also be noted that Satan’s setting Christ "on the highest Pinnacle" ("highest plac’t" as he himself puts it—IV, 553) is parodic of Psalm 91.14: "Because he hath set his love upon me, therefore will I deliver him: I will set him on high . . . ").</note></p>
          <p>Blake further enhances this view by the positioning of his angels both in relation to each other and to Christ, and to the plummeting, defeated Satan. Our eye movement over the angels’ configuration seems to me to proceed both downward and upward, each angel being, as it were, a kind of still portrait, the three together constituting a cinematographic sequence. The downward movement, from upright posture to kneeling upright to the gesture of obeisance, is implicitly rejected by the self-sustained Christ. The upward movement from the lowered arms of the bottom angel up through the wings of the other two (echoed in the prayerful hands of the middle angel) reasserts that self-containedness. Contrariwise, Satan to the right of Christ falls heavily, the encompassing mass of flame ironically repeating the angelic configuration, and his divided beard and struggling legs grotesquely parodying the angels’ wings. Thus just as Milton has Satan enact his own challenge to Christ ("if not to stand, / Cast thyself down"—IV, 554-55), so Blake dramatizes the inadequacy of physical strength or balance in his muscular Satan to paralle the superfluousness of aid from the angels.</p>
          <p>Finally, Blake’s Christ thus stands between both angelic and physical natures, between youth and age, between heaven and earth (as well as heaven and hell), comprising, yet triumphing over, both in the cruciform position set against the penumbral background of cloud and sky:
<q>
Whether thron’d<lb/>
In the bosom of bliss, and light of light<lb/>
Conceiving, or remote from Heaven, enshrin’d<lb/>
In fleshly Tabernacle, and human form. . . .<lb/>
(IV, 596-99)
</q>
Franson’s conclusion is sound, then: Blake reveals and illustrates "Milton’s fundamental concern in the work," that is "to dramatize his conception of Christ’s unique nature" (51). But Blake also, via the positional dynamics and spatial movement of his entire illustration, enacts the several complexities and implicit contrasts in Milton’s poem that even more fully than Franson shows illuminate the precise nature of that uniqueness.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p11-127" n="127"/>
        <figure/>
        <pb id="p11-128" n="128"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">CUMBERLAND BIBLIOGRAPHY</hi> ADDENDA</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E.</hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, <hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>If the <hi rend="i">Cumberland Bibliography</hi> is worth noting in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, it may deserve to be supplemented here with information which came to my notice because of the publication of the <hi rend="i">Bibliography.</hi></p>
          <p>Part C. MANUSCRIPTS WHICH HAVE BEEN TRACED.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Tour in North Wales.</hi> 1784 (?1796)</p>
          <table rows="6" cols="2">
            <row>
              <cell>TITLE:</cell>
              <cell>Tour in North Wales. | 1784 | [pasted on vignette] | by George Cumberland | and | C L [<hi rend="i">i.e., Charles Long</hi>] | [description of the vignette] <hi rend="i">N.B.</hi> The <hi rend="i">Tour</hi> was made by Cumberland and Long, but the manuscript is entirely by and about George Cumberland.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>BINDING:</cell>
              <cell>Bound in three quarter leather over brow marbled boards.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>PAPER:</cell>
              <cell>Shard[?] [date cut off] on titlepage. None on other leaves; the leaves bearing sketches are distinctly heavier than the text-leaves. After p. 36, the leaves are waterstained.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>SIZE:</cell>
              <cell>30.5 × 38.1 cm (12" × 15")</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>NUMBERING:</cell>
              <cell>The pages are numbered 1-62 (sometimes trimmed off) at the top outer corners (misnumbered after p. 47, so that pp. "49"-"62" should be 48-61); the last, unnumbered, page is blank.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>CONTENTS:</cell>
              <cell>Flyleaf, titlepage (verso blank), text on pp. 1-61 (numbered 1-47, 49-62), [63]; three flyleaves. After pp. 4, 6, 8, 14, 16, 18, 22, 24, 28, 32, 34, 40, 44, 46 (2 leaves), [48](2 leaves), [56] (two leaves) are inserted heavier leaves bearing pasted-on sketches numbered 1-36, many with flimsy guard-leaves. There are 55 leaves in all (not counting flimsies).</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>HISTORY: Probably the manuscript left the Cumberland family about 1873 (see <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of George Cumberland 1754-1848</hi> [1975], 83-84). According to the present owner, it was found in a somewhat damp cellar in Newport, Monmouthshire, by a female book-seller, who sold it about 1960 to Major Herbert LLOYD-JOHNES, O.B.E., T.D., LL.D., F.J.A., who has promised it to the National Library of Wales and who is publishing an account of the manuscript in the Journal of the National Library of Wales. I am deeply grateful to Major Lloyd-Johnes for allowing me to see and describe the manuscript and to look at his remarkable library of books on Wales and pictures of his family and their sometime estate at Hafod.</p>
          <p>DATE: The manuscript was clearly composed from notes Cumberland had made at the time, for once he explains lacunae by saying that he had "lost my notes on this part of the tour" (p.[61]). In the text he refers to "a very agreeable fortnight there [<hi rend="i">at Hafod</hi>] in 1795" and "the description of it" he has "since published" (1796), and he mentions a third excursion he made to Wales in 1796 (p. [61]). Perhaps the manuscript was composed from the earlier notes about 1796. An insertion of two leaves after p. 34 bears a poem dated "New y<hi rend="s">rs</hi>. day 1796", suggesting that the previous version of the <hi rend="i">Tour</hi> had been completed by then. Cumberland clearly kept the manuscript by him and looked it over from time to time, for a footnote on the first page of text identifying his companion as Charles Long has two or three addenda at later dates identifying him as "a Privy Counsellor, in 1800—now a Knight of the Bath [1820] and Lord Farnborough [1826]".</p>
          <p>NOTE: A large part of the purpose of the manuscript is to put in context the series of sketches which Cumberland made on his 1784 tour and which are pasted in here—except for a few which he had lost by the time he wrote the <hi rend="i">Tour.</hi> There is a long section on the beauties of the neighborhood of Hafod (pp. 42-61), before Thomas Johnes had built his seat there, and another on the village of "Abbey Tintern" (pp. 14-17). One passage in particular (p. 36) may remind us of Cumberland’s friendship (c. 1790-1827) with the painter-poet Blake:
<q>
At sun rise . . . after bathing a few minutes in its refreshing stream, I found myself so invigorated, and my spirit so exalted with the laughing scene around, that taking out my pencil instead of drawing I wrote the following Song [<hi rend="i">on the River Dee</hi>]. . . .
</q>
A related "merry scene" in which a "dimpling stream runs laughing by" appears in Blake’s "Laughing Song" in his <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p11-129" n="129"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">MARK SCHORER 1908-1977</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Contributions in memory of Mark Schorer, who died 12 August, may be made to The School of American Ballet, 144 West 66 Street, New York NY.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE AT THE TATE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>After a prospect of further delays owing to yet another hold-up over the Tate Gallery’s new extension, it has been decided to hold the long-promised Blake exhibition in the old exhibition galleries next spring. The tentative dates are 8 March to 21 May 1978. Very roughly 250 works will be exhibited, selected less for scholarly interest than to stress Blake’s achievement in the visual arts. MARTIN BUTLIN, KEEPER OF THE BRITISH COLLECTION, TATE GALLERY, LONDON.</p>
          <figure/>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">"WARRING ANGELS"</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The drawing titled "Warring Angels," reported on by Frances Carey in this issue, pp. 116-19, has been acquired by the Bolton Art Gallery in Lancashire.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">MRS. BLAKE &amp; <hi rend="i">FAERIE QUEENE</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The May issue of <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>—a special issue on Petworth—reported the discovery among the archives of a letter from Mrs. Blake discussing the coloring of <hi rend="i">The Characters of Spenser’s Faerie Queene.</hi></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE ON THAMES TV</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Thames Television has announced plans for "a celebration of the poetry and painting of Blake to mark the 150th anniversary of his death," according to Lester Clark, of their division of Features in Education &amp; Religion.</p>
          <figure/>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">CORRECTION</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41 we summarized the contents of an article from the <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, "A Blake Discovery," outlining the new Blake acquisitions made by the Pierpont Morgan Library of New York. On 11 March 1977 <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> ran a correction as follows: "The article . . . was written by Thomas V. Lange and Charles Ryskamp. Mr Lange is Assistant Curator of Printed Books at the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York, of which Mr Ryskamp is Director. . . ."</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">THE SONG OF MILOS</hi>
              </hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Alan Rowlands, of Newport, England, has sent us a copy of his illustrated booklet titled <hi rend="i">The Song of Milos</hi>, consisting of halftone reproductions of twelve drawings and line shots of lithographs with illustrations accompanying poetry. The booklet is available for £1.65 from C. M. Rowlands, Salters Hall Cottage, Salters Lane, Newport, SALOP, England. The reproductions are also available as lithographs in various combinations and in a range of prices. Rowlands states that "the influences which motivated Blake have, in a very much more minor key, influenced my own work. At this point I regret the similarity ends as my admiration for Blake far exeeds my own aspirations and my abilities likewise are of a diminutive quality. However, it may be encouraging to see that tradition in this area still prevails and, although freely adapted in ‘The Song of Milos,’ I firmly believe myth and symbol is still its best vehicle."</p>
          <figure/>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">FITZWILLIAM WITHDRAWS BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>P. Woudhuysen, Keeper, Department of Manuscripts &amp; Printed Books at the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, has written an appeal to <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> readers as follows:
<figure/><q>
I wonder whether I might address, through your Blake Quarterly, an appeal for financial help to all Blake scholars who may, or who may not as yet, have studied and enjoyed the large and important Blake collection in my Department in the Museum.<lb/><lb/>
All of our original Blake material, and many of the early facsimiles like Muir’s, are now, after many years of constant use, in an extremely fragile and sorry condition. The bindings are very worn, the gatherings are loose, the paper torn, dirty, and extremely acid. They are all in urgent need of repair and conservation.<lb/><lb/>
At present, however reluctant a decision this was to make, all the originals have been withdrawn from use and will remain so until we can find the funds to have them repaired.
<pb id="p11-130" n="130"/>
                            The estimated cost for rebinding, paper repair, deacidification, etc., is ca. £1500 ($2500), which is totally beyond the Museum’s means and resources in the present difficult financial climate.<lb/><lb/>
I should be grateful if you would consider publishing this letter . . . about our problem . . . in the hope that the combined generosity of all Blake scholars and lovers of his work will enable us to have our collection restored to its former glory, and once again available to scholars and the general public.
</q>
The address of the Fitzwilliam Museum is Cambridge CB2 1RB England.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">WORKS BY &amp; ABOUT BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Edwin C. Epps, Jr., has issued a second list of "A Fine Group of Works by and about William Blake, Poet, Printer, Prophet," dated 16 May 1977, and including ten items for sale. Address Epps at Antiquarian Books and Prints, P.O. Box 6444, Columbia, South Carolina 29260.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">GOLGONOOZA BESTIARY</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Animal Forms of Wisdom: A William Blake Bestiary</hi> is available for $50 from Alexandra Eldridge, Golgonooza, R.R. #1, Millfield, Ohio 45761. The edition is limited to 35 copies, handbound in quarter calf and Nideggen paper. There are 25 pages, silk-screen on rag paper, illuminated and hand-colored by the author.</p>
          <figure/>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">PROSE STUDIES 1800-1900</hi>
              </hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Under the auspices of the Victorian Studies Centre at the University of Leicester, Philip Dodd and J. C. Hilson will soon be editing a new journal devoted to the study of non-fictional prose between 1800 and 1900, under the title <hi rend="i">Prose Studies</hi> (<hi rend="i">PS</hi>). According to the editors, their journal will "provide a much-needed forum for genuinely interdisciplinary discourse," with one major aim being "to evolve,
<figure/>
through the elucidation and discussion of individual works . . . a distinctive critical vocabulary for the analysis of non-fictional prose . . . ." There will also be a yearly annotated bibliography and reviews of current work in the field. There are forthcoming articles by David DeLaura on Matthew Arnold; Elizabeth Strode on William Morris’ lectures; and A. W. Bellringer on Pater.</p>
          <p>The journal will appear three times a year, with the first number to be published probably in September 1977 in conjunction with a Ruskin conference in Leicester. Subscription rates are as follows: individuals, £2.50 or $4.50 per year; institutions, £3.50 or $6.50. Address the editors, Department of English, University of Leicester, Leicester LE1 7RH England.</p>
          <figure/>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p11-131" n="131"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">CLQ BLAKE ISSUE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <figure/>
          <p>The June 1977 issue of <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> has a number of articles on Blake: by Christopher Heppner, on "Identity and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>"; by Janet Warner, on "Blake and the Language of Art"; by Warren Stevenson, on Blake’s drawings of the Canterbury Pilgrims; by Edward J. Rose, on the Spectre; and by John Sutherland, on the Bard’s Song in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Recently John Sutherland, the editor of the <hi rend="i">Quarterly</hi>, announced that it would pay special attention to essays on Blake, as well as on psychology and literature, and the visual arts and literature. Extra copies of the special Blake issue are available at $1, postpaid, as long as they last. Address the editor at Colby College, Waterville, Maine 04901.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">LAVATER MARGINALIA</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>David Erdman writes to say that he agrees with the changes in the text of the Lavater marginalia suggested by Richard J. Shroyer in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41, and that he will make the appropriate changes in the text when Doubleday publishes a new edition of Erdman’s edition of Blake’s poetry and selected prose.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">TAURUS PRESS <hi rend="i">AMERICA</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Blake’s text of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, printed with "handcut" type in scarlet, illustrated with linocuts by Peter Paul Piech printed in black is being sold for £50 by Taurus Press of Willow Dene, 2 Willow Dene, Bushey Heath, Herts. WD2 1PS England. There is an introduction by Hugo Manning and Roger R. Easson. The linocut illustrations are also available without the text, signed by the artist, £50.</p>
          <figure/>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
