<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
 <idno>019-02</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <hi rend="b">
            <hi rend="i">Blake AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi>
          </hi>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <front>
      <pb id="p19-53-54" n="53-54"/>
                  <div1 id="cover">
                                <figure n="cover.019.02.bqscan" rend="file">
                                              <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
                                                            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
                                                            VOLUME 19<lb/>
                                                            NUMBER 2<lb/>
                                                            FALL 1985</figTranscr>
                                </figure>
                  </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0001">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">CONTENTS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <table id="contents" rows="15" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>Samuel Palmer’s <hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors of West
                                Kent, 1832</hi> Rediscovered by David Bindman</cell>
            <cell>56</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors of West Kent, 1832</hi> by
                            Samuel Palmer</cell>
            <cell>60</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Keynes and Blake at Cambridge by G.E. Bentley, Jr.</cell>
            <cell>69</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>The Crying of Lot 318; or, Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
                                Thoughts</hi> Colored Once More by Karen Mulhallen</cell>
            <cell>71</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>An Unpublished Poem by S. Foster Damon by Josephine McQuail</cell>
            <cell>72</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>A Pencil Sketch for Blake’s Dante Illustrations by Jenijoy La
                            Belle</cell>
            <cell>73</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Stephen C. Behrendt, <hi rend="i">The Moment of Explosion: Blake and
                                the Illustration of Milton</hi> and Edward Hodnett, <hi rend="i">Image and Text: Studies in the Illustration of English
                                Literature</hi>, reviewed by Karl Kroeber</cell>
            <cell>75</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William
                                Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem, reviewed by V.A. De Luca</cell>
            <cell>76</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>G.E. Bentley, Jr., Robert N. Essick, Shelley M. Bennett, and Morton D.
                            Paley, <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers</hi>, and Joseph
                            Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Prints by William Blake and His Followers</hi>,
                            reviewed by Raymond Lister</cell>
            <cell>80</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Dover facsimiles of <hi rend="i">America, Europe</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, reviewed by Jenijoy La
                            Belle</cell>
            <cell>83</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Gregory Forbes, <hi rend="i">Selections from William
                                Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience; <hi rend="i">Musical Settings by Gregory Forbes</hi>, reviewed by Joseph
                            Viscomi with Margaret LaFrance</cell>
            <cell>84</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>ASECS Clifford Prize</cell>
            <cell>89</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">CONTRIBUTORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">G.E. BENTLEY, JR.</hi>, of the University of Toronto has just
                    completed <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi> and <hi rend="i">Thomas
                        Macklin: Picture-Publisher and Patron.</hi></p>
        <p><hi rend="b">DAVID BINDMAN</hi>, Reader in History of Art, Westfield College,
                    University of London, has written books on Hogarth, Blake, and English
                    sculptors. His <hi rend="i">The Thames &amp; Hudson Encyclopedia of British
                        Art</hi> was published this year.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">V.A. DE LUCA</hi> is Professor of English at the University of
                    Toronto. His most recent essay on Blake, “A Wall of Words: The Sublime as
                    Text,” appears in the collection <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake
                        and Textuality</hi>, edited by Nelson Hilton and Thomas Vogler.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">KARL KROEBER</hi>, Professor of English and Comparative Literature
                    at Columbia University, recently published <hi rend="i">Wordsworth: An Annotated
                        Bibliography:</hi> in his forthcoming <hi rend="i">British Romantic
                    Art</hi>, Blake’s work is one of the principal foci.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JENIJOY LA BELLE</hi>, Associate Professor of Literature at the
                    California Institute of Technology, is currently working with a previously
                    unknown group of letters containing references to Blake.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">RAYMOND LISTER</hi> is a Fellow of Wolfson College, Cambridge, and a
                    Syndic of the Fitzwilliam Museum. From 1976-80 he was Chairman of the Board of
                    Governors of the Federation of British Artists and from 1970-80 President of the
                    Royal Society of Miniature Painters, Sculptors, and Gravers. He has written
                    several books on Blake and his followers.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JOSEPHINE MCQUAIL</hi> received her B.A. and M.A. degrees from the
                    University of Virginia, Charlottesville, where she took a course from Leopold
                    Damrosch, the memory of which still inspires her. She is currently working
                    towards a doctorate in English literature at the University of California,
                    Berkeley.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">KAREN MULHALLEN</hi>, Professor of English at Ryerson Polytechnical
                    Institute, Toronto, is the editor and 
                    <pb id="p19-55" n="55"/> publisher of <hi rend="i">Descant</hi>, a literary
                    quarterly, and Arts Editor of <hi rend="i">The Canadian Forum</hi> magazine, a
                    journal of politics and the arts. She is now completing a study of
                    Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JOSEPH VISCOMI</hi>, Assistant Professor of English at the
                    University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, has written on Blake and other
                    eighteenth-century printmakers. He is the author of <hi rend="i">The Art of
                        William Blake’s Illuminated Prints</hi>, and has edited for videotape
                    his stage adaptation of <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, with original
                    music composed by <hi rend="b">MARGARET LAFRANCE</hi>, a flutist teaching and
                    performing in Ithaca, New York.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">EDITORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editors:</hi> Morris Eaves, University of New Mexico, and Morton D.
                    Paley, University of California, Berkeley.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Bibliographer:</hi> Thomas L. Minnick, Ohio State University.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Review Editor:</hi> Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia,
                    Athens.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Associate Editor for Great Britain:</hi> Frances A. Carey, Assistant
                    Curator, Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Production Office:</hi> Morris Eaves, Department of English,
                    University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131, <hi rend="b">Telephone</hi>
                    505/277-3103.<lb/> Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of
                    California, Berkeley, CA 94720.<lb/> Thomas L. Minnick, University College, Ohio
                    State University, 1050 Carmack Road, Columbus, OH 43210.<lb/> Nelson Hilton,
                    Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602.<lb/> Frances A.
                    Carey, Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum, Great Russell Street,
                    London WC1B 3DG, United Kingdom.</p>
        <figure/>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">INFORMATION</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Managing Editor:</hi> Robin Tawney.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the
                    sponsorship of the Department of English, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Subscriptions</hi> are $18 for institutions, $15 for individuals.
                    All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer
                    issue. Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be applied to
                    the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and Mexico)
                    require a $3 per volume postal surcharge for surface mail, a $10 per volume
                    surcharge for air mail delivery. U.S. currency or international money order
                    necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications
                    to Robin Tawney, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of
                    New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131, USA.</p>
        <p>Many <hi rend="b">back issues</hi> are available at a reduced price. Address
                    Robin Tawney for a list of issues and prices.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Manuscripts</hi> are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented
                    according to the forms suggested in the MLA Style Sheet, 2nd ed., to either of
                    the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of New Mexico,
                    Albuquerque, NM 87131; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of
                    California, Berkeley, CA 94720.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">International Standard Serial Number:</hi> 0006-453x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is <hi rend="b">indexed</hi> in the
                    Modern Language Associations International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities
                    Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and
                    Literature, <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>’ annual Romantic
                    Bibliography, ART bibliographies <hi rend="b">MODERN</hi>, American Humanities
                    Index, and the Arts and Humanities Citation Index.</p>
        <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1985 Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note>
        <figure/>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <pb id="p19-56" n="56"/>
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">Samuel Palmer’s <hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors
                                of West Kent, 1832</hi> Rediscovered</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">DAVID</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">BINDMAN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>In 1975 I gave a lecture at London University on Samuel Palmer in which I
                    attempted to relate some major themes in his work to the political upheavals of
                    his time. The idea was to demonstrate that the study of politics could be as
                    relevant to the discussion of visionary artists as it was to those like Madox
                    Brown and Courbet who made direct reference to political issues in their
                    paintings. Palmer seemed a good example because his letters of the later 1820s
                    reveal him as bitterly hostile to radicalism and dissent in all its forms.
                    Furthermore Palmer was known to have been moved in the face of the Reform Act of
                    1832 to produce an anonymous political pamphlet, <hi rend="i">An Address to the
                        Electors of West Kent</hi>, by “an Elector.” No copy appeared
                    to have survived, but its existence was known from a reference to it in a letter
                    by John Linnell, and Geoffrey Grigson had found some extracts held up for
                    derision in a reform newspaper, the <hi rend="i">Madistone Gazette</hi> for 11
                    December 1832.<ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> In preparing my lecture I
                    made strenuous efforts to find the pamphlet but without success, and I had to
                    rely for my picture of Palmer’s political views on the extracts and
                    various passages from his letters. Some time later I mentioned the missing
                    pamphlet to Michael Collinge of the Institute of Historical Research of London
                    University. As it happens he was going shortly afterwards to the Maidstone
                    Public Record office which I had searched in vain, and a few days later he sent
                    me a photocopy of the whole pamphlet. It is here reprinted in full for the first
                    time since 1832, and it is Palmer’s longest and most considered piece of
                    prose to have survived, dating from a critical period in his career. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. Grigson, <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: The
                            Visionary Years</hi> (1947), pp. 104-107.</note></p>
        <p>In this introduction I want to discuss briefly the political background to the
                    pamphlet and suggest some possible connections with his art. To a degree I will
                    be following in the footsteps of Geoffrey Grigson who in an article in <hi rend="i">Horizon</hi> of 1944<ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> and his
                    book on Palmer of 1947 argues that Palmer’s political reactions in the
                    period around the Reform Act were symptomatic of his retreat from the visionary
                    basis of his work which led to his eventual departure from Shoreham. The
                    pamphlet as we already know from the published fragments is strongly
                    anti-radical and defensive of the Established Church which he believed to be the
                    true Apostolic Church through its descent from the pre-Reformation Catholic
                    Church, as he makes clear in a letter to George Richmond of 24 June 1828:
                    “I hope, Sir, that the Lord will confirm you &amp; comfort you in true
                    and sweet affiliation to the Apostolic Church which has only Bishops and pastors
                    (tho’ many drones &amp; wolves) in which only are the efficacies of the
                    holy sacraments, the authority and absolution &amp; blessing, the delegated
                    power of Jesus Christ, the eternal shield against the gates of Hell, The chief
                    corner stone . . . the rock St Peter, the indissoluble foundation of the
                    apostles &amp; prophets, stronger than the pillars of the world &amp; the
                    fabric of the universe &amp; the gift of the Holy Ghost.”<ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> In this devotion to the Church of England
                    Palmer was perfectly consistent throughout his life and he accepted the paternal
                    view of society it implied, but in 1828 it did not alienate him from his friends
                    in the Shoreham circle many of whom were, like John Linnell, themselves
                    dissenters: “Politics we dabble in: Mr. L[innell] though of no party
                    magnifies the peasants; I, also, as you know, of no party, as I love our fine
                    British peasantry, think best of the old high tories, because I find they gave
                    most liberty to the poor, and were not morose, sullen and blood-thirsty like the
                    whigs, liberty jacks and dissenters; whose cruelty when they reign’d, was
                    as bad as that of the worst times of the worst papists; only more sly and
                    smoothlier varnish’d over with a thin shew of reason.”<ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref><note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “Samuel Palmer: The Politics of an
                        Artist,” <hi rend="i">Horizon</hi>, 4 (1944), 314-28.</note><note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> The Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>,
                        ed. R. Lister (1974), I, no. 1828 (4), p. 24.</note><note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Palmer, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, I, no. 1828
                        (9), p. 31.</note></p>
        <p>The year 1828 saw the final repeal of the Test and Corporation Acts which removed
                    the statutory bar upon non-Anglicans from holding public and municipal offices.
                    The issue neatly polarized political and religious attitudes, with Radicals and
                    Dissenters on one side, and the “old high tories” and the Church
                    of England, who rightly feared that the Act would spell the end of what Norman
                    Gash calls the “oligarchic Anglican constitution of the eighteenth
                        century,”<ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> on the other. For the
                    Church of England the 1820s were years of ever-increasing threat, and Palmer,
                    like Constable who spent much time in the close of Salisbury Cathedral, saw the
                    Church, the repository of all true values, progressively isolated by the spread
                    of dissent, especially in the towns where Anglicans <pb id="p19-57" n="57"/>
                    were often in a minority. In the countryside the complaints of Radicals gathered
                    around the issue of tithes, the traditional method of paying the clergy whereby
                    a farmer was obliged to give one tenth of his produce either in cash or kind to
                    the local parish. The problems this system created were endless, for assessment
                    could always be at issue; in hard times there was always the cry that the clergy
                    should abate their demands. While some clergy were genuinely poor themselves
                    there were church pluralists who lived very comfortably without ever seeing
                    their parishioners. Furthermore Dissenters normally regarded the Church as an
                    “unscriptural institution” and denied the Church its title to the
                    tithe in the first place. Most threatening from the point of view of the Church
                    was the fact that the issue of tithes could unite farmers and farm laborers in
                    common cause against them.<ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref><note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> N. Gash, <hi rend="i">The Age of Peel</hi>
                        (1968), p. 2.</note><note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> E.J. Evans, “Some Reasons for the Growth
                        of English Rural Anti-Clericalism,” <hi rend="i">Past and
                            Present</hi>, Feb. 1975.</note></p>
        <p>On what grounds could the Church mount a defense of the system of tithes which
                    made the clergy such an obvious target for Reform? An unsigned article in the
                        <hi rend="i">Quarterly Review</hi> of 1830<ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> claimed among other things that the Church in consequence of its
                    independence from the state provided a means of betterment for poor men without
                    social advantages. These men having acquired a good education would then return
                    to rural areas the advantage of a learned clergy; here the author quotes Burke:
                    “In retired parishes, the family of the clergyman is often a little
                    centre of civilization, from which gleams of refinement of manners, of neatness,
                    of taste, as well as of science and general literature, are diffused through
                    districts into which they would otherwise never penetrate.” In the last
                    resort, however, the anonymous author rests the defense of tithes on more
                    ineffable ideas, in this case those of the mature Wordsworth of the <hi rend="i">Excursion</hi>, first published in 1814, in particular the words of the
                    country pastor in Book VI: <q> Hail to the state of England and conjoin<lb/>
                        With this a salutation as devout<lb/> Made to the spiritual fabric of her
                        church,<lb/> Founded in truth; by blood of martyrdom<lb/> Cemented; by the
                        hands of wisdom reared<lb/> In beauty of holiness, with ordered pomp,<lb/>
                        Decent and unreproved. . . .<lb/> And O, ye swelling hills and spacious
                        plains,<lb/> Besprent from shore to shore with steeple towers<lb/> And
                        spires, whose silent finger points to heaven<lb/> Nor wanting at wide
                        intervals, the bulk<lb/> Of ancient minster, lifted above the cloud<lb/> Of
                        the dense air which town or city breeds,<lb/> To intercept the sun’s
                        glad beams—may ne’er<lb/> That true succession fail of English
                        hearts,<lb/> Who with ancestral feeling can perceive<lb/> What in those holy
                        structures ye possess<lb/> Of ornamental interest, and the charm<lb/> Of
                        pious sentiment diffused afar,<lb/> And human charity and Social love.<lb/>
                        Thus never shall the indignities of time<lb/> Approach their reverend graces
                        unopposed;<lb/> Nor shall the elements be free to hurt<lb/> Their fair
                        proportions; nor the blinder rage<lb/> Of bigot zeal, madly to
                        overturn:<lb/> And if the desolating hand of war<lb/> Spare them, they shall
                        continue to bestow<lb/> Upon the thronged abodes of busy men<lb/> (Depraved,
                        and ever prone to fill their minds<lb/> Exclusively with transitory
                        things,)<lb/> An air and mien of dignified pursuit,<lb/> Of sweet civility,
                        on rustic wilds.<lb/></q><note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Quarterly Review</hi> (1830), pp.
                        105-47.</note></p>
        <p>I have quoted that passage at length because it seems to be in sympathetic accord
                    with the painting by Palmer in the Tate Gallery entitled by him <hi rend="i">Coming from Evening Church, Shoreham</hi>, dated 1830. It shows a group of
                    people leaving a village church set in a valley beneath the moon. The bold form
                    of the church is balanced by the warm and homely cottage on the right, and the
                    villagers represent all ages and generations from small children to old men; in
                    the middle distance can be seen the parson in the midst of his flock. The church
                    spire whose “silent finger points to heaven” (in fact Shoreham
                    Church did not have a spire, though most others in that part of Kent do)
                    dominates the village but seems to grow out of the hillside, which with the
                    overhanging trees appears to protect the village. The painting is a
                    representation of the village as part of the natural order of things, under the
                    benign auspices of the Old English Church, which guarantees the indivisible
                    harmony of nature, nation and religion.</p>
        <p>The painting, therefore, offers a positive if highly idealized vision of rural
                    life, and one that can be paralleled in Palmer’s letters of 1828, like
                    the one already cited. It is all the more striking that the <hi rend="i">Address</hi> should be so bleak in tone even though it cannot have been
                    written much more than two years after the painting. It expresses primarily
                    Palmer’s rage at the very idea of electoral reform, the supporters of
                    which are seen as nothing less than beasts and despoilers who wish only for the
                    destruction of the Church. The note of hysterical intolerance can be matched
                    with that in a letter to George Richmond of 21 September 1832 in which he
                    repents of the indulgence he had shown to friends even until quite recently: <q>
                        If people knew how deeply the whole world lieth in wickedness, and how
                        totally it is estranged &amp; set in opposition against God; they would I
                        cannot help thinking, no longer wonder why all kinds of sects &amp; schisms
                        may not equally be term’d the Churches of Christ. . . . Once I was
                        full of this lightness and folly—yea even to the present time my old
                        Adam can see no reason why the sleek &amp; sober Quaker or the meek &amp;
                        moral Unitarian should be beholden to the Church, claiming the power of the
                        keys of the kingdom of Heaven—But blessed be God. I am changed ever
                        since you saw me—I am a free thinker in art in literature in music in
                        poetry—but as I read of but one way to Heaven &amp; that a narrow
                        one it is not for me to chuse which way, I will be saved &amp; make it a
                        pretty speculation or matter of taste, &amp; run to seek my Saviour in
                        holes &amp; corners, but go at once where He is ever to be found, at the
                        Apostolick altar of the Melchisedekian priesthood.<ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref><note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Palmer, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, I, no.
                            1832 (1), pp. 58-59.</note></q></p>
        <pb id="p19-58" n="58"/>
        <figure>
          <head>Samuel Palmer.</head>
          <figDesc><hi rend="i">Coming from Evening Church, Shoreham</hi> (1830). Courtesy
                        of Tate Gallery Publications Department.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p19-59" n="59"/>
        <p>Evidently something traumatic had happened to Palmer in the years before 1832,
                    and Grigson astutely pointed out that the early 1830s were the time of the
                    “Captain Swing” riots when unemployed and hungry farm laborers
                    terrorized farmers, particularly in Kent, by setting fire to ricks. In fact
                    Shoreham was right in the heart of the discontents and Palmer by moving there in
                    the late 1820s with the dream of finding “a primitive village where none
                    of the King-choppers had set up business”<ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> found himself in a position similar to someone who had recently
                    sought refuge from civilization in the Falkland Islands. By the end of the 1820s
                    more than a third of the population of the Kentish Weald was unemployed
                    following the agricultural recession after Waterloo. According to Hobsbawm and
                    Rudé, in the counties of Southern England by 1828 “Pauperism,
                    degradation, desperation, and sullen discontent were almost
                        universal.”<ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> In 1829 a
                    disastrous harvest was followed by a cruel winter, and misery increased even
                    further especially in Kent. In 1830 the farm laborers turned to open revolt in
                    the form of rick burning and the destruction of threshing machines, sometimes
                    accompanied by sinister letters in the name “Captain Swing,” which
                    became part of life in the area around Shoreham. In retrospect the causes of the
                    revolt can be seen to have lain in local desperation and it was not part of a
                    general uprising. But 1830 was the year of a revolution in France and renewed
                    agitation for Reform in the towns, so one can well see how someone of
                    Palmer’s temperament might persuade himself that the pathetic actions of
                    the rick burners were fomented by Jacobins rushing over from France to join with
                    their English counterparts in the destruction of the property-owning classes.
                    The first recorded outbreak came in Orpington on 1 June 1830 and by the end of
                    20 September fires were reported within the area of a few miles about Shoreham,
                    including one on land belonging to Mr. Love of Filston Hall Farm in Shoreham
                    whom Palmer had described as “one of the best farmers
                        hereabout.”<ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> The revolt was
                    suppressed by the end of the year, but one may presume that the fires consumed
                    not only Palmer’s hopes of a rural retreat but also his faith in the
                    “fine old English peasantry.” <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Palmer, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, I, no. 1828 (11), p. 51.</note><note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> E. Hobsbawm and G. Rudé, <hi rend="i">Captain Swing</hi> (1969), p. 81.</note><note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Palmer, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, I, no.
                        1827 (3), p. 14.</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors of West Kent</hi> was published in
                    support of the Tory candidate Sir William Geary in December 1832 in the general
                    election which followed the passing of the Reform Act, which would have further
                    confirmed Palmer’s despairing vision of the future. The political imagery
                    of the pamphlet is essentially of the kind popularized by Canning and the <hi rend="i">Anti-Jacobin</hi> and also the caricatures of Gillray, in which the
                    movement for Reform even in its most moderate and respectable form was equated
                    unequivocally with the worst excesses of the French Revolution; to support
                    Reform was to open the floodgates to mob rule and the imposition of French
                    atheism and equality, for in Palmer’s words it was “the
                    importation of yesterday, from poor, degraded, dishonoured, Atheistical
                    France.” It is easy to see on reading the pamphlet why a radical
                    newspaper should complain of its “gross invectives and foul
                    vituperation,” and why it should have offended John Linnell who also
                    complained of its impertinent imitation of Milton. Nonetheless it is full of
                    stirring imagery, even a certain visionary quality which is not incompatible
                    with the rapturous imagination of the Shoreham paintings. This pamphlet deserves
                    to be regarded not as an aberration nor simply the product of disillusionment,
                    but as the other side of the coin of the political and religious vision which is
                    implicit in Palmer’s Shoreham paintings. In the last resort
                    Palmer’s art is as essentially High Tory in spirit as Blake’s is
                    indelibly Radical and apocalyptic.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p19-60" n="60"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0006">
        <figure/>
        <pb id="p19-61" n="61"/>
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">AN ADDRESS TO THE ELECTORS OF WEST KENT.</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>My Lords and Gentlemen ;</title>
          </head>
          <p>An individual, who has the honour to be of your number, ventures to address
                        you on the subject of the approaching election; and entreats you to afford
                        him a few moments’ serious attention; which he claims, not for
                        himself, but for the importance of his subject.</p>
          <p>Sir William R. P. Geary comes forward, and offers himself as your
                        Representative; promising an assiduous attention to Parliamentary duties. He
                        will strenuously support the agricultural interest; and such a modification
                        of the tithe laws as may comport with the security of all other kinds of
                        property. He will also promote, to the utmost of his power, every rational,
                        effective and substantial reform. He comes from the heart of the county; and
                        from his family and connections, we cannot but believe him to be a lover of
                        agriculture; an interest now upon the very verge of destruction. Sir William
                        is an INDEPENDENT CANDIDATE, and the son of a late INDEPENDENT MEMBER.</p>
          <p>Surely no person connected with the agricultural interest, and solicitous for
                        the welfare of this great county, can for a moment lend his influence to the
                        opposing faction, who denounce the protecting duties as a “Bread
                        Tax,” and taunt Sir William with a desire of continuing it. Now as
                        every Kentish farmer, who is in his right wits, conceives some sort of
                        “Bread Tax” to be the very condition of his existence, how
                        could our adversaries be so very simple as to tell him plainly, that his
                        only chance of preserving it was by voting for Sir William Geary? However,
                        as they have been so kindly explicit, I hope, like men of common sense, we
                        shall take them at their word, and vote for Sir William, as they advise.
                        Their hostility to Agriculture, which could not long be concealed,
                        notwithstanding any professions they might have made to the contrary,
                        sufficiently bespeaks them to belong to the caste of the Radical Reformers,
                        MOST FALSELY SO CALLED; who are the natural enemies of the farmer, and, by
                        consequence, of the manufacturer; for commerce and agriculture must stand or
                        fall together;—and, therefore, of all national prosperity.</p>
          <p>One is almost tempted to believe that some cunning Agriculturist, in
                        disguise, drew up their manifesto, and laughed at them in his sleeve; for
                        certainly it is its own best refutation. Sir William Geary has promised to
                        support the Agriculturist; and this is the very reason for which
                        agricultural Kent is called upon to repudiate him! <hi rend="i">Risum
                            teneatis.</hi> Rome was saved by the cackling of geese: and truly, if
                        the jacobinic citadel might be preserved by similar multitudes, it must be
                        acknowledged to be impregnable!</p>
          <p>Thus have they forfeited the support of all sensible farmers; and at the same
                        time disgusted every honest man, whether Whig or Tory, by retailing, in the
                        true spirit of jacobinism, a falsehood respecting the income of the Church,
                        so outrageous; that it looks like a droll burlesque and caricature, even of
                        the flagitious system of misrepresentation and imposture, by which that
                        profligate faction is supported.</p>
          <p>With respect to the Candidates themselves, who have been unitedly soliciting
                        your suffrages; nothing can be farther from the writer’s intention
                        than to offer them personal disrespect: he would be the first to yield them
                        that deference which all gentlemen have a right to claim from each other in
                        private society: but he feels it his duty to speak very plainly of the
                        faction whose support those gentlemen have deigned to conciliate.</p>
          <p>Another objection to Sir William is his youth. It is said, “We want
                        men of experience in Parliament:” But, beside that often one man of
                        thirty will be found wiser than another of seventy; that multitude of years
                        does not always teach wisdom: that every profession affords numerous
                        instances of the young attaining honours and distinction; and of aged men
                        who could never rise from mediocrity; and that some of our most splendid
                        public characters have signalized themselves when but scarcely out of their
                        minority: how, we should be glad to know, are we to obtain Representatives
                        of great Parliamentary experience, unless by sending them in betimes, we
                        give them an opportunity to acquire it? If we return none but old men, we
                        defeat that object entirely; and our <hi rend="i">Council of Ancients</hi>
                        must ever be a bench of venerable novices. But, above all, I would ask, is
                        it not most expedient, that in the great senate of a nation there should be
                        found the energy and fire of youth, as well as the deliberative sagacity of
                        age? The parents of all sublime works are Intellect and Will.</p>
          <p>Some have strangely refused to support Sir William Geary, on account of their
                        being, from early associations, attached to the Whigs. Alas! it is but an
                        ill compliment to the Whigs of sixteen hundred and eighty-eight, to mistake
                        for their successors a rabble of incendiaries and jacobins. The politics
                        promulgated by our adversaries are not those of MARLBOROUGH or CHATHAM, but
                        of THISTLEWOOD and BRAN-DRETH!</p>
          <p>NO! Brother Electors!—The Radical upas tree never sprouted from the
                        stock of ancient British Whiggism; <pb id="p19-62" n="62"/> but it is the
                        importation of yesterday, from poor, degraded, dishonoured, Atheistical
                        France.</p>
          <p>That once gay nation long led the mode in our more innocent fripperies of
                        dress and fashion: we amused ourselves with her toys and trinkets; and with
                        perfect good humour saw her play the Harlequin to Europe. But she rose in
                        our estimation, when she began to struggle against aristocratic tyranny. She
                        obtained her freedom: and, alas! immediately lost it again, irretrievably;
                        by confiding it, as the people of England are at this moment confiding their
                        own—to revolutionary empyrics. Then, when suddenly distracted with an
                        infernal phrenzy, her songs and dances became the yells and contortions of
                        possession; and, in a frantic spasm, she hurled over the Continent
                        fire-brands, arrows, and death: who, with more alacrity than the Kentish
                        patriot, sprang forward, and bound the demoniac?</p>
          <p>And shall <hi rend="i">we</hi>, even now, bitten with that selfsame madness;
                        while, though somewhat exhausted with her paroxysm, France yet heaves in
                        incurable distraction; shall <hi rend="i">we</hi> mistake her ravings for
                        the voice of Delphic Sibyl; and proceed to model, or rather unmodel, every
                        institution of our country, and tumble them all together, into the semblance
                        of that kingless, lawless, churchless, Godless, comfortless, and most
                        chaotic Utopia of French philosophy?</p>
          <p>Shall we assay to repair here and there a crumbing pinnacle of our
                        Constitution, by cannonading the buttresses and sapping the foundations?</p>
          <p>Shall we invite over the Gaul to help us raze those bulwarks, which he too
                        well knows to be thunder-proof; and put up a pagoda of trash and tinsel on
                        the site?</p>
          <p>But now, behold, you are called out, Men of Kent—yes, YOU, whose frown
                        has made the Frenchman shiver—to mince and caper in the ballet of
                        liberalism; and to bring up the death-dance of Parisian assassins and
                        sanscullotes!</p>
          <p>They were the Men of Kent who dictated terms to the Norman Conqueror: and
                        they are Men of Kent, who are now asked to become morally the vassals of
                        France.</p>
          <p>Who does not remember that crisis—God forbid any Englishman should
                        forget it!—when Wordsworth sang, <q> “Ye men of Kent,
                            ’tis Victory or Death!” </q></p>
          <p>Then, even as one man, rose up this noble county; and with a front of
                        spotless loyalty, scared Napoleon from our shore. O let not their degenerate
                        children crouch to an invasion of much more fatal principles and
                        doctrines.</p>
          <p>The mane of the British Lion can receive no decoration from shreds of
                        tri-coloured ribbon; nor will he cut any very majestic figure in the eyes of
                        Europe, if we suffer our new-fangled politicians to retrench his tusks and
                        talons; and to lead him about as a show, with the Monkey of French
                        innovation mounted upon his back.</p>
          <p>O my countrymen, for shame! for shame!—Methinks I see the mouldered
                        heroes of Crecy and Agincourt, of Trafalgar and Waterloo rise up to hoot us
                        from among the nations!</p>
          <p>But let it be so no longer! Put on, once more, the invincible armour of old
                        English, of old Kentish loyalty. Strangle the snake corruption wherever you
                        shall find it; and every where promote, in God’s name, effectual
                        reform: but leave not your hearths and altars a prey to the most heartless,
                        the most bloody, most obscene, profane, and atrocious faction, which ever
                        defied God and insulted humanity.</p>
          <p>You will NOT suffer those temples where you received the Christian name to
                        fall an easy prey to sacrilegious plunderers! You will NOT let that dust
                        which covers the ashes of your parents, be made the filthy track of
                        Jacobinical hyenas!</p>
          <p>Farmers of Kent—we are tempted with a share of the promised spoliation
                        of the CHURCH!—There <hi rend="i">was</hi> a time when every Kentish
                        yeoman would have spurned at the wretch who should have dared to tickle him
                        with such a bait—to offer him such an insult! But piety and honour
                        are in the sepulchre.</p>
          <p>I would fain hope, however, that there are still very few of us who would not
                        experience some shudder of conscience, at the thought of thieving from the
                        Church of England her freehold lands and tenements: few among the
                        uncultivated; few among the vicious: few in our jails and halls: few
                        anywhere, but within the precincts of our political unions. There are
                        gradations even in atrocious felony. It is not every burglar who would
                        violate an altar. But what are we to think of those vassals of perdition who
                        would put forth their hands to the freeholds of the Church: who are not
                        afraid to appear in the presence of their Creator branded with sacrilege! It
                        is scarcely, perhaps, to be regretted, that these lepers are now catalogued,
                        and marked, and numbered, and huddled together in the pest-house of the
                        unionists.</p>
          <p>So much for the Church lands. As to the tithe laws, they are about to undergo
                        revision: perhaps very considerable alteration. Sir William Geary has
                        offered to promote any amelioration; any equitable adjustment: nor can any
                        one be more likely to watch the interests of the Kentish farmer closely,
                        during the discussion in Parliament.</p>
          <p>But there are some very honest and well meaning persons to be found, who
                        imagine that an abolition of the tithe altogether would relieve the farmer
                        from his present difficulties: who suppose that if the tenth sheaf were not
                        put into the tithe waggon, the farmer would put the value of that sheaf into
                        his own pocket; whereas nothing can be more false; because the tithe is
                        always allowed for in the rent, which would be so much greater if there were
                        no tithe. Land will always be let to the <pb id="p19-63" n="63"/> best
                        bidders; and whatever men will give for a piece of land to-day, knowing it
                        to be subject to tithe; they would give proportionably more for it
                        to-morrow, tithe free; whether the tithe be a real tenth, or seventh, as
                        some say; or whatsoever proportion it bears to the farmer’s
                        returns.</p>
          <p>Farmers! Messrs. Hodges and Rider are to attempt two things in behalf of
                        their constituents. In the first place, they will sweep away the
                        “Bread Tax,” that is, the protecting duties on foreign corn;
                        which you know will utterly ruin you. But then, they tell you that they will
                        try to abolish the payment of tithe: and who would not gladly be ruined, for
                        the pleasure of seeing the tithe laws abolished! Now it is not unlikely that
                        they may bring about a free trade in corn; because free trade is the
                        fashion: but it is by no means so probable they will succeed in immediately
                        abolishing the tithe, because that can scarcely be done without a
                        revolution. Well; you know that a free trade in corn will throw the farms
                        out of cultivation; starve the whole of the peasantry; and force many of you
                        to emigrate from your native country for ever: but I will show you that the
                        abolition of tithe, at the same moment, would not put a farthing into your
                        hands, to defray the expences of the melancholy passage!</p>
          <p>In all matters of sale and traffic <q> “—The worth of
                            anything<lb/> Is as much money as ‘twill bring.” </q> A
                        tithe-free farm fetches a proportionably high rent: therefore were all the
                        farms tithe free, from the abolition of the tithe laws; all the farms would
                        fetch a rental proportionably increased. What then would the farmer gain by
                        it? Supposing the tithe were doubled: you would go [to] the landlord for an
                        equivalent deduction in your rent—supposing the tithe abolished; he
                        would come to <hi rend="i">you</hi> for an equivalent increase. Our mistake
                        lies in not clearly understanding <hi rend="i">what it is</hi> that we rent
                        of our landlord. We may, perhaps, imagine that we pay him for the whole of
                        the crops which we produce; and that the tithe card takes away a tenth of
                        that produce, for the whole of which we have made our landlord a
                        consideration: but it is no such thing: we never paid for that tenth: it was
                        not charged in our rent. In short, we pay our landlord for the right of
                        disposing of nine tenths of the produce of his land; and if the other tenth
                        were not removed by the tithe man the landowner would take care to demand it
                        in rent. It is irksome to be put to the proof of anything so self-evident,
                        where every argument is like a truism.</p>
          <p>The best informed authors will inform us that the ancient landowners, who
                        built most of our parish churches, left to their children only nine tenths
                        of the profits of the estates which descended to them: the remaining tenth
                        they bequeathed in the shape of the present tithe, to their respective
                        churches for ever: and that bequest was and is ratified by the laws of our
                        country. Therefore the landowner who is possessed of a thousand acres,
                        receives only the profits of nine hundred: to-morrow, were the tithe law
                        repealed, he would have ten hundred, bona fide disposable to his own use and
                        benefit. Now when we can suppose our landlord not to be aware that a
                        thousand acres are worth a higher rental than nine hundred, then indeed we
                        may expect to be benefited by an abolition of the tithes!</p>
          <p>The small tradesman and the poor would be losers indeed, by the proposed
                        innovation: for the money which is in most cases spent and distributed among
                        them by the clergyman’s family, would be often drawn away by absentee
                        landlords, and spent at a distance from the parish, if not in a foreign
                        land.</p>
          <p>As to the very ancient triple distribution of the tithe, which has been
                        spoken of in certain quarters; one part to the poor; another to the
                        parochial clergy; and a third towards the repairs of the Cathedral; a
                        moment’s reflection will convince us of its impractibility at
                        present; when by the blessing of God our parish churches are so vastly
                        multiplied; and I am happy to add, multiplying. The solicitude of the enemy
                        for the beauty of our cathedrals is a little out of character: we may
                        believe it to equal their sympathy for the poor: with respect to whom, be it
                        remembered, that the clergyman <hi rend="i">pays his full share of poor-rate
                            upon his income</hi>; to say nothing of the innumerable private
                        charities, and neighbourly benefits conferred on their parishioners, by the
                        great majority of that amiable and venerable, though most shamefully
                        calumniated order.</p>
          <p>But the landholder would, in effect, gain little more than the farmer, by the
                        abolition of tithe: for, as the whole income of the Church, divided equally
                        among her clergy, has been calculated scarcely to afford a decent
                        maintenance to each; at least as much as was before levied in tithe, must
                        then be imposed as a tax by government. So long then as the clergy should be
                        decently supported, there would be no transfer of their incomes to the
                        landed proprietor or to any one else. And if a revolutionary government were
                        to ensue, and abolish our religious establishment altogether; which would be
                        one of its first achiev[e]ments; the landholder will not be so simple as to
                        believe that the Radicals would suffer him to sit down quietly with his
                        increased rent: that is, supposing there were any rent to be had, after free
                        trade had emptied his farms and exiled his tenants. No; they will tax him,
                        and fleece him to the skin; and then confiscate his estates. The demagogue
                        is the natural enemy of the landholders: for he finds in them at once the
                        toughest obstacles to his ambition, and the most delicious temptations to
                        his voracity. He will, therefore, spare no pains to decoy and devour
                        them.</p>
          <p>I will not attempt to adumbrate the gradations of <pb id="p19-64" n="64"/>
                        slow torment, through which the crew of a triumphant political union would
                        pare down the wretch who should fall into their clutches; condemned of that
                        crime, in their estimation the most inexpiable; the possession of wealth.
                        The spectacle of a whale under the hatchets of his harpooners; or rather of
                        the South American Indian, made through a summer day the amusement of his
                        captors, would present a lively type of the proceedings of these national
                        anatomists with the catalogue of his possessions; and, perhaps, with the
                        members of his person! I most humbly confess myself inadequate to do justice
                        to that consummation of fraud, rapine, outrage, and barbarity, which may be
                        expected from the Radicals of England, improving upon the example of the
                        French Jacobins.</p>
          <p>The British landholders are, however, too well aware of the motives of the
                        Liberals, very readily to accept any boon from their hands. But, lest the
                        people at large should be wired in a like gin; I shall take the liberty to
                        exhibit before them, for a few moments, their French neighbours, gulled by
                        the bait, and struggling in the toils: and it is then to be hoped that they
                        will take care not to render themselves most forlorn exceptions to the
                        general verity of the sacred proverb, that “the snare is surely
                        spread in vain, in the sight of any bird.”</p>
          <p>“Having”—“prepared the public mind, the assembly
                        made a bold attack on the Church. They discovered, by the light of
                        philosophy, that France contained too many churches, and, of course, too
                        many pastors. Great part of them were therefore to be suppressed; and to
                        make the innovation go down with the people, all tithes were to be
                        abolished. The measure succeeded; but what did the people gain by the
                        abolition of the tithes?—not a farthing; for a tax of twenty <hi rend="i">per cent.</hi> was immediately laid on the lands in consequence
                        of it. The cheat was not perceived till it was too late.”</p>
          <p>“But, the abolition of the tithes, the only motive of which was to
                        debase the Clergy in the opinions of the people, was but a trifle to what
                        was to follow.”</p>
          <p>Then, with respect to the seizure of the landed property of the French
                        Church; which was, beyond comparison, more extensive than that of our
                        own:—“To obtain the sanction of the people to this act, they
                        were told, that the wealth of the Church would not only pay off the national
                        debt, but render taxes in future unnecessary. No deception was ever so
                        barefaced as this; but even this was not wanted; for the people themselves
                        had already begun to taste the sweets of plunder. Avarice tempted the
                        trading part of the nation to approve of the measure. At the time of passing
                        the decree they were seen among the first to applaud it. They saw an easy
                        means of obtaining those fine rich estates, the possession of which they
                        had, perhaps, long coveted. In vain were they told, that the purchaser would
                        partake in the infamy of the robbery; that, if the title of the communities
                        could not render property secure, that same property could never be secure
                        under any title the plunderers could give. In vain were they told, that in
                        sanctioning the seizure of the wealth of others, they were sanctioning the
                        seizure of their own, whenever that all-devouring monster, the sovereign
                        people, should call on them for it. In vain were they told all this: they
                        purchased: they saw with pleasure the plundered Clergy driven from their
                        dwellings; but scarcely had they taken possession of their ill-gotten
                        wealth, when not only that, but the remains of their other property were
                        wrenched from them. Since that we have seen decree upon decree launched
                        forth against the rich: their account books have been submitted to public
                        examination: they have been obliged to give drafts for the funds which they
                        possessed even in foreign countries: all their letters have been intercepted
                        and read. How many hundreds of them have we seen led to the scaffold, merely
                        because they were proprietors of what their sovereign stood in need of!
                        These were acts of unexampled tyranny; but, as they respected the persons
                        who applauded the seizure of the estates of the Church, they were perfectly
                        just. Several of these avaricious purchasers have been murdered within the
                        walls of those buildings, whence they had assisted to drive the lawful
                        proprietors: this was just: it was the measure they had meted to others.
                        They shared the fate of the injured Clergy, without sharing the pity which
                        that fate excited. When dragged forth to slaughter in their turn, they were
                        left without even the right of complaining: the last stab of the assassin
                        was accompanied with the reflection, that it was just.”</p>
          <p>“I have dwelt the longer on this subject, as it is, perhaps, the most
                        striking and most awful example of the consequences of a violation of
                        property, that the world ever saw. Let it serve to warn all those who wish
                        to raise their fortunes on the ruin of others, that sooner or later, their
                        own turn must come. From this act of the Constituent Assembly we may date
                        the violation, in France, of every right that men ought to hold dear. Hence
                        the seizure of all gold and silver as the property of the nation: hence the
                        law preventing the son to claim the property of his father: hence the
                        abominable tyranny of requisitions; and hence thousands and thousands of the
                        murders, that have disgraced unhappy France.”</p>
          <p>These extracts are from pages 169, and 180, of a little book printed at
                        Philadelphia, and reprinted in London about the year 1797: it is entitled,
                        “The Bloody Buoy, thrown out as a Warning to the Political Pilots of
                        America; or, a Faithful Relation of a Multitude of Acts of Horrid Barbarity,
                        such as the Eye never witnessed, the Tongue never expressed, or the
                        Imagination conceived, until the commencement of the French Revolution. To
                        which is added an Instructive Essay, tracing these dreadful Effects to their
                        real Causes.”</p>
          <p>My Countrymen! the primary sources of all, were <pb id="p19-65" n="65"/>
                        INFIDELITY; and those <hi rend="i">principles</hi> of rebellion and plunder,
                        its legitimate offspring, which are now so industriously disseminated among
                        ourselves: and if it be reasonable to anticipate like effects from like
                        causes, we should be holding ourselves in solemn preparation for the worst:
                        yet with no dreary misgiving, that the Providence which has so long signally
                        blessed and protected this island, will forsake us in extremity: but with an
                        ardent faith and confidence that He who has now withdrawn Himself for a
                        while, and from His high and invisible watch tower in the heavens, is
                        beholding the fury of His enemies, and the lukewarmness of his servants;
                        will suddenly descend among us, and deliver us gloriously, at that moment
                        when we shall lay the ark of our liberties on the altar of the sanctuary;
                        and, banded together in one impregnable phalanx of holy
                        patriotism—SWEAR TO DEFEND THEM IN HIS NAME!</p>
          <p>Is this the rant of a fanatic?—NO. It is the zealous but sober voice
                        of one who dares to speak what millions think: millions, who seem stunned
                        and panic-stricken, by the yelling of a crew of savages, and a thoughtless
                        rabble who follow them. It is the voice of one who would deem it happiness
                        and glory indeed, to die for his country, in some great struggle against
                        some great enemy: but who shudders to take his death at the talons of a club
                        of runnagates whom his fathers would have hissed into the sea! It is the
                        voice of one, who, among other histories, has perused the awful annals of
                        the great French revolution, and has not nodded over the book: wherein
                        rivers of blood, and plains of desolation; conflag[r]ation, assassination,
                        violation, treachery, sacrilege, blasphemy, and every variety of
                        wretchedness, and every enormity of abomination, are as familiar as
                        household words.</p>
          <p>And it is to this, Kentish Yeomen, that our heartless adversaries are
                        reducing <hi rend="i">us:</hi> it is thus they began in France: and the most
                        ready dupes of the Parisian radicals became the earliest victims of their
                        fury, the moment they hesitated to plunge with them into gulfs of blood.</p>
          <p>We charge the Radicals of England; and they will, perhaps, glory in the
                        charge; with having eulogized that revolution through all its stages: with
                        having palliated its atrocities, that they might promulgate its principles.
                        Nor have they, from that day to this, left a stone unturned to accomplish an
                        imitation of it among ourselves. Indeed we cannot refuse to admire the
                        industry and ingenuity of these spiders; though we desire to tear their web:
                        nay we could find in our heart, to pity the unfortunate fowler, who, after
                        completing all his trains and contrivances; and standing ready in mute
                        expectation with his hand half extended toward the prey; should suddenly
                        behold all his nets, and gins, and springes broken in pieces. There will,
                        indeed, be much sympathy, and much surprise, should we venture to transfer
                        these doctors of absurdity, and “architects of ruin” from the
                        University of Europe to the Academy of Laputa: should our frigid obtuseness
                        be unable to conceive the sublimity of their vast plans for the emancipation
                        of the species; after all the breath which the illuminati of more genial
                        climates have spent upon us:—after all their <hi rend="i">performances</hi> on the Continent of Europe, to demonstrate
                        it:—should we still be found unable precisely to apprehend, how the
                        subversion of all government will tend to the security of peace, liberty,
                        and property; and how exceedingly both learning and virtue, and above all
                        religion and piety would be promoted, by the plunder and extirpation of
                        Christian establishments!</p>
          <p>The sentimental Ceruti said, with his last breath, “The only regret I
                        have in leaving the world, is, that I leave a religion on earth.” His
                        words were applauded by the Assembly, the Radical Assembly of France. And it
                        is, no doubt, with many of our own tender hearted liberals, a melancholy
                        reflection; that their most venerable and hoary sages of revolution may,
                        even now, perhaps, not survive <hi rend="i">every</hi> civil and religious
                        institution:—that they may “go to their own place,”
                        before they have amassed a full legacy of curses for their posterity.
                        However, no exertions have been wanting on their part: their efforts have
                        been alike patient, orderly, united, and energetic. Their army is at last
                        drawn out; and is about to make the grand charge. It has many raw recruits:
                        but many disciplined veterans, and able marshals. Their watchwords are
                        Liberty, and Reform: noble words indeed, but most foully abused. Let us
                        execrate their principles; but imitate, for once, their union and energy. If
                        we are divided, and disorganized; and above all, if we are panic-stricken,
                        every thing is lost. No superiority of numbers will avail us, if we are
                        separated, or wavering, or unprepared. In 1780 eight hundred thousand
                        Londoners looked on in consternation, while a handful of pickpockets ravaged
                        their property for three days! An eye witness of the Bristol outrages
                        declared, that at the beginning, forty persons might have dispersed the
                        rioters easily. On the 9th of November 1830, the leaders of the Radicals not
                        being prepared to show themselves; and being disconcerted by a premature
                        discovery of their plot; their mobs being consequently not so well organized
                        as the police; the latter saved the metropolis from destruction. It was, I
                        think, Marat, one of the Radical Reformers of France, who boasted that with
                        three hundred ruffians hired at a Louis d’or per day, he could govern
                        all France: and why? because all France was dismembered and
                        panic-stricken.</p>
          <p>Let us remember the fable of the lion and the bulls.</p>
          <p>It is true we vastly, and beyond comparison outnumber the enemy: but then we
                        are men of peace; and they are beasts of prey. We are strongest by day: they
                        ravine in the night; for their optics are adapted to darkness. And it is now
                        a very dark night for Europe. The radicals are elated; for it is a dark and
                        foggy night; when <pb id="p19-66" n="66"/> thieves are always on the alert.
                        They are housebreakers: we are quiet householders, who have drawn the
                        curtains, and retired to rest!</p>
          <p>Permit me to suggest to you, Electors of West Kent, that this is no time to
                        multiply party distinctions, or to remember old grudges. We should travel in
                        Caravan; prepared against a horde of thieves far more cruel than wandering
                        Arabs. These highwaymen will rifle us if they catch us singly; but take to
                        their heels over hedge and ditch, should they once meet us walking together
                        on the King’s Highway.</p>
          <p>Let the <hi rend="i">good old</hi> Whigs, the Tories high and low, and the
                        men of no party, for once come together, and twist a threefold cord which
                        may not easily be broken.</p>
          <p>It was thus Britain was saved in 1792, from a revolution which our illuminati
                        were then on the very point of effecting. She was saved by nothing less than
                        an inspiration from Heaven: by nothing else than a most sudden, universal
                        revulsion of patriotism; and a simultaneous consociation, from one end of
                        the kingdom to the other. And this revolution our abandoned Liberals had
                        striven to bring about, while the blood of France was yet hot and reeking;
                        and with the stench of that great butchery under their nostrils! In the
                        extension of their philanthropy, which, indeed, they truly allege to be
                        trammelled with no vulgar demarkations of patriotic geography, they were
                        instituting a flesh market for the cannibals of Europe; and preparing to
                        slay their brethren for the shambles. France was too narrow for them: and
                        they were about to enlarge that slaughter-house of Europe by throwing into
                        it the habitations of their fathers.</p>
          <p>The French had been smitten with giddiness from God; and distracted with
                        delirious theories, more multitudinous than the tongues of Babel: but it was
                        not while they were aspiring to raise a pinnacle to the skies; but were
                        laying, in the very depths of Hell, the foundations of a charnel-house for
                        Christendom.</p>
          <p>But they meted out upon <hi rend="i">themselves</hi> the “line of
                        confusion and the stones of emptiness.” After laying waste one of the
                        richest countries in the world, to obtain liberty and equality; they fell at
                        once into the most abject military bondage, under a remorseless tyrant; who,
                        wonderful to say, has ever been the pagod of our own most furious
                        republicans and levellers: at whose spoliation of the liberties of Europe
                        they exulted: at whose signal defeat and overthrow, by the blessing of God
                        on the valour of their countrymen, they have scarcely ceased their wailings
                        to this day.</p>
          <p>In words, they are peace-makers and philanthropists: in deeds, they are
                        incendiaries and assassins. They extenuated Buonaparte’s most
                        unprovoked a[g]gressions and invasions; and had he invaded <hi rend="i">their own country</hi>, would have hailed him with acclamations! But,
                        when the standard of Spanish independence was lifted up; no sooner did
                        Wellington and British valour drive him from the Peninsula, and unbind the
                        nations; than truly, on a sudden, no cloistered maiden was to be found so
                        sensitive, nay, so pious as the Radical! Yes, he who had beheld with sullen
                        indifference the excesses of Robespierre, and with savage transport the
                        exploits of Napoleon; would now, forsooth, doubt the very lawfulness of
                        defensive warfare! He would question whether any true disciple of the Prince
                        of Peace could take up arms! He would faint at the clash of a sword or the
                        beating of a drum!</p>
          <p>Gratitude the Radicals do not know. Their insolence ever increases with
                        indulgence. Till they get the power into their hands, they whimper like
                        school-boys; nay they can sob, and lisp, and languish like an
                        infant:—the moment they are elevated, they dash in pieces the dupe
                        who lifted them up. They are a generation of crocodiles, who mimic the
                        wailings of distress, and devour those who come to relieve it.</p>
          <p>They can put on the most saintly garb of Apostolic simplicity; and associate
                        with the disciples that they may betray the Master. They are, at present,
                        filled with apprehension, lest Christiantiy should suffer through an
                        over-fed priesthood; and are most politely assiduous to relieve them of
                        their superfluities: nay, so earnest are they found in this pious work; that
                        even freehold estates, secured by the most indubitable titles to the Church,
                        and legacies entailed upon it with the most awful sanctions, would be
                        alienated at their touch: and signatures, and seals, and stamps, and rolls
                        of parchment, would become dissolved in a moment, in the furnace of their
                        Evangelical charity! Did our fathers pour forth their treasures at the feet
                        of the Redeemer; and, in the most solemn manner, endow the Church with them
                        for ever?—Hark!—these children of Judas Iscariot are
                        inquiring, “Why is not all this sold, and the money given to the
                        poor?[”]—But this they say, not because they care for the
                        poor; but because they are thieves, and desire to clutch the bag, and to
                        make off with its contents!” [sic]</p>
          <p>The Radicals have long clamoured for Parliamentary Reform, and a full
                        representation, as the national panacea. This has been granted them, even to
                        the extent of their own desires: and are they satisfied? Are they about to
                        treat this reformed Parliament, this darling of their hopes, as nursing
                        mothers?—or have they, while it is yet in the womb, prepared their
                        political unions to hector over, and bully it?</p>
          <p>They now declare that this is but a <hi rend="i">first step:</hi> it is
                        tolerated, however, because they imagine that they behold in it the dawn and
                        twilight of a republic.</p>
          <p>By this faction the Queen has already been most publicly menaced with the
                        scaffold, in terms aggravated by personal insult: and our Sovereign, whose
                        venerable parent’s memory is, at present, a favourite butt of their
                        savage vituperation: our beloved Sovereign, whose reign has been hitherto
                        one series of concession; will fall the <pb id="p19-67" n="67"/> earliest
                        victim to their baseness and perfidy; unless it should please the Almighty
                        to dash their projects, and to “turn the counsel of Ahitophel into
                        foolishness.”</p>
          <p>The English Radical, and the Gallic Jacobin “are brethren; instruments
                        of cruelty are in their habitations. O my soul, come not thou into their
                        secret; unto their assembly, mine honour, be not thou united: for in their
                        anger they slew a man, and in their self-will they digged down a wall.
                        Cursed be their anger, for it was fierce; and their wrath, for it was
                        cruel.” They are the abortions and monsters of the moral universe;
                        uncouth, perverse, and opposite to nature. They will grovel in the dust
                        before a tyrant: but with a gentle and parental Sovereign “their neck
                        is as an iron sinew; and their brow brass.” They will cringe under
                        the rod; and bite the hand that caresses them.</p>
          <p>And will you, my countrymen, suffer this deplorable faction to pour out, not
                        their representatives, but their delegates over the counties: to send forth
                        their foxes, two by two, into your harvests, tied together by revolutionary
                        pledges; and dragging between them the firebrands of destruction? Samson
                        sent fire-b[r]ands to the <hi rend="i">Philistine</hi> fields. But <hi rend="i">we</hi>, if we make Constituents of these foxes of free trade
                        and liberalism; shall be directing the matches of a starving peasantry to
                        our own garners; and politically, shall light up such a fire in our country,
                        as nothing will extinguish but the waters of desolation.</p>
          <p>Samson, in death as in life heroic, brought down upon his head the vault of
                        Dagon; and perished with his foes. But <hi rend="i">we</hi> are shattering
                        the citadel of <hi rend="i">our own</hi> strength; the tabernacle of our
                        constitution, the temple of our liberties, and the sanctuary of our God. We
                        are tugging at those two main pillars; our loyalty and our piety; and shall
                        be ground to powder, in the crash and perdition of our country.</p>
          <q> So fond are mortal men,<lb/> Fallen into wrath divine,<lb/> As their own
                        ruin on themselves t’ invite;<lb/> Insensate left or to sense
                        reprobate;<lb/> And with blindness internal struck.”<lb/> Milton. </q>
          <p>Brother Electors; we have been requested to return to Parliament two
                        Gentlemen, who have, unhappily, ranked themselves under the standard of the,
                        so called, Radical Reformers. Personal remark is remote from my intention:
                        but I would remind you that the Radicals have ever been found adverse to the
                        agricultural interest: that whatever they may pretend; they will, if
                        possible, sweep away your protecting duties.</p>
          <p>Farmers! They were the wretched leaders of this wretched faction, who, during
                        the late dreadful fires, strenuously encouraged the incendiaries! Some of
                        the most abandoned of them published cheap tracts for distribution among the
                        poor, stimulating them to fire their master’s property. But now, if
                        there be a Radical Parliament; the starvation produced by free trade, and
                        the consequent reckless desperation of the peasantry; will supersede the
                        necessity of all other stimulants. If, then, you patronise Radicalism, in
                        any shape, you will have yourselves to thank for the consequences.</p>
          <p>Already, the fires have begun. Do you wish them to blaze once more over the
                        kingdom? If you do; send Radicals into Parliament; make Radicals of the
                        poor; and as those principles effectually relieve all classes from every
                        religious and moral restraint; neither property nor life will be for a
                        moment secure. Conflagration has already ravaged your harvests; and
                        assassination and massacre are in its train.</p>
          <p>Landholders, who have estates to be confiscated, or laid in ashes: Farmers,
                        who have free trade, and annihilation impending over you: Manufacturers, who
                        must be beggared in the bankruptcy of your country: Fund-holders, who desire
                        not the <hi rend="i">wet sponge:</hi> Britons, who have liberty to lose:
                        Christians, who have a religion to be blasphemed: now is the time for your
                        last struggle! The ensuing Election is not a question of party politics;
                        much less, a paltry squabble of family interests: but Existence, or
                        Annihilation, to good old England!</p>
          <p>Let us then rally once more: Whigs, Tories, Moderates; and especially every
                        Christian man in West Kent;—it may be for the last time;—round
                        the noble standard of Old Kentish Loyalty; and defend it to the last. If we
                        triumph; our children will say of us;—“These were the sacred
                        heroes, who, amid the convulsion of the world, serenely held fast, and
                        transmitted to us the birthright of our liberties: nay, all our glory, in
                        the inheritance of the British Name.” If we perish in the contest;
                        let it not be, O Spirit of Albion, as recreants and dastrads: but with Thy
                        standard clenched in our grasp; or folded about our hearts!</p>
          <p>God prosper the good old cause: it is His Own. Is it the cause of old
                        England: of our beloved Monarch: of our nobles: most truly of all our middle
                        classes; and preeminently of the poor; who, in the destruction of commerce
                        and agriculture; of order and property, get nothing of the spoil; but suffer
                        every extremity of wretchedness and famine.</p>
          <p>The other cause is that of the Devil and his Angels; masked under a pretended
                        indignation at State tyranny, and Church corruption: witness, again, the
                        great French Revolution: wherein the King, after making every just
                        concession, and much more was savagely murdered: the nobles were massacred
                        and banished: the Clergy butchered by companies, or assassinated at their
                        church doors. A strumpet was dressed up, and publicly adored in the
                        Cathedral of Paris, as the Goddess of Reason: our Saviour was denounced as
                        an arch imposter, and the profession of his religion was prohibited!</p>
          <p>The whole Radical and Atheistical party of England is now marshalled against
                        the constitutional and religious; <pb id="p19-68" n="68"/> and Europe is
                        looking on in solemn expectation[.]</p>
          <p>The result of the ensuing Election will turn the balance. <hi rend="i">One
                            additional Conservative Member may save this great nation:—the
                            vote of any one individual may secure that Member’s
                            election.</hi> Every friend to our cause, however humble, should
                        energize as if all depended on himself.</p>
          <p>Unanimous co-operation and individual energy may do all things.</p>
          <p>Electors; he who has thus taken the liberty to address you, however
                        inadequate to the task; claims, at last, the merit of disinterestedness. Sir
                        William Geary is personally unknown to him: nor will he obtain any sort of
                        benefit by that Gentleman’s return to Parliament. He has addressed
                        you, without the instigation of a second person: without the knowledge of
                        Sir William, or any of his Committees. The writer receives not one farthing
                        of the great or small tithe: <hi rend="i">he has no connection with, or
                            dependence on the Clergy:</hi> he is neither a prophet, nor the son of a
                        prophet. Alas! it is no longer a little cloud of the bigness of a
                        man’s hand, which hovers in our political horizon, but a blackness of
                        [word illegible] which it requires no prophetic direction to perceive. He is
                        not accustomed to push himself forward: he loves not to hear himself talk;
                        but would rather have listened while another spoke. He has not obtruded into
                        the front ranks of the loyal army: but would be overwhelmed by the sense of
                        such presumption. He has waited long in the rear and outposts, hoping that
                        some stronger arm might be lifted up against the big and boastful Philistine
                        of Jacobinism, who has hurled defiance alike at the institutions of men and
                        the armies of God. And he has no heartier desire than that while he is
                        picking up these few pebbles from the brook, and cutting out this rustic
                        sling, he may be superseded and borne away by one sudden acclamation of
                        re-kindled patriotism from Guernsey to the Hebrides: that Britain may never
                        become intellectually a province of France: that her wolves of revolution
                        may hear once more the British lion roaring from the cliffs of Kent, and be
                        discomfitted: that we may never like the Trojans; whom old historians repute
                        our ancestors; be undone by the presents of an enemy: but that the liberty
                        and equality which our treacherous neighbours have offered us, as winged
                        steeds to be yoked into the car of human improvement; may be timely
                        suspected to be full of armed men: and, finally: that all our countrymen who
                        have been deceived and over-persuaded by the internal troublers of our
                        peace, may have the true nobility of mind readily and frankly to confess
                        their mistake: and, instead of setting by the ears every class and order of
                        society; may strive as heartily to promote that universal good will, and
                        blessed brotherly union, which are the only root and basis of our prosperity
                        and strength: which are able to lift us up, once more, in the scale of
                        nations; and to constitute Britannia, as she was ever wont to be, the
                        arbitress of the destinies, and the guardian of the liberties of Europe.</p>
          <p>FINIS.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p19-69" n="69"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Keynes and Blake at Cambridge</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>G.E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>When Sir Geoffrey Keynes died on 5 July 1982 at the age of ninety-five, he
                        had the greatest Blake collection in private hands in Britain, and his Blake
                        collection was only a small part of the entire library, though it seemed to
                        be where his heart lay. His collections were the basis of his own
                        bibliographies of, inter alia, John Donne (1914; 1932; 1958; 1973), Sir
                        Thomas Browne (1924; 1968), William Harvey (1928; 1953), Jane Austen (1929),
                        William Hazlitt (1931; 1981), John Ray (1941; 1951), Rupert Brooke (1954;
                        1959), Robert Hooke (1960), Siegfried Sassoon (1962), George Berkeley
                        (1976), and Henry King (1977), and among these the contemporary copies of
                        books by Blake were comparatively small in number. But when to these were
                        added books with commercial engravings by Blake (such as five copies of <hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi> [1825; 1826] in different original boards),
                        proofs, prints, sketches, paintings, imitations, embroidery, facsimiles, and
                        the scholarship of the subject (much of it his own), the size of his Blake
                        collection became substantial, and its interest to students of Blake was
                        unsurpassed of its kind—particularly when displayed by the
                        collector.</p>
          <p>The mark of the collector was strongly impressed upon these cherished and
                        beautiful books, from his bookplate, to his manuscript notes on provenance
                        and condition, to his published descriptions of them, and it was exceedingly
                        desirable that the collections should be kept together, both as an aid to
                        scholars of the future—what <hi rend="i">has</hi> become of
                        Blake’s transcription of a poem by Sheridan which Sir Geoffrey
                        alluded to so tantalizingly in 1964?—and as a memorial to the
                        collector. Sir Geoffrey’s intentions altered from time to time, and
                        there seemed to be a strong possibility that the collection would be
                        separated subject by subject, which would have been a great pity.</p>
          <p>Fortunately that has not occurred, for the collection of books was sold to
                        Cambridge University Library. There they have been arranged by subject in
                        the exceedingly handsome Keynes Room, which is to be used as a meeting-place
                        for the Syndics of the Library. Not only are the books in a beautiful room,
                        but they are now for the first time gathered in one place, for in his London
                        residence and at Lammas House, Brinkley, not far from Cambridge, the books
                        were scattered in many rooms—and sometimes shelved five deep. They
                        make a brave display in the Keynes Room, and my only regret when I saw it in
                        November 1984 was that, for reasons of security and convenience, mere
                        scholars will not be able to work there, though they may of course use the
                        books in the rare book reading room.</p>
          <p>There was a Keynes exhibition at the University Library in the summer of
                        1983, without a catalogue, but it is only fairly recently that the final
                        payment has been made for the collection and the books have become
                        officially the property of the University and accessible to readers.</p>
          <p>What Blakes are here? In general, everything associated with Blake printed
                        from movable type or in manuscript is in the Keynes Room in the Cambridge
                        University Library. The easiest means of identifying what is there at the
                        moment is Sir Geoffrey’s own description of his collection, <hi rend="i">Bibliotheca Bibliographici</hi> (1964), supplemented by the
                        card file he made (also in the collection) of about five hundred important
                        works he acquired after 1964. In terms of Blake, the most exciting addition
                        to the 1964 list is <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> copy P, which was
                        previously described, at least by me, only at second hand. That description
                        should read as follows:</p>
          <q><hi rend="i">BINDING:</hi> “BOUND BY RIVIERE &amp; SON”
                        (according to a stamp on the front inner board) in Green morocco, gilt, top
                        edge gilt, other edges untrimmed, with the Advertisement and pp. 57-70 in
                        type-facsimile, the Advertisement of remarkably persuasive quality
                        (titlepage size: 13.7 × 22.1 cm). The book has no MS correction and
                        almost certainly passed at Blake’s death to Catherine Blake and
                        thence to Tatham.<lb/><hi rend="i">HISTORY:</hi> (1) Acquired from Quaritch about 1900 (according
                        to Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> [1949]) by (2) General Archibald
                        Stirling of Keir, who added on a flyleaf his initials and a note of 12
                        February 1921 about the presence of the facsimile gatherings; from him, it
                        passed to (3) Lt.-Col. William Stirling, who sold it; (4) Sold anonymously
                        at Sotheby’s, 25 April 1978, lot 50, to (5) Sir Geoffrey Keynes, who
                        sold it in 1982 to (6) Cambridge University Library. </q>
          <p>But there are treasures for the scholar which will not be found in either <hi rend="i">Bibliotheca Bibliographici</hi> or in Sir Geoffrey’s
                        card-addenda to it. Naturally he did not trouble to list copies of ordinary
                        books which any modern scholar might be expected to own, such as
                        Butlin’s <hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>
                        (1981) or Paley’s presentation copy of his Phaidon <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1978). Some of the most interesting features of the
                        collection are the annotations which Sir Geoffrey made in his books,
                        particularly in copies of his own publications. These occasionally contain
                        information of significant value, so minor that Sir Geoffrey thought them
                        scarcely worth printing but which are yet of real interest to those with
                        somewhat lower standards of novelty. For instance, in the interleaved proof
                        copy of his <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William Blake</hi> (1921) he
                        annotated the 1868 Camden Hotten facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                            Heaven and Hell:</hi> “Edward Gordon Duff told John Sampson that
                        Lord Houghton <pb id="p19-70" n="70"/> lent his copy of the original [<hi rend="i">Copy F</hi>] to Swinburne, and that Camden Hotten made his
                        facsimile without permission, whereat Lord Houghton was much
                        incensed.” This provides a persuasive context for the otherwise
                        puzzling relationship between Lord Houghton and Camden Hotten; it was not
                        previously known that “Camden Hotten made his facsimile without
                        permission.”</p>
          <p>Similarly, in his copy of the Keynes &amp; Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi>
                        (1953), Keynes inserted a facsimile of a letter from the U.S. artist Francis
                        Lathrop of 9 January 1908 to Mr. [Beverley] Chew (the original is in the
                        Grolier Club Library) offering “the ‘Stothard copy’ of
                        the Book of Thel [<hi rend="i">Copy E</hi>]—the original Blake, that
                        I spoke about” for $350. Lathrop had not previously been known to
                        have any original Blake—and Chew is not known to have owned a copy of
                            <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi></p>
          <p>In the interleaved copy of his <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William
                            Blake</hi> at p. 371 he drew attention to a reference to Blake which has
                        not heretofore been reprinted: <q> Anon., “Art. VIII. <hi rend="i">The Chimney-Sweepers’ Friend, and Climbing-Boys’
                                Album</hi> . . . Arranged by James Montgomery . . . Price 9s.
                            London, 1824.” <hi rend="i">Eclectic Review</hi>, N.S., XXI (June
                            1824), 558-562.<lb/> The review includes on pp. 559-560 a puzzled
                            reference to “The Chimney Sweeper” with a quotation of the
                            poem from Montgomery’s book:<lb/> We know not how to characterize
                            the song given from Blake’s ‘Songs of Innocence.’
                            It is wild and strange, like the singing of ‘a maid in Bedlam in
                            the spring,’ but it is the madness of genius. </q>
                        Montgomery’s book has long been known, but this printing of
                        Blake’s poem, showing the “madness of genius,” has not.
                        Most accounts of Blake omitted the phrase “of genius.”</p>
          <p>Finally in his 1921 <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>, at p. 417, Sir Geoffrey
                        referred to a work by Joseph Hallett Junior which apparently belonged to
                        Blake but which has not heretofore been associated with him in print. It is
                        in three volumes, each with a different titlepage: <q> A | Free <hi rend="i">and</hi> Impartial Study <hi rend="i">of the</hi> | HOLY SCRIPTURES
                                <hi rend="i">recommended:</hi> | BEING | NOTES | ON SOME | PECULIAR
                            TEXTS; | WITH | Discourses and Observations | ON | The following
                            Subjects; <hi rend="i">viz.</hi> | I. Of the Quotations from the <hi rend="i">Old Testament</hi> in the Apocrypha. | II. Of the <hi rend="i">Septuagint</hi> Version of the <hi rend="i">Bible;</hi> and
                            the Diffe-|rence between the <hi rend="i">Citations</hi>, as they lie in
                            the <hi rend="i">New Testa-|ment</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Original
                                Passages</hi> in the <hi rend="i">Old.</hi> | III. <hi rend="i">Christians</hi> not bound by any Authority of the <hi rend="i">Law</hi> of | <hi rend="i">Moses</hi> in the <hi rend="i">Ten
                                Commandments.</hi> | IV. Of the Doxology at the End of the
                            Lord’s-Prayer. Of | blessing the <hi rend="i">Eucharistical
                                Elements</hi>, and of Grace before | and after Meat, | V. The Son of
                            God knows the Hearts of Men; and, of Anger, | Catechising, <hi rend="i">&amp;c.</hi> | VI. A Passage in Bishop <hi rend="i">Pearson</hi>
                            on the Creed, and another | in Bishop <hi rend="i">Patrick’s</hi>
                            Commentaries examin’d. | VII. Of the Soul; its Immortality,
                            Immateriality, <hi rend="i">&amp;c.</hi> with | the Impossibility of
                            proving a Future State by the Light | of Nature; and of the Place where
                            Good Men shall dwell | after the Resurrection. | - | By <hi rend="i">JOSEPH HALLETT</hi>, Jun<hi rend="s">r</hi>. | - | <hi rend="i">LONDON;</hi> | Printed for J. Noon, at the <hi rend="i">White-Hart</hi> in <hi rend="i">Cheapside</hi>, near | <hi rend="i">Mercers-Chapel.</hi> M. DCC. XXIX [1729].<lb/><lb/> A | SECOND
                            VOLUME | OF | NOTES | AND | DISCOURSES: | CONTAINING | I. A New List of
                            Errors noted in the present <hi rend="i">Hebrew</hi> Copies | of the <hi rend="i">Old Testament.</hi> | II. Notes on several Texts of
                            Scripture. | III. Discourses on the Reality, Kinds, and Number of our |
                            Saviour’s Miracles; occasion’d by Mr. <hi rend="i">Woolston’s</hi> Six | Discourses. | The Meaning of the Word,
                                <hi rend="i">God;</hi> and the Doctrine of Providence. | The Nature
                            of <hi rend="i">Sacrifices;</hi> particularly of the Sacrifice of | <hi rend="i">Christ.</hi> | The Original of <hi rend="i">Evil.</hi> |
                            The Nature of <hi rend="i">Ordination.</hi> | A <hi rend="i">Review</hi>
                            of the former <hi rend="i">Volume</hi>, particularly relating to the |
                            Passage in Bishop <hi rend="i">Pearson</hi> on the <hi rend="i">Creed.</hi> concerning the | Meaning of the Word, <hi rend="i">Almighty</hi>, in the Sixth Article; | and to the Nature of <hi rend="i">Anger.</hi> | - | <hi rend="i">By</hi> JOSEPH HALLETT <hi rend="i">jun.</hi> | - | <hi rend="i">LONDON:</hi> | Printed for J.
                            Noon, at the <hi rend="i">White Hart</hi> in <hi rend="i">Cheapside</hi>, near <hi rend="i">Mercers-chapel.</hi> M.DCC.XXXII [1732].<lb/><lb/><figure/></q> Sir Geoffrey’s note says that in each octavo volume of an
                        untraced set of three volumes in old calf is Blake’s autograph, dated
                        1799, with the price he paid for it (£1.5.0) in the first volume. Sir
                        Geoffrey probably found the reference to Blake’s copy of
                        Hallett’s book in the Anderson Gallery sale catalogue of The Library
                        of the Late H. Buxton Forman, Part Two (26 April 1920), lot 46, where the
                        price, however, is given as a guinea, not as £1.5.0.</p>
          <p>Doubtless other “discoveries” concerning Blake and many other
                        authors remain to be found in the very rich collection of books which passed
                        from Sir Geoffrey Keynes to the Cambridge University Library. But for
                        efficient access to them we must wait for the collection to be catalogued.
                        Many besides myself will hope for the appearance at least of a handlist
                        concerning William Blake as soon as possible.</p>
          <p>Over the years Sir Geoffrey clearly changed his mind about the destination of
                        his Blakes; a few he gave away and sold, as is recorded in Robert N.
                        Essick’s great catalogue raisonné of <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake’s Separate Plates</hi> (1981). The final decision was that
                        the Blakes which were printed from movable type and in manuscript should go
                        with the rest of his books to the University Library. Most of the Keynes
                        collection of “paintings, drawings, and prints by William
                        Blake” were handed over to the Fitzwilliam Museum as this article
                        went to press (according to Donald Wintersgill, “Museum Is Given
                        Blakes,” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi>, 16 May 1985, p. 5).</p>
          <p>One may lament their separation from Blake’s purely literary works but
                        recognize that this is a twentieth century commonplace. It is paralleled by
                        the division of the splendid Rosenwald Collection a few years ago between
                        the Library of Congress and the U.S. National <pb id="p19-71" n="71"/>
                        Gallery, and it will be paralleled by the separation of the illuminated and
                        other graphic works in the British Museum Print Room from the typographical
                        and manuscript works in the British Library when the latter eventually finds
                        its new quarters. It is a touching irony that Blake labored all his life to
                        unite the arts of the eye and the ear, the vision and the word, but that
                        this union is posthumously divorced in the disposition of the great
                        collections of his works.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>The Crying of Lot 318; or, Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
                                Thoughts</hi> Colored Once More</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Karen <name>Mulhallen</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <q> Sotheby’s (London, Monday, 17 December 1984, 2.30 p.m.)<lb/><lb/>
                        318<lb/><lb/> Blake (William)—Young (Edward) The Complaint and the
                        Consolation, or Night Thoughts, 43 pictorial borders designed and engraved
                        by William Blake and coloured by hand, slightly soiled, three borders
                        slightly offset, a few short tears in margin of explanation leaf and one
                        slightly affecting one border repaired, red straightgrained morocco gilt,
                        uncut, folio, R. Noble for R. Edwards, 1797 </q>
          <p>The Clarendon edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi><ref target="n12" type="note">1</ref> lists and describes 23 colored copies
                        of the engraved work, and refers to one more, the Moss-Bentley copy G<ref target="n13" type="note">2</ref> recently rediscovered by Thomas V.
                        Lange in a closet of the Lutheran Church of America (<hi rend="i">Blake
                            Quarterly</hi> 59, pp. 134-36). To these 24, in 1983, James McCord added
                        the copy housed for over 50 years, but not recorded, in the library of
                        Washington University, St. Louis.<ref target="n14" type="note">3</ref> While
                        doing research in London in the winter of 1984-85, I came upon yet another
                        unrecorded copy of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, bringing to 26 the
                        number of recorded copies. Following the format of the Clarendon census, I
                        would list this most recent copy as<lb/> III-2 (Previously unknown) Grey
                        Death. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s
                                Designs for Edward Young’s “Night
                                Thoughts,”</hi> edited by John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose,
                            Michael J. Tolley, coordinating editor David V. Erdman (Oxford:
                            Clarendon Press, 1980), pp. 62-72.</note><note id="n13"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi>, p. 61 and n. 81, p. 92; G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977), pp.
                            636-46.</note><note id="n14"><hi rend="s">3</hi> James McCord, “An Unrecorded
                            Colored Copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 18 (Fall 1984),
                            116-18. McCord’s tally of copies includes Bentley copy T, the
                            Cook copy, which he argues is not included in the Clarendon census. He
                            is incorrect, as this is Clarendon copy I-15.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Description:</hi> Handsome, early twentieth century “Arts
                        &amp; Crafts Style” binding in red straight-grained morocco gilt
                        with five raised bands running horizontally across the spine terminating in
                        stamped fruit and leaf motifs. Binding stamp WHS (for W.H. Smith and Sons)
                        on lower border of inner back cover. Spine stamped in gold “Night
                        Thoughts By Edward Young. Designs By W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake
                        1797.” Pale pink and blue marbled endpapers. All edges uncut.
                        Watermarked in lower right hand corner on ten sheets, pp. iii-iv, 3-4, 5-6,
                        29-30, 31-32, 49-50, 55-56, 69-70, 85-86, and 91-92, as well as on the
                        “Explanation of the Engravings” sheet which appears after page
                        95, “J Whatman 1794.”</p>
          <p>The prints are in good condition, except for one repair slightly affecting
                        the border of pp. 89-90, a few short tears in the margin of the explanation
                        leaf, some slight soiling, and three borders a little offset. As is usual,
                        in a few instances the plate marks extend slightly beyond the foredge of the
                        leaf, but only five borders have the engraved surface touching the page
                        edge.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Provenance:</hi> Inscribed on the verso of the title page in
                        pencil in the upper left hand corner is “Baron Dimsdale”.
                        According to Sotheby’s, this copy was acquired by Charles John, fifth
                        Baron Dimsdale, together with copies of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>
                        and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi><ref target="n15" type="note">4</ref> Sold by Sotheby’s (London, 17 December 1984) to Sims,
                        Reed &amp; Fogg, £13, 750. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The
                            Dimsdale copies of the illuminated works are described in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pp. 170, 180, 384, and 410. The Sotheby’s
                            catalogue states that the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> was
                            “probably acquired . . . together with copies of <hi rend="i">The
                                Book of Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence.</hi>” No evidence is given for this assertion,
                            although Michael Heseltine of Sotheby’s confirmed the
                            copy’s provenance and wrote the catalogue entry. However, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> notes that it was the <hi rend="i">first</hi> Baron Dimsdale (1712-1800) who acquired copies of the
                            illuminated books, whereas the Sotheby’s catalogue states that it
                            was the <hi rend="i">fifth</hi> Baron Dimsdale who acquired all
                            three.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Pencil Markings:</hi> There are four sets of pencil markings in
                        this copy: Front of fly-title “2.P 7”; verso of title page,
                        upper left, “Baron Dimsdale”; page 50 “1.5
                        <hi rend="s">—</hi>” or “1. <inline-image n="019-02-p71-curved-stroke"/> .”, or upside down “<hi rend="s">—</hi>
                        6.1”, difficult to make out but likely bookseller’s price
                        code; verso of Explanation leaf, near gutter in lower right hand corner,
                        “EB”.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Some other distinctive features:</hi> Page 23 has a faint
                        L-shaped line in ink in the bottom margin, as if the plate accidentally
                        skipped in the press, thereby creating a line with the same configuration as
                        one of the etched/engraved lines in the plate.</p>
          <p>Pages 23, 26, 27 and 33 use the color red for drapery, clothing and wine, and
                        in some instances the color seems blotchy, as if, as the color dried, the
                        pigment has come out of suspension in patches.</p>
          <p>Pages 37 and 70 stand out from all the others in that the foliage and ground
                        are in various shades of green, appearing as a surprisingly naturalistic use
                        of color, especially in comparison to other of the engravings.</p>
          <p>The title page to Night III displays Narcissa, illustrated in the
                        Sotheby’s catalogue in color, as remarkably naked, the slight drapery
                        on the front of her body emphasizing this.</p>
          <p>Page 75, Phoebus, shows quite clearly the coloring technique. The whole page
                        was first washed in yellow, grey was then added to the clouds and hair, then
                        a deeper yellow was added to the sun and to the body of Phoebus. Finally,
                        his body while still wet was wiped and a pink wash applied. In coloring this
                        plate seems to have a close connection with one copy in the Rosenwald
                        Collection (Copy I-4), where the horses, the sun, and Phoebus are all golden
                        yellow. In I-4, the gold is set against an irridescent sky of reds, blues,
                        purples and yellows. While it would be difficult to make a case for one as a
                        model for another, the similarity of some of the coloring and the coloring
                        steps as revealed in the Dimsdale copy together suggest a close dating for
                        the two copies.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Issues raised by the Dimsdale Copy (III-2):</hi> The Clarendon
                            <pb id="p19-72" n="72"/> census codes copies according to the color of
                        Death’s gown on the title page to Night I, the most common color
                        being white (Type I), the next green (Type II), with a single copy, in the
                        Houghton Library at Harvard, being grey (Type III). Grey is the key color
                        for the entire Dimsdale copy. Not only is Death charmingly portrayed in a
                        grey gown, but many other figures are also robed in grey. The angels, for
                        example, from pages 40-42, are depicted with grey wings, whereas in several
                        other copies these are multi-colored with an iridescent effect. And on page
                        80, the red-faced Thunder God with gold rays emanating from his head is
                        dressed by dramatic contrast in grey clothes while the sea beneath is grey
                        and green.</p>
          <p>In III-2 special attention has also been paid to skin, hair and eyes.
                        Death’s skin is quite tanned and many figures show very careful
                        highlighting and pale blue veining. Hair is often cap- or wig-like, and the
                        eyes are usually brightly demarcated.</p>
          <p>Pages 53-54, 60 and 62 of the Clarendon census discuss the
                        “non-standard” details of Type III, “the colouring of
                        the beard of Time in 11E (NT36)<ref target="n16" type="note">5</ref> being
                        brown, rather than white or grey as in all other copies.” In the
                        Dimsdale copy, however, Time’s beard is white, although his topknot
                        by contrast is black. The Clarendon editors conjecture that the Harvard copy
                        was “quite likely to have been done by some possessor of an
                        uncoloured copy for his own enjoyment, or as a forgery” (p. 60). They
                        conclude that III-1 “Stands apart from all others. In such specific
                        details as the colour of Death’s garments and the colours of the
                        garments and hair of other figures as well as in its general character, this
                        copy is peculiar. Of all copies it seems most likely to have been done
                        without close reference to any copy that might have had Blake’s
                        authorization” (p. 62). <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">5</hi> 11E is in
                            the masculine state.</note></p>
          <p>The discovery of the Dimsdale copy necessitates a re-examination of the
                        Clarendon speculations about Type III, and the similarity of III-2 to Type I
                        copies reconfirms the need to be sceptical about fixity of coloring patterns
                        and their dating.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>An Unpublished Poem by S. Foster Damon</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Josephine <name>McQuail</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>On a particularly gloomy winter day in 1984 I attempted to cheer myself up by
                        a visit to my friend John Guillot’s bookstore in Charlottesville,
                        Virginia. John, now the proprietor of Magnum Opus in Charlottesville,
                        usually had some tempting volume in the antiquarian section of Heartwood
                        Books, which he managed then. That day he came up with a first edition of S.
                        Foster Damon’s <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and
                            Symbols</hi>, in which, he said, there was an amusing poem inscribed by
                        the author. Sure enough, the flyleaf traced a mysterious exchange involving
                        this book, which fell eventually into its author’s hands. The book
                        bears several bookplates, including one of “Richard and Caroline
                        Hogue,” and Damon predicated the poem: <q> From Caroline Hogue<lb/>
                            to S. Foster Damon<lb/> and back again<lb/> April 29, 1941 </q> The poem
                        itself reveals S. Foster Damon’s sense of humor, which is quite
                        refreshing! He imagined that <q> Hamlet once met William Blake<lb/> They
                            chatted, for politeness’ sake.<lb/> Said Hamlet: “Do you
                            see that cloud?”<lb/> Said William: “Yes! It is a
                            crowd<lb/> Of Seraphim shouting ‘Glory! Hail!’
                            ”<lb/> Said Hamlet: “No. It’s like a
                            whale.”<lb/> And so they parted, each one glad<lb/> that the
                            other, and not he, was mad. </q> The readers of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                        will understand why I immediately purchased the book. I am happy to share it
                        with the readers of the <hi rend="i">Quarterly</hi>, and I would like to
                        thank Morton Paley for suggesting that I submit the poem to <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, and Catherine Brown, S. Foster Damon’s literary
                        executor, for giving permission to print it.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p19-73" n="73"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>A Pencil Sketch for Blake’s Dante Illustrations</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Jenijoy <name>La Belle</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The Huntington Library is known the world over for its great collection of
                        books, for its splendid eighteenth century paintings, and for its lovely
                        gardens. It now seems also to be the place for discovering previously
                        unknown drawings by William Blake. In 1982 a pencil sketch of Blake’s
                        “Pestilence” was discovered in a group of uncatalogued
                        drawings which apparently had been languishing in the Library’s rare
                        book stacks for many years.<ref target="n17" type="note">1</ref> Recently,
                        yet another Blake drawing has come to light. <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Shelley M. Bennett, “A Newly Discovered Blake in
                            the Huntington,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Calendar</hi>
                            (July-August 1983), 2-4; and Bennett, “A Newly Discovered Blake
                            at the Huntington,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-85), 132-39.</note></p>
          <p>Since December 1916, the Huntington Art Gallery has owned an important pencil
                        sketch for Blake’s Dante Illustrations, “The Six-Footed
                        Serpent Attacking Agnolo Brunelleschi.”<ref target="n18" type="note">2</ref> This somewhat rubbed and stained yet powerful drawing has long
                        been firmly pasted down on all four edges to its backing mat, probably
                        supplied by A.S.W. Rosenbach, the great book dealer from whom Henry E.
                        Huntington acquired this and many other Blake materials.<ref target="n19" type="note">3</ref> Late in December of 1984, Carol Verheyen, the
                        Preparator/Registrar for the Huntington Art Collections, decided that the
                        preservation of the drawing required its removal from the highly acidic mat
                        board. As soon as the operation was completed, she found on the verso a
                        pencil sketch of a standing woman (illus. 1) near the left margin of the
                        sheet. The figure may be holding something in her right hand, but stains in
                        the paper and some abrasion obscure this area. The verso also bears the
                        number “8/16” in pencil—perhaps a price or other
                        notation made by a dealer. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">2</hi> C.H. Collins
                            Baker, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of William Blake’s Drawings and
                                Paintings in the Huntington Library</hi>, revised edition by R. R.
                            Wark (San Marino: Huntington Library, 1957), p. 46, pl. xxxvi; Martin
                            Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>
                            (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1981), No. 822, pl. 1073 (hereafter cited
                            as “Butlin No. —”).</note><note id="n19"><hi rend="s">3</hi> To the provenance information supplied by
                            Butlin, No. 822, I can add that this drawing is very probably the design
                            for “Dante’s ‘Inferno’ ” offered for
                            sale in Rosenbach’s catalogue 18 of 1916, <hi rend="i">Catalogue
                                of A Remarkable Collection of Rare and Choice Books Manuscripts and
                                Autograph Letters</hi>, item 17, with a collection of other works by
                            Blake including the Thomas set of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> designs for
                            $29,000. This entire group was acquired by Henry Huntington in December
                            1916 for $17,200 (according to Rosenbach’s receipt of 1 January
                            1917 in the Huntington Archives). I am grateful to Robert N. Essick, who
                            is now completing a new catalogue of all original Blake materials at the
                            Huntington, for this information.</note></p>
          <p>The basic features of the woman’s anatomy, the slightly <hi rend="i">contrapposto</hi> stance with her head in profile but her body twisting
                        towards us, and the qualities of the draftsmanship are all representative of
                        Blake’s work. The hesitancy and sketchiness of the lines, while
                        hardly indicative of Blake’s theories about firm and determinate
                        bounding lines, are nonetheless typical of his drawing style late in his
                        life. In his description of a stylistically similar work, a “sketch,
                        probably for ‘Bunyan’s Dream,’ ” (Butlin No.
                        830), Butlin has nicely characterized this technique as one “in which
                        a multitude of lightly sketched lines gradually picks out the main
                            forms.”<ref target="n20" type="note">4</ref> Several of the Dante
                        drawings left at an early stage of development (e.g., Butlin Nos. 812.68,
                        812.70, 812.71, 812.83, 812.100) also exemplify this method. Thus all
                        features of the newly discovered drawing, including of course its presence
                        on the verso of a known work by Blake, indicate that it too is from
                        Blake’s hand. It was probably sketched in the period when Blake was
                        working on the Dante designs, ca. 1824-1827. <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, catalogue of the
                            Tate Gallery exhibition (London, 1978), p. 147. In correspondence,
                            Butlin has accepted the newly discovered drawing as Blake’s
                            work.</note></p>
          <p>There are a good many females in Blake’s art generally similar to the
                        Huntington sketch, but none that I can find is identical. The drawing has
                        all the qualities of a preliminary design, and the first possibility that
                        springs to mind is that it relates to one of the large Dante watercolors.
                        Martin Butlin has suggested in correspondence that the Huntington drawing is
                        an early version of the figure second from the left margin in
                        “Beatrice Addressing Dante from the Car” (illus. 2). If this
                        is indeed the case, then it seems likely that this verso drawing was
                        executed prior to the composition on its recto (“The Six-Footed
                        Serpent Attacking Agnolo Brunelleschi”) because the latter is
                        probably a preliminary drawing for the engraving of 1826-1827 rather than
                        for the slightly earlier watercolor.<ref target="n21" type="note">5</ref><note id="n21"><hi rend="s">5</hi> As Butlin points out under his No. 822,
                            the Huntington recto drawing, which he dates to 1826-1827.</note></p>
          <figure>
            <head>1. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc>Pencil sketch of a standing woman, ca. 1824-1827, on the verso of
                            “The Six-Footed Serpent Attacking Agnolo Brunelleschi.”
                            Sheet 24.5 × 32.9 cm; image 17.5 × approx. 5.5 cm.
                            Huntington Art Galleries, accession no. 000.43 verso.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p19-74" n="74"/>
          <p>The woman in the newly revealed verso sketch and the much more highly
                        finished figure in “Beatrice Addressing Dante” have similar
                        feet and leg positions, torsos, and extended right arms. Indeed, the two
                        women are about the same size and are similarly situated in relationship to
                        the edges of the sheets of paper on which they appear, suggesting that even
                        in the sketch Blake was thinking about the location of his figure within a
                        larger design. However, the head positions and hair of these two women are
                        very different, and the left arm of the sketched woman is not shown.
                        Actually, the head in profile with the face turned slightly upward and the
                        coiffure with hair piled up on top of the head associate the pencil drawing
                        with the central figure (second from the right) who looks toward Beatrice
                        standing on the chariot. It seems as though Blake has made use of the
                        preliminary figure by dividing her characteristics between two women in the
                        finished composition. While the newly discovered drawing is far from being a
                        major work, it does provide some interesting insights into Blake’s
                        methods of developing a composition as he moved from first thoughts on paper
                        to a highly wrought watercolor design.</p>
          <figure>
            <head>2. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc>“Beatrice Addressing Dante from the Car,” ca.
                            1824-1827. Pen and watercolor, 37.2 × 52.7 cm. Tate Gallery,
                            London.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p19-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure/>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Stephen C. Behrendt. <hi rend="i">The Moment of Explosion:
                                    Blake and the Illustration of Milton.</hi> Lincoln and Lond:
                                University of Nebraska Press, 1983. 235 pp., 24 color plates, 54
                                b&amp;w illus. $32.50.; Edward Hodnett. <hi rend="i">Image and
                                    Text: Studies in the Illustration of English Literature.</hi>
                                London: Scolar Press, 1982. 280 pp., 42 illus. $35.00.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Karl</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Kroeber</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Behrendt presents us with a conscientious study of Blake’s Milton
                        illustrations, which he regards as undertaking to “correct not only
                        Milton but also the presumed faults of his eighteenth- and early
                        nineteenth-century critics” (p. 1). Blake’s designs accomplish
                        this double correction by abstracting the spiritual or symbolic essence of
                        the poetry, rediscovering and realigning Milton’s mythical and
                        metaphorical structures in order to induce in the reader a visionary
                        perception comparable to the artist’s. This alertness to
                        Blake’s concern for his art’s effect is salutary. Behrendt,
                        naturally enough, begins with a discussion of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> that
                        leads logically into an analysis of <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and
                            <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> illustrations. The crux of his findings
                        is developed in the second chapter treating “The Theme of
                        Choice,” in Behrendt’s view “central to all
                        Blake’s Milton illustrations” (p. 34), and the foundation for
                        his correcting both in his poetry and in his illustrations what he took to
                        be misreadings of Milton. The centerpiece for all such considerations must
                        be, of course, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, and for Behrendt the epic
                        proves the core of Blake’s re-orienting of tradition, deformed in
                        part by Milton’s own obscuring of the true thrust of his poem.
                        Blake’s re-clarifying of Milton’s self-obscuring pivots on
                        insistence that the Son is the “absolute hero of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>,” effecting and providing “the
                        paradigm for eternal spiritual and imaginative resurrection” (p.
                        185). Behrendt’s thesis is difficult to disagree with, and it is no
                        denigration of his good sense and perspicuity to suggest that his
                        book’s most exciting feature is its eighty large, clear
                        illustrations, most of Blake’s designs, of course, but including
                        well-chosen examples from other Milton illustrators. The bibliography,
                        however, is highly “selected” indeed, and the index of names
                        only is virtually useless.</p>
          <p>Hodnett’s book is far more provocative and stylistically surprising.
                        The chapter on Blake seems a shade more impressive than other chapters, but
                        its manner is, I should judge, representative. On p. 87 we are told of Blake
                        that “nudes were his stock in trade, and he did his best to draw them
                        correctly.” Our man gets an E for effort here, but later in the
                        paragraph the accolade is a bit clouded: “By reducing most of his
                        figures to nudes, by picturing types rather than individuals, and by
                        generalizing or eliminating backgrounds, Blake sought to achieve a sense of
                        universality, and to a degree he succeeded.” One does wonder what
                        degree of universality might be regarded as successful. Pressing on to p.
                        92, however, one encounters a reference to “Enitharman,” to
                        add new diversity to Blake’s sexual ambiguities in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, the passage climaxing, if that is the word: “The
                        extraordinary title-page design pictures Urizen as a naked long-bearded man
                        huddled cross-legged on an open book writing with a quill in both extended
                        hands. The colours are said to have been mixed with glue and applied by a
                        second impression of the plate.” I wish I had space to explore fully
                        Hodnett’s sequiturs, but I can at least suggest a possible source for
                        that quill in both extended hands: it is found on p. 102, where we are
                        reassured, sort of, that “Blake probably got his effects
                        unintentionally to a certain extent.” Particularly when dealing with
                        an eccentric like Blake, a scholar can’t be too careful</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p19-76" n="76"/>
        <div2>
          <figure/>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Morton D. Paley. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William
                                    Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1983.
                                330 pp., 22 illus. $57.00</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">V.A.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">De Luca</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s reputation as a great English poem is
                        essentially a post-war phenomenon. Indeed this reputation, in so far as it
                        commands reasonably wide assent in the profession, is largely a product of
                        the past twenty years, gathering its momentum from the enthusiasms of the
                        apocalyptically inclined sixties. By the time the poem began to be taken
                        seriously, the New Criticism, with its emphasis on nuances of language and
                        subtleties of formal technique, was well on the wane. The older modes of
                        literary scholarship—the elaboration of historical background, the
                        tracing of sources and influences, the inventorying of themes and formal
                        features—were even more remote to nascent Blakeans. The criticism of
                        Blake’s longer poems found its distinctive voice in an impassioned
                        translation or paraphrase of themes, in which a certain evangelical impulse
                        played no small part. This enthusiastic approach was enormously valuable for
                        kindling a widespread interest in Blake, and only now is it beginning to
                        give way to more specialized and technical kinds of inquiry into his work.
                        But the approach also led to an impoverishment in our sense of the ways in
                        which <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> works as a poem and of its place in a
                        historical and cultural context. Because of its belated arrival in the
                        canon, the study of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> has passed from fervent
                        interpretation to scholarly specialization without having paused to offer a
                        clearly outlined, basic <hi rend="i">description</hi> of the thing itself.
                        Categorical description, the forte of the older modes of criticism and
                        regularly applied to poems whose reputation consolidated earlier, say, <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Tales, The Faerie Queene</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>, has not until now figured significantly in work on
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>—much to our cost.</p>
          <p>These circumstances heighten the importance of Morton Paley’s
                        much-awaited study. As Paley himself points out, “at this point we do
                        not need yet another recension of the beliefs of an idealized Blake”
                        (p. 32), and in <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> he avoids any such
                        thing. The originality and strength of the book lie in its refusal of a
                        thematic centering, in its disinclination to translate Blake’s poem
                        into an argument or to impose an argument of the author’s own
                        devising. Although Paley refrains from stating what he considers the aim of
                        his study to be, that aim is clear enough from the design of the whole: to
                        explore the essential frames of reference in which an adequate study of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> might begin. It attempts more or less to
                        describe in an orderly fashion what the poem contains, where it finds
                        models, models, and how it works. Sometimes, as in the introductory chapter
                        and occasionally elsewhere, this approach involves a survey of familiar
                        material (such as a review of the poem’s publishing history and of
                        its critical reception) that is readily available in other secondary
                        sources. The inclusion of such material indicates that Paley aims ultimately
                        not for novelty but for comprehensiveness. Indeed, in its range of coverage
                        and its willingness to stoop to the familiar and to basic facts, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> resembles nothing so much as those
                        impressively magisterial introductions that one or two generations ago would
                        accompany critical editions of major texts—say, Maynard Mack on <hi rend="i">The Essay on Man</hi> in the Twickenham Pope or Frank
                        Kermode’s introduction to the Arden <hi rend="i">Tempest.</hi> It is
                        precisely this sort of treatment—erudite but plain-speaking,
                        objective, comprehensive, topically subdivided—that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> has sorely lacked, as it has lacked the honor of a
                        definitive annotated critical edition (a need, incidentally, that Paley
                        recognizes). <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi>, more leisurely in pace,
                        more loosely textured, is perhaps not quite in the class of Mack on Pope,
                        but the comparison serves to suggest the kind of scholarly company that
                        Paley’s work keeps and the importance of what <pb id="p19-77" n="77"/> he has accomplished.</p>
          <p>Like the imaginative city that gives the book its title and provides the
                        subject of its central chapter, this work too is a structure with many
                        gates, each leading from a different direction to the sanctuary of the poem
                        itself. There are chapters on the verse of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and
                        its relation to period styles and theories, on approaches to the reading of
                        the designs, on the millenarian framework and its symbolism, on the dramatis
                        personae, and on the formal organization. This varied set of concerns calls
                        for a range of different skills in handling them, and although certain
                        chapters do rise above others in distinction, virtually all parts of the
                        work display a shrewd common sense, a facility in discovering relevant
                        connections, a resourcefulness in posing interesting kinds of issues to
                        address, and a thorough command of background information.</p>
          <p>Paley is at his best when he has tangible kinds of evidence before him to
                        engage his attention. He clearly likes to gather and correlate information,
                        to probe it for its implications, and to dispose it in orderly arrangements
                        for his reader. The role of literary historian seems particularly congenial,
                        and one of the most impressive things in <hi rend="i">The Continuing
                            City</hi> is the devotion that Paley bestows in detailing a tradition of
                        analogues to Blake’s four-gated city. As Paley proceeds methodically
                        from Ezekiel, Revelation, and Josephus, through such later visionaries of
                        millennial architecture as Villapandus, Lightfoot, and John Wood, the very
                        accumulation of examples gives the reader a vividly heightened sense of the
                        perennial force of the visionary impulse, a process aptly caught in
                        Blake’s trope of Golgonooza, “ever building, ever
                        falling” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 6.2), only to give rise again in
                        successive prophets. As a summary account of sources and analogues for
                        Blake’s city of vision, this part of Paley’s book is likely to
                        remain definitive; future students of the subject will want to consult it
                        before any other account.</p>
          <p>But the triumph of Paley’s empirical approach comes not in his
                        investigations of literary history but in his analysis of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s form. His skill in handling formal matters is
                        evident early in the book, in the chapter on versification, where through an
                        array of resourceful and patiently applied methods—scansion,
                        syntactical analysis, comparison with analogues—he arrives at
                        characterizations that are virtually always on the mark (e.g.,
                        “pauses do not typically create a balanced tension, as often in
                        Augustan poetry, but rather appear to resist the onrush of the verse and
                        then yield to it; . . . enjambement transfers energy from one line to
                        another and creates a sense that statements [not always sentences] are
                        structural units” [p. 51]). The best treatment of form in the book is
                        reserved, however, for last. In this chapter, simply called
                        “Form,” Paley unquestionably makes his most useful
                        contribution to the criticism of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> After
                        surveying some possible models for the poem’s peculiarities of
                        organization (the most interesting of which, from the Blake critic’s
                        point of view, is Handel’s <hi rend="i">Messiah</hi>), he launches
                        into a scrutinizing analysis of the work’s construction. There is a
                        valuable exposition of the problem of the two extant arrangements of plates
                        in Chapter 2, and although this treatment cannot be taken as definitive (the
                        interested reader may wish to compare Paley’s findings with my own
                        somewhat different account of the same matters, previously published in
                        these pages [Spring 1983]), it demonstrates clearly that a critical
                        understanding of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s foundations cannot
                        proceed without a firm bibliographical understanding. More important still
                        is Paley’s comprehensive and illuminating attempt to chart the
                        recurrences of the important narrative and thematic motifs in the poem.
                        Borrowing his technique from synoptic tabularizations of the four gospels
                        (why has no one thought of applying this technique to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> before?), Paley analyzes these motifs into their
                        component parts and pinpoints their recurrences on a spatial grid
                        representing <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s four chapters. As a result
                        any reader consulting these tables may henceforth take in at a glance the
                        location of the major narrative strands and motifs, the distribution of
                        their recurrences throughout the poem, and the weight of concentration Blake
                        gives to each. At once a concordance of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s
                        motifs and a map of its thematic structure, these tables are likely to prove
                        an indispensable reference tool.</p>
          <p>Paley’s close investigations of the poem’s construction pay off
                        in some finely judicious observations on the rationale of the structure of
                        the whole. Usefully distinguishing what he calls the
                        “organization” of the work (its “official”
                        symmetrical division into four equal chapters) from its “form”
                        (small, potentially shiftable gatherings of plates, or synchronous narrative
                        events recurring in unpredictably distributed clusters), he concludes that
                        Blake’s technique, in effect, is to set the two kinds of order in a
                        kind of antagonism to one another: “The organizational container
                        reinforces the expectation of a strong narrative line, an expectation which
                        is subverted time after time in the work itself”; “regularity
                        is an aspect of what I have called the ‘container’; the poem
                        and the designs build up a tension with that regular order” (pp. 302,
                        307). From this strong insight it follows that “attempts to view the
                        chapters as discrete units depend upon rationalizing after the fact, and
                        quite different chapter constructions could be so rationalized” (p.
                        303). One hopes that this firmly persuasive observation will lay to rest
                        finally all those by now wearisome attempts to allegorize <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s four-part scheme as a thematic medley or as
                        stages in a conceptual argument. The schematic divisions of the text, it
                        would seem, confer meaning no more readily than rhyming or isochronous meter
                        do in prosody. They are formal points <pb id="p19-78" n="78"/> of departure
                        for an unpredictable play of intellectual and emotional energy, the definite
                        outlines from which an infinite potential recoils.</p>
          <p>Paley’s finest critical insights, then, are reserved for matters of
                        form. In its handling of theme and meaning, however, the distinction of <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> is oddly enough not so assured. The
                        two explicitly thematic chapters “The Myth of Humanity”
                        (Albion-Vala-Jerusalem) and “The Prophetic Myth”
                        (Los-Enitharmon-Spectre) are not themselves problematic; they do not bring
                        many new large-scale insights to bear on these “myths” (there
                        are many gratifying small illuminations) but the mode of exposition is as
                        lucidly and as rationally organized as we are likely to find in any
                        commentary on Blake’s longer poems. The chapter on
                        “Art” however raises problems of a larger order, for here
                        Paley’s concern is explicitly with the search for meaning itself and
                        the principles according to which such a search might be based. Using five
                        designs from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, chosen as exemplary of differing
                        kinds of interpretative problems posed by the visual side of Blake’s
                        work, Paley hopes to show “How to Read Blake’s
                        Pictures” (p. 89). As usual, his principles are sensible, his
                        observations keen, and his references learned. But the discussion as a whole
                        begs the question of what it means to “read” a picture. It
                        proceeds on the assumptions that interpretation is a self-evident
                        desideratum and that the meaning of a picture is to be found in a presumed
                        doctrinal intention paraphrasable in words. But such assumptions merely
                        extend to the world of designs that yearning for a “recension of
                        beliefs” or for “rationalizations after the fact” about
                        which Paley is properly skeptical elsewhere in the book as a program for
                        Blake criticism. Paley appears somewhat uncomfortable with the otherness of
                        the pictorial medium, with the evasiveness of its reponse to demands that it
                        serve a signifying role; hence his preference that ambiguous
                        “readings” of certain designs be settled on one side of the
                        argument or the other. Yet one needs to ask why Blake takes refuge
                        intermittently in pictures at all, if the pictures can be re-spoken as words
                        conformable to unequivocal words that the poet has already used.</p>
          <p>Take, for instance, what from the standpoint of interpretation are the two
                        most difficult of Paley’s five exemplary cases. According to various
                        critics the crucifixion scene on pl. 76 depicts either a vegetated Christ,
                        in which case we are to deplore Albion’s posture of reverence, or a
                        Christ sacrificing himself in divine Friendship, in which case we are
                        enjoined to imitate Albion’s <hi rend="i">imitatio.</hi> But are we
                        to assume that Blake’s advice regarding which attitude we should
                        choose is somehow encoded in the visual lines of the picture? It seems more
                        likely that the design is an invitation to choice, not a determination of
                        it. After alluding to the crucifixion in various contexts, positive and
                        negative throughout <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake is saying, in effect,
                        here is the thing itself, the visual sign for a permanent act or reality, a
                        “Representation of what Eternally Exists. Really &amp;
                        Unchangeably.” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E 554). He who would see in
                        this visual depiction a display of divine love and he who would see a
                        religion of atonement with a corpse as centerpiece see, to borrow a phrase
                        from Wallace Stevens, nothing that is not there in the design itself. The
                        alternatives are both encoded in its iconographic details and in the
                        religious assumptions of viewers, whether liberated or benighted. Paley is
                        on the right track when he suggests that it is better to trust our intuitive
                        response to designs such as this than to consult some doctrinal abstract of
                        Blake’s thought for our opinion. But what is required here is an
                        intuitive response to the crucifixion itself, not to a
                        “message” of the poet regarding it. Perhaps the function of
                        this design, and many others in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as well, is to
                        suspend the strongly directive <hi rend="i">voice</hi> of the poet and to
                        yield to the spectator the opportunity to test his or her own imaginative
                        capacities in an act of <hi rend="i">seeing.</hi></p>
          <p>The same point holds for the other difficult case among Paley’s
                        samples. The notoriously recondite chariot vision on pl. 41[46] is, as Paley
                        admits, “almost a Rorschach test for Blake scholars.” Prolific
                        with unknown metamorphic forms and half-recognizable iconographical hints at
                        accessible meaning, it virtually begs for interpretation. But what it so
                        conspicuously invites it then proceeds to impede. Paley is inclined to see
                        this design as a dark vision, a triumph of Vala, but if one is inclined to
                        view the design as a representation of the fulfillment of apocalyptic
                        prophecy, the supports for such a reading are also readily available. If the
                        woman in the chariot is clothed, and hence Vala, as Paley argues, one might
                        point out that Jerusalem also appears clothed on pls. 26 and 92; the older
                        bearded figure embracing the woman appears somber, but no more somber than
                        he does in similar embraces in the indisputably ecstatic and apocalyptic
                        contexts of pls. 96 and 99; and the last line of verse on pl. 41, directly
                        over the design of the embracing couple, refers to “The Bride and
                        Wife of the Lamb” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 41.28). As for the drawers,
                        one might be reminded, as Paley is, of certain pictorial sources that
                        suggest Covering Cherubs or rides through the underworld; but iconography
                        even more readily yields, in response to the lion-maned, human-faced,
                        ox-hooved, eagle-guided creatures depicted here, the traditional scriptural
                        emblems of the Four Living Creatures that surround the Divine Vision; from
                        Blake’s own works one might point to the collaboration of serpents,
                        eagles, lions, and men in <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 15 to bring grand works of
                        art into being, or to those vehicular serpents on which energetic children
                        joyously ride in <hi rend="i">America</hi> 11 and <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6.
                        To collect counter-evidence against Paley’s position is not, however,
                        my point here; it is not a question of <pb id="p19-79" n="79"/> right and
                        wrong interpretations. If Paley’s treatment falls short of a full
                        response to the complexities that pl. 41 poses, it is not for any lack of
                        skill in the reading of emblems; rather, it is because he bypasses an issue
                        that Blake’s technique in many parts in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        raises insistently: why does the “Rorschach” effect appear so
                        frequently in the designs (and not just the designs) unless Blake is making
                        a point about the process of signification itself?</p>
          <p>If a design or a passage of verse (such as the notorious vortex passage in
                            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 15) perennially begets fresh interpretations
                        and controversy, while continuing to frustrate the formation of a consensus
                        opinion, then the interpretive effort becomes not a vehicle for overcoming a
                        difficulty but rather a signifier of that difficulty;
                        “difficulty” itself is foregrounded as the
                        “message.” Perhaps spots such as the design on pl. 41 have
                        been established as interpretive Free Zones, fashioned so as perpetually to
                        invite and to evade univocal readings. Such points might act as vortices in
                        the surface of accessible meaning, drawing us down into the depths where all
                        meanings are seen as potential, as “regenerations terrific or
                        complacent” varying according to our perceptions or to the turns in a
                        visionary conversation dramatic. The unreadable (or too variously readable)
                        chariot of pl. 41 compacts such a conversation in a tightly determinate
                        visual form.</p>
          <p>Plausibly, Paley might respond to this argument with one of his own
                        interpretive principles: “Interpretations according to which mutually
                        exclusive meanings are seen as equally valid are not likely to be helpful.
                        We should remember Blake’s love of the definite” (p. 118).
                        What one finds helpful of course depends on what one is asking the poem to
                        supply; if it is a series of securely identifiable “correct”
                        meanings, then Paley’s cautions are well taken. But generally Blake
                        praises the definite not as an attribute of meaning but as an attribute of
                        form; it is a quality of the bounding outline, or to use Paley’s own
                        terminology, the regularity of the “container,” and it applies
                        to the incisive visual clarity of the signifier, not to the possibilities of
                        the signified. For within the walls of the definite there ricochets its
                        antonym the infinite, equally loved, a surging and ultimately untameable
                        waywardness that will not abide our question or accommodate itself to our
                        paraphrases. Despite some excellent remarks in Chapter II on the
                        “Titanic striving” of Blake’s sublime mode in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and on the effort of its “language to
                        abandon its function as mediator and to become meaning itself” (p.
                        64), in general Paley shows little responsiveness to this wayward element in
                        the poem. It is a lack that demarcates the limits of his study of the
                        subject.</p>
          <p>I speak of limits not in any pejorative sense. A different kind of critical
                        approach would have curbed the excellence that <hi rend="i">The Continuing
                            City</hi> achieves in its own kind, and one can only be grateful for a
                        study that manages to pack between two covers as many valuable observations
                        as it does in such a wide range of contexts. If one ventures to weigh the
                        actual achievements of this work against the possibilities that it has
                        neglected to explore, it is simply because the appearance of a major book on
                        a great English poem impels us to take stock of the critical tradition
                        gathering around that poem, locating the book in hand within the tradition
                        by glancing at what has gone before and what might come after. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> functions as a practical guide; it is not
                        surprising that Paley invokes the “helpful” as a principle in
                        reading Blake’s designs, for such a principle underlies his whole
                        enterprise. This is indeed a genuinely helpful book, seeking everywhere to
                        accommodate the strangeness and difficulty of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to
                        our understandings and vice versa, and its commonsense approach accomplishes
                        what had to be accomplished sooner or later. But one suspects that a future
                        criticism will make strangeness and difficulty its very theme, bringing to
                        the fore a Blake who is himself anything but accommodating. Such a criticism
                        is likely to differ as much from Paley’s lucid, well-rounded course
                        of instruction as that mode differs from the evangelical commentaries of the
                        past generation, mentioned at the outset. Newer readings will have come to
                        terms with a sensibility that in mood and in expressive tendency can be
                        brooding, obsessive, devious, secretive, sometimes even brutal, even as it
                        is also radiant and humane. Here lies a fruitful direction for the criticism
                        of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to take, not because a conception of Blake as
                        problematic is desirable for its own sake (though a certain clearing of the
                        air of pieties is always welcome) but because an unsentimental gauging of
                        the human complexities and strenuous tensions in his work will serve to
                        underscore his genius and to deepen our own thought. One need only glance at
                        the history of Wordsworth criticism in the past twenty years to see the
                        effects of a resourceful phenomenological probing of ambiguities; not only
                        is Wordsworth now seen as a difficult proto-modern poet but he has moved to
                        the center of that revival of Romantic concerns which has so significantly
                        nourished the most venturesome and vital strands of recent critical
                        discourse. To establish Blake, a poet of equivalent genius, in a similar
                        nourishing and energizing role is an enterprise that all of us should
                        want.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, as a conspicuously Orcan figure of our own day once phrased it,
                        if you can’t always get what you want you can get what you need.
                        Before anyone can scale the craggiest heights or probe the gloomiest caverns
                        of Blake’s most demanding poem, there needs to be an expertly
                        conducted exploration of the basic terrain, and this Paley has provided. As
                        it stands, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> is the most significant and
                        useful book on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that we have.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p19-80" n="80"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">G. E. Bentley, Jr., Robert N. Essick, Shelley M. Bennett,
                                Morton D. Paley. Preface by Robert R. Wark. <hi rend="i">Essays on
                                    the Blake Followers.</hi> San Marino, California: Huntington
                                Library and Art Gallery, 1983. 71 pp., 51 illus. $8.00; Joseph
                                Viscomi. <hi rend="i">Prints by William Blake and His
                                    Followers.</hi> Ithaca, New York: Herbert F. Johnson Museum of
                                Art, Cornell University, 1983. 36 pp., 18 illus. No price
                                stated.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Raymond</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Lister</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Samuel Palmer, the most important of William Blake’s followers, was a
                        few years ago in the news in England on account of the crude fakes of his
                        work, executed by the late Tom Keating, which appeared on the London art
                        market. Several of us said at once that they were not authentic; others
                        appeared to give them their blessing. Some were reproduced in the book <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi> by James Sellars (London, 1974)<ref target="n22" type="note">1</ref> and one in the <hi rend="i">Burlington
                            Magazine.</hi><ref target="n23" type="note">2</ref> One at least was
                        accepted by the late Edward Croft-Murray of the British Museum, and Martin
                        Butlin of the Tate Gallery said there was “a considerable case for
                        their being by the artist.”<ref target="n24" type="note">3</ref>
                        Which surely all goes to show that enthusiasm, even when combined with
                        academic scholarship, is not always supported by perfect connoisseurship.
                            <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Plates 41, 43, 78, 87, 89.</note><note id="n23"><hi rend="s">2</hi> August 1965, p. 439.</note><note id="n24"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> The Times</hi>, 16 July 1976, pp. 1-2.</note></p>
          <p>But the fact remains that this all did Palmer’s reputation
                        considerable harm if only temporarily, for when leading experts, especially
                        if they are also important museum officials, are deceived into accepting
                        fakes as original works, and when the fakes are illustrated in a leading art
                        journal and in an otherwise scholarly book, people begin to ask themselves
                        if the original artist’s work is as good as it is reputed to be,
                        considering that it apparently could be so easily faked as to deceive such
                        expert opinion. This point is often put to me by those outside art circles.
                        Even on Keating’s own assessment his fakes were “crude
                            daubs,”<ref target="n25" type="note">4</ref> so the non-expert
                        must have found it doubly puzzling that, if Palmer were such an outstanding
                        artist, experts should have been prepared to accept the
                        “daubs” as original work. Consequently the non-expert observer
                        could hardly be blamed for thinking Palmer a lesser figure than before.
                            <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> The Times</hi>, 20 August 1976, p. 13.</note></p>
          <p>The books under review, especially the Huntington volume, should do something
                        towards correcting this. Indeed few of those who even glance over the
                        reduced reproductions in the Huntington book would possibly imagine that
                        Palmer could have been the same man who made the fakes. The essays in the
                        book provide further evidence of the way in which the authentic Palmer
                        thought and worked, how he translated his visual and literary experiences
                        into original works of his own, how his own complicated personality acted as
                        a catalyst on his reading of, for instance, the poems of Milton, or on his
                        visual experience of the drawings and paintings of Claude Lorrain,
                        transforming each experience into visions of the English countryside with,
                        later on, accents derived from his visits to Devon, Wales, and Italy.</p>
          <p>In the first essay, G. E. Bentley, Jr., places the Palmer circle, “The
                        Ancients” as they called themselves, in the Blake milieu, noting,
                        correctly, the prudery and religious conventionality of some of them.
                        Strangely, they seem to have had little comprehension of the mind of their
                        great mentor. It is practically certain that one of them, Frederick Tatham,
                        destroyed much of Blake’s work on religious grounds. Again, when
                        Eliza Finch wrote her memoir of her husband, Francis Oliver Finch, another
                        Ancient, she did not even mention Blake; the Finches were Swedenborgians and
                        Blake had thrown the beliefs of that sect aside, so obviously his views
                        rankled. And in a letter of 27 June 1862 to Anne Gilchrist, who was
                        preparing her late husband’s life of Blake for press, Palmer advised:
                        “Pray don’t send to the printers any <hi rend="i">extracts</hi> made from the book itself [<hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                            Heaven and Hell</hi>] which has not been looked over and prepared for
                        the press as I saw this ev—g an indecent word in the text—at
                        least a coarse one.”<ref target="n26" type="note">5</ref> To which he
                        added a footnote: “I would recommend the same caution as to all Blake
                        manuscripts not already prepared—on account of other matters which
                        ‘crop up’ now and then and which would be considered
                        BLASPHEMOUS and might ruin the sale of the work if shown up in any
                        illnatured review.”<ref target="n27" type="note">6</ref><note id="n26"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Raymond Lister, ed., <hi rend="i">The
                                Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi> (Oxford, 1974), p. 657.</note><note id="n27"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Letters</hi>, p. 661.</note></p>
          <p>As a matter of fact Palmer had little, if any, understanding of the bulk of
                        Blake’s poetry. The lyric poems he could no doubt appreciate, but
                        when it came to the mythological books he was all at sea. “His poems
                        were variously estimated,” he wrote. “They tested rather
                        severely the imaginative capacity of their readers. Flaxman said they were
                        as grand as his designs, and Wordsworth delighted in his <hi rend="i">Songs
                            of Innocence.</hi> To the multitude they were unintelligible. In many
                        parts full of pastoral sweetness, and often flashing with noble thoughts or
                        terrible imagery, we must regret that he should sometimes have suffered
                        fancy to trespass within sacred precincts.”<ref target="n28" type="note">7</ref><note id="n28"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Letters</hi>, p. 509.</note></p>
          <p>In truth these young followers of Blake followed him in a very limited way.
                        Edward Calvert was in a visual sense more influenced by him than any other
                        member of the circle; in his few engravings references to Blake may be
                        traced again and again.<ref target="n29" type="note">8</ref> There is a <pb id="p19-81" n="81"/> little of Blake in Richmond’s early work,
                        and Palmer’s visionary mode had been developed before he ever met
                        Blake, although after they had met the younger man made considerable
                        borrowings. Even so, the influence of the old man was mainly through his
                        wood-engravings for Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi> and his <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings, and to a lesser extent through his designs
                        for <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and through a few of his
                        watercolors. Within a few years of his death the Ancients were each going
                        separate ways: George Richmond as a fashionable portrait painter, Calvert as
                        a painter of idealized classical scenes, and Palmer as a landscape painter
                        developing along more conventional, though far from uninteresting lines; F.
                        O. Finch had always painted Claudean landscapes and continued to do so. Here
                        and there there is a backward glance at Blake, as in Calvert’s
                        “A Young Shepherd on a Journey”<ref target="n30" type="note">9</ref> which is an almost exact copy of Blake’s illustration to
                        the line “With wand’ring feet unblest . . . ” in
                        Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil.</hi> Nevertheless the impact of these
                        little engravings on the young men was, for a few years, enormous; and if
                        the period of their ascendancy was brief, it did enable them to produce, at
                        least for that time, work as compelling as anything they were to produce in
                        the future. <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Edward Calvert</hi> (London, 1962), Chapter 5, <hi rend="i">passim.</hi></note><note id="n30"><hi rend="s">9</hi> c. 1860. British Museum.</note></p>
          <p>Robert N. Essick’s essay on “John Linnell, William Blake, and
                        the Printer’s Craft” is, as one has come to expect from him,
                        an elegantly written and well argued study. The influence of Samuel
                        Palmer’s father-in-law, John Linnell, among the Ancients has not
                        often been seriously considered, and it is refreshing to see it given some
                        prominence here. But who has influenced whom it is sometimes difficult to
                        decide; some early Linnells, drawn or painted before the two men had met,
                        seem to be precursors of works by Palmer (for example “Primrose
                            Hill”<ref target="n31" type="note">10</ref> and
                            “Twilight”<ref target="n32" type="note">11</ref>), whereas
                        his “The Weald of Kent,”<ref target="n33" type="note">12</ref>
                        drawn years after Linnell’s first meeting with Palmer, might almost
                        be the work of the younger man. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">10</hi> 1811.
                            Fitzwilliam Museum.</note><note id="n32"><hi rend="s">11</hi> c. 1819. Private collection,
                            England.</note><note id="n33"><hi rend="s">12</hi> 1833. Fitzwilliam Museum.</note></p>
          <p>Essick’s study is, as its title implies, concerned with printmaking
                        rather than with drawings, but much the same remarks apply: Linnell’s
                        etchings, “Sheep at Noon” and “Woodcutters
                        Repast” (both 1818) again look like precursors of later work by
                        Palmer, especially in the composition and shape of those watercolors he
                        called “Little Longs.”</p>
          <p>But the most compelling part of this section is Essick’s analysis of
                        the engraving techniques used by Blake and Linnell, in which he endeavors to
                        demonstrate Linnell’s influence on Blake, especially in their jointly
                        executed plates (for example in “Wilson Lowry,” begun in
                        1824). It is illuminating, too, to read his remarks, brief though they are,
                        on the relationship between Palmer’s only known wood-engraving,
                        “Harvest under a Crescent Moon,” and Blake’s Virgil
                        wood-engravings. It is, he writes, “very close in size, mood, and
                        technique to Blake’s Virgil cuts. Palmer once noted that Blake
                        particularly admired some of Claude Lorrain’s paintings because,
                        ‘when minutely examined, there were, upon the focal lights of the
                        foliage, small specks of pure white which made them appear to be glittering
                        with dew.’ The Virgil wood engravings, with their bold but skillfully
                        deployed flick work, exhibit a graphic equivalent to this technique. In
                        turn, Palmer’s single effort in wood achieves its moon-lit effects
                        through an almost identical, if slightly less energetic, use of the
                        graver.”</p>
          <p>Shelley M. Bennett, who compiled an attractive catalogue of the 1982
                        Huntington Library and Art Gallery exhibition, <hi rend="i">Prints by the
                            Blake Followers</hi>, contributes an essay entitled, “The Blake
                        Followers in the Context of Contemporary British Art.” In this Palmer
                        and his circle are considered against the background of the work of Turner,
                        Constable and other Romantics. Bennett, also with considerable originality,
                        compares them with certain aspects of the Pre-Raphaelites; one piquant
                        comparison concerns their similar surface textures: “The dense rich
                        surfaces of the meticulously worked plates, woodblocks and drawings of the
                        Blake followers produced a glowing, often jewel-like effect. The
                        Pre-Raphaelites obtained a similar luminosity in their oils by working on a
                        wet white ground which created a bright cloisonnélike clarity and
                        sparkle.”</p>
          <p>Bennett also makes interesting points concerning portraits by the Palmer
                        circle, claiming that they were indebted in some measure to Blake’s
                        Visionary Heads, and drawing attention to “their frontal, almost
                        iconic presentation.” She makes a similar point about
                        Linnell’s portrait of John Varley, painted against a star-studded sky
                        which, she writes, combined with “the fixed, hypnotic stare of the
                        eyes,” produces “an emotionally charged, almost visionary,
                        effect quite different from Lawrence’s slick grand-manner
                        exhibition-style portraits.” She might, more tellingly, have used
                        George Richmond’s later portraits as a comparison instead of those of
                        Lawrence.</p>
          <p>If I have a minor criticism of Bennett’s essay (and this also applies
                        in places to the other essays) it is of her continual reference to the
                        “Shoreham circle” and to the “Shoreham period.”
                        Shoreham, though highly important to the young men as a place of spiritual
                        recreation and inspiration, was their center for only a brief period; Palmer
                        alone was there for any length of time and the other members of the circle
                        were only intermittent visitors. Moreover, some of Palmer’s most
                        intensely visionary works—the great sepia watercolors of
                        1825—were completed before he moved there. There is nothing against
                        using “Shoreham” as a convenient label—and that is
                        doubtless what Bennett has done—but this ought to be kept in
                        perspective.</p>
          <p>The final chapter in <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers</hi> is by
                        Morton D. Paley and is entitled “‘To Realize After A Sort the
                        Imagery of Milton’: Samuel Palmer’s Designs for <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso.</hi>” It is
                        in many ways the <pb id="p19-82" n="82"/> most interesting in the book, for
                        it deals with a group of watercolors, painted in Palmer’s later
                        years, which have attracted little critical attention during the present
                        century, though there is now strong evidence of a revival of interest.<ref target="n34" type="note">13</ref> Commissioned by Leonard Rowe Valpy,
                        John Ruskin’s solicitor, the series contains some of the most
                        powerful works created by Palmer during his middle and old age. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Arnold Fawcus, Sir Geoffrey Keynes,
                            Raymond Lister and Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: A Vision
                                Recaptured</hi> (London, 1978); Helen Irwin, “Samuel Palmer,
                            Poet of Light and Shade,” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> (August 1981),
                            pp. 109-13.</note></p>
          <p>Milton’s influence on Palmer was strong; he loved especially <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso.</hi> He
                        also loved <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, which provided subjects for an earlier
                        series of watercolors, which though splendid in many ways, are less vital
                        than the Valpy watercolors. In the later Miltons Palmer drew on the
                        experiences of a lifetime, and it is possible to discover in them
                        recollections of his visionary years, of his visit to Italy, and of his work
                        in Devon, Surrey and Wales. His technique had matured impressively since his
                        early years, and he was now a complete master of the watercolor medium.
                        Incidentally, it is not surprising that Keating did not attempt to forge
                        works in Palmer’s later style with its formidable mastery of
                        technique. The mannerisms present in the works of the 1820s and early 1830s
                        made them misleadingly more inviting, though even here Keating did not come
                        within miles of making convincing forgeries.</p>
          <p>Paley discusses the Milton watercolors with great perception, relating them
                        to other contemporary interpretations of the same themes, and contrasting
                        their conception with that of similar works by William Blake, in the course
                        of which he demonstrates Palmer’s artistic independence, at least in
                        his maturity, of the older man.</p>
          <p>Yet it is a pity that he does not write more of the influence of earlier
                        artists on these works. Of these the influence of Claude Lorrain is the
                        strongest; indeed “A Towered City” seems to have been based
                        largely on an idealized view of Tivoli in Claude’s <hi rend="i">Liber
                            Veritatis</hi>,<ref target="n35" type="note">14</ref> which Palmer
                        probably knew through the mezzotints of Richard Earlom, published in 1777.
                        But Paley is absolutely right when he claims that among those of his
                        contemporaries who painted subjects from Milton, “only Palmer
                        captures the enticing atmosphere of poetic mystery we find in ‘The
                        Bellman’ and ‘The Lonely Tower.’ ” <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Reproduced in Michael Kitson, <hi rend="i">Claude Lorrain: Liber Veritatis</hi> (London, 1978), plate
                            67.</note></p>
          <p>It is to be hoped that Paley’s impressive essay will help to initiate
                        a more widespread interest in these works which, even if they lack the
                        intense visionary qualities of the artist’s more youthful work,
                        remain sublime evocations of the mind of the poet whose work they
                        illustrate. They are also a survey in old age of the artist’s
                        lifetime of artistic endeavor, of wide reading and of deep thought; akin to
                        what W.B. Yeats called “An old man’s eagle mind.”<ref target="n36" type="note">15</ref><note id="n36"><hi rend="s">15</hi> “An Acre of Grass” from
                                <hi rend="i">Last Poems</hi> (1936-39).</note></p>
          <p>Joseph Viscomi’s survey, <hi rend="i">Prints by Blake and His
                            Followers</hi>, is more specialized than <hi rend="i">Essays on the
                            Blake Followers</hi>, but within its self-imposed limits it is a
                        successful little work. It contains, in addition to the essay, a catalogue
                        of an exhibition held in March and April 1983 at the Herbert F. Johnson
                        Museum of Art at Cornell University. It is a shame that the unique
                        impression of Welby Sherman’s mezzotint “Illustration to
                        Byron’s <hi rend="i">Sennacherib</hi>,” now in the British
                        Museum, did not come to light soon enough to have been discussed by Viscomi,
                        for it is a remarkable little work, a tiny plate that seems to show the
                        influence of John Martin. It is to be included in the big exhibition <hi rend="i">Palmer and</hi> “<hi rend="i">The Ancients</hi>”
                        at the Fitzwilliam Museum during the coming autumn [1984].</p>
          <p>Incidentally, Viscomi is not quite right in claiming that George
                        Richmond’s “The Robber” and “The
                        Shepherd” were the only plates he executed, for later, in 1844, he
                        made a first class etching of Filippino Lippi’s portrait of Masaccio
                        in the Uffizi Gallery, Florence.<ref target="n37" type="note">16</ref><note id="n37"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">George
                                Richmond</hi> (London, 1981), p. 176, pl. XXIX.</note></p>
          <p>Viscomi’s discussions of technique are always trenchant. To take an
                        example, his argument against Bo Lindberg’s views of how Blake
                        prepared the designs on his <hi rend="i">Job</hi> plates are convincing. I
                        do not know what studies Viscomi has made during his career, but it would
                        not surprise me if he were a practical engraver, as he seems to be familiar
                        with nuances of technique that usually become apparent only to a
                        practitioner.</p>
          <p>But the author is at his best in discussing the engravings of Calvert, that
                        wonderful world of <hi rend="i">multum in parvo</hi>, of callipygous
                        beauties, of Christian allegories in classical landscapes. Here again he
                        analyzes with intelligence the practical methods used by Calvert, explaining
                        how he arrived at his effects; this is particularly fascinating in the case
                        of his lithographs.</p>
          <p>Of Palmer, Viscomi’s remark that “compared to the vibrantly
                        free etched lines of James McNeil Whistler and Seymour Haden,
                        Palmer’s etchings are paintings executed with needles and
                        acid” is perceptive. Palmer’s approach to etching was always
                        that of a painter—how could it be otherwise?—so it is strange
                        that he was so cautious in his attitude to retroussage,<ref target="n38" type="note">17</ref> a device which gave to his etchings some of their
                        most painterly effects. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Increasing the
                            strength of the lines by dropping a piece of muslin on to the plate to
                            drag up the ink in them before a print is taken.</note></p>
          <p>To sum up, these two books, small though they are, are serious studies which
                        should help to bring greater understanding to Blake’s followers, and
                        should also help to show those who were misled by the Keating forgeries how
                        to look at their works.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p19-83" n="83"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">William Blake. <hi rend="i">America: A Prophecy</hi> and
                                    <hi rend="i">Europe: A Prophecy.</hi> Facsimile Reproductions of
                                Two Illuminated Books with 35 Plates in Full Color. New York: Dover
                                Publications, 1983. $5.95; William Blake. <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                    Experience.</hi> Facsimile Reproduction with 26 Plates in Full
                                Color. New York: Dover Publications, 1984. $3.00</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Jenijoy</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">La Belle</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Dover Publications has made a fine reputation for itself by publishing
                        well-made paperbacks useful to students and scholars. Among its Blake titles
                        are <hi rend="i">Drawings of William Blake</hi> (1970) and a reduced
                        facsimile reproduction of Richard Edwards’ 1797 edition of
                        Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1975). In 1971 Dover
                        embarked upon the production of color facsimiles with an original-size
                        reproduction of copy B of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> Some of the
                        plates are fuzzy and the backgrounds are a little too dark, but for only two
                        dollars (later raised to three), the volume is valuable for handy reference
                        and classroom use. Dover has recently issued two further volumes containing
                        color reproductions of three illuminated books.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> are reproduced
                        original size in a single pamphlet-style paperback. The brief
                        “Publisher’s Note” includes the following information:
                        “The present volume reproduces the complete copy M of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (printed on paper made in 1799), whereas the complete <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> reproduced here includes colored plates from copies
                        B and G of that book and the black-and-white plate from copy K (all these
                        copies are privately owned). Note that <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> contains two
                        plates numbered 9—referred to in the present edition as 9(a) and
                        9(b)—and has no plate numbered 11.” Some of this information
                        is wrong, and the whole statement is misleading. Copy M of <hi rend="i">America</hi> and B of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> are indeed in private
                        collections, but copy G of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is now in the Pierpont
                        Morgan Library and copy K has been in the Fitzwilliam Museum since 1950. The
                        comment about two plates numbered 9 implies that this repetition appears in
                        original copies of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and that none contains a plate
                        numbered 11. This is not the case at all. Both copies B and G are numbered
                        consecutively, and the presence of two plates numbered 9 in the facsimile
                        results from its composite nature. In copy G, plate 12 (following the plate
                        numbers in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>) is numbered 9, while the
                        same number is given to plate 13 in copy B.</p>
          <p>The Publisher’s Note implies that the Dover reproductions were made
                        directly from the original copies cited. I am highly suspicious of
                        this—partly because none of the owners of the originals is named and
                        also because there is no statement of permission to reproduce. Further, the
                        mixture of three copies of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is exactly the same as
                        that appearing in the Blake Trust/Trianon Press facsimile of 1969. The copy
                        of <hi rend="i">America</hi> reproduced by Dover is the same as the one used
                        by the Blake Trust for its 1963 facsimile. The Dover reproductions of both
                        illuminated books show distinct boundary lines between contiguous colors,
                        and this feature is typical of the Blake Trust method of stencil coloring,
                        rather than of Blake’s own method with its gentle gradations of
                        tones. Thus it would appear that the Dover volume is based on two Blake
                        Trust facsimiles and that these are the books “privately
                        owned” (perhaps by Mr. Hayward Cirker, founder and owner of Dover?).
                        Since the volume lacks any reference to the Blake Trust, I assume that no
                        permission was necessary.</p>
          <p>Using the Blake Trust facsimile of <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy M as a
                        standard, I find that most of the plates in the Dover reproduction have
                        acceptable color fidelity. The only major problem would seem to be a dulling
                        of the blue tones, particularly on plates 3 and 5 (as numbered in copy M).
                        The sunburst on plate 7 has lost some of its brilliance, and the outlining
                        of the ram and the two figures has become a little unfocused. Several other
                        plates suffer from indistinct outline in design areas, but the only really
                        bad reproductions are plates 8 and 9. Both have a brown tint to the white
                        paper in text areas, and this browning has seriously affected the blues on
                        plate 8 and the greens on plate 9. Clearly, the Dover reproductions are not
                        suitable for the detailed analysis of Blake’s hand coloring. No one,
                        however, should expect an inexpensive reproduction to provide the basis for
                        such analyses. The Dover reproductions are certainly adequate for many other
                        types of studies.</p>
          <pb id="p19-84" n="84"/>
          <p>The color work in the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> facsimile is also generally
                        satisfactory. Three plates, however, have a distinct color shift not found
                        in their Blake Trust archetypes: plate 9 (inscribed “6” in the
                        reproduction) has been given a rather ghoulish green tint; plate 11
                        (inscribed “8”) has the same brown shift found in some of the
                            <hi rend="i">America</hi> plates; and the final plate is a little too
                        yellow. I would not be surprised to find variations among copies of the
                        Dover volume—particularly if they continue to print from the same
                        transparencies. The later printings of the Dover <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi> show just this sort of decay of both color and sharpness
                        of outline.</p>
          <p>In addition to the reproductions, the volume includes exceedingly brief
                        summaries of the poems and descriptions of the designs. The latter seem to
                        be summary paraphrases of Sir Geoffrey Keynes’s notes on the designs
                        in the Blake Trust facsimiles. The Dover volume concludes with a
                        transcription of the texts. Lacking any indication to the contrary, the
                        typographic texts appear to be new transcriptions rather than reprints of a
                        previously published edition. The details of punctuation do not follow
                        Keynes, Erdman, Stevenson, or Bentley.</p>
          <p>Dover’s new facsimile of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> has the
                        same format as its 1971 <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> facsimile. The two
                        volumes are clearly meant to be companions. In this later volume, the
                        publisher’s only reference to the copy reproduced is a statement on
                        the verso of the typographic title-page that the facsimile is based on
                        “a copy printed ca. 1826.” On the back cover, this same date
                        is given rather misleadingly as the date of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
                            and of Experience.</hi> The appearance of the Dover plates makes it
                        clear that the work reproduced is the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> section
                        from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, copy Z, with
                        Blake’s inscribed plate numbers, but not his hand-drawn framing
                        lines, eliminated. For unexplained reasons, the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> is also omitted. Copy Z is well known from the fine
                        Blake Trust facsimile of 1955. The appearance of fairly definite boundary
                        lines between colors in the Dover reproduction makes me suspect that, once
                        again, Dover is silently reproducing the work of the Trust. It is even
                        possible that the plates are based on the 1967 Orion Press/Rupert Hart-Davis
                        reproductions of Z, reissued in 1970 by Oxford University Press. These
                        complete reproductions of copy Z are themselves based on the Blake Trust
                        facsimile, and thus the Dover volume could be a reproduction of a
                        reproduction of a reproduction. (I doubt that this is what Blake meant by
                        “Fourfold Vision.”) In comparison to all of these possible
                        forebears, Dover’s plates show a strong and most unfortunate shift
                        towards a magenta tint. This feature, plus the fact that about half the
                        plates seem a little out of focus, make the volume less handsome and less
                        useful than the <hi rend="i">America/Europe</hi> facsimile. The <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> volume concludes with a transcription of the text.</p>
          <p>Although I’ve been rather grumpy about the problems, these are nice
                        volumes (particularly for the classroom) and well worth having—as
                        long as they are not treated with the same sort of trust we give to the real
                        Trust facsimiles. Dover is to be congratulated for producing these books and
                        for offering them for a song.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <figure/>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">Selections from William Blake’s</hi>
                                Songs of Innocence and of Experience; <hi rend="i">Musical Settings
                                    by Gregory Forbes</hi>, Ecchoing Green Records, 1983. <hi rend="i">A Companion to the New Musical Settings by Gregory
                                    Forbes.</hi> Gregory Forbes. Kingston, Ontario: Quarry Press,
                                1983. 48 pages. Together $27.70; with a set of 20 slides, $35.70.
                                Slide set only, $11.20. Prices include shipping.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Joseph</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Viscomi</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">with</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Margaret</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">LaFrance</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>As Ruthven Todd points out, “no one can fully understand the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> divorced of their setting.”<ref target="n39" type="note">1</ref> Some fine, hand-colored facsimiles have made it
                        possible to read Blake’s illuminated poetry as graphic art consisting
                        of text and illustration in complex relations. In short, to read it as
                        originally presented. Or have they? Poetry and painting were only two of the
                        “three Powers in Man of <pb id="p19-85" n="85"/> conversing with
                        Paradise which the flood did not Sweep away” (K 609). The third Power
                        was Music, and music, according to Cunningham, was an integral part of the
                        composing process as manifest in the illuminated print: “As he drew
                        the figure he mediated the song which was to accompany it, and the music to
                        which the verse was to be sung, was the offspring too of the same
                            moment.”<ref target="n40" type="note">2</ref> Must the
                        poetry’s setting, then, be musical as well as visual? <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (Norwood, Pa.:
                            Norwood Editions, 1973), p. viii.</note><note id="n40"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Allan Cunningham, <hi rend="i">Lives of
                                the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors and Architects; Blake
                                Records</hi>, p. 482.</note></p>
          <p>That music was important to Blake, there can be no doubt. According to
                        Gilchrist, Blake “was very impressionable . . . to simple national
                        melodies . . . though not so to music of more complicated structure.”
                        At the Linnells’, he “would sit by the pianoforte, tears
                        falling from his eyes, while he listened to the Border Melody” sung
                        by Mrs. Linnell. Even then, as late as 1825, he “still sang, in a
                        voice tremulous with age, sometimes old ballads, sometimes his own songs, to
                        melodies of his own.”<ref target="n41" type="note">3</ref> Blake is
                        recorded as having died with a song on his lips, while some of our earliest
                        accounts of him as a poet emphasize his singing.<ref target="n42" type="note">4</ref> At Mrs. Mathew’s salon, “he was
                        listened to by the company with profound silence and allowed by most of the
                        visitors to possess original and extraordinary merit.”<ref target="n43" type="note">5</ref> And although Blake “was entirely
                        unacquainted with the science of music, his ear was so good, that his tunes
                        were sometimes most singularly beautiful, and were noted down by musical
                            professors.”<ref target="n44" type="note">6</ref> In <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> (c. 1784), in large part a satire of salon
                        society, Quid, Blake’s caricature of himself, continually bursts into
                        song. True, Gittipin, Gimblet, Obtuse Angle, and the other Islanders may not
                        have been musically sophisticated, but Blake’s real salon audience
                        certainly was. “Being a musical house,” the Mathew gatherings
                        included accomplished singers like Elizabeth Billington, composers like
                        Thomas Billington, famous musicologists like Dr. Charles Burney (perhaps one
                        of the music professors?) and Flaxman, who evidently “sang
                        beautifully, having an excellent and beautiful voice.”<ref target="n45" type="note">7</ref> Singing to people who knew a thing or
                        two about music suggests not only that Blake was confident of his voice and
                        compositions, but that he actually was a good singer. Like the Italian
                        saying: If you want to see if you can sing, go to where women wash clothes;
                        if they stop singing, you’re good. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">3</hi>
                            Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (London: J.
                            M. Dent &amp; Sons, 1942), p. 41.</note><note id="n42"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Fredrick Tatham; <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Records</hi>, p. 305.</note><note id="n43"><hi rend="s">5</hi> J. T. Smith, in Gilchrist, p. 41.</note><note id="n44"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi></note><note id="n45"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Tatham; <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>,
                            p. 521. For a list of possible guests at the Mathews’ and of the
                            pleasure gardens and theatres where Blake would have heard popular
                            music, see. B.H. Fairchild, <hi rend="i">Such Holy Song</hi> (Kent,
                            Ohio: Kent State University Press, 1980), p. 7.</note></p>
          <p>That Blake should sing while he worked is as natural as words and images
                        generating and being generated by melodies. It is more interesting, though,
                        that the simultaneity in the illuminated printing process of melos, logos,
                        and graphics is manifest in the reception of the illuminated print. In the
                        “Introduction” to the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>,
                        music, singing, and writing, though executed sequentially by the Piper, come
                        together in the form of the book, so that “all [who] read” the
                        “happy songs . . . may joy to hear” (K 111). Reading is
                        hearing the songs, the melody being the activity of mind as it reads. As
                        Blake says, “Nature has no Tune, but Imagination has” (K 779).
                        Because “Melody,” like “Invention [and]
                        Identity,” is one of the “Objects of Intuition” (K
                        474), the songs are given settings each time they are read. Historically, it
                        is the only time the three Powers do come together, for Blake is not known
                        to have passed out illuminated prints as song sheets as he read or sang
                        them.</p>
          <p>Gregory Forbes, with his album of twelve songs selected from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, sixteen “facsimiles
                        of Blake’s coloured engravings,” a set of twenty slides, and a
                        large size illustrated commentary, attempts to combine the aural and visual
                        Blake within a historical context.<ref target="n46" type="note">8</ref> His
                        “aim . . . in writing . . . has been to bring the listener to an
                        understanding of the song lyrics in a way that Blake intended them”
                        (p. 9). Blake’s exact intentions, of course, aren’t known,
                        since he never wrote down the music (it is not “lost,” p.
                            7),<ref target="n47" type="note">9</ref> but Forbes reasons that
                        “because [Blake’s] sympathies were always with the common
                        people . . . traditional folk music stylings are especially appropriate for
                        Blake’s songs” (p. 7).<ref target="n48" type="note">10</ref>
                        So, “to bring Blake to the people,” he based his aural
                        reconstructions on children’s hymns, folk ballads, and Elizabethan
                        songs, as well as “the street music of Blake’s London, the jig
                        and reels of itinerant fiddlers and pipers” (p. 7), and used
                        contemporaneous instruments, such as guitars, flutes, flageolers, violin,
                        and hand-drums. From <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> he has set
                        “Introduction,” “The Shepherd,” “The
                        Lamb,” “The Divine Image,” “Laughing
                        Song,” “The Ecchoing Green” [side A]; from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> “Introduction,” “London,”
                        “A Little Girl Lost,” “The Garden of Love,”
                        “The Tyger,” “Ah! Sun-flower” [side B]. The
                        songs were chosen to represent “the main themes of the complete
                        cycle” (p. 8). Blake’s contrary states and their accompanying
                        symbols and images are discussed in some detail (pp. 24-27), but the song
                        order, instrumentation, and arrangement of the reproductions do not pair
                        contrary states or make explicit the connections within or between the two
                        sets. <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The basis for the album project is
                            the series of workshops Forbes conducted for secondary school children
                            in “Frontenac County, Ontario, Canada, and later presented . . .
                            at two conferences of the Ontario Council of the Teachers of English.
                            All of these were arranged by David Schleich of St. Lawrence College,
                            Kingston” (p. 47). With the encouragement of Schleich, also
                            editor of Quarry Press and tom-tom player on “The Tyger,”
                            Gregory Forbes seems to have done everything himself, including writing
                            the accompanying commentary. Despite its elaborate presentation, the
                            project is quite Blakean in spirit. The logo for Ecchoing Green Records
                            (a company certainly created for this project) is the Piper from the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> title page, while the record label is
                            “The River of Life,” printed in green, with its flute
                            players on either side of the spindle hole.</note><note id="n47"><hi rend="s">9</hi> There is an odd use of sources and
                            significant omissions. Forbes describes the music as
                            “lost,” referring, one assumes, to those tunes Smith says
                            were “noted down by musical professors.” However, he never
                            refers to Smith, but to Cunningham’s statement that Blake
                            “wanted the art of writing it down” (p. 7), which leaves
                            the reader with the impression that Blake’s unrecorded musical
                            notations are missing or lost. Cunningham also notes that if they
                            “equalled many of his drawings and some of his songs, we have
                            lost melodies of real value” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
                            482).</note><note id="n48"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Forbes is certainly correct to argue
                            that an understanding of the music of Blake’s day is the first
                            step to hearing the poetry as Blake meant us to hear it. But I think he
                            overstates the case when he says that “not much has been written
                            about Blake’s musical sources since very little is known about
                            the subject; the study must be based almost entirely on Blake’s
                            lyrics” (p. 47). By citing only one work in the bibliography on
                            the subject, Martha England’s “Blake and the Hymns of
                            Charles Wesley” (<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public
                                Library</hi>, 70 [1966], 7-33), he makes clear the need for his
                            album project at the expense of strengthening it as an introduction to
                            the subject, about which much is actually already known. What is not
                            known is if Blake’s familiarity with popular ballads derived from
                            reading or singing them. Forbes does mention (p. 22) Thomas
                            Percy’s <hi rend="i">Reliques of Ancient English Poetry</hi>
                            (1765), a copy of which Blake owned; but not Christopher Smart’s
                                <hi rend="i">Hymns for the Amusement of Children</hi> (3 editions
                            between 1770-1775); Joseph Ritson’s <hi rend="i">A Select
                                Collection of English Songs</hi> (1783), for which Blake engraved
                            several plates; nor any of the contemporary essays on the relation
                            between music and poetry, like John Aiken’s <hi rend="i">Essays
                                on Song-Writing</hi> (1774); Ambrose Philips’ “Letter
                            on Song-writing,” in <hi rend="i">The Guardian</hi>, #16 (1713);
                            Anselm Bayly’s <hi rend="i">The Alliance of Musick, Poety, and
                                Oratory</hi> (1789); or Daniel Webb’s <hi rend="i">Observations on the Correspondence between Poetry and Music</hi>
                            (1769); nor does he mention recent theoretical work, like Bertrand H.
                            Bronson’s <hi rend="i">Music and Literature in England in the
                                Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries</hi> (Los Angeles: Clark
                            Memorial Library of the University of California at Los Angeles, 1953),
                            or Herbert M. Schueller’s “Correspondences between Music
                            and the Sister Arts, According to Eighteenth-Century Aesthetic
                            Theory” (<hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art
                                Criticism</hi>, 11 [1953], 334-59). These works may be too esoteric
                            for Forbes’ audience of high school students, but he seems not to
                            have read them himself or six works that are crucial to discussing the
                            influence of hymns and popular ballads on Blake’s poetry: Albert
                            B. Friedman’s <hi rend="i">The Ballad Revival: Studies in the
                                Influence of Popular on Sophisticated Poetry</hi> (Chicago: Chicago
                            University Press, 1961), George Sampson’s “The Century of
                            Divine Songs,” in <hi rend="i">Proceedings of the British
                                Academy</hi>, 29 (1943), Martha England and John Sparrow’s
                                <hi rend="i">Hymns Unbidden: Donne, Herbert, Blake, Emily Dickinson,
                                and the Hymnographers</hi>; Nick Shrimpton “Hell’s
                            Hymnbook: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                                Experience</hi> and Their Models,” in <hi rend="i">Literature
                                of the Romantic Period: 1750-1850</hi>, Ed. R. T. Davies and B.G.
                            Beatty (New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1976), pp. 19-35; John
                            Adlard’s <hi rend="i">The Sports of Cruelty: Fairies, Folk-Songs,
                                Charms and other Country Matters in the Work of William Blake</hi>
                            (London: Cecil &amp; Amelia Woolf, 1972); and, most important, B.H.
                            Fairchild’s <hi rend="i">Such Holy Song: Music as Idea, Form, and
                                Image in the Poetry of William Blake</hi> (Kent, Ohio: Kent
                            University Press, 1980).</note></p>
          <p>The slides are for “classroom presentation,” to be viewed
                        “while listening to the music,” an audio-visual presentation
                        which Forbes believes will “project [the listener] into that time
                        when Blake created each illustration and, at the same time ‘meditated
                        the song which was to accompany it’ ” (p. 10). The slides,
                        which are of the same plates as the reproductions, plus Linnell’s
                        sketch of Blake and the three title pages to <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, are
                        used not only to accommodate a student audience, but because they
                        “are much clearer and more vivid than the printed reproductions, and
                        the lyrics can be read without difficulty” (p. 8). Indeed, the 16
                        photomechanical reproductions (the songs, frontispieces, and “The
                        Voice of the Ancient Bard,” which is not set to music), though
                        printed on fine, heavyweight ivory paper, are in no way <pb id="p19-86" n="86"/> facsimiles. None is easily readable; all give a poor idea of
                        what illuminated prints look like. The copy is not identified, but seems to
                        be copy Z without the frame lines.<ref target="n49" type="note">11</ref><note id="n49"><hi rend="s">11</hi> The reproductions seem to be of 6 and 8
                            color offset reproductions of copy Z, published by Rupert Hart-Davis
                            Ltd. in 1967. Forbes mentions twice (pp. 23, 47) that the first color
                            facsimile of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> was 1967, which, of course, is
                            not true, but it does seem to indicate that he used the 1967 volume to
                            make his “facsimiles.” (Hard to believe that offset
                            lithography could have undone so many!) For a list of early color
                            facsimiles of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, see <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1978), pp. 432-39. For a history of
                            Blake facsimiles, see Robert N. Essick’s review of the Manchester
                            Etching Workshop facsimiles, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi>, 19 (1985), 39.</note></p>
          <p>Introducing Blake through song and image is both creative and practical, and
                        a logical extension of what W.H. Auden said—or almost
                        said—somewhere: “No poetry is good poetry that is not good
                        when read aloud.” One would think that the voice of the balladeer
                        could easily join those of piper, bard, and prophet, and, like theirs, add
                        to our understanding and enjoyment of Blake. But, unfortunately, the
                        Donovan-like style of these settings does little to enhance the inherent
                        musicality of Blakes words—let alone reveal the meaning of the
                            songs.<ref target="n50" type="note">12</ref> Missing here is the
                        poet’s ear for what a poet said. <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">12</hi>
                            The Donovan album they recall most clearly is <hi rend="i">A Gift from a
                                Flower to a Garden</hi> (Epic, 1967), which is probably only
                            coincidence, but it is interesting to note that Donovan in this
                            two-record set seems to think he’s Blake. As a
                            “minstrel,” he sings his “poems” so that
                            “all may see and know . . . that God is Love,” sings one
                            of them to experienced “youth” and the other to innocent
                            “children of the dawning generation.” The texts of the 12
                            songs for children are printed and illustrated with pen line drawings,
                            and the sheets form both a booklet and a song cycle.</note></p>
          <p>A familiarity with eighteenth-century folk stylings and ballad structures may
                        be necessary to capture the popular sounds of Blake’s age, but it is
                        no assurance of communicating the spirit of Blake’s poems. Because of
                        the musical limitations of Forbes’ compositional style, the settings
                        too often seem like impositions on, rather than expositions of, the text.
                        Indeed, the style seems even more limited than it is because Forbes, perhaps
                        confusing the distinction between simplicity and monotony, not only sings
                        all the songs himself, but uses only one instrument, the guitar, as the
                        dominant accompanimental instrument in all of the settings. While his guitar
                        playing is more than adequate, his voice is not the sort that can sustain
                        interest for an entire album. While Forbes does incorporate other
                        instruments throughout the album, using sometimes as many as six musicians,
                        he uses them in such limited and subordinate ways that their presence almost
                        frustrates more than it pleases. The flute, for instance, which he uses to
                        represent the innocent Piper, often plays trills in the background, which
                        are meant to sound pastoral and serene. But the trills rarely grow
                        organically from the musical context, seeming instead to have been a concept
                        of innocence thought of and tacked on after the setting was complete. A more
                        successful use of other instruments is in the jig-like sections that follow
                        “Laughing Song” and the “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, although in both instances, the jigs
                        go on so long that we lose the initial freshness of the idea. And, while
                        this type of postlude certainly captures the energetic spirit of the former,
                        it seems a questionable ending to the latter.</p>
          <p>From <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, “The Lamb” is the setting
                        that works best. In this song, Forbes’ compositional techniques (a
                        small melodic range, and repetitive rhythms and harmonies) enhance the text.
                        Here the gentle arpeggiation in the guitar and the quiet flute obligato lend
                        a lovely simplicity to the song without becoming monotonous or saccharine.
                        These same compositional techniques do not, however, work in every song.
                        Indeed, in “The Divine Image,” Forbes’ style actually
                        destroys the meaning of the poem. The melody for the first line
                        (“Mercy, Pity, Peace, and Love”) is mi, re, ti, do, a
                        seemingly inoffensive and simple arrangements of tones. But when this melody
                        is imposed on the text, and in the syllabic rhythm of the text, the effect
                        is unsettling at best. The seventh step of the scale (ti) is unstable
                        because of its half-step proximity—and its consequent need to
                        “pull”—to tonic (do). That the word
                        “peace” occurs on ti and is then given rhythmic stress (i.e. a
                        longer note value) is not only awkward and unaccomplished writing, but it
                        destroys the very peacefulness and harmony that the words (as a phrase) are
                        trying to convey.</p>
          <p>From <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, “London” and “Ah!
                        Sun-flower” are the best. In “London,” the drone bass
                        note successfully portrays the hopeless plodding of downtrodden people and
                        the wailing guitar notes become the cries of the “chimney
                        sweeper” and “youthful harlot.” In this song,
                        Forbes’ technique of repeating his melodies by couplets rather than
                        stanzas (a technique which contributes to the stasis of many of the
                        settings) works very well as a way of accentuating the key words and images.
                        The coda to “Ah! Sun-flower,” which goes on almost as long as
                        the song itself (but, unfortunately, at such a reduced audio level that it
                        is difficult to hear), features a guitar solo by Thomas Handy, the
                        improvisatory nature of which is a welcome change from Forbes’
                        consistent and controlled guitar accompaniments to the songs. One only
                        wishes that Forbes had been this adventurous in all of his settings.</p>
          <p>The commentary is in two parts and, with forty-eight pages of wide double
                        columns of type, is quite extensive. “William Blake and the Age of
                        Revolution,” the first section of part I, examines the
                        “Political” “Industrial,”
                        “Intellectual,” “Social,” and
                        “Romantic” revolutions of Blake’s day, and his
                        reactions to them. “William Blake’s Life and Writing,”
                        the second section, focuses on those events of Blake’s life and his
                        other writings that have a “bearing on the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>” (p. 9). “The Poetics of the Songs,”
                        section three, analyses the form, diction, and symbolism of the poems and
                        discusses the main literary devices Blake employs. Irony, unfortunately, is
                        not included, but an erroneous definition of illuminated printing is. Part
                        II is primarily an explication of each of the twelve songs and designs, with
                        a very “Select Bibliography.” The booklet is decorated with
                        monochrome vignettes from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and other illuminated
                        books, none of which is identified or discussed in the text.</p>
          <p>The background material is mostly derived from Bronowski’s <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Age of Revolution</hi>, while the
                        interpretation of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> is mostly derived from
                        Wicksteed and Hirsh. Oddly, though, Forbes ignores the latter’s sense
                        of change and the former’s warning of reading Blake backwards, in
                        favor of reading the songs within Blake’s “system,” an
                        approach more in keeping <pb id="p19-87" n="87"/> with Adams and
                            Gleckner.<ref target="n51" type="note">13</ref> At any rate, Forbes has
                        written a very solid introductory text, with Blake intelligently placed in
                        his time, and the poems, “London” and the “Garden of
                        Love” in particular, given fine, detailed explications. The page or
                        two on each poem is designed to help the student read the poem, literally,
                        by identifying verbs, nouns, antecedents, and parallel structures, and by
                        pointing out important biblical and historical allusions, key words,
                        symbols, and recurrent images. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Jacob
                            Bronowski, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Age of Revolution</hi>
                            (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1965); Joseph H. Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Innocence and Experience</hi> (London: J.M. Dent
                            &amp; Sons Ltd., 1928); E.D. Hirsh, Jr., <hi rend="i">Innocence and
                                Experience: An Introduction to Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale
                            University Press), which was published in 1964, not “1927”
                            (p. 47); Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Reading of the
                                Shorter Poems</hi> (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1963);
                            Robert Gleckner, <hi rend="i">The Piper and The Bard</hi> (Detroit:
                            Wayne State Univerity Press, 1959).</note></p>
          <p>In the discussion of the poems, of diverse “revolutions, . . . and how
                        [Blake] reacted to them” (p. 11), it is obvious that Forbes knows his
                        audience well. His definition of Experience for woman as sexual repression,
                        for example, and his comments about the marriage of love (and thus
                        Blake’s own marriage), the arranged marriage, and the influence of
                        the role of women in the American Colonies on Blake, Wollstonecraft, and
                        other writers, will, I think, be of particular interest to high school
                        students (“Social Revolution: Marriage and Women’s
                        Rights,” p. 15). So, too, will many of the facts he cites: “A
                        teenage boy could be hanged for minor theft. There were 150 crimes
                        punishable by hanging (although murder was not one of them); most of them
                        were crimes against public property” (pp. 11-12); “there were
                        50,000 prostitutes, not counting mistresses kept by men of wealth,”
                        in Blake’s London (p. 16); “of the 70 years of Blake’s
                        life, Britain was at war for 35” (p. 11).</p>
          <p>Some of his facts, though, are wrong. He defines engraving as a technique in
                        which “a design was copied on to a copper plate with an
                        acid-resistant varnish; when acid was applied to the plate, the design would
                        remain in relief” (p. 23). In other words, he confuses engraving with
                        relief etching, as well as the concepts of negative and positive (using them
                        to mean reverse and regular writing). He cites Todd and Hayter’s 1948
                        experiments as the last word, ignoring Essick’s <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake, Printmaker</hi> (Princeton University Press, 1980), a careful
                        reading of which would have prevented these and a number of other technical
                            errors.<ref target="n52" type="note">14</ref> And he sees the stimulus
                        for illuminated printing in the printing of the <hi rend="i">Poetical
                            Sketches</hi> (1783). It is, however, highly unlikely that Blake sought
                        “an inexpensive method of self publication” because the
                        apology in the advertisement proved an “embarrassing
                        experience” (p. 19). Publishing juvenilia was very fashionable
                        (especially in the 1770’s and 1780’s) and, though Blake was
                        certainly no “untutored youth,” excusing its merit quite
                            common;<ref target="n53" type="note">15</ref> fashion and convention are
                        still to be seen in Byron’s preface to <hi rend="i">Hours of
                            Idleness</hi>, 1807. Besides, Blake was given the book in sheets; that
                        he made no attempt to distribute it cannot be attributed to one offending
                        page, which could have been easily extracted. <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">14</hi> A few technical corrections: Blake’s apprenticeship
                            was not to the Society of Antiquaries but to Basire, the
                            Society’s official engraver (pp. 23, 26). Illuminated books of
                            the Middle Ages were not “hand-printed” (p. 19), nor is
                            “illuminated printing” a “technique that married
                            the arts of engraving with watercolor painting” (p. 7). It is
                            doubtful that “Blake was a victim of technological change in that
                            engraving was a dying craft, gradually giving way to lithography in the
                            first two decades of the 18th century [sic]” (p. 13). Forbes
                            means, of course, the nineteenth century, but during this period the
                            most popular reproductive method was aquatint, the mainstay of the
                            picturesque view industry, and engraving, even after Hullmandel set up
                            his lithography press, 1817-1818, was in great demand, because the
                            development of steel engraving (1822) made it possible to print tens of
                            thousands of impressions with great detail and without loss of
                            quality.</note><note id="n53"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Margaret Ruth Lowry, <hi rend="i">Windows of the Morning: A Critical Study of William
                                Blake’s</hi> Poetical Sketches, <hi rend="i">1783</hi> (New
                            Haven: Yale University Press, 1940), pp. 39-41.</note></p>
          <p>We can dismiss the idea that for five years Blake was actively looking for an
                        alternative means for publishing his works—or four years, if the
                        “illuminate the manuscript” phrase in <hi rend="i">An Island
                            in the Moon</hi> (1784) is misinterpreted as referring to illuminated
                        printing. He would have been one very unimaginative printmaker had he not
                        known that texts could be illustrated and multiplied on one page by etching
                        or engraving; the former, after all, is the method Blake used for three of
                        his illuminated books, and one or the other method is what all
                        eighteenth-century writing engravers and trade card makers used to print and
                        illustrate their texts. Why Blake used relief etching instead of any other
                        method and waited till 1788 to begin experiments are important questions,
                        but they go unanswered when relief etching is pictured as a major
                        breakthrough after years of trying and searching.<ref target="n54" type="note">16</ref><note id="n54"><hi rend="s">16</hi> For a discussion of why Blake chose to
                            use relief etching when other, more conventional, methods would have
                            enabled him to combine text and illustrations on one plate, see my <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated Prints</hi>
                            (Manchester: Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983), pp. 1,
                        19-20.</note></p>
          <p>The picture of Blake as a graphic artist is a bit out of focus in other ways,
                        too. Forbes inadvertently perpetuates an image of Blake that we recognize as
                        Victorian, though its originator was himself a contemporary of
                        Blake’s. Borrowing from Cunningham, Forbes pictures Blake as
                        “a man of tireless industry, and after a day’s work . . . for
                        other artists and booksellers . . . he would paint or write through the
                        night” (p. 20). Cunningham says: “During the day [Blake] was a
                        man of sagacity and sense, who handled his graver wisely, and conversed in a
                        wholesome and pleasant manner; in the evening, when he had done his
                        prescribed task, he gave loose to his imagination.”<ref target="n55" type="note">17</ref> But the image of an artist who “engraved by
                        day,” as though in some shop, but “saw visions at
                            night”<ref target="n56" type="note">18</ref> while laboring in
                        his own studio, presents a schizophrenic artist and a melodramatic scene
                        worthy of George Sand, and one which appeals to those who need conflict in
                        order to see meaning in what would otherwise be plotless day-to-day living.
                        But there was no physical or temporal separation between Blake’s
                        commissioned works as an engraver or designer and his own work in relief
                        etching. All the plates were executed at home, in his own studio, cut and
                        drawn on the same tables, proofed and printed with the same ink, on the same
                        press. Blake did not work in a copperplate printer’s workshop, or a
                        large engraving studio, or a pressroom. It is a mistake to think of him as a
                        craftsman constantly under someone’s watchful eye, or under the
                        pressure of deadlines like nineteenth-century wood engravers working for the
                            <hi rend="i">Illustrated London News.</hi><note id="n55"><hi rend="s">17</hi><hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 488.</note><note id="n56"><hi rend="s">18</hi> P. 501.</note></p>
          <p>The image of Blake as a mere craftsman, and not just a mistaken notion of the
                        relation between invention and execution (a relation beyond the scope of
                        this or probably any introductory text), is partly responsible for the idea
                        that Blake “wanted . . . skill of hand,”<ref target="n57" type="note">19</ref> an idea that Blake fought so hard to overcome. Why
                        the “Tyger” looks like a harmless cat, for example, cannot be
                        explained by a lack of skill on Blake’s part, or, as Forbes suggests,
                        a case in which Blake, “in executing the drawing . . . ended up with
                        a creation quite different <pb id="p19-88" n="88"/> from what he had in
                        mind” (p. 44). Picturing Blake as a nineteenth-century craftsman is
                        not only misleading, but contradicts Cunningham’s own image of Blake
                        as a multitalented artist “sketching designs, engraving plates,
                        writing songs, and composing music” all at the same time<ref target="n58" type="note">20</ref>—of a man conversing with
                        Paradise with all his Powers. <note id="n57"><hi rend="s">19</hi> P.
                            485.</note><note id="n58"><hi rend="s">20</hi> P. 482.</note></p>
          <p>Forbes’ settings are not art songs or compositions like those of
                        Benjamin Britten, Ralph Vaughan Williams, or George Rochberg.<ref target="n59" type="note">21</ref> Nor are they “Airs simple and
                        etheral to match the designs and poems of William Blake,” which, as
                        Gilchrist admits, “would be a novelty in music.”<ref target="n60" type="note">22</ref> As simple folk songs, they are more
                        successful at introducing Gregory Forbes than the spirit of William Blake.
                        The settings are not “aural facsimiles,” but, then, what is
                        appealing in theory is almost always impossible in practice. Whatever the
                        album’s scholarly merit, and despite the commentary’s minor
                        misrepresentations, Forbes’ triadic presentation (and sound argument
                        for such a presentation) ought to stimulate lively and imaginative
                        discussion about the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in and out of the classroom.
                            <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Britten, <hi rend="i">Songs &amp;
                                Proverbs of William Blake</hi>, for baritone and piano, op. 74
                            (London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1965); Williams, <hi rend="i">Ten Blake
                                Songs</hi>, for voice and oboe (London: Oxford University Press,
                            1958); Rochberg, <hi rend="i">Blake Songs</hi>, for soprano and chamber
                            ensemble (New York: Leeds Music Corp., 1963). There is, admittedly, a
                            thin line between poor translation and exciting variation. New settings
                            of a song or play can become works of art in their own right,
                            celebrating the original and displaying what may have been hid. It seems
                            that musicians have been more successful in creating new works of art
                            based on Blake’s songs than have other artists. Illustrations of
                            Blake’s poetry struck Ruthven Todd as “the most horrible
                            of all things”—though, admittedly, he had the
                            “whimsical drawings of some cheery, chintzy girl, who is
                            ‘so fond of Blake as he inspires her so much.’ From such
                            nightmares as these, Good Lord, Deliver us!” (Todd, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, p. viii). He is
                            apparently referring to (and quite rightly, I think) Pamela
                            Bianco’s line drawings in <hi rend="i">The Land of Dreams</hi>
                            (New York: Macmillan, 1928).</note><note id="n60"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Gilchrist, p. 41.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p19-89" n="89"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0009">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>ASECS CLIFFORD PRIZE</title>
          </head>
          <figure/>
          <p>The American Society for Eighteenth-Century Studies is currently soliciting
                        nominations for its 1984-85 James L. Clifford Prize. The Prize carries an
                        award of $300 and goes to the best nominated article, an outstanding study
                        of some aspect of eighteenth-century culture, interesting to any
                        eighteenth-century specialist, regardless of discipline. The following rules
                        also apply: (1) The article should not be longer than 7500 words. (2) The
                        article must have appeared in print in a journal, festschrift, or other
                        serial publication between July 1984 and June 1985. (3) The article may be
                        nominated by a member of the Society or by its author. (4) Nominations must
                        be accompanied by an offprint or copy of the article and must be postmarked
                        by February 1, 1986 and sent to the ASECS office. (5) The winning author
                        must be a member of the Society at the time of the award. Nominations or
                        inquiries should be sent to the following address: ASECS, R.G. Peterson,
                        Executive Secretary, St. Olaf College, Northfield, MN 55057, (505)
                        663-3488.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
