<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
 <idno>040-03</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><hi rend="b">BLAKE</hi> AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2006/2007</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2006-07</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">40.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Börrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Marsha Keith Schuchard</name>
              <name>Keri Davies</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2006/2007"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_40">
    <front>
      <pb id="p40-81-82" n="81-82"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.040.03.bqscan" rend="file">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            O Br&#252;der: Keith Schuchard and Keri Davies Revisit the Moravians<lb/>
            VOLUME 40<lb/>
            NUMBER 3<lb/>
            WINTER 2006-07</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0001">
        <head>
          <title>CONTENTS</title>
        </head>
        <table id="contents" rows="7" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Articles</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Young William Blake and the Moravian Tradition of Visionary Art<lb/><hi rend="i">By Marsha Keith Schuchard</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">84</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Jonathan Spilsbury and the Lost Moravian History of William Blake’s Family<lb/><hi rend="i">By Keri Davies</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">100</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particular</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>An Analogue to the “Greatest Men” Passage in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi><lb/><hi rend="i">By Thomas R. Frosch</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">110</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Newsletter</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Events to Celebrate the 250th Anniversary of Blake’s Birth</cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">111</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Western Ontario</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p40-83" n="83"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Marsha Keith Schuchard (keithschuchard@hotmail.com) has recently published <hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried: William Blake and the Sexual Basis of Spiritual Vision</hi> (London: Century-Random House, 2006). She is currently completing a sequel to <hi rend="i">Restoring the Temple of Vision: Cabalistic Freemasonry and Stuart Culture</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 2002), which will cover British and international Masonic developments and their political and cultural ramifications from 1689 to 1750.</p>
        <p>Keri Davies (keri.davies@ntu.ac.uk) is secretary of the Blake Society. He is currently research fellow in the Department of English, Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <p>Thomas R. Frosch (tfrosch@nyc.rr.com) is professor of English at Queens College (CUNY) and is the author of a book on Blake, <hi rend="i">The Awakening of Albion</hi> (Cornell University Press, 1974) and a forthcoming book, <hi rend="i">Shelley and the Romantic Imagination: A Psychological Study</hi> (University of Delaware Press).</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Alexander S. Gourlay</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sarah.jones@rochester.edu TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Alexander S. Gourlay, Department of English, Rhode Island School of Design, 2 College Street, Providence RI 02903-2717<lb/>
Email: agourlay@risd.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham NG11 8NS UK<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals. All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the US, Canada, and Mexico require a $15 per volume postal surcharge for surface delivery, or $20 for airmail. Credit card payment is available. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for information on issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>Manuscripts are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to either of the editors. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a disk, or send your article as an attachment to an email message; please number the pages of electronic submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are usually acceptable.</p>
        <p>International Standard Serial Number: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, American Humanities Index, Arts and Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover: <hi rend="i">Der Christen ABC</hi> (1750), letter O (detail). Ephrata Cloister, Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2007 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb id="p40-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title>ARTICLES</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Young William Blake and the Moravian Tradition of Visionary Art</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Marsha Keith <name>Schuchard</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <q>
The Scripture says that our entire work of the Gospel is to portray Jesus, to paint Him before the eyes, to take the spirit’s stylus and etch—yes, engrave—the image of Jesus in the fleshly tablets of the heart....<lb/>
Zinzendorf, <hi rend="i">Nine Lectures</hi> 81<lb/><lb/>
I would choose <hi rend="i">Fancy</hi> rather than <hi rend="i">Philosophy.</hi> Feeling is ascertained by Experience; Reasoning is hurtful, or makes us lose ourselves.<lb/>
Zinzendorf in Rimius, <hi rend="i">Candid Narrative</hi> 48<lb/><lb/>
Thank God I never was sent to school<lb/>
To be Flogd into following the Style of a Fool<lb/>
                        Blake (E 510)<ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref></q>
          <p>In the months following the publication of Davies and Schuchard, “Recovering the Lost Moravian History of William Blake’s Family,” more material on Blake’s mother and first husband was discovered in the Moravian Church Library, Muswell Hill, London. We learn that Catherine and Thomas Armitage had a child, Thomas, who died in March 1751; thus, William Blake is actually her fourth, not third, child.<ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> We also learn that the Armitages were intimately and practically involved in Moravian affairs and that Peter Boehler, the charismatic leader of the Congregation of the Lamb, made a special effort to help Catherine after her husband died on 19 November 1751.<ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> An intriguing note on 20 March 1753 urges Brother West, an Armitage-Blake family friend, to speak to “Sr. Arm.” (Sister Armitage?) about some financial matter, thus suggesting that she continued her contacts with the Moravians even after she married James Blake in October 1752.<ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Perhaps she withdrew only from the highly selective, time-consuming congregation and not from a less formal association with the Brothers and Sisters. If the John Blake who appealed to Boehler for membership in the congregation was indeed the brother of James Blake, Catherine’s new husband, then William Muir’s claim (made to Thomas Wright) that William Blake’s “parents attended the Moravian Chapel in Fetter Lane” gains new plausibility, for they could have attended the services which were open to the public (Wright 1: 2, Lowery 14-15, 210n57).<ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Wright’s further assertion that “Blake’s father had adopted the doctrines of Swedenborg, whose followers, however, did not separate from other religious bodies till later” gains a new historical context, for the Armitages and Blakes could have known or heard about Swedenborg, who also attended services at Fetter Lane in the 1740s and, even after breaking with the Brethren, continued to have Moravian friends and to utilize Moravian publishers.<ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> While the Moravian-Swedenborgian milieu raises many questions and provokes many speculations concerning William Blake’s spiritual and intellectual development, I will here focus on the possible Moravian influence—especially through his mother—on his early artistic development.<ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref><note id="n0">*All citations from Blake are from <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, newly rev. ed. (New York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988), abbreviated “E”.</note><note id="n1">1. Moravian Archive, Moravian Church House, London: C/36/7/5, p. 10 (1 March 1751). I am grateful to Lorraine Parsons, archivist, for assisting me with research and for sharing the new findings with me.</note><note id="n2">2. Moravian Archive: C/36/14/2 (13 August 1750); C/36/11/6 (12 September, 20 November, 4, 11, and 19 December 1751).</note><note id="n3">3. Moravian Archive: C/36/11/6 (20 March 1753).</note><note id="n4">4. Keri Davies is currently investigating the many references to Blakes in the archives, which suggest—but do not yet prove—that some of James Blake’s relatives were Moravians.</note><note id="n5">5. For Swedenborg’s Moravian experiences in London in 1744-45, see Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">Dream Diary</hi> 12-17, 30-38, 54-58. He wrote more about the London Moravians in his <hi rend="i">Spiritual Diary</hi> (1746-65). Swedenborg used the Moravian publisher John Lewis and, after Lewis’s death in 1758, his Moravian widow Mary Lewis continued to sell Swedenborg’s works. Many of his readers (in England and Sweden) had Moravian parents (such as C. B. Wadström and the Nordenskjöld brothers), while Dr. Husband Messiter, Jacob Duché, and Richard Cosway were interested in Zinzendorf’s teachings.</note><note id="n6">6. For background on the Moravian-Swedenborgian milieu, see Schuchard, “Why Mrs. Blake Cried,” written before my discovery of the Armitage-Blake documents at Muswell Hill, and <hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried</hi> passim.</note></p>
          <p>In 1828 John Thomas Smith recalled that Blake as a child showed “an early stretch of mind, and a strong talent for drawing,” while also demonstrating the ability to compose and perform “singularly beautiful” songs, despite being “entirely unacquainted with the science of music” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 605-06). Two years later, Allan Cunningham wrote that “the love of art came early upon the boy,” who “it seems, was privately encouraged by his mother.” It was “his chief delight to retire to the solitude of his room, and there make drawings, and illustrate these with verses, to be hung up together in his mother’s chamber” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 628, 631-32). From his earliest years, he also revealed his visionary tendency, reporting at age four that he saw God put his forehead to the window and, when he played outdoors, he saw a tree filled with angels and the prophet Ezekiel under a tree. Despite his mother’s worry at such excited claims, she usually protected him from a “thrashing from his honest father” (Gilchrist, quoted in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 19-20). Unfortunately, nothing more emerged about this important maternal influence, leading Alexander Gilchrist to lament in 1863 that after the death of Blake’s mother at age seventy in 1792, “She is a shade to us, 
                        <pb id="p40-85" n="85"/>
alas! In all senses: for of her character, or even her person, no tidings survive” (Gilchrist 1: 95).</p>
          <p>Fortunately, the new Moravian documents allow us to put some flesh on the shade of Catherine Armitage Blake and to recover the religious milieu that rendered her so sympathetic to her son’s development as a visionary artist. In order to bring to the surface this submerged history, it will be necessary to discuss briefly the career of Count Nikolaus Ludwig von Zinzendorf, leader of the renewed Unitas Fratrum, and the spiritual-artistic ethos of the “Sifting Time” (c. 1743-53), a turbulent and creative period of spiritual, sexual, and artistic experimentation.<ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> That Catherine and Thomas Armitage, John Blake, and possibly James Blake were attracted to the Moravian Chapel during the most intense years of the Sifting Time would become relevant to William Blake’s later radical and antinomian beliefs about eroticized spirituality. Through this association, they enjoyed unusual—even unique—access to an international network of ecumenical missionaries, an esoteric tradition of Christian Kabbalism, Hermetic alchemy, and Oriental theosophy, along with a European “high culture” of religious art, music, and poetry. <note id="n7">7. Moravian historians differ on the length of the Sifting Time, but I date it generally from 1743, when Zinzendorf returned from Pennsylvania, to 1753, when a publishing campaign against him began in England. Though some Moravian officials attempted to suppress the radically eroticized spirituality from 1749 on, the themes continued to attract many members in London and elsewhere but were handled with much greater secrecy.</note></p>
          <p>The beliefs and activities of Count Zinzendorf (1700-60) continue to provoke controversy among historians, with most praising him as an innovative theologian and pioneer of religious and racial toleration and some condemning him as a Gnostic heretic and sexual pervert.<ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> Born in Dresden, Saxony, to an aristocratic Lutheran family, he rejected his Pietist mentors’ emphasis on ascetic self-denial and morbid spiritual struggle. In 1722 he welcomed to his estate a band of Moravian refugees, heirs to the Protestant reform movements stimulated by Jan Hus in the fifteenth century and Jan Amos Comenius in the seventeenth. Known as the Unitas Fratrum, the persecuted Moravians preserved “the Hidden Seed” of their irenic spiritual traditions, while they assimilated concepts and symbols developed by Boehmenist and Pietist writers. Under Zinzendorf’s leadership at Herrnhut and other communities, the Moravians developed a passionate <hi rend="i">Herzensreligion</hi> (religion of the heart), which affirmed that Jesus’s <hi rend="i">Menschwerdung</hi> (“humanation”) made him experience the full range of human pain and pleasure and that his self-sacrifice and intense suffering on the cross were sufficient to fully redeem fallen human beings. Thus, pious and self-righteous standards of behavior, which led to hypocrisy and joylessness, were not the proper expressions of Christian worship, for one should utilize one’s <hi rend="i">Herz</hi> (heart) to <hi rend="i">sensate</hi> Jesus’s love and to identify
            <figure n="eccehomo.40.3.bqscan" rend="file"><figTranscr>EGO PRO TE HÆC PAS SUS SUM<lb/>
            TU VERO QUID FECISTI PRO ME</figTranscr><head>1. Domenico Feti, <hi rend="i">Ecce Homo</hi> (seventeenth century).</head><figDesc>Unitätsarchiv, GS 036. Archiv der Brüder-unität, Herrnhut.</figDesc></figure>
with his bloody wounds—from the first wound of circumcision to the final wound in his side. <note id="n8">8. For an introductory biography, see Arthur Freeman. For the most accurate histories of the Sifting Time, see Podmore; Peucker, “Blut”; Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Drawing on his Hebrew studies and discussions with mystical Jews, Zinzendorf identified the German <hi rend="i">Herz</hi> with the Hebrew <hi rend="i">Lev</hi>, the location of emotion and intellect: “In the Old Testament, heart [<hi rend="i">Lev</hi>] is the point of contact with God. ‘Heart’ is more visceral and affective than the Greek word for the personality [<hi rend="i">Psyche</hi>]” (Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 32-33). Moreover,
<q>
Zinzendorf defined “Heart” as the inner person which had five senses as did the outer person. The “Heart,” especially when it has been brought to life by the Holy Spirit, can perceive the Savior objectively and directly. In modern terms we might speak of this as “intuition” or “extrasensory perception.” Zinzendorf’s approach is very similar to Teresa of Avila’s “intellectual vision.” (Arthur Freeman 7)
</q>
In a typically irenic assimilation, Zinzendorf affirmed that the sensually perceptive <hi rend="i">Lev</hi> could be stimulated to “intellectual vision” by meditating upon great religious art, especially the Catholic art produced by Renaissance and Baroque painters. Thus, he argued against the Old Testament prohibition of “graven images,” which influenced the intense iconoclasm of
<pb id="p40-86" n="86"/>
most British Dissenters, and praised the Lutheran rejection of that commandment:
<q>
In the New Testament this commandment is at an end: we have seen. Therefore the Lutherans are right in leaving this commandment out of the catechism, for it no longer has any relation on earth to us. This makes the particular distinction between us and the Reformed, for they combine the ninth and tenth commandments to make room for the commandment forbidding images, which we Lutherans . . . leave out of the Decalogue. We do not hold that a person should make himself no picture or image in the New Testament; a person may make an image, no, he should. (Zinzendorf 81)
</q></p>
          <p>Zinzendorf preached this antiiconoclastic sermon at Fetter Lane to counter the hostile attacks of Dissenting and Methodist critics, who claimed that Moravian artistic practices were crypto-Papist. Thus, he recounted his life-changing experience in which art first opened his heart (<hi rend="i">Herz-Lev</hi>). During his student travels, he visited a gallery in Düsseldorf, which featured Domenico Feti’s <hi rend="i">Ecce Homo</hi>, a poignant painting of Jesus’s suffering under the crown of thorns before his crucifixion. Under the wounded body scrolled a Latin caption: “All this I have suffered for you, but what have you done for me?” (Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 97) (illus. 1). An emotional Zinzendorf recalled that “My blood rushed because I was not able to give much of an answer, and I prayed to my Saviour to make me ride in the comradeship of his suffering with force.” The rushing blood, yearning for forced intimacy, comradeship in suffering—religious passions stimulated by a work of art—intensified the young nobleman’s determination to serve Jesus and to identify with his fully humanized nature, which he came to believe included not only suffering but sexuality. An admirer of Catholic doctrines of confession and forgiveness of sins, he hoped to utilize Catholic artistic traditions to invigorate the ecumenical <hi rend="i">Herzensreligion.</hi></p>
          <p>What made his commitment to religious art so creative and controversial was his injection of Kabbalistic concepts of sacramental
<figure n="theendless.40.3.bqscan" rend="file"><figTranscr><rtl>אין סוף</rtl><lb/>
  THE ENDLESS<lb/><lb/>
  <rtl>כתר</rtl><lb/>
  CROWN<lb/><lb/>
  <rtl>חכמה</rtl> WISDOM<lb/><lb/>
  <rtl>בינה</rtl><lb/>
  INTELLIGENCE<lb/><lb/>
  <rtl>חסד</rtl><lb/>
  LOVE<lb/>
  <rtl>תפארת</rtl><lb/>
  BEAUTY<lb/><lb/>
  <corr><rtl>צדק</rtl></corr><lb/>
  JUSTICE<lb/><lb/>
  <rtl>יסוד</rtl><lb/>
  FOUNDATION<lb/><lb/>
  <rtl>נצח</rtl><lb/>
  FIRMNESS<lb/><lb/>
  <rtl>הוד</rtl><lb/>
  SPLENDOUR<lb/>
  <rtl>מלכות</rtl><lb/>
  KINGDOM</figTranscr><head>2. “Adam Kadmon.”</head><figDesc>Frontispiece of Christian Ginsburg, <hi rend="i">The Essenes: Their History and Doctrines; The Kabbalah: Its Doctrines, Development and Literature</hi> (1863-64; London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1955).</figDesc></figure>
sexuality into his portrayal of the fully incarnated Jesus.<ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> He drew on Jewish mystical beliefs concerning the sexual dynamics of the male-female emanations (the <hi rend="i">Sephiroth</hi>) that bodied forth the Divinity, and transformed the Christian allmale Trinity into a male-female divine family. Thus, he argued that the Holy Spirit is female (a Christianized version of the Kabbalists’ <hi rend="i">Shekhinah</hi>, or female potency within God), and described a <hi rend="i">hieros gamos</hi> in which the Holy Spirit is the wife of God and mother of Jesus, the God-Man (the Kabbalists’ microcosmic <hi rend="i">Adam Kadmon</hi>) (illus. 2). Influenced by Kabbalistic and Jesuit meditation techniques, he urged the Moravians to focus intently on the bloody wounds of the crucified Jesus, which he interpreted in highly eroticized language—i.e., as the centurion’s phallic spear penetrated the vaginal side-wound, new souls were birthed in the gushing blood from this mystical intercourse.<ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Because all human souls are female (<hi rend="i">animas</hi>), both men and women can achieve a psychoerotic consummation with Jesus, the divine bridegroom, as they are enfolded into “the sidehole” (a figurative back-to-the-womb experience). Because Jesus was conceived in a female womb and was born with male genitals, these organs should be honored and utilized sacramentally within human marriage, which reenacts the divine marriage and the sexual reintegration of the God-Man. <note id="n9">9. For Jewish and Kabbalistic influences on Zinzendorf, see Deghaye, Dithmar. He implemented the <hi rend="i">Judenmission</hi>, which appealed to Jews in London, Amsterdam, Hamburg, New York, and other cities, and many Jews attended Moravian services.</note><note id="n10">10. For Moravian sexual theosophy, see Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 185-94 and “Sleeping” 25-51; also Podmore 130-31.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-87" n="87"/>
          <p>In the process, Zinzendorf revived the Renaissance artistic tradition that linked the <hi rend="i">ostentatio vulnerum</hi> (showing forth of the wounds) with the <hi rend="i">ostentatio genitalium</hi> (showing forth of the genitals), a linkage which stressed the full “humanation” of Jesus (Steinberg 3, 16, 18, 57, 83, 373). In 1750 the count predicted that “one of these days” artists will portray the crucified Jesus in a new way, fully nude without a cloth covering his sexual organs; his genitals will again express “his honor and innocence,” for “he is no fallen Adam” (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 137).<ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Though no records of such paintings survive, the portrayals may have been used more privately, within Zinzendorf’s family and inner circle, for in 1748 his niece, Sophie Reuss, made a miniature drawing of a nude Christ on the cross, with no covering cloth and with blood flowing profusely from his five wounds. This religiousartistic belief perhaps found an echo in Blake’s affirmation, “The head Sublime, the heart Pathos, the genitals Beauty, the hands &amp; feet Proportion” (E 37). <note id="n11">11. I am grateful to Paul Peucker, Moravian archivist formerly at Herrnhut and now at Bethlehem, PA, for sending me this important article and for help with identifications.</note></p>
          <p>As a highly educated and basically skeptical intellectual, Zinzendorf spoke about his own struggle to move beyond speculative abstraction to imaginative visualization. He granted that the capacity for vision—“that extraordinary state” when one is “in the Spirit”—was not equally shared by every Brother and Sister:
<q>
This may happen with more or less sense experience, with more or less distinctness, with more or less visibility, and with as many kinds of modifications as the different human temperaments and natural constitutions can allow in one combination or another. One person attains to it more incontestably and powerfully, the other more gently and mildly; but in one moment both attain to this, that in reality and truth one has the Creator of all things . . . standing . . . in the form of one atoning for the whole human race—this individual object stands before the vision of one’s heart, before the eyes of one’s spirit, before one’s inward man. (Zinzendorf 82-83)
</q>
One should be able to say, “I see him as clearly as if he were here; I could paint him right now,” for then “He remains engraved in one’s heart. One has a copy of this deeply impressed there; one lives in it, is changed into the same image” (Zinzendorf 84-85). By focusing intensely and reverently on Jesus’s body and the intercourse between phallic spear and vaginal wound, the Moravian devotee could achieve a state of trance, of psychosexual euphoria, in which he or she “shook with love’s fever” and experienced the “mystical marriage” (Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 219).</p>
          <p>To increase the congregation’s capacity to “see,” “paint,” and “engrave,” Zinzendorf recruited and commissioned artists to create vivid portrayals of Christ’s life and sufferings for the Brothers and Sisters to study while powerful hymns, guitars, violins, and trombones provided background music. At the chapel in Fetter Lane and at Lindsey House in Chelsea (the count’s headquarters), the whitewashed walls were covered with paintings of biblical and allegorical scenes, as well as portrayals of Moravian history and international missionary work. Adding to the mystical atmosphere were watercolored transparencies, through which lanterns and candles projected luminous visions into the congregation rooms. Given the often bloody and sometimes sensual symbolism of the paintings and hymns, these scenes would provoke much controversy and hostile attacks from critics. However, the passionate letter of Catherine Armitage, which reveals her deep immersion in the spiritual-erotic themes of the Sifting Time, suggests that Blake’s mother responded positively to the Moravians’ stress on the role of art and music in the development of visionary spirituality.<ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> As she encouraged the artistic productions of her imaginative son, she was perhaps implementing Zinzendorf’s peculiar but progressive notions of “infant education.” <note id="n12">12. Moravian Archive: C/36/2/159.</note></p>
          <p>Zinzendorf admired the “pansophic” educational theories of Comenius, whose portrait was displayed at Lindsey House, and he implemented them in his voluminous sermons, songs, and lessons for children (Meyer 94-105). Comenius stressed the innocence of childhood, the importance of parental affection, the healthy effects of outdoor free play, and, most importantly, the use of pictorial images to inculcate religious sentiments. What was surprisingly modern or Freudian in the count’s pedagogy was his belief that even embryos and infants were receptive to his sex, blood, and wounds theology and that “the process of religious education and socialization began <hi rend="i">in utero</hi>” (Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 178-83; “Blood” 192-93). Within the “embryo choir,” the pregnant mother was pampered and counselled; after birth, she and her infant became part of the “suckling choir,” and joyous love feasts were held for them. In order to sensate the “assembled image” of the God-Man in one’s heart, mother and child must “view, picture, and meditate about the saviour from head to foot.” These injunctions were sung by the mother in the home and by the children in catechistical hymns. In a Moravian drawing from 1754, Zinzendorf’s two-year-old daughter is shown meditating upon a painting of the crucified Jesus (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 170).<ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref><note id="n13">13. Because Elizabeth von Zinzendorf was born in 1740, the 1754 portrayal probably had a pedagogical purpose for current infant education.</note></p>
          <p>Zinzendorf was evidently familiar with sixteenth-century paintings that portrayed the infant Christ with an erect penis and giving a flirtatious “chin-chuck” to his adoring mother, and there were hints of such themes in his lyrics for children.<ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> When Blake wrote his provocative “Cradle Song,” he seemed to draw on the Moravians’ maternal and infant sexual psychology.
<pb id="p40-88" n="88"/>
In Blake’s song, the mother strokes the soft limbs, the babe’s face and heart respond with smiles and peaceful beat, and she recognizes the erotic pleasure stimulated in the infant:
<q>
Sweet Babe in thy face<lb/>
Soft desires I can trace<lb/>
Secret joys &amp; secret smiles<lb/>
[Such as burning youth beguiles <hi rend="i">del.</hi>] (E 468, 852)
</q><note id="n14">14. The occasional erection of the infant penis is a normal and natural phenomenon, but many Renaissance artists stressed it as proof of the full “humanation” of Jesus. Steinberg (3, 10, 76-79 and plates 83-88) gives examples such as Alvise Vivarini’s <hi rend="i">Madonna and Child with Saints</hi> (c. 1500), Perino del Vaga’s <hi rend="i">Holy Family</hi> (c. 1520), Perugino’s <hi rend="i">Madonna and Child</hi> (c. 1500), Correggio’s <hi rend="i">Madonna of the Basket</hi> (c. 1523-25), etc.</note></p>
          <p>Though Blake deleted the last line, he went even further in his paean to free love, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, where Oothoon proclaims:
<q>
Take thy bliss O Man!<lb/>
And sweet shall be thy taste &amp; sweet thy infant joys renew!<lb/><lb/>
Infancy, fearless, lustful, happy! nestling for delight<lb/>
In laps of pleasure .... (E 49)
</q>
Blake’s “laps of pleasure” takes on a new connotation when placed in a context of Zinzendorf’s pedagogical instruction that the school of the female Holy Spirit was “a family school, that is, a school on the lap, in the arms of the eternal Mother.” In German, the same word (<hi rend="i">Schoss</hi>) is used for lap and womb, and the mother’s “school” for her infant took on a spiritualerotic connotation, which was vividly expressed in hymns for the embryo and suckling choirs. Blake’s lustful, nestling infant recalls the sung injunction to each mother, “That your child lay naked and bare on your lap” (Atwood, <hi rend="i">Community</hi> 178-79). Following Comenius’s teaching, the Moravians advocated maternal breast feeding rather than farming infants out to wet nurses. Blake’s mother may well have heard Peter Boehler’s talks to the married Sisters, when he stressed that “suckling” must be done with “gracious ideas as a Divine Worship.”<ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Decades later, Blake would lament that so many selfish parents reject this beneficial practice: “The child springs from the womb . . . / The young bosom is cold for lack of mother’s nourishment, &amp; milk / Is cut off from the weeping mouth” (E 285). <note id="n15">15. Moravian Archive: C/36/7/3 (28 May 1749). Boehler was the main “marriage counsellor” for the Brothers and Sisters, and he spoke frankly about intercourse, orgasm, conception, etc., in a surprisingly modern way.</note></p>
          <p>Determined to make the sensating of Jesus a joyous experience, Zinzendorf advocated that parents and children—of every age, class, and background—should participate in a rich Renaissance-Baroque culture of painting, poetry, and music. Remembering his own unhappy childhood, when he was sent away to boarding school and instructed by puritanical pedants, he urged the Moravians to home-school their children. Preaching at Fetter Lane in 1753, he instructed the parents to build a home “for a Christian family life which will make possible the ideal church in the home with proper religious training of children”; moreover, “parental training is the natural method as compared with institutional training which is artificial” (Meyer 138, 142). Unusually for the time, he believed that an affectionate mother was the best teacher for a young child, and that she should inculcate a love of art and music to stir the visionary senses of the <hi rend="i">Herz-Lev.</hi></p>
          <p>From infancy on, a Moravian child was exposed to religious art and script, including the German artistic technique of <hi rend="i">Frakturschriften</hi>, the ornamental breaking or fracturing of letters, which Zinzendorf and Boehler had observed when they visited the Boehmenist-Rosicrucian community at Ephrata, Pennsylvania (Sachse 1: 354-64, 401-02). In the Ephratans’ mystical calligraphy, the scribe represented the breaking of the artist’s self-will and opening to union with Christ by breaking the letters and surrounding them with swirling ornamentation, which created the “sprouting of a florid paradise” (Bach 182-84). The “illuminations” were usually “drawn with pen and ink, and then embellished with vigorous colors.” The actual practice of <hi rend="i">Fraktur</hi>, with its intense concentration and visualization, could produce mystical states, for “each scribe has the birthing process in himself after rebirth.” In the magnificently illuminated <hi rend="i">Ephrata ABC</hi> book, Sisters Anastasia and Efigenia drew capital letters
<q>
constructed with a series of swinging, voluptuous curves, all interstices of the letters filled with additional scrollings and floral forms. A passionate devotion to the work caused the individual calligrapher to further elaborate all possible areas with minute stipplings and dottings, in the manner of steel engraving. Significant symbolistic motifs also entered into the enrichment of the capitals. (Frances Lichten, quoted in Alderfer 125-26)
</q>
Alderfer adds that
<q>
some of them, such as the <hi rend="i">A</hi> and the <hi rend="i">O</hi>, make use of the human form to portray a provocative symbolism. . . . The <hi rend="i">O</hi> suggests Anastasia’s vision of Beissel [the community leader] being crowned with the Holy Spirit . . .; it may also reflect her sublimated love for him. . . . The borders are astonishing .... (126) (illus. 3)
</q></p>
          <p>Despite their opposition to the Ephratans’ policy of celibacy (they believed that earthly marriage would prevent divine marriage with Sophia), the Moravians borrowed liberally from the sect’s mystical art and symbolism (Stoudt 94-96). Like Conrad Beissel, Zinzendorf believed that “art, literature, and music were not [to be] regarded as separate disciplines; they united in one common spiritual experience” (Alderfer 125). Thus, a comment by the Pennsylvanian art historian John Stoudt becomes suggestive; referring to the <hi rend="i">Ephrata ABC</hi> book, he observes that the frontispiece “is a drawing much like those of William Blake” (Stoudt 138) (illus. 4 and 5). At this time in London, the walls at Fetter Lane and Lindsey House were hung with papers and canvases of Moravian poetry and hymns, ornamented with painted letters (often in elaborate German Gothic script), whose twisting and curving gave them “a florid quality” (Podmore 133, 151-52; Atwood,
<pb id="p40-89" n="89"/>
“Blood” 171) (illus. 6). Paintings and drawings were often surrounded with <hi rend="i">Spruchbänder</hi>, sayings or aphorisms that illustrated the text (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 166). Catherine Armitage Blake would have seen these elaborate and charming “illuminations,” which also decorated private rooms. The Moravians’ love of religious art provoked iconoclastic Dissenters to criticize “our innocent pictures and crucifixes in
<figure n="40.3.der.bqscan" rend="file"><figTranscr>O</figTranscr><head>3. <hi rend="i">Der Christen ABC</hi> (1750), letter O. Ephrata Cloister, Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission.</head></figure>
our Rooms” (Podmore 152). It was probably no coincidence that Catherine’s young son William loved to make drawings and illustrate them with verses to be “hung up together in his mother’s chamber.”</p>
          <p>At Fetter Lane, Catherine Armitage was also exposed to the Jesuit emblem tradition of “iconomysticism.” Thomas Armitage had written his application letter to John Cennick, a
<pb id="p40-90" n="90"/>
            <figure n="ChristenABC.frontispiece.40.3.bqscan" rend="file">
              <figTranscr>Dies ist mein lieber<lb/>
                Sohn, an dem ich<lb/>
                wohlgefallen habe<lb/><lb/>
                WER DA GLAUBET U[ND] GETAUFFT WIRD DER WIRD SELIG WERDEN X<lb/>
                WER ABER NICHT GLAUBET DER WIRD VERDAMMT WERDEN<lb/><lb/>
                Folget mir nach, ich bin das A, u[nd] das O, der<lb/>
                Anfang u[nd] das Ende, der Erste u[nd] der Letzte.</figTranscr><head>4. <hi rend="i">Der Christen ABC</hi> (1750), frontispiece.</head><figDesc>Ephrata Cloister, Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission.</figDesc></figure>
talented poet and composer, who often discussed Hermann Hugo’s <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria</hi>, a seventeenth-century Jesuit emblem book, with the Brothers and Sisters (Cennick 24). Cennick and Zinzendorf agreed with Comenius’s advocacy of emblem books, which can “explain the whole of pansophy” and which function like the “signatures” of Paracelsus and Boehme (Sadler 28, 42-43, 201, 282). From descriptions in the Congregation Diaries of “our little childlike Hieroglyphicks,” “many childlike emblematical Doings, with Candles, Leaf-work,” and “emblematical Pictures, suddenly shifting &amp; successively presenting themselves to the Eye,” it is clear that Cennick encouraged the implementation of Hugo’s theories.<ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> According to Mario Praz, Jesuit emblematics follows “the tracks of hieroglyphics” and “aims at establishing a mode of expression which only a few may understand; in a word, an esoteric language”—and thus relevant to Zinzendorf’s frequent use of an encoded secret language (Praz 1: 155). At the same time, emblematics “aims at being a way of making ethical and religious truths accessible to all, even to the illiterate and to children, through the lure of pictures.” While Catherine Blake home-schooled her children, did she introduce them to Hugo’s “little books of emblems,” which offer to the eyes “charming <hi rend="i">Zinnepoppen</hi>,
            <figure n="s-inn.b.p2-3" rend="db" id="s-inn.b.illbk.02"><figTranscr>SONGS<lb/>
              of<lb/>
              Innocence<lb/><lb/>
              1789<lb/><lb/>
              The Author &amp; Printer WBlake</figTranscr><head>5. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789), copy B, title page.</head><figDesc>Library of Congress.</figDesc></figure>
or dolls for the spirit . . . the toys of a bewitched kindergarten” (Praz 1: 136)? <note id="n16">16. Moravian Archive: C/37/7/3 (30 December 1749; 19, 24 May 1751).</note></p>
          <p>Cennick, who greatly admired the Moravian paintings and engravings he observed in Germany and England, would have recognized the relevance of Jesuit emblematic techniques to Zinzendorf’s artistic-pedagogic goals. As Praz observes, the “didactic properties” of emblems were “calculated to further the Ignatian technique of the application of the senses, to help the imagination to picture to itself in the minutest detail circumstances of religious import”:
<q>
They made the supernatural accessible to all by materializing it. Rather than mortifying the senses in order to concentrate all energies in an ineffable tension of the spirit, according to the purgative way of the mystics, the Jesuits wanted every sense to be keyed up to the pitch of its capacity, so as to conspire together to create a psychological state pliant to the command of God. (Praz 1: 156)
</q>
Similarly, Moravian artists were instructed to arouse and utilize all the senses, so the viewer would move beyond mere understanding and would fully participate in, fully <hi rend="i">sensate</hi>, Jesus’s experiences from crucifixion to resurrection (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 169).</p>
          <p>The fine engravings in <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria</hi>, by Boëce van Bolsvert, drew on the Jesuits’ spiritual-sensual interpretation of the techniques of engraving. As Praz observes,
<pb id="p40-91" n="91"/>
            <figure n="lief.40.3.bqscan" rend="file">
              <figTranscr>Lief heim<lb/>
                Mein Seidelein<lb/>
                Lief heim ins Seitelein<lb/><lb/>
                Christian Gottfried Beidel. Ann: MDCCXLVIII. di 5.Febr: Ætat: 30.</figTranscr><head>6. “Lief heim ins Seitelein.”</head><figDesc>Unitätsarchiv, R.20.E.36.12. Archiv der Brüder-unität, Herrnhut.</figDesc></figure><q>
The fixity of the emblematic picture was infinitely suggestive; the beholder little by little let his imagination be eaten into as a plate is by an acid. The picture eventually became animated with an intense, hallucinatory life, independent of the page. The eyes were not alone in perceiving it; the depicted objects were invested with body, scent, and sound .... (Praz 1: 156)
</q></p>
          <p>In Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, he employed a similar engraving metaphor of acid eating into plate. He may also have drawn on the Moravians’ iconomystical and antinomian sense of erotic visualization, which reversed the orthodox Christian denigration of the senses and sexuality:
<q>
. . . the whole creation will be consumed, and appear infinite, and holy whereas it now appears finite &amp; corrupt.<lb/>
This will come to pass by an improvement of sensual enjoyment.<lb/>
But first the notion that man has a body distinct from his soul, is to be expunged; this I shall do, by printing in the infernal method, by corrosives, which in Hell are salutary and medicinal, melting apparent surfaces away, and displaying the infinite which is hid.<lb/>
If the doors of perception were cleansed every thing would appear to man as it is: infinite. (E 39)
</q></p>
          <p>Praz’s description of iconomysticism reveals why it was such an effective vehicle for Moravian concepts of the mystical marriage, for this Jesuit “cult was wonderfully suited to a society accustomed to picture human love under the guise of the Alexandrian Eros” (1: 132). Hugo’s great popularity arose from his use of the Song of Solomon and the Psalms,
<q>
texts whose metaphors inevitably suggested emblems with the Oriental lusciousness of their appeal to the senses. Tears and sighs, . . . voluptuous swoonings and sweet and subtle pains, what a part they play in the <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria</hi>! In a nocturnal garden, heavy with perfume, Anima feels her knees give way under her, . . . while from her bared breast burning ejaculations <hi rend="i">Ah! Utinam! Heu!</hi> shoot like arrows towards the ears of God. . . . Suddenly the garden is all a-bubble with springs. . . . Love darts from his mouth a quivering tongue of flame, and, caressed by that heat, Anima exudes huge drops from head to foot. . . . What wild races through that nocturnal garden heavy with perfumes! (Praz 1: 133-34)
</q>
Zinzendorf similarly compared the Moravians’ visualization of Christ to the bride’s in the Song of Songs. Quoting the lines “This is my beloved,” he stressed that her lover is actually Christ, and “there He is painted piece by piece” (Zinzendorf 81). In May 1749 at Fetter Lane, his birthday was celebrated with “illuminated Pictures” which showed “Fountains springing” and the count “solacing himself in a Garden where the Fountains spouted Blood” (Stead 300).</p>
          <pb id="p40-92" n="92"/>
          <p>Hugo’s most famous illustration, “Anima Trying to Soar on Wings, but Held Back by a Weight Tied to Her Foot,” perhaps finds an echo in Blake’s tiny emblem book, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> (Hugo 334) (illus. 7). On the plate designated V, Blake drew a figure soaring with hands raised, while the inscription reads, “More! More! Is the cry of a mistaken soul, less than All cannot satisfy Man” (E 31). On the plate headed VI, he drew a naked man chained and fettered by his ankles, with the text, “If any could desire what he is incapable of possessing, despair must be his eternal lot” (E 31) (illus. 8). Hugo’s Jesuit work had been expurgated and published in English translations by Protestant writers, such as Frances Quarles and Edmund Arwaker, who de-emphasized the pictorial “iconomysticism” and added more moralistic and puritanical literary comments (R. Freeman 114, 133, 140-42, 207). But for Cennick and Zinzendorf, it was the Jesuitic stress on intense visualization and the arousal of spiritualerotic desire that was the most important aspect of Hugo’s mystical emblems.</p>
          <p>In 1806 Blake’s friend Benjamin Heath Malkin reported that the artist, “very early in life, had the ordinary opportunities
            <figure n="pia.40.3.bqscan" rend="file"><figTranscr>Coarctor autem e duobus; desiderium habens dissolui<lb/>
              et esse cum Christo. Ad Philip. 1.<lb/>
              39.</figTranscr><head>7. Hermann Hugo, <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria</hi>, Editio 6. emendata (1624; Antuerpia: apud Henricum Aertssens, 1634), plate 39.</head><figDesc>Engraving by Boëce van Bolsvert. Robert W. Woodruff Library, Emory University.</figDesc></figure>
of seeing pictures in the houses of noblemen and gentlemen, and in the king’s palaces,” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 562) which perhaps included Lindsey House and other residences of Zinzendorf’s aristocratic friends. Since these visits took place before his tenth birthday in 1767, Blake must have been taken by a parent, probably his mother, who would have been aware of the vivid paintings at Lindsey House and Fetter Lane, as well as their pedagogical role.<ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> When Catherine and Thomas Armitage raised their son Thomas, they would have known Brother Christopher Henry Müller, who had “much discourse with
            <figure n="nnr.l.p7-b8" rend="db" id="nnr.l.illbk.07"><figTranscr>VI<lb/>
              If any could de-<lb/>
              -sire what he is in-<lb/>
              -capable of posses-<lb/>
              sing. despair must<lb/>
              be his eternal<lb/>
              lot</figTranscr><head>8. William Blake, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> VI (1788), copy L.</head><figDesc>Pierpont Morgan Library and William Blake Archive.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p40-93" n="93"/>
Brother Boehler,” Catherine’s protective friend.<ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> A German immigrant, who had earlier ministered to the black slaves in Georgia, Müller had “the Care of the Children’s Oeconomy” in London, in which charge “he acted with great Faithfulness.” Significantly, part of this care was instruction in art and engraving. <note id="n17">17. In <hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried</hi> 144-45, 270-71, I discuss the Moravian-Swedenborgian interests of Dr. Husband Messiter and Richard Cosway, who were both associated with Henry Pars’s Drawing School, where Blake studied from age ten to fourteen. During Blake’s apprenticeship and studies at the Royal Academy, he possibly knew the young Moravian artist and architect Benjamin Henry Latrobe, whose radical politics eventually led to his emigration to America (in 1795). Talbot Hamlin, who was unaware of the mutual Moravian background of Latrobe and Blake, notes the unusual Blakean qualities in the former’s watercolor paintings (Hamlin 246, 540-41).</note><note id="n18">18. Moravian Archive: C/36/7/5 (1 March 1751). I am grateful to the Reverend Kai Dose for sending me the full account of Müller in the Congregation Diary.</note></p>
          <p>Having studied at Herrnhaag, the most radical center of Sifting Time theosophy, Müller was familiar with the daring experiments in sexual, ritual, poetic, and artistic innovation which occurred there (and which led to the Moravians’ expulsion).<ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> When Zinzendorf moved to London in 1749, Müller took over “the oeconomical Care of Bloomsbury-House,” while continuing his artistic and engraving work. According to his obituary, “The last Piece of Work he did in his own Art, (wherein he was very ingenious) was ingraving a small Picture of the Ordinary [Zinzendorf].” Having become sick with “a malignant fever,” Müller “was kissed home into the Sidehole” on 9 March 1751, apparently at the same time that “Thomas, the Child of Br + Sisr Armitage” died. Their shared funeral notice reports that the Armitage child “was buried in the Ground near Bloomsbury,” while Müller was carried from Bloomsbury “and deposited in the Earth at Chelsea,” thus becoming the first interment in the new Moravian cemetery. According to the German church historian Kai Dose, who is researching Müller’s life, he was a talented artist whose surviving portraits and engravings are worth renewed interest.<ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref><note id="n19">19. On the “poetic world” of “spiritualized sexuality” at Herrnhaag, see Erbe. The radical leader of the “youth movement” at Herrnhaag was Zinzendorf’s charismatic son, Christian Renatus, who in 1749 moved to London, where he was revered by the Fetter Lane congregation, who considered his death in 1752 at age twenty-four a great tragedy.</note><note id="n20">20. Another Moravian artist, Johann Jakob Müller, spent a brief period in London in the 1740s, where he opposed “daubers of reason” and “naturalists”; he then moved to Herrnhut, where he became “director of the Wound and Nailhole Painting Academy” (Peucker, “Painter”).</note></p>
          <p>Because of the sale of Lindsey House in 1774 and the Nazi bombing of the Fetter Lane Chapel in 1941, the great Zinzendorfian collection of paintings and engravings was dispersed or destroyed (Kroyer 50-63). However, from pre-1941 descriptions and surviving paintings at the Brethren’s other centers, we can learn more about the Moravian artists who moved in the Armitage-Blake milieu in the 1750s and 60s. More famous than Müller was Abraham Louis Brandt (1717-97), a talented Franco-Swiss engraver and painter (“Brandt”; “Lebenslauf”). He was the brother of Louise Hutton, who had earlier been a member of the “French Prophets” before marrying the English minister James Hutton and converting to Moravianism (Benham 95, 194-96, 375). She shared with her brother an interest in Boehmenist and mystical writers, and he expressed these themes in the religious paintings he produced for Zinzendorf in England, before moving on to a Moravian community in Russia in 1764. Less famous was John Cooke, a Catholic artist from Leghorn (called “the Italian”), who acted as ship’s mate on Moravian voyages to America, where his joyous temperament, violin playing, and artistic productions made him a beloved visitor (Hamilton 171-72, Nelson et al. 19, 48). After participating in the Fetter Lane Society in the 1740s, Cooke moved on to the “Pilgrim Congregation” in Germany.<ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Even more intriguing—and more relevant to Blake—was the Dantzig-born Johan Valentin Haidt (1700-80), whose significant role in the London art world is receiving new attention from scholars (Nelson, <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi>). As we shall see, a Moravian art historian suggests that Blake was influenced by one of Haidt’s paintings. <note id="n21">21. Moravian Archive: Box A2, Pilgrim House Diary (1743-48), p. 8; C/36/5/1, p. 4.</note></p>
          <p>Originally apprenticed as a goldsmith, the young Haidt determined to follow his real love, religious and historical painting. After traveling through Europe to study the Old Masters, he moved to London in 1724, married a Huguenot woman, and, while practising his craft, opened an “academy” in his home, where he and his students studied “live nudes.” His comment about the importance of the nude model “may be the earliest such reference in English art” (Nelson, “Haidt’s Theory”). He eventually befriended George Michael Moser (1704-83), a Swiss-born gold-chaser, who shared his yearning to participate in higher art. The two men “seemed to have started a predecessor to the Royal Academy of Arts in Haidt’s house,” which influenced Moser’s later role as a founding member of the Royal Academy. When William Blake applied to study at the Royal Academy in 1779, it would be Moser, “the venerable Keeper,” who evaluated his work and oversaw his subsequent studies (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 49-51). However, it was Haidt’s role as a Moravian artist—known as “the painting Preacher”—which is most suggestive when exploring the Blake family’s attitudes towards art.</p>
          <p>Attracted by the passionate preaching he heard at Fetter Lane in 1738-39, Haidt experienced a “heart-warming” similar to that of John Wesley, who was intensely attracted to the Moravians at that time. In 1740 Haidt traveled to Herrnhaag, where he achieved “a mystical experience which he remembered all his life” (Nelson, <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi> 9-13). Though Wesley had been rejected by the Germans as a <hi rend="i">homo perturbatus</hi>, Haidt was eventually accepted into the congregation. Moving between Germany and England, he began the painting of large symbolic works with life-size figures, sometimes influenced by the Jews he observed at Moravian services. Deeply infused with the “blood and wounds” theosophy, Haidt’s emphasis on the role of art in the spiritual development of children inspired much of the creative and imaginative teaching in Moravian families. Catherine Armitage could have heard about Haidt’s impressive paintings from John Cennick, who studied and admired those exhibited in Moravian halls in Germany (Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 138). In 1749, when Zinzendorf moved to London, he commissioned Haidt to paint dozens of portrayals of events in Jesus’s life and in Moravian history, to be displayed
<pb id="p40-94" n="94"/>
            <figure n="haidt.40.3.bqscan" rend="file"><head>9. Johann Valentin Haidt, <hi rend="i">The Cruxifiction.</hi></head><figDesc>Collection of the Moravian Historical Society, Nazareth, PA.</figDesc></figure>
at Fetter Lane and Lindsey House. In 1754 Haidt emigrated to Bethlehem, Pennsylvania, where he became known as America’s “first religious painter,” but his artistic teachings continued to influence parents and children in London.<ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref><note id="n22">22. Haidt took some of his London paintings with him to Pennsylvania, and they provide a clue to the content and style of the pictures that were destroyed by the 1941 bombing of Fetter Lane.</note></p>
          <p>According to Haidt, young students should first master drawing with a firm outline before attempting painting, and they should study classical sculpture and copper engravings of the Old Masters. Though Blake’s mother is credited as the primary inspiration for his artistic interests, his father eventually supported William’s artistic bent: “The love of designing and sketching grew upon him, and he desired anxiously to be an artist” (Cunningham, in Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 628). James Blake began to encourage William’s drawing, bought plaster casts of classical sculpture, and funded his purchases of engravings of Old Masters. Possibly more important for James, who initially intended his son for the hosier’s shop, was Haidt’s insistence on the importance of an independent religious spirit in the young artist, for talent “is a gift from God, and whoever is sure of that and convinced of it, he can paint.” Moreover, “each one knows best what his inclinations are, and he should follow them.” Zinzendorf preached and Haidt taught that engraving was a form of “high art,” which required sophisticated and erudite training in order to capture the soul and beauty of drawings and paintings. It also had a spiritual resonance, for the image of Jesus should be engraved in one’s <hi rend="i">Herz/Lev.</hi> When the adolescent Blake, with his parents’ blessing, decided to apprentice himself as an engraver, he may have absorbed such lofty ambitions for his craft.</p>
          <p>Haidt shared Zinzendorf’s reverence for Mary Magdalene, and they maintained the medieval tradition that she was a prostitute and adulteress, until Jesus cast out the seven devils, who plagued her with illicit erotic desires. They also seemed familiar with a controversial theme in that tradition—i.e., “all things that she had willingly done before in the service of the flesh she now in sorrow turned to the service of her Lord” (Phipps 139). At Fetter Lane, Zinzendorf preached that Christ
<pb id="p40-95" n="95"/>
            <figure id="but495.1.wc.01" rend="db" n="but495.1.1.wc"><figTranscr>inv<lb/>
              WB 1800<lb/>
              John XIX c. 23 &amp; 24 v</figTranscr><head>10. William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Soldiers Casting Lots for Christ’s Garments</hi> (1800).</head><figDesc>Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</figDesc></figure>
occupies himself “with the harlot who had seven devils,” for “He is the rightful Husband of . . . even the most detestible [sic] prostitute” (Zinzendorf 4, 15). Moravian hymns included many references to the Magadalene, which stress her intense attraction to Jesus, sometimes with hints of Jewish sexual mysticism: for example, “Comes <hi rend="i">Mary</hi>, by Love’s Power drawn, With other two still weeping, To see where <hi rend="i">Rabbi</hi> lies” (Hutton 64). During the most radical period at Herrnhaag, Zinzendorf praised the high-spirited, eroticized youth culture as “<hi rend="i">So siindermassig spielerisch, so Maria Magdalenerlich</hi> (so moderately sinfully playful, so Mary Magdalenish)” (Erbe 121). Blake’s mother may have heard (and sung) an especially provocative hymn, in which Mary is called “The Lamb’s Sinner Bride,” who plants a “Thousand Magde’len kisses” on Jesus’s body: “Lamb and Saviour, / Take from me, from Head to Feet all over; / All thy Skin, each Pore and Hair, / Take of my Salutes to Share” (<hi rend="i">Collection of Hymns</hi> 2: 344). Such lines led Zinzendorf’s critics to charge that he implied a romantic relationship between Jesus and the Magdalene. Even worse, they claimed that his erotic descriptions of her were “intended to justify the Count’s strolling about with Anna Nitschman,” leader of the Sisters and his frequent traveling companion, whom they accused of having an adulterous relationship with him (Rimius, <hi rend="i">Supplement</hi> xxiv).</p>
          <p>Given this context, Haidt’s painting <hi rend="i">The Crucifixion</hi> seems to express Zinzendorf’s version of the Jesus-Magdalene relationship, for he portrayed her sensuously with long yellow hair and emotionally attached to Jesus. Vernon Nelson, who was unaware of the Moravian association of Blake’s mother, observes that in Haidt’s painting “the pose of the soldiers gambling for Jesus’ cloak should be compared to that in Blake’s portrayal of the Crucifixion” (Nelson, <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi> 21; Butlin #495) (illus. 9 and 10).<ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Nelson points out that in another Haidt painting, <hi rend="i">At the Foot of the Cross</hi>, the Magdalene kisses Jesus’s feet, thus revealing the artist’s immersion in the Sifting Time ethos, with its eroticization of spiritual relationships (Nelson, <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi> 21) (illus. 11).<ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> In Blake’s picture <hi rend="i">Mary Magdalene Washing Christ’s Feet</hi>, she is actually kissing his feet (Butlin #488) (illus. 12); Martin Butlin notes that in Blake’s painting, <hi rend="i">Christ the Mediator: Christ Pleading before the Father for St. Mary Magdalene</hi>, the subject is not biblical but possibly from John Bunyan; however, “the apparent application of the theme to the Magdalene is Blake’s own” (Butlin #429). It is suggestive that Blake produced these paintings during a period (c. 1800-07) of friendly contact with two liberal Moravians, the artist Jonathan Spilsbury and the poet James Montgomery, who both participated in services at Fetter Lane.<ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> Could they have taken Blake to his mother’s former church, where Haidt’s paintings were still exhibited?<ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref><note id="n23">23. Unfortunately, the photo in Nelson’s <hi rend="i">Haidt</hi> is misnumbered, for the description of plate 35 should refer to a painting which includes the gambling soldiers (not reproduced in the catalogue), which is owned by the Moravian Historical Society in Nazareth, PA. I am grateful to the archivist, Mark Turdo, for sending me a photo of the correct picture.</note><note id="n24">24. For other Moravian paintings of Mary Magdalene kissing and embracing Jesus’s feet, see Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 135, 142.</note><note id="n25">25. Blake possibly knew Spilsbury when both exhibited at the Royal Academy in the 1780s, and he described his conversation with the Moravian artist in 1804 (E 755). For Spilsbury’s career, see Young. On Blake’s association with Jonathan Spilsbury and its Moravian significance, see Keri Davies, “Jonathan Spilsbury and the Lost Moravian History of William Blake’s Family” [in this issue—Eds.]. Blake may have met Montgomery during the radical writer’s visits to the London Corresponding Society in the 1790s. Though we have no definite evidence for their acquaintance, Bentley notes that Robert Cromek’s letter to Montgomery in 1807 “suggests a connexion between Blake and James Montgomery” and “implies an easy and personal contact between the two men”; see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 234-35, 262, 277. For Montgomery’s career and Moravian association, see Montgomery, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> and Everett. I provide more information on the Oriental interests of Spilsbury, Montgomery, and Blake in <hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried</hi> 322-29.</note><note id="n26">26. The striking similarities between Blake’s “tempera series” of “the Life of Christ” for Thomas Butts and the surviving description of Haidt’s thirty-four paintings of the “<hi rend="i">sacramentlichen Handlungen des Heylands</hi>” (Jesus’s life-story from conception to resurrection) is worth further study. Haidt’s series was discussed and commissioned at “a conference in Bloomsbury, 2 October 1749,” when Blake’s mother was a participant in Moravian affairs. After the sale of Lindsey House in 1774, many of these paintings were moved to the Fetter Lane Chapel, where they survived until the 1941 bombing. See Peucker, “Kreuzbilder” 172-73; Kroyer 52; Bindman 121-31.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-96" n="96"/>
          <figure n="footcross.40.3.bqscan" rend="file">
            <figTranscr>INRI</figTranscr>
            <head>11. Johann Valentin Haidt, <hi rend="i">At the Foot of the Cross.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Collection of the Moravian Historical Society, Nazareth, PA.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Recent biographers of the engraver and caricaturist James Gillray (1756-1815), who was raised and educated as a Moravian, have inaccurately characterized the Unitas Fratrum as “an austere and unattractive religious sect,” who “deplored all joy and pleasure” and who provided children with a “grim” upbringing (Godfrey and Hallett 12). However, Moravian notions of child rearing were actually and unusually benevolent. In 1766, when the Moravian minister James Hutton was questioned by Lord Shelburne—“Pray, how do your children go on? Do they take after their parents?”—he answered emphatically, “Yes, God be praised!” Hutton then described the Moravian pedagogical methods with children:
<q>
Ingenuous and affectionate treatment, without force and violence, we find has a blessed effect on their education. We once thought otherwise; but we succeeded better by gentleness. We do all we can to prevent that servile imitation and hypocrisy which severity always or, at least, is most likely, to produce. O! My Lord, could you but see the heartiness of our children, you would be touched. (Benham 417)
</q></p>
          <p>As she home-schooled her children, Blake’s mother seems to have adopted this notion of educational “gentleness,” for she was “a tender and sympathetic mother, more inclined to overlook faults than to punish them” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 5). For Moravians, the “heartiness” of their children was a resonant, multileveled quality; <hi rend="i">Herzlichkeit</hi> meant passionate, enthusiastic, and imaginative visualization of and engagement with the body of the God-Man. Unaware of the erotic-artistic emphasis of Zinzendorf’s pedagogy, the Gillray scholar Draper Hill lamented that “at the threshold of understanding,” Moravian four-year-olds “were pushed to terrifying heights of introspection” (Hill 8). But it was more the <hi rend="i">terribilità</hi> of Michelangelo (who was revered by Zinzendorf and his artists); it was a transforming, energizing, imaginative passion to which the children were “pushed.” When Isaac Disraeli later observed that “Blake often breaks into the ‘<hi rend="i">terribil via</hi>’ of Michael Angelo,” he meant <hi rend="i">terribilità</hi> (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 329fn).</p>
          <p>The Moravian-educated poet and art critic, James Montgomery, attributed his own youthful “heartiness” to the vivid paintings
<pb id="p40-97" n="97"/>
and powerful music he studied at the Moravian school in Fulneck, Yorkshire, in 1777-87, while his missionary parents served (and died) in the West Indies. The schoolboys assembled and stood for a few minutes in front of “a superb painting of a dead Christ,” rendered more dramatic by the illuminating rays of a strategically placed lantern (Montgomery, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> 1: 31, 59). In his dormitory, Montgomery meditated upon a “huge painting of the Entombment of Christ, by the old Moravian
            <figure n="but488.1.1.wc" rend="db" id="but488.1.wc.01"><figTranscr>inv<lb/>
              WB</figTranscr><head>12. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Mary Magdalene Washing Christ’s Feet</hi> (c. 1805).</head><figDesc>Philadelphia Museum of Art: Gift of Mrs. William Thomas Tonner, 1964.</figDesc></figure>
Brandt,” as well as others which depicted striking events in the history of the Brotherhood. To heighten the children’s passionate response, their concentration on the pictures was intensified by “the full-toned piano, accompanied by a French bugle,” which broke the silence with profound music. As a young adult, Montgomery left the Moravians and pursued a career as a radical writer and publisher, but he later returned to them and remembered with some nostalgia his early schooling:
<pb id="p40-98" n="98"/><q>
There is no system of religion, which I have yet seen, which, taking all in all, has half the charm for a young, a warm, and a feeling heart, as that professed by these people. I <hi rend="i">once</hi> believed; I <hi rend="i">once</hi> enjoyed its blessings; I <hi rend="i">once</hi> was happy! . . . The hymns of the Moravians are full of ardent expressions, tender complaints, and animated prayers; these were my delight. As soon as I could write and spell, I imitated them, and before I was thirteen I had filled a little volume with sacred poems. (Montgomery, <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> 1: 46)
</q></p>
          <p>Was it a similar early influence that inspired the adolescent Blake to write poems of spritual and romantic yearning? Bentley notes that in Blake’s precocious love poems, the “sexual suggestiveness is astonishing” (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 260-61). The adult Montgomery was an early admirer of Blake’s “wild &amp; wonderful genius,” especially in his illustrations to Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808), which critics scorned for their “libidinous” combination of carnality with spirituality (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 260-61; Essick and Paley 23-25). Montgomery probably knew that Zinzendorf had also been criticized for expressing a “<hi rend="i">Fleischlische Spiritualität</hi>” (fleshly spirituality) (Deghaye 167n41). Blake, in turn, praised Montgomery’s publication, <hi rend="i">The Wanderer of Switzerland, and Other Poems</hi> (1806), assuring him that it will command the applause of “all Lovers of the Higher Kinds of Poetry” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">BR</hi>[2] 236). In this volume, Montgomery praised the Moravians’ renewed missionary and abolitionist efforts, and he made a provocatively Blakean allusion to the “Daughters of Albion,” whom he exhorted to “Weep!” (in his autobiographical account of a frustrated, youthful love affair) (Montgomery, <hi rend="i">Wanderer</hi> 11, 167, 135, 147).</p>
          <p>Fortunately, a new generation of Moravian scholars is lifting up the blanket of darkness that was thrown over the Sifting Time by conservative church historians after Zinzendorfs death in 1760.<ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> As they shed new light on the historical realities of that fascinating and controversial period, they make it possible to uncover the equally suppressed artistic history of the Sifting Time, whose painters, engravers, and poets may have influenced Catherine Armitage Blake and her visionary son William. Thus, it will be fitting to conclude with a tribute to Blake’s mother by quoting lines from a Moravian hymn, the “Te Matrem,” which Zinzendorf believed was especially effective at instilling “heartiness” in children.<ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> Praising the creative and inspirational power of the Divine Mother, wife of God and mother of the God-Man, the congregation joyfully sang to “Thee, that Mother of Christ his Bride”:
<q>
Thou didst inspire the Martyrs tongues,<lb/>
In the last Gasp to raise their songs,<lb/>
Thou dost impel the four <hi rend="i">Zoa</hi>,<lb/>
Who singing rest not night nor day . . .<lb/>
Thou Mother of God’s Children all,<lb/>
Thou Sapience archetypal! . . .<lb/>
That thou the Prophets dost ordain,<lb/>
And gifts and wonders to them deign.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Collection of Hymns</hi> 2: 297-98)
</q><note id="n27">27. Vernon Nelson began the recovery of Haidt’s artistic career, while the revisionist works of Colin Podmore, Craig Atwood, and Paul Peucker shed new light on the theology and art of the Sifting Time. Christiane Dithmar contributes important new Jewish material relevant to the psychoerotic themes of the “mystical marriage.”</note><note id="n28">28. For the once central but then censored role of the “Te Matrem” hymn, see Atwood, “Mother.”</note></p>
          <p>In 1797 Blake gave the title <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> to his visionary, prophetic epic, which begins with the words, “The Song of the Aged Mother,” whose verses herald “the day of Intellectual Battle”:
<q>
Four Mighty Ones are in every Man; a Perfect Unity<lb/>
Cannot Exist. but from the Universal Brotherhood of Eden<lb/>
The Universal Man. To Whom be Glory Evermore Amen<lb/>
(E 300)
</q>
Around 1807, at a time of friendly Moravian contacts, he changed the title to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and “those Living Creatures” (<hi rend="i">zoa</hi>, Greek plural) subsequently became “the Four Eternal Senses of Man”—senses contained within the earthly man and the God-Man (Albion) (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Stranger</hi> 198, 310). Did Blake remember the reference to “the four <hi rend="i">Zoa</hi>” in the Moravian hymn to the Divine Mother, while he revised his phantasmagoric tale of psychoerotic disintegration and reintegration within the human and divine worlds?<ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref> This and similar questions, provoked by ongoing discoveries in the international archives of the Unitas Fratrum, suggest that new answers and new perspectives will emerge, as we continue to explore the esoteric, erotic, and artistic underworld of Moravian “heartiness” and <hi rend="i">terribilità.</hi><note id="n29">29. Justin Van Kleeck points to the previously unnoticed apostrophe between the “a” and “s” of the “Zoas” (i.e., “Zoa’s”) on Blake’s title page (Van Kleeck 39). This may reflect a mnemonic slip from the “four <hi rend="i">Zoa</hi>” of the Moravian hymn, or his uncertainty about how to anglicize the Greek plural.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-99" n="99"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Alderfer, Everett Gordon. <hi rend="i">The Ephrata Commune: An Early American Counterculture.</hi> Pittsburgh: U of Pittsburgh P, 1985.</p>
            <p>Atwood, Craig. “Blood, Sex, and Death: Life and Liturgy in Zinzendorf’s Bethlehem.” Diss. Princeton Theological Seminary, 1995.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Community of the Cross: Moravian Piety in Colonial Bethlehem.</hi> University Park: Pennsylvania State UP, 2004.</p>
            <p>—. “The Mother of God’s People: The Adoration of the Holy Spirit in the Eighteenth-Century Brüdergemeine.” <hi rend="i">Church History</hi> 68 (1999): 886-909.</p>
            <p>—. “Sleeping in the Arms of Jesus: Sanctifying Sexuality in the Eighteenth-Century Moravian Church.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Sexuality</hi> 8 (1997): 25-51.</p>
            <p>Atwood, Craig, and Peter Vogt, eds. <hi rend="i">The Distinctiveness of Moravian Culture: Essays and Documents in Moravian History in Honor of Vernon H. Nelson on His Seventieth Birthday.</hi> Nazareth: Moravian Historical Society, 2003.</p>
            <p>Bach, Jeff. <hi rend="i">Voices of the Turtledoves: The Sacred World of Ephrata.</hi> University Park: Pennsylvania State UP, 2003.</p>
            <p>Benham, Daniel. <hi rend="i">Memoirs of James Hutton.</hi> London: Hamilton, Adams &amp; Co., 1856.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> 2nd ed. New Haven: Yale UP, 2004. Cited as <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2).</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Stranger from Paradise: A Biography of William Blake.</hi> New Haven: Yale UP, 2001.</p>
            <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi> Oxford: Phaidon, 1977.</p>
            <p>“Brandt, Abraham Ludwig.” <hi rend="i">Saur Allgemeines Künstlerlexikon.</hi> München: K. G. Saur, 1996. 13: 632.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. New Haven: Yale UP, 1981.</p>
            <p>Cennick, John. <hi rend="i">The Life of Mr. John Cennick.</hi> 2nd ed. Bristol: Printed for the Author, 1745.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">A Collection of Hymns of the Children of God in All Ages . . . Designed Chiefly for the Use of the Congregations in Union with the Brethren’s Church.</hi> London, 1754.</p>
            <p>Davies, Keri, and Marsha Keith Schuchard. “Recovering the Lost Moravian History of William Blake’s Family.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 38.1 (summer 2004): 36-43.</p>
            <p>Deghaye, Pierre. <hi rend="i">La doctrine ésotérique de Zinzendorf.</hi> Paris: Klincksieck, 1969.</p>
            <p>Dithmar, Christiane. <hi rend="i">Zinzendorfs nonkonformistische Haltung zum Judentum.</hi> Heidelberg: C. Winter, 2000.</p>
            <p>Ellis, Samuel. <hi rend="i">Life, Times, and Character of James Montgomery.</hi> London: Jackson, Walford and Hodder, 1864.</p>
            <p>Erbe, Hans-Walter. “Herrnhaag: Eine religiöse Kommunität im 18. Jahrhundert.” <hi rend="i">Unitas Fratrum</hi> 23/24 (1988): 13-224.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> London: Oxford UP, 1975.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N., and Morton D. Paley. <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave <hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake: A Study with Facsimile.</hi> London: Scolar P, 1982.</p>
            <p>Freeman, Arthur. <hi rend="i">An Ecumenical Theology of the Heart: The Theology of Count Nicholas Ludwig von Zinzendorf.</hi> Bethlehem: Moravian Church in America, 1998.</p>
            <p>Freeman, Rosemary. <hi rend="i">English Emblem Books.</hi> 1948. New York: Octagon, 1966.</p>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. Rev. ed. 1880. New York: Phaeton, 1969.</p>
            <p>Godfrey, Richard, and Mark Hallett. <hi rend="i">James Gillray: The Art of Caricature.</hi> London: Tate Publishing, 2001.</p>
            <p>Hamilton, Kenneth, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">The Bethlehem Diary, Vol. I, 1742-1744.</hi> Bethlehem: Archives of the Moravian Church, 1971.</p>
            <p>Hamlin, Talbot. <hi rend="i">Benjamin Henry Latrobe.</hi> New York: Oxford UP, 1955.</p>
            <p>Hill, Draper. <hi rend="i">Fashionable Contrasts: Caricatures by James Gillray.</hi> London: Phaidon, 1966.</p>
            <p>Hugo, Hermannus. <hi rend="i">Pia Desideria.</hi> 1624. Antwerp: Henry Aertssens, 1632.</p>
            <p>[Hutton, James, ed.] <hi rend="i">A Collection of Hymns: Consisting Chiefly of Translations from the German, Part III. Hymnbook of the Moravian Brethren.</hi> 2nd ed. London: Printed for James Hutton, Bookseller in Fetter Lane, 1749.</p>
            <p>Kroyer, Peter. <hi rend="i">The Story of Lindsey House, Chelsea.</hi> London: Country Life, 1956.</p>
            <p>“Lebenslauf des Bruders Abraham Louis Brandt, heimgegangen den 23. Juli 1797 in Sarepta.” <hi rend="i">Nachrichten aus der Brüdergemeine</hi> (1857): 49-56.</p>
            <p>Lowery, Margaret. <hi rend="i">Windows of the Morning: A Critical Study of William Blake’s</hi> Poetical Sketches, <hi rend="i">1783.</hi> New Haven: Yale UP, 1940.</p>
            <p>Meyer, Henry. <hi rend="i">Child Nature and Nurture according to Nicolaus Ludwig von Zinzendorf.</hi> New York: Abingdon, 1928.</p>
            <p>Montgomery, James. <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James Montgomery.</hi> Ed. John Holland and James Everett. 7 vols. London: Longmans, 1854-56.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Wanderer of Switzerland, and Other Poems.</hi> London: Verner and Hood, 1806.</p>
            <p>Nelson, Vernon. <hi rend="i">Johann Valentin Haidt.</hi> Williamsburg: Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Folk Art Collection, 1966.</p>
            <p>—. “John Valentine Haidt’s Theory of Painting.” <hi rend="i">Transactions of the Moravian Historical Society</hi> 23 (1984): 71-78.</p>
            <p>Nelson, Vernon, Otto Dreydoppel, Jr., and Doris Rohland Yob, eds. <hi rend="i">The Bethlehem Diary, Vol. II, January 1, 1744-May 31, 1745.</hi> Trans. Kenneth Hamilton and Lothar Madeheim. Bethlehem: Archives of the Moravian Church, 2001.</p>
            <p>Peucker, Paul. “‘Blut auf unsre grüne Bändchen’: Die Sichtungszeit in der Herrnhuter Brüdergemeine.” <hi rend="i">Unitas Fratrum</hi> 49/50 (2002): 41-94.</p>
            <p>—. “Kreuzbilder und Wundenmalerei: Form und Funktion der Malkunst in der Herrnhuter Brüdergemeine um 1750.” <hi rend="i">Unitas Fratrum</hi> 55/56 (2005): 125-74.</p>
            <p>—. “A Painter of Christ’s Wounds: Johann Langguth’s Birthday Poem for Johann Jakob Müller.” Atwood and Vogt 19-33.</p>
            <p>Phipps, William E. <hi rend="i">The Sexuality of Jesus.</hi> Cleveland: Pilgrim P, 1996.</p>
            <p>Podmore, Colin. <hi rend="i">The Moravian Church in England, 1728-1760.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1998.</p>
            <p>Praz, Mario. <hi rend="i">Studies in Seventeenth-Century Imagery.</hi> 2 vols. London: Warburg Institute, 1939.</p>
            <p>Rimius, Henry. <hi rend="i">A Candid Narrative of the Rise and Progress of the Herrnhuters.</hi> London: A. Linde, 1753.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">A Supplement to the Candid Narrative of the Rise and Progress of the Herrnhuters.</hi> London: A. Linde, 1755.</p>
            <pb id="p40-100" n="100"/>
            <p>Sachse, Julius. <hi rend="i">The German Sectarians of Pennsylvania, 1742-1800.</hi> 2 vols. 1899-1900. New York: AMS, 1971.</p>
            <p>Sadler, John. <hi rend="i">J. A. Comenius and the Concept of Universal Education.</hi> London: Allen and Unwin, 1966.</p>
            <p>Schuchard, Marsha Keith. “Why Mrs. Blake Cried: Swedenborg, Blake, and the Sexual Basis of Spiritual Vision.” <hi rend="i">Esoterica: The Journal of Esoteric Studies</hi> 2 (2000): 45-93. &lt;http://www.esoteric.msu.edu&gt;.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried: William Blake and the Sexual Basis of Spiritual Vision.</hi> London: Century-Random House, 2006.</p>
            <p>Sessler, Jacob John. <hi rend="i">Communal Pietism among Early American Moravians.</hi> New York: Henry Holt, 1933.</p>
            <p>Stead, Geoffrey and Margaret. <hi rend="i">The Exotic Plant: A History of the Moravian Church in Britain, 1742-2000.</hi> Peterborough: Epworth, 2003.</p>
            <p>Steinberg, Leo. <hi rend="i">The Sexuality of Christ in Renaissance Art and In Modern Oblivion.</hi> 2nd ed. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1996.</p>
            <p>Stoudt, John Joseph. <hi rend="i">Pennsylvania Folk-Art.</hi> Allentown: Schlechter’s, 1948.</p>
            <p>Swedenborg, Emanuel. <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Diary.</hi> Trans. Alfred Acton. 1962. London: Swedenborg Society, 1977.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">Swedenborg’s Dream Diary.</hi> Ed. Lars Bergquist, trans. Anders Hallengren. West Chester: Swedenborg Foundation, 2001.</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck, Justin. “Blake’s Four . . . ‘Zoa’s’?” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 38-43.</p>
            <p>Wright, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. 1929. New York: Burt Franklin, 1969.</p>
            <p>Young, Ruth. <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter: Jonathan and Maria Spilsbury, 1737-1812: 1777-1820.</hi> London: Epworth, 1952.</p>
            <p>Zinzendorf, Nikolaus Ludwig von. <hi rend="i">Nine Public Lectures on Important Subjects in Religion Preached in Fetter Lane Chapel in London in the Year 1746.</hi> Trans. and ed. George Forell. Iowa City: U of Iowa P, 1973.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Jonathan Spilsbury and the Lost Moravian History of William Blake’s Family</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Keri <name>Davies</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The engraver, painter, and miniaturist Jonathan Spilsbury (1737-1812), who had strong links to the Moravian church, was most likely, as I shall demonstrate, an associate of William Blake.<ref target="n00" type="note">*</ref> This casts a new light on Blake’s possible involvement in the London Moravian community, with which he had connections through his mother’s early adherence to that faith. The following discussion will take in the circumstances of Spilsbury’s links to the African Chapel in Peter Street, Soho, resemblances to Moravian custom and culture in the reportage of Blake’s death, and the parallels between Blake’s and Spilsbury’s lives in forging a living in the engraving trade.</p>
          <p>Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> contains three references to a person or persons surnamed “Spilsbury.” On 28 June 1802, Charlotte Collins wrote to William Hayley at Felpham in Sussex about “a new Family settled at Midhurst by the name of <hi rend="u">Spilsbury</hi>—the Gentleman has devoted his Time to the study of animals, and he has lately made a drawing of M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Poyntz’s <hi rend="u">Prize Bull</hi>.”<ref target="n30" type="note">1</ref> The following year, on 21 March 1803, John Flaxman wrote to Hayley: “I am sorry for M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Spilsbury’s illness.”<ref target="n31" type="note">2</ref> And on 14 October 1806, Hayley’s young friend E. G. Marsh wrote to him inquiring “I wonder, whether M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Spilsbury has ever seen Warwick castle, because there is a painting of two lions there, which pleased me . . . beyond anything of the kind I had ever seen.”<ref target="n32" type="note">3</ref><note id="n00">*My research into the Moravian connections of William Blake’s family was funded by the Arts and Humanities Research Council. I am most grateful to Lorraine Parsons, archivist, for permission to examine and publish documents in the Moravian Church Library and Archive, Muswell Hill, London. Colin Davies, Will Easton, Keith Schuchard, Angus Whitehead, David Worrall, and Charlotte Yeldham contributed helpfully to my thinking about Blake and Spilsbury.</note><note id="n30">1. G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale University Press) 134, hereafter abbreviated “<hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2)”.</note><note id="n31">2. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 150.</note><note id="n32">3. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 231.</note></p>
          <p>Edgar Ashe Spilsbury (1780-1828?) was an animal painter who exhibited at the Royal Academy and the British Institution and, because of the nature of the references, it seems likely that he is the Spilsbury referred to.<ref target="n33" type="note">4</ref> He was the son of the noted “chymist” Francis Spilsbury (1736-93) of Soho Square (author of the learned treatise <hi rend="i">Free Thoughts on Quacks</hi>), and the younger half-brother to Francis Brockhill 
                        <pb id="p40-101" n="101"/>
Spilsbury (b. 1761), naval surgeon and amateur landscape painter.<ref target="n34" type="note">5</ref> Edgar Ashe Spilsbury was a friend and sometime protégé of William Hayley.<ref target="n35" type="note">6</ref><note id="n33">4. See J. C. Wood, <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of British Animal Painters</hi> (Leigh-on-Sea: F. Lewis, 1973) 61.</note><note id="n34">
                            5. Francis Spilsbury was the author of <hi rend="i">Free Thoughts on Quacks and Their Medicines: Occasioned by the Death of Dr. Goldsmith and Mr. Scawen; or, A Candid and Ingenuous Inquiry into the Merits and Dangers Imputed to Advertised Remedies</hi> (London: Printed for J. Wilkie, No. 171, St. Paul’s Church-yard, and Mr. Davenhill, No. 30, Cornhill, 1776). A “second edition, revised and corrected” appeared in 1777. See Peter Isaac, “Charles Elliot and Spilsbury’s Antiscorbutic Drops,” <hi rend="i">Pharmaceutical Historian</hi> 27.4 (December 1997): 46-48.
                            <p>Francis Brockhill Spilsbury was the author of <hi rend="i">Account of a Voyage to the Western Coast of Africa: Performed by His Majesty’s Sloop Favourite, in the Year 1805: Being a Journal of the Events Which Happened to That Vessel, from the Time of Her Leaving England till Her Capture by the French, and the Return of the Author in a Cartel</hi> (London: Printed for Richard Phillips by J. G. Barnard, 1807); <hi rend="i">Advice to Those Who Are Afflicted with the Venereal Disease</hi> (London, 1789); <hi rend="i">The Art of Etching and Aqua Tinting, Strictly Laid Down by the Most Approved Masters: Sufficiently Enabling Amateurs in Drawing to Transmit Their Works to Posterity; or, as Amusements among Their Circle of Friends</hi> (London: Printed for J. Barker, 1794); <hi rend="i">Every Lady and Gentleman Their Own Dentist, As Far As the Operations Will Allow, Containing the Natural History of the Adult Teeth and Their Diseases with the Most Approved Methods of Prevention and Cure, etc.</hi> (London: Barker, 1791); and <hi rend="i">Picturesque Scenery in the Holy Land and Syria: Delineated during the Campaigns of 1799 and 1800</hi> (London: Edward Orme, 1803).</p></note><note id="n35">6. Ruth Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter: Jonathan and Maria Spilsbury</hi> (London: Epworth Press, 1952) 5.</note></p>
          <p>Bentley notes, however, that the Midhurst Spilsbury “does not seem to be the professional artist to whom Blake refers familiarly in his letter to Hayley of 28 Sept 1804.”<ref target="n36" type="note">7</ref> The relevant passage reads as follows:
<q>
I send Washingtons 2<hi rend="s">d</hi> Vol:— 5 Numbers of Fuselis Shakspeare &amp; two Vol’s with a Letter from M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Spilsbury with whom I accidentally met in the Strand. he says that he relinquishd Painting as a Profession. for which I think he is to be applauded. but I concieve that he may be a much better Painter if he practises secretly &amp; for amusement than he could ever be if employd in the drudgery of fashionable dawbing for a poor pittance of money in return for the sacrifice of Art &amp; Genius. he says he never will leave to Practise the Art because he loves it &amp; This Alone will pay its labour by Success if not of money yet of True Art. which is All—(E 755)<ref target="n37" type="note">8</ref><note id="n36">7. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 150fn.</note><note id="n37">8. Letter 50, “To William Hayley Esq<hi rend="s">re</hi> Felpham,” 28 September 1804. Citations from William Blake’s writings follow the text established by David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (New York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988), hereafter abbreviated “E”.</note></q>
The “M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Spilsbury” of Blake’s letter is clearly not Edgar Ashe Spilsbury, who had not given up painting, but equally clearly he must be somebody who was well acquainted both with Blake and with Hayley. Our perception of Blake’s life, with Gilchrist (drawing on the testimony of Linnell and Palmer) and Tatham as our primary sources, tends to see Blake as a lonely and isolated figure until taken up in later life by Linnell, Varley, and the “Ancients.”<ref target="n38" type="note">9</ref> This meeting in the Strand with Mr. Spilsbury is evidence, if any were needed, that Blake had a wide social acquaintanceship long before he met Linnell. 
                        <note id="n38">9. Prefiguring the familiar fin de siècle trope of the artist’s tragic solitude, on which see, for instance, Frank Kermode, <hi rend="i">Romantic Image</hi> (London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1957), especially his chapter 1, “The Artist in Isolation.”</note></p>
          <p>Spilsbury cousins included Jonathan Spilsbury (1737-1812), a portraitist and mezzotint engraver. Spilsbury is itself an unusual surname, and there are few artists of that name.<ref target="n39" type="note">10</ref> I therefore suggest that Jonathan was the Mr. Spilsbury whom Blake “accidentally met in the Strand,” and that, in view of the recent discovery of the involvement of William Blake’s mother with the Moravian church, it could prove of interest to consider the life and career of Jonathan Spilsbury, another engraver with a Moravian affiliation.<ref target="n40" type="note">11</ref><note id="n39">10. According to Daryl Lloyd, Richard Webber and Paul Longley, <hi rend="i">Surname Profiler: Surnames as a Quantitative Resource</hi> &lt;http://www.spatial-literacy.org/UCLnames&gt;, the surname Spilsbury ranked 5861st among British surnames in 1881, with just 21 occurrences per million names. It occurred most frequently in Worcestershire. (By 1998, it had fallen to 6124th, with 22 occurrences per million names.) The US Census Bureau &lt;http://www.census.gov&gt; records no occurrences of the surname Spilsbury in the 1990 US census.</note><note id="n40">11. On Blake’s mother and her membership in the Moravian church, see Keri Davies and Marsha Keith Schuchard, “Recovering the Lost Moravian History of William Blake’s Family,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 38.1 (summer 2004): 36-43.</note></p>
          <p>Jonathan Spilsbury came of a Worcestershire family; there were Spilsburys in the West Country in the fifteenth century.<ref target="n41" type="note">12</ref> He was born at Worcester on 2 February 1737. His mother apprenticed him (9 September 1750) to a cousin, George Spilsbury, a noted “japanner” (manufacturer of lacquer ware) of Birmingham, to whom he was bound for seven years.<ref target="n42" type="note">13</ref> When the seven years were ended, he found his way to London, where he entered Thomas Hudson’s studio soon after the young Joshua Reynolds had quarreled with Hudson.<ref target="n43" type="note">14</ref> Jonathan Spilsbury entered the Royal Academy Schools on 25 March 1776, aged 39. He had exhibited three works at the Society of Artists between 1763 and 1771, and was to show thirteen paintings at the Royal Academy between 1776 and 1784.<ref target="n44" type="note">15</ref> Academy students were then admitted for six years, so Spilsbury’s friendship with Blake (admitted 8 October 1779) probably dates from their overlapping time at the R.A. Schools.<ref target="n45" type="note">16</ref><note id="n41">12. Ruth Young, <hi rend="i">Mrs. Chapman’s Portrait: A Beauty of Bath of the Eighteenth Century</hi> (Bath: George Gregory Bookstore, 1926) 96.</note><note id="n42">13. Ian Maxted, <hi rend="i">The London Book Trades, 1775-1800: A Preliminary Checklist of Members</hi> (Folkestone: Dawson, 1977) 211.</note><note id="n43">14. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter 6.</hi></note><note id="n44">15. Algernon Graves, <hi rend="i">The Royal Academy of Arts: A Complete Dictionary of Contributors and Their Work from Its Foundation in 1769 to 1904</hi>, 8 vols. (London: Henry Graves, 1905-06) 7: 221. Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy on five occasions between 1780 and 1808.</note><note id="n45">16. Spilsbury’s admission to the R.A. Schools is recorded by Daphne Foskett, <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of British Miniature Painters</hi>, 2 vols. (London: Faber, 1972) 1: 528. Foskett suggests that Spilsbury may have been a pupil of the miniature painter Thomas Worlidge (1700-66). Since Worlidge is associated both with Birmingham and with Bath, as well as London, there is some plausibility in this claim. For Blake at the R.A. Schools, see <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 18-19.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-102" n="102"/>
          <p>Although he worked in London, Jonathan did not cut himself off from the West Country. He lived a good deal in Bath and in Bristol, where he painted a portrait of Charles Wesley.<ref target="n46" type="note">17</ref> And it was in Bristol that Spilsbury met Rebecca Chapman (b. 1748), whom he married after a ten years’ courtship.<ref target="n47" type="note">18</ref> Rebecca was the eldest daughter of the Rev. Dr. Walter Chapman (1711-91), once Wesley’s colleague in Pembroke College, Oxford, and later prebendary of Bristol Cathedral, a well-known evangelical clergyman in the family home of Bath.<ref target="n48" type="note">19</ref> Walter Chapman’s mother, Mary, seems to have been a friend of Wesley’s brother Samuel. <note id="n46">17. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 9.</note><note id="n47">18. Young, <hi rend="i">Mrs. Chapman’s Portrait</hi> 95.</note><note id="n48">19. A letter from Walter Chapman to John Wesley dated 27 February 1737/38 is printed in Frank Baker, ed., <hi rend="i">The Works of John Wesley, Vol. 25: Letters I, 1721-1739</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980) 531.</note></p>
          <p>Even before his marriage, Spilsbury had sought membership in the Moravian church, and he was later to engrave portraits of the Moravian “Labourers” (as the church’s fulltime workers were called) John Gambold (illus. 1) and Benjamin La Trobe, the latter after a drawing by Rebecca.<ref target="n49" type="note">20</ref> In a letter of 116 closely written lines dated 2 October 1769, Spilsbury transcribed for Rebecca “a little discourse delivered at Bedford Oct. 5 N.S. 1751 by the Rt. Rev. late Ordinary of the Brethrens Churches.”<ref target="n50" type="note">21</ref> To this discourse, he added a postscript:
<q>
I have said nothing upon ye subject of marriage, and you know my reason for being silent on that head. However, I cannot forbear wishing that if ever you change your state, it may be with one who would receive you penniless with as much pleasure as with a million of money, and as to yourself that it may be an act of faith done in ye assurance of God’s grace and favour.<ref target="n51" type="note">22</ref></q><note id="n49">20. The mezzotint portrait of John Gambold, engraved by Jonathan Spilsbury after Abraham Louis Brandt, was published in 1771; a mezzotint portrait of Benjamin La Trobe, engraved by Jonathan Spilsbury after R. Spilsbury (presumably his wife Rebecca), was published in 1781.</note><note id="n50">21. The “Ordinary” was one of the terms by which the Moravians in England referred to their leader, Nicolaus Ludwig, Count Zinzendorf.</note><note id="n51">22. Quoted in Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 10. Alexander Gilchrist, in his <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, “Pictor Ignotus,”</hi> 2 vols. (London: Macmillan, 1863), comments of Catherine Blake: “Uncomplainingly and helpfully, she shared the low and rugged fortunes which over-originality insured as his unvarying lot in life” (1: 38).</note></p>
          <p>They married in 1775, and in 1777 Mrs. Spilsbury bore her husband twins. The boy died immediately, but the girl, Rebecca Maria Ann, generally known as Maria, survived.<ref target="n52" type="note">23</ref> The child’s gifts as an artist were early recognized; indeed, the fame of Maria Spilsbury would surpass her father’s.<ref target="n53" type="note">24</ref> There was also a younger son, Jonathan Robert Henry, baptized 7 December 1779 at St. Marylebone.<ref target="n54" type="note">25</ref><note id="n52">23. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 10.</note><note id="n53">24. Graves 7: 221-22 lists 47 paintings exhibited by Miss Mary Spilsbury between 1792 and 1808.</note><note id="n54">25. Data from Charlotte Yeldham, “Spilsbury, (Rebecca) Maria Ann (1777-1820),” <hi rend="i">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004), subsequently cited as <hi rend="i">Oxford DNB.</hi> I presume the child, Jonathan Robert Henry, died in infancy, since he disappears from the documentary record. Susan Sloman, in “Spilsbury, Jonathan (bap. 1737, d. 1812),” <hi rend="i">Oxford DNB</hi>, corrects the inaccurate information provided by some well-regarded reference sources such as Raymond Lister’s <hi rend="i">Prints and Printmaking: A Dictionary and Handbook of the Art in Nineteenth-Century Britain</hi>, which gives Jonathan Spilsbury’s dates as “<hi rend="i">f.</hi> 1766-1823.” I have provided some additional data relating to Spilsbury’s brothers and half-brother.</note></p>
          <p>It seems to have become evident to Spilsbury that he would not find success in the London art world, and 1789 saw him in Ireland, acting as art master to the daughters of Mrs. Tighe, Wesley’s friend, on her estate, Rossana, County Wicklow.<ref target="n55" type="note">26</ref> It was perhaps through the Wesleys or Mrs. Tighe that the Spilsburys became acquainted with Walter Taylor of Portswood Green, Southampton.<ref target="n56" type="note">27</ref> Certainly, by 1798 Jonathan and his daughter were staying at Bevers Hill, Southampton, where they were in daily touch with the Taylor family.<ref target="n57" type="note">28</ref> Walter Taylor of Portswood Green died in 1803, but the friendship formed between his family and the Spilsburys continued, and by 1807, his son, John Taylor, had become engaged to Maria.<ref target="n58" type="note">29</ref> They were married in 1808; Maria was 31 and her husband 23.<ref target="n59" type="note">30</ref><note id="n55">26. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 13.</note><note id="n56">27. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 19.</note><note id="n57">28. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 20.</note><note id="n58">29. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 25.</note><note id="n59">30. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 28.</note></p>
          <p>Maria found some success as a portraitist in Southampton, and Hayley’s friend Richard Vernon Sadleir, a local worthy, sat to her in 1798, responding to the portrait with a set of verses.<ref target="n60" type="note">31</ref> The verses bear the title “Palemon’s expostulations to his Looking Glass—inscribed to Miss Spilsbury which drew his Picture in the seventy six year of his age”:
<q>
Cease, faithless Mirror, to persuade<lb/>
That I am old and coarsely made;<lb/>
.......................................<lb/>
Maria, if thy pencil thus can give<lb/>
Beyond this poor Existence to survive,<lb/>
Oh! Could my Verse thy Lovely Form shew forth,<lb/>
Thy Manners gentle and thy modest Worth,<lb/>
Melodious numbers should transmit thy Name<lb/>
To shine distinguished in the Rolls of Fame!<ref target="n61" type="note">32</ref></q>
Thus we find the Spilsburys on the fringes of William Hayley’s circle, just three years before Blake was induced to settle at Felpham under Hayley’s patronage. <note id="n60">31. Richard Vernon Sadleir (1722-1810) was a subscriber to Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> in 1808 (“Richard Vernor [sic] Sadleir, Esq. Southampton”). On Sadleir’s friendship with Hayley, see Morchard Bishop, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Hayley: The Life, Works, and Friendships of William Hayley</hi> (London: Gollancz, 1951) passim.</note><note id="n61">32. Quoted in Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 18-19. The poem so resembles Hayley’s own occasional verse that one suspects he may have had a hand in it.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-103" n="103"/>
          <figure n="spilsbury.40.3.bqscan" rend="file">
            <figTranscr>A. L. Brandt pinxt<lb/>
              J. Spilsbury fecit<lb/>
              The Revd. JOHN GAMBOLD, M.A.<lb/>
              Formerly Minister of Stanton Harcourt, late one of the Bishops of the Unitas Fra:<lb/>
              Publish’d as the Act directs, Decr. 10, 1771, by J. West, No. 10, Nevils Court, Fetter Lane</figTranscr>
            <head>1. Mezzotint by Jonathan Spilsbury: “The Rev<hi rend="s">d</hi>. John Gambold, M.A. Formerly Minister of Stanton Harcourt, late one of the Bishops of the Unitas Fra: A. L. Brandt pinx<hi rend="s">t</hi>. J. Spilsbury fecit.</head>
            <figDesc>Publish’d as the Act directs, Dec<hi rend="s">r</hi>. 10, 1771, by J. West, No. 10, Nevils Court, Fetter Lane.” John Gambold, 1711-71, an Oxford Methodist, was ordained in 1733, becoming vicar of Stanton Harcourt, Oxfordshire, where John Wesley’s sister Kezia was a member of his household for two years. In 1742 he resigned his living to join the Moravians, of whose community he was consecrated a bishop in 1754. Courtesy of the Moravian Church Archive and Library, Moravian Church House, Muswell Hill, London.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p40-104" n="104"/>
          <p>As early as 1761, Jonathan had been engraving in mezzotint, mostly copies of portraits by other hands.<ref target="n62" type="note">33</ref> As his daughter’s fame grew, he seems to have given up painting entirely (like the Mr. Spilsbury that Blake met in 1804) and concentrated on mezzotint engraving while supporting his daughter’s career. Like Blake a decade later, by the 1770s Spilsbury was finding the London engraving market a more promising career move than chancing his luck exclusively in painting. <note id="n62">33. Spilsbury’s engraved portraits are listed in John Chaloner Smith, <hi rend="i">British Mezzotinto Portraits: Being a Descriptive Catalogue of These Engravings from the Introduction of the Art to the Early Part of the Present Century</hi>, 4 vols. in 5 (London: H. Sotheran &amp; Co., 1878-83); Charles E. Russell, <hi rend="i">English Mezzotint Portraits and Their States, from the Invention of Mezzotinting until the Early Part of the Nineteenth Century</hi>, 2 vols. (London: Halton &amp; Truscott Smith; New York: Minton, Balch, 1926); [Freeman Marius O’Donoghue], <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Engraved British Portraits Preserved in the Department of Prints and Drawings in the British Museum</hi>, 6 vols. (London: Printed by Order of the Trustees, 1908-25).</note></p>
          <p>Jonathan Spilsbury and his brother John were the children of Thomas Spilsbury (1681-1741) of Worcester, whose second wife was Mary Wright (1718?-73) of Broadwas.<ref target="n63" type="note">34</ref> John (1739-69) during his short life kept a print shop in Covent Garden, where he sold the work of both his elder brother (chiefly mezzotint portraits) and himself (principally maps). The identities of the two brothers are often confused—both signing their work “J. Spilsbury.” Jonathan Spilsbury was the engraver of <hi rend="i">A Collection of Fifty Prints from Antique Gems, in the Collections of the Right Honourable Earl Percy, the Honourable C. F. Greville, and T. M. Slade, Esquire</hi> . . . (London: John Boydell, 1785), but Boydell mistakenly printed John’s name on the title page.<ref target="n64" type="note">35</ref> Blake also worked for Boydell around this time, thus perhaps renewing his acquaintanceship with the Spilsbury family.<ref target="n65" type="note">36</ref> John Spilsbury styled himself an “Engraver and Map Dissector in Wood, in Order to Facilitate the Teaching of Geography,” and is credited with the invention of “dissected maps”—hand-colored maps, mounted on thin sheets of wood and cut into pieces according to the political borders of the region being mapped.<ref target="n66" type="note">37</ref> He is sometimes regarded as the inventor of the jigsaw puzzle. John’s widow Sarah married Harry Ashby, with whom James Gillray (himself from a Moravian family) served his apprenticeship.<ref target="n67" type="note">38</ref><note id="n63">34. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 5.</note><note id="n64">35. Sloman, <hi rend="i">Oxford DNB</hi> entry. Jonathan was also responsible for an etching of the Moravian settlement at Bethlehem, Pennsylvania (illus. 2).</note><note id="n65">36. On Blake’s work for Boydell, see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations: A Catalogue and Study of the Plates Engraved by Blake after Designs by Other Artists</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991) 42-45.</note><note id="n66">37. See Jill Shefrin, <hi rend="i">Neatly Dissected for the Instruction of Young Ladies and Gentlemen in the Knowledge of Geography: John Spilsbury and Early Dissected Puzzles</hi> (Los Angeles: Cotsen Occasional Press, 1999).</note><note id="n67">38. Richard Godfrey, <hi rend="i">James Gillray: The Art of Caricature</hi> (London: Tate Publishing, 2001) 12, 45. Godfrey’s description of Moravian church life during Gillray’s childhood as “austere and unattractive” and “grim” (12) misrepresents it entirely. David Erdman, in <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 2nd rev. ed. (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1969) 38, 214-21 argues that Blake followed Gillray’s career closely and was influenced by his style.</note></p>
          <p>An elder half-brother, Thomas Spilsbury (b. 1733; d. 1 December 1795), was a printer in Holborn.<ref target="n68" type="note">39</ref> He was one of the first English printers to specialize in printing French books accurately, “even superior to Parisian printers.”<ref target="n69" type="note">40</ref> He is best known, or maybe notorious, as the printer of Payne Knight’s <hi rend="i">Account of the Remains of the Worship of Priapus.</hi><ref target="n70" type="note">41</ref> His sons William and Charles succeeded their father at 57 Snow Hill, Holborn. <note id="n68">39. Confusingly, it seems that Jonathan Spilsbury had both an elder half-brother Thomas, born 1733, and a younger full brother Thomas, born about 1742.</note><note id="n69">40. Maxted 212. The French texts printed by Thomas Spilsbury include Emanuel Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">Doctrine de la Nouvelle Jérusalem, touchant le Seigneur</hi> (Londres: T. Spilsbury, 1787), a translation by B. Chastanier of <hi rend="i">Doctrina Novae Hierosolymae de Domino.</hi></note><note id="n70">41. Richard Payne Knight, <hi rend="i">An Account of the Remains of the Worship of Priapus, Lately Existing at Isernia, in the Kingdom of Naples: In Two Letters; One from Sir William Hamilton . . . to Sir Joseph Banks . . . and the Other from a Person Residing at Isernia: To Which Is Added a Discourse on the Worship of Priapus, and Its Connexion with the Mystic Theology of the Ancients</hi> (London: T. Spilsbury, 1786).</note></p>
          <p>It seems that Jonathan and Rebecca Spilsbury made a joint application for reception into the Moravian congregation at Fetter Lane in August 1781: “The Candidates for Reception into the Congregation, still remaining on the List, Aug. 13. . . . are . . . Jonathan &amp; Rebecca Spilsbury.”<ref target="n71" type="note">42</ref> Rebecca’s candidature was refused, and Jonathan Spilsbury alone was received into the Moravian church in November 1781. The Fetter Lane Church Book notes as follows: “Jonathan Spilsbury M[arried] B[rother] Ch. of Eng. Portrait Painter | [born] Worcester feb. 2. 1745. | [received] Nov: 11<hi rend="s">th</hi> 1781. | [first admitted to the Sacrament] March 28 1782 | Departed this life Oct 31<hi rend="s">st</hi> 1812. Buried in Bunhill Fields.”<ref target="n72" type="note">43</ref> In fact, Rebecca Spilsbury was refused admission to the Moravian congregation several times, and thus, although sympathizing with her husband, remained nominally Anglican.<ref target="n73" type="note">44</ref> Their daughter Maria was confirmed a member of the Church of England at St. George’s, Hanover Square, on 30 April 1795.<ref target="n74" type="note">45</ref><note id="n71">42. Moravian Church Archive C/36/10/10 (Minute Book, 4 August 1781-31 December 1782), entry for 3 November 1781.</note><note id="n72">43. Moravian Church Archive C/36/5/1 (Church Book no. 1), p. 52. I cannot explain the incorrect year of birth other than as a simple arithmetic error.</note><note id="n73">44. Personal communication from Charlotte Yeldham, 19 July 2005.</note><note id="n74">45. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 11-12.</note></p>
          <p>The circumstances of Jonathan’s acceptance, and Rebecca’s refusal, as members to be received into the Moravian community are sufficient in themselves to remind us that spiritualities even within a marriage could remain friendly but diverse. Since Jonathan Spilsbury engaged in the same trade as Blake, it is not inconceivable that such arrangements would have been well known, even commonplace, amongst others in the late eighteenth-century engraving trade. One recalls from Blake’s reported deathbed conversation that during the course of discussing his last wishes, Mrs. Blake offered him a choice as to funeral arrangements; that
<pb id="p40-105" n="105"/>
            <figure n="spilsburybethlehem.40.3.bqscan" rend="file"><figTranscr>N. Garrison &amp; Oerter delint. 1784<lb/>
              J. Spilsbury sculpt.<lb/>
              A View of BETHLEHEM in North America</figTranscr><head>2. Etching by Jonathan Spilsbury: “A View of Bethlehem, in North America.</head><figDesc>N. Garrison &amp; Oerter delin<hi rend="s">t</hi>. 1784 J. Spilsbury sculp<hi rend="s">t</hi>.” Courtesy of the Moravian Church Archive and Library, Moravian Church House, Muswell Hill, London.</figDesc></figure>
is, “whether he would have the Dissenting Minister, or the Clergyman of the Church of England, to read the service.”<ref target="n75" type="note">46</ref> It’s as though Catherine, his own wife, did not know where his preferences lay. Blake, in this account, chose the Church of England. I shall return to this conversation later. <note id="n75">46. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 625, citing J. T. Smith, <hi rend="i">Nollekens and His Times</hi>, 2 vols. (London: Henry Colburn, 1828).</note></p>
          <p>The Moravian church had open preaching services that anyone could attend and other meetings that were intended just for church members. Spilsbury had been a “constant hearer” since at least 1769. When, in 1781, Spilsbury was “received” into the church, that meant he took part in the whole range of services (with some exceptions) and was allotted to a “band” (in his case the married Brethren) which had its own “quarter hour” in which members could discuss spiritual matters privately. In 1782, he was admitted to Holy Communion, which was a special privilege, marking him as part of a spiritual élite: “A Letter was read from the mar. B<hi rend="s">r</hi> Jonathan Spilsbury for admission to the holy Communion.<ref target="n76" type="note">47</ref><note id="n76">47. Moravian Church Archive C/36/12/3 (Congregation Council Minutes 16 June 1778-21 November 1782) [loose sheets (C/36/12/3/12) for Wednesday 17 January 1782].</note></p>
          <p>Admission to Communion was taken extremely seriously. When partaking of the Blessed Sacrament was announced, communicating members were expected to look into their hearts to see if they considered themselves worthy of that privilege. On occasion, the elders would intervene to withhold the Sacrament. In 1738, John Wesley and Benjamin Ingham, the Yorkshire evangelist, visited the Moravian community at Marienborn. Ingham was invited to partake of the Sacrament; Wesley was conspicuously excluded. The grounds the Brethren gave for their action was that he was <hi rend="i">homo perturbatus</hi>—that is, a disturbed man.<ref target="n77" type="note">48</ref><note id="n77">48. John R. Weinlick, <hi rend="i">Count Zinzendorf</hi> (New York: Abingdon Press, 1956) 143. Not long after he was back in England Wesley became critical of Zinzendorf and his Moravian followers and began going his separate way.</note></p>
          <pb id="p40-106" n="106"/>
          <p>In a curious parallel to Blake’s career in Felpham, Spilsbury while in Southampton had sought employment as a miniature painter.<ref target="n78" type="note">49</ref><q>
I am preparing an Ivory for a Miniature Picture and I find (what I formerly did) that after all the care taken in preparing Gum or Paste, to paste paper at the back of it, the Ivory appears cloudy and not of a very good colour, perhaps Mr. Cosway woud be so kind as to tell me how I should manage it, if I cou’d get the Ivory prepared to my wish my Miniatures woud be much better than I can otherwise do them. After Maria has seen Lady de Lally, I think I shall write to Mr. Cosway on the subject ....<ref target="n79" type="note">50</ref><note id="n78">49. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 104-07 records Hayley’s encouragement of Blake in the painting of miniature portraits.</note><note id="n79">50. Spilsbury’s letter to his wife (28 August 1798), quoted in Young, <hi rend="i">Mrs. Chapman’s Portrait</hi> 114. (Could Lady de Lally have lent part of her name to “Tilly Lally” in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon?</hi> The suggestion, made by Morton Paley in a private email, is certainly a provoking one.)</note></q>
This letter seems to imply that Spilsbury, like Blake, is a friend of Richard Cosway, the society painter and mystic. Cosway had been the young William Blake’s instructor at Pars’s Drawing School from 1767 to 1772, and became his lifelong friend. Cosway also had an enduring friendship with James Hutton, founder of the Fetter Lane Moravian church, and painted his portrait.<ref target="n80" type="note">51</ref> The simian-featured Cosway, it seems generally to be agreed, is satirized as “Mr. Jacko” in Blake’s <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, where it is noted that he and his wife “have black servants lodge at their house” (E 457).<ref target="n81" type="note">52</ref> One of these black servants was the writer and campaigner Ottobah Cugoano. 
                        <note id="n80">51. Now in Moravian Church House, 5-7 Muswell Hill, London N10 3TJ. A mezzotint engraving of this portrait, by J. R. Smith after Cosway, was published in 1786. On Cosway (1742-1821) and the Moravians, see John Nichols, <hi rend="i">Literary Anecdotes of the Eighteenth Century</hi>, 9 vols. (London: Printed for the Author, 1812-15) 3: 435-37.</note><note id="n81">52. A point originally made by Erdman in <hi rend="i">Blake, Prophet Against Empire</hi> 96. See also R. J. Shroyer, “Mr. Jacko ‘Knows What Riding Is’ in 1785: Dating Blake’s <hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.4 (spring 1979) 250-56; Paul Edwards, “An African Literary Source for Blake’s ‘Little Black Boy’?” <hi rend="i">Research in African Literatures</hi> 21 (1990): 179-81.</note></p>
          <p>In 1787, Blake engraved “Venus Dissuades Adonis from Hunting,” after Richard Cosway.<ref target="n82" type="note">53</ref> That year is also, I have suggested, the most plausible date for the writing of <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>,<ref target="n83" type="note">54</ref> and is, coincidentally, the date of publication of a campaigning book by Cugoano. <note id="n82">53. Number XXVIII in Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1983) 145-49 and plate 64.</note><note id="n83">54. Alan Philip Keri Davies, “William Blake in Contexts: Family, Friendships and Some Intellectual Microcultures of Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-Century England,” diss., University of Surrey, 2003, 148.</note></p>
          <p>Quobna Ottobah Cugoano, usually known by the shorter form Ottobah Cugoano, was born in present-day Ghana around 1757. Kidnapped and taken into slavery, he worked on plantations in Grenada before being brought to England, where he obtained his freedom. He was baptized as John Stuart—“a Black, aged 16 years”—at St. James’s Church, Piccadilly (the Blake’s parish church), on 20 August 1773.<ref target="n84" type="note">55</ref> While working as manservant to Richard Cosway, he wrote his <hi rend="i">Thoughts and Sentiments on the Evil and Wicked Traffic of the Slavery and Commerce of the Human Species</hi> (1787). This work—part autobiography, part political treatise, and part Christian exegesis—has an enduring legacy as the first directly antislavery text written in English by an African.<ref target="n85" type="note">56</ref><note id="n84">55. Vincent Carretta, “Cugoano, Ottobah (b. 1757?),” <hi rend="i">Oxford DNB.</hi></note><note id="n85">56. Ottobah Cugoano, <hi rend="i">Thoughts and Sentiments on the Evil and Wicked Traffic of the Slavery and Commerce of the Human Species: Humbly Submitted to the Inhabitants of Great Britain by Ottobah Cugoano, a Native of Africa</hi> (London: Printed in the year 1787). There are modern editions by Paul Edwards (London: Dawsons, 1969) and by Vincent Carretta (London: Penguin, 1999).</note></p>
          <p>Spilsbury’s hopes of ordination as a Moravian minister were never realized.<ref target="n86" type="note">57</ref> Such hopes indeed were perhaps impossible while his wife remained excluded from the congregation. He was, however, encouraged by the Moravian church as a preacher. Spilsbury’s obituary memoir in the Fetter Lane Congregation Diary refers to his involvement with the African Chapel in Peter Street, Soho. This seems to have been a special place of worship for African Christians in London. <note id="n86">57. Sloman, <hi rend="i">Oxford DNB</hi> entry.</note></p>
          <q>
His [Spilsbury’s] character among us was that of an humble, steady disciple of Jesus, whose heart was truly attached to him &amp; his cause. It was his delight to invite sinners to Christ, &amp; to testify unto them of his redeeming love. Thus in our Chapel here &amp; in Chelsea, also at the Chapel of the African &amp; Asiatic Society, in Peter Street, Soho, he has been engaged in labors of love of this kind, to edification. How much his heart was devoted to this employment may be gathered from the following in a Letter to B<hi rend="s">t</hi> Montgomery of date Sep<hi rend="s">t</hi> 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> this year.<lb/>
“Next Sunday it has been expected that I should preach to the Africans who assemble in Peter Street but this my present indisposition obliges me to decline. If You should on that day be at liberty to supply my place in inviting, at least, I suppose forty or fifty Africans &amp; other persons who attend at the same time, to partake of redeeming love I should be extremely gratified, &amp; I am persuaded You would enjoy a blessing in the opportunity if You can embrace it.—<lb/>
“As we have Missionaries in Africa and You are well acquainted with the success attending their labors in that part of the World, You would have it in your power to communicate many things, which would afford pleasure &amp; encouragement to the members of the African Society in London;—If You cannot preach to them, perhaps some one of our other Labourers, now in London, may be disposed to embrace this opportunity of publishing the Glad Tidings of the Gospel.<ref target="n87" type="note">58</ref><note id="n87">58. Moravian Church Archive C/36/7/31 (Congregation Diary vol. 31: 10 September 1810-31 December 1816) [unnumbered pages for October 1812].</note></q>
          <pb id="p40-107" n="107"/>
          <p>Could Spilsbury then have known Cugoano, perhaps through his involvement with this Chapel of the African and Asiatic Society?<ref target="n88" type="note">59</ref> The African Chapel in Peter Street, Soho, seems to have been a former Church of Scotland building before it was used by the African congregation, and after 1820 or thereabouts it was used by the Methodists. This transfer of licensed dissenting meeting houses from one sect to another was not uncommon; the Moravians’ Fetter Lane church was previously used by Thomas Bradbury’s Independent congregation.<ref target="n89" type="note">60</ref> Peter Street is connected to Broad Street (with the Blake family home at no. 28) by Hopkins Street, where the black ex-slave Robert Wedderburn had his Unitarian Chapel in a former hayloft.<ref target="n90" type="note">61</ref> How many of the African churchgoers may have moved around the corner to form Wedderburn’s congregation? <note id="n88">59. The African and Asiatic Society had been set up around 1805 with William Wilberforce as president and Zachary Macaulay as treasurer “for the benefit of the poor natives of Africa and Asia and their descendants residing in London and its vicinity, to relieve their ignorance as well as the accumulated distress of poverty, nakedness, hunger, and sickness” (<hi rend="i">Times</hi> 6 July 1819, page 2 column A [classified advertising]).</note><note id="n89">60. Colin Podmore, <hi rend="i">The Fetter Lane Moravian Congregation, London 1742-1992</hi> (London: Fetter Lane Moravian Congregation, 1992) 3.</note><note id="n90">61. On Wedderburn, the former slave turned preacher (father a Scot, mother a slave in Jamaica, came to Britain c. 1790, linked to the Spenceans in the late 1810s, jailed in 1821 for blasphemy), see Iain McCalman, <hi rend="i">Radical Underworld: Prophets, Revolutionaries and Pornographers in London, 1795-1840</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1988) and David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Radical Culture: Discourse, Resistance and Surveillance, 1790-1820</hi> (New York: Harvester Wheatsheaf, 1992).</note></p>
          <p>It is worth noting here possible sources of Blake’s ideas of Africa and Africans. Blake would probably have known Ottobah Cugoano through his friendship with Cosway. Paul Edwards points out that Cugoano was “one of the leaders, with his friend Olaudah Equiano, of the London black abolitionists, an active radical group which corresponded with Granville Sharp and published letters to the press under the name ‘the Sons of Africa,’ Cugoano signing with his ‘English’ name, John Stuart.”<ref target="n91" type="note">62</ref> Other Blake scholars have drawn our attention to the so-called St. Giles’ blackbirds, poor loyalist African former naval servicemen from the American War, who were often seen in the streets of London; their poverty was a visible social problem. But the African Chapel in Soho, a specifically Christian context for Africans in London (and very near to Broad Street where James Blake had his hosier’s shop), sheds a new light on Blake’s antislavery views, and on the strong religious feeling of “The Little Black Boy”:
<q>
And we are put on earth a little space,<lb/>
That we may learn to bear the beams of love,<lb/>
And these black bodies and this sun-burnt face<lb/>
Is but a cloud, and like a shady grove. (E 9)
</q><note id="n91">62. Edwards 181.</note></p>
          <p>Rebecca Spilsbury died in February 1812 and was buried in Bunhill Fields. The <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> records: “In London, deeply lamented, Mrs. Spilsbury, eldest daughter of the late Rev. Dr. Chapman, Prebendary of Bristol Cathedral and master of St. John’s Hospital, Bath.”<ref target="n92" type="note">63</ref> Jonathan Spilsbury survived his wife only until the following October, when he died aged 75, for he was eleven years older than Rebecca.<ref target="n93" type="note">64</ref><note id="n92">63. <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> 82 (April 1812): 397. Strangely, it makes no reference to her husband.</note><note id="n93">64. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 30.</note></p>
          <p>The Moravian Congregation Diaries record Spilsbury’s last illness—“[October 1812, Thursday] 29<hi rend="s">th</hi> We received information, late in the evening, that our dear &amp; valuable B<hi rend="s">r</hi> Spilsbury, had been taken ill at the house of his Son in law, M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Taylor, S<hi rend="s">t</hi> George’s Row, N side of Hyde Park, &amp; that he wished to be visited”<ref target="n94" type="note">65</ref>—and then, the following day, his dying. <note id="n94">65. Moravian Church Archive C/36/7/31 (Congregation Diary vol. 31: 10 September 1810-31 December 1816) [unnumbered pages for October 1812].</note></p>
          <p>It is worth exploring in some detail here how the accounts given of William Blake’s death in 1827 appear to parallel much of the ceremony, observance, and spiritual validation in death which was commonplace in Moravian accounts of the “good death.”
<q>
[Friday] 30<hi rend="s">th</hi> Early in the morning, B<hi rend="s">r</hi> Montgomery accordingly went thither, &amp; found that he [Spilsbury] had been seized with a Paralytic Stroke, on Tuesday Evening last.—About two months ago he had had a slight affection [affliction?] of the same Kind, from which however, he soon recovered, &amp; when he was with us the last time, at the H. Com<hi rend="s">n</hi> on Sept: 27<hi rend="s">th</hi> he was very lively &amp; cheerful, &amp; apparently in y<hi rend="s">e</hi> enjoyment of his usual state of health. From the very weak, enfeebled state in which he now was, it was evident the Stroke at this time must have been a very severe one. His whole frame appeared shattered &amp; broken down, &amp; there was but a faint hope, if any, of his surviving the shock it had received. So much the more comfortable was it to find that his Soul was cheered &amp; comforted in an uncommon degree by the sweet presence &amp; peace of God his Saviour. His speech, tho’ somewhat touched by the stroke, was still very intelligible, &amp; his testimonies &amp; declarations were of the most pleasing &amp; edifying Kind. His confidence &amp; his rejoicing in his Redeemer were without any thing either of wavering on the one hand, or of presumptuous boasting on the other. He spoke as a poor sinner that had found pardon &amp; the forgiveness of sin in the blood of Jesus, &amp; therefore now knew him in whom he believed, &amp; rejoiced. He expressed his gratitude to our Sav<hi rend="s">r</hi> shewn to him at this time in a lively manner, &amp; said “How thankful might I to be to our Sav<hi rend="s">r</hi>, who deals so graciously with me, that, notwithstanding all sickness &amp; infirmity, I have neither any bodily pain, nor any anxiety of mind to trouble me.” Again he observed “How this sickness will end I know not, but, whether it be for life or death, this I know, that I shall be the property of Jesus, and that in his own time, he will come &amp; fetch me:—those that are in Christ can never die, for he is the Resurrection &amp; the life, and therefore I shall attain to Life eternal”. . . . After
<pb id="p40-108" n="108"/>
B<hi rend="s">r</hi> Montgomery, at his request, had prayed with him, a great number of his friends &amp; Relations being present, he gave out the Verse “Praise God from whom all Blessings flow” &amp;c &amp; requested the whole company to join singing it, which was accordingly done.—About 9 O’Clock the same evening he fell asleep, and without waking again to the things of this vain world, his Soul passed over into the arms of its heavenly Bridegroom, about 5 O’Clock in the morning following. So the bitterness of death was taken away that he did not taste it. He was in the 76<hi rend="s">th</hi> year of his age.<ref target="n95" type="note">66</ref><note id="n95">66. Moravian Church Archive C/36/7/31 (Congregation Diary vol. 31: 10 September 1810-31 December 1816) [unnumbered pages for October 1812].</note></q>
Compare Alexander Gilchrist’s account of Blake’s death:
<q>
The final leave-taking came he had so often seen in vision; so often, and with such child-like, simple faith, sung and designed. With the very same intense, high feeling he had depicted the <hi rend="i">Death of the Righteous Man</hi>, he enacted it—serenely, joyously. . . . “On the day of his death,” writes Smith, who had his account from the widow, “he composed and uttered songs to his Maker, so sweetly to the ear of his Catherine, that when she stood to hear him, he, looking upon her most affectionately, said, ‘My beloved! they are <hi rend="i">not mine. No!</hi> they are <hi rend="i">not</hi> mine!’” . . . To the pious Songs followed, about six in the summer evening, a calm and painless withdrawal of breath; the exact moment almost unperceived by his wife, who sat by his side. A humble female neighbour, her only other companion, said afterwards: “I have been at the death, not of a man, but of a blessed angel.”<lb/>
A letter written a few days later to a mutual friend by a now distinguished painter, one of the most fervent in that enthusiastic little band I have so often mentioned, expresses their feelings better than words less fresh or authentic can. . . .<lb/>
“Lest you should not have heard of the death of Mr. Blake, I have written this to inform you. He died on Sunday night at six o’clock, in a most glorious manner. He said he was going to that country he had all his life wished to see, and expressed himself happy, hoping for salvation through Jesus Christ. Just before he died his countenance became fair, his eyes brightened, and he burst out into singing of the things he saw in heaven. In truth, he died like a saint, as a person who was standing by him observed. . . .<ref target="n96" type="note">67</ref><note id="n96">67. Gilchrist 1: 360-62.</note></q></p>
          <p>There are striking similarities: Spilsbury and Blake both die joyously and to the sound of hymns. Gilchrist’s account of Blake’s death has recently been deemed unlikely on medical grounds by Aileen Ward, and by Lane Robson and Joseph Viscomi.<ref target="n97" type="note">68</ref> However, like the account given of Spilsbury’s death, it conforms closely to the customary Moravian trope of the good death, including the emphasis on singing at the point of death. Thus, when John Seniff, the German-born shoemaker who was Swedenborg’s friend in London, died on 2 May 1751, the Fetter Lane Congregation Diary reads:
<q>
His last Sickness was short, (being the Gravel) &amp; not so threatening in appearance as some he had before: When any visited him, he always testified with a peaceful Heart &amp; Countenance the Satisfaction he felt in the Sav<hi rend="s">r’s</hi> Love, &amp; in the Hopes of going to Him; &amp; the last Words he utter’d were the two concluding Verses of that German Hymn, “O Haupt voll Blut und Wunden,” which he began to sing of his own accord, &amp; B<hi rend="s">r</hi> Hintz (his old Acquaintance, who also happen’d to lodge in his House) accompanied it by gently touching the Guitar; &amp; directly he expired.<ref target="n98" type="note">69</ref></q><note id="n97">68. Aileen Ward, “William Blake and the Hagiographers,” in Frederick R. Karl, ed., <hi rend="i">Biography and Source Studies</hi> (New York: AMS Press, 1994); Lane Robson and Joseph Viscomi, “Blake’s Death,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 30.2 (fall 1996): 36-49.</note><note id="n98">69. Moravian Church Archive C/36/7/5 (Congregation Diary for the Fetter Lane Congregation vol. 5: 1 January 1751-31 December 1751), p. 31. On Seniff’s friendship with Swedenborg, see R. L. Tafel, ed., <hi rend="i">Documents concerning the Life and Character of Emanuel Swedenborg, Collected, Translated, and Annotated</hi>, 2 vols. in 3 (London: Swedenborg Society, 1875-77) 2: 586-87.</note></p>
          <p>Perhaps the most striking parallel to Gilchrist’s account occurs not in the Congregation Diaries but in David Cranz’s 1767 history of the Moravian mission in Greenland:
<q>
But the full grain that was sown in the earth this year, nay the first and hitherto only European helper in this mission was Mrs. Drachart, the wife of the Danish missionary. Towards the end of last year she was seized with a violent burning fever, soon after she came to live at New-Herrnhut. The first day of this year she was delirious, but it was of a lovely kind; she incessantly sung verses of her own composing, and that in such a coherent manner, as if she had been one of the most excellent poets. Towards night she was quite still, and in a short time afterward fell gently and happily asleep in the Lord, in the thirty-sixth year of her age. Her corpse was deposited in a walled sepulchre in the burying-ground at New-Herrnhut.<ref target="n99" type="note">70</ref><note id="n99">70. David Cranz, <hi rend="i">The History of Greenland, Containing a Description of the Country and Its Inhabitants, and Particularly a Relation of the Mission, Carried On for above These Thirty Years by the Unitas Fratrum at New Herrnhuth and Lichtenfels in That Country</hi>, 2 vols. (London: Printed for the Brethren’s Society for the Furtherance of the Gospel among the Heathen, 1767) 2: 148.</note></q>
And when Maria (Spilsbury) Taylor died in Dublin on 1 June 1820, “with great self-control her husband sang a hymn beside her bed as she faded out of the world, for he remembered how she loved the United Brethren’s custom of singing whilst a spirit was passing.”<ref target="n100" type="note">71</ref><note id="n100">71. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 35.</note></p>
          <p>The Congregation Diary also contains a note on Spilsbury’s burial in Bunhill Fields:
<q>
[November 1812, Saturday] 7<hi rend="s">th</hi> Agreeably to a request of our late B<hi rend="s">r</hi> Spilsbury, that his Corpse might be laid in the same grave with that of his Wife in Bunhill fields, &amp; that he might
<pb id="p40-109" n="109"/>
be buried in the manner usual among the B<hi rend="s">rn</hi>, B<hi rend="s">r</hi> Montgomery accompanied his remains from S<hi rend="s">t</hi> George’s Row thither, &amp; kept the funeral—After a short address in reference to the solemn occasion &amp; during the Reading of our Burial Litany, his mortal part was committed to the ground, to be quickened in due time by the Spirit of Jesus which had dwelt in it.<ref target="n101" type="note">72</ref><note id="n101">72. Moravian Church Archive C/36/7/31 (Congregation Diary vol. 31: 10 September 1810-31 December 1816) [unnumbered pages for November 1812].</note></q>
As a Moravian, Spilsbury would in the normal course of events have been laid to rest in the Moravian Burying Ground at Chelsea. However, husband and wife could be laid together in the same grave at Bunhill Fields, not separately, women apart from men, as was the Moravian custom.<ref target="n102" type="note">73</ref><note id="n102">73. Young, <hi rend="i">Father and Daughter</hi> 30.</note></p>
          <p>Thus both Spilsbury and Blake are buried at Bunhill Fields, not out of sectarian conviction (the “Dissent” that preoccupies so many Blake scholars), but for simple family reasons:
<q>
A little before his death, Mrs. Blake asked where he would be buried, and whether a dissenting minister or a clergyman of the Church of England should read the service. To which he answered, that as far as his own feelings were concerned, she might bury him “where she pleased.” But that as “father, mother, aunt, and brother were buried in Bunhill Row, perhaps it would be better to lie <hi rend="i">there.</hi> As to service, he should wish for that of the Church of England.”<ref target="n103" type="note">74</ref><note id="n103">74. Gilchrist 1: 361. See also my note 46 for an alternative citation.</note></q></p>
          <p>Blake’s deathbed reference to his beloved younger brother reminds us of Gilchrist’s account of Robert’s own joyous end: “At the last solemn moment, the visionary eyes beheld the released spirit ascend heavenward through the matter-of-fact ceiling, ‘clapping its hands for joy’—a truly Blake-like detail.”<ref target="n104" type="note">75</ref> This finds a parallel in Draper Hill’s citation of an account of the death of James Gillray’s elder brother Johnny while at the Moravian school at Bedford: “‘Pray don’t keep me. O let me go, I must go—’ which were his last words.”<ref target="n105" type="note">76</ref><note id="n104">75. Gilchrist 1: 59.</note><note id="n105">76. Draper Hill, <hi rend="i">Mr. Gillray the Caricaturist: A Biography</hi> (London: Phaidon Press, 1965) 12.</note></p>
          <p>There is one last parallel to draw. The “Br. Montgomery” who attended Spilsbury’s deathbed and officiated at his burial in Bunhill Fields was the Rev. Ignatius Montgomery (b. 1776), younger brother of the Sheffield poet, journalist, hymn writer, and abolitionist James Montgomery (1771-1854). Bentley, in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, cites a letter of April 1807 from Robert Hartley Cromek to James Montgomery that “suggests a connexion between Blake and James Montgomery and Blake’s admiration for Montgomery as a ‘Man of Genius’, of which we should not otherwise have known.” The letter “implies an easy and personal contact between the two men.”<ref target="n106" type="note">77</ref> Indeed, “Mr. Montgomery, Sheffield” was one of the subscribers to Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi><ref target="n107" type="note">78</ref> Is it possible that, during the years 1804 to 1807 of Blake’s friendship with Spilsbury and Montgomery, when both men attended the services at Fetter Lane, they may have taken Blake back to his mother’s former church?<ref target="n108" type="note">79</ref><note id="n106">77. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 239. The letter is far too long to cite in its entirety and yet resistant to selective quotation.</note><note id="n107">78. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 277fn. There are references to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs in Montgomery’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, vol. 1 (London, 1854)—see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977) 835. James Montgomery included Blake’s “The Chimney Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> in his <hi rend="i">The Chimney-Sweeper’s Friend and Climbing-Boy’s Album</hi> (London: Longman, Hurst, etc., 1824) 343-44.</note><note id="n108">79. A suggestion made by Marsha Keith Schuchard in her paper “Young William Blake and the Moravian Tradition of Visionary Art” [in this issue—Eds.].</note></p>
          <p>Spilsbury and Blake, two deeply religious men, would have met at the Royal Academy Schools, and later as engravers working for Boydell. Both had had experience of running printshops, Spilsbury with his brother until John’s death in 1769, Blake in partnership with James Parker from 1784 to 1785.<ref target="n109" type="note">80</ref> Both left London to find work elsewhere, and were reduced to the mundane work of provincial miniature portrait painters. Both were friends with the Montgomery brothers, prominent members of the Moravian church. The accounts of their deaths, as steadfast, virtuous, and joyful ends witnessed and recorded by friends, follow a very similar pattern, as do their eventual burials in Bunhill Fields. <note id="n109">80. <hi rend="i">BR</hi>(2) 33-34.</note></p>
          <p>The years when Blake’s mother worshipped at Fetter Lane constitute a period of great creativity in the life of the Moravian church, in terms both of its theology and of its liturgy and ritual. The Fetter Lane Congregation Diaries contain an account of an adult baptism, that of Sister Jane James:
<q>
[13 November 1749] . . . the Floor being covered with a white Cloth, &amp; the Vessel of Water brought in by 2 Sisters, (one of whom had herself been baptized when an Adult) the Candidate also approached in a white Dress made for the purpose, the Hem or Guard of which was red, &amp; a red Streak from the Throat down to the Feet; then B<hi rend="s">r</hi> B[oehler] first, with several of the Sister-Labourers, laid the Hand on her Head, under that Verse, “Where agonizing Blood,” &amp;c. and afterwards baptized her in a very solemn Manner by the Name of Anna.<ref target="n110" type="note">81</ref><note id="n110">81. Moravian Church Archive C/36/7/3 (Diary of the Congregation at London, for the Year 1749), p. 115 [November].</note></q>
In the account of the baptism of Jane James, the red ribbon running from the throat down to the feet symbolizes the cleansing blood of the Savior. I suggest that William Blake’s Moravian inheritance runs like such a crimson ribbon throughout his life from his mother’s first involvement with the Moravian church even to his death. Or, to put it more prosaically, I suspect that the Blake family’s involvement with the Moravian church extended long after Catherine had supposedly left the congregation, and if not persisting throughout Blake’s life, certainly seems to have been renewed after 1800.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p40-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title>MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">An Analogue to the “Greatest Men” Passage in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Thomas R. <name>Frosch</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In teaching <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, I always found a stumbling block in the Devil’s speech on plates 22-23: “The worship of God is. Honouring his gifts in other men each according to his genius. and loving the greatest men best, those who envy or calumniate great men hate God, for there is no other God.” If “every thing that lives is Holy” (pl. 27), if, as in <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>, all men are the equals of the king (line 193), how can there be great men—not just great gifts or great works, not just the particular genius of every individual—that should be worshiped?</p>
          <p>It was not until I visited the Panthéon in Paris that the passage appeared to me in a different light. The building that became the Panthéon had originally been conceived as a church dedicated to St. Geneviève, patron saint of Paris, but in April 1791, just before its completion, it was converted into a secular temple for the remains of great men, with Mirabeau and Voltaire the first to be interred. Emmet Kennedy points to the desanctification of the church and its rededication to honor great men as the “ultimate expression” of a revolutionary “religion of humanity” (xxv).</p>
          <p>The question of what constituted greatness provoked considerable debate, and indeed that debate and the interest in, or cult of, “grands hommes” had predated the Revolution, with Diderot, Voltaire, and Rousseau among the contributors. In general, though, a great man, in what Jean-Claude Bonnet calls a “métamorphose de la gloire” (29), was no longer a military hero, much less a man of status and wealth, but a man who had superior inner powers and had contributed in a disinterested way to the common good.<ref target="n111" type="note">1</ref> For the French revolutionaries, patriots and martyrs of the Revolution were particularly qualified. <note id="n111">1. This was specifically the formulation of the Abbé de Saint-Pierre; see Bonnet 34.</note></p>
          <p>For some, the “pantheonized” were even divine. In the radical <hi rend="i">Révolutions de Paris</hi>, Jesus was a prophet, Marat a God (Kennedy 336). As for Jesus, Leonard Bourdon called him no more than a man but a great one, “a friend of the people,” Marat’s sobriquet, and “the first sansculotte” (Kennedy 336). The Marquis de Villette, who had first suggested the idea of a Panthéon, spoke of making a cross into a lyre (Bonnet 267), and Quatremère, the architect in charge of remodeling the Church of Sainte-Geneviève into the Panthéon, envisioned a new religion of arts and artists (Kennedy 333). Meanwhile, as E. P. Thompson has documented, English radical tradition had included such as John Reeve, who said that there was no other God but the man Jesus (157), and other partisans of a “humanist and antinomian Jesus Christ” (228). Blake of course was fond of citing the humanity of Jesus and the divinity of one’s own humanity: “Thou art a Man God is no more / Thy own humanity learn to adore” (<hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi>, E 520).</p>
          <p>Blake’s concept of greatness differed in basic ways from the greatness that figured in the Panthéon. His great man was not a patriot and, unlike the great men of the Panthéon, who had to be French, was not associated with the glory of a nation, nor was he incorporated into an institutionalized, ceremonial form of worship. Blake was not engaged with either revolt against or transformation of specifically Catholic traditions, and he was interested not in any reverence of the dead but in the potentiality within the living. Blake’s concept of greatness did include Jesus the sansculotte, as the passage in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> goes on to make clear: “If Jesus Christ is the greatest man, you ought to love him in the greatest degree”; his Jesus broke several of the Ten Commandments and “was all virtue, and acted from impulse: not from rules” (pls. 23-24). And <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> develops a concept of the prophetic artist as central man, who reveals “the infinite which was hid” (pl. 14) and brings about apocalyptic human change. Later, in the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> engraving, “Jesus &amp; his Apostles &amp; Disciples were all Artists” (E 274).</p>
          <p>Mirabeau and Marat were soon “depantheonized.” The Panthéon became a church again, was later resecularized and then once again resanctified. It then served as an arsenal for the Communards in the insurrection of 1871 before being established once and for all with the interment of Victor Hugo in 1885 as a secular temple of the great. Meanwhile, in England the debate on greatness took many famous literary forms, including Byron’s satire of heroes, Carlyle’s hero worship, and Wordsworth’s democratization of greatness.<ref target="n112" type="note">2</ref> Blake went on to give his concept of greatness epic elaboration in the figures of Los and Jesus. <note id="n112">2. See Gaull for a discussion of some of the attitudes towards the hero in the romantic period (145-72). Abrams (91) formulates succinctly the romantic tendency to diminish and at the extreme to eliminate the role of God, leaving as “the prime agents man and the world.”</note></p>
          <p>This is the context in which the passage on the greatest men in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> belongs, the context of a humanistic, and volatile, redefinition of greatness, a contemporary example of which was the reconceptualization of the Church of Sainte-Geneviève, with its implication of the replacement of God by humanity.</p>
          <pb id="p40-111" n="111"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Abrams, M. H. <hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism: Tradition and Revolution in Romantic Literature.</hi> New York: Norton, 1971.</p>
            <p>Bonnet, Jean-Claude. <hi rend="i">Naissance du Panthéon: Essai sur le Culte des Grands Hommes.</hi> Paris: Fayard, 1998.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> New York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988. All Blake quotations are from this edition, abbreviated “E”.</p>
            <p>Gaull, Marilyn. <hi rend="i">English Romanticism: The Human Context.</hi> New York: Norton, 1988.</p>
            <p>Kennedy, Emmet. <hi rend="i">A Cultural History of the French Revolution.</hi> New Haven: Yale UP, 1989.</p>
            <p>Thompson, E. P. <hi rend="i">Witness Against the Beast: William Blake and the Moral Law.</hi> New York: New P, 1993.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-40-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title>NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <p>The village of Felpham is celebrating the 250th anniversary of Blake’s birth by planning a festival of arts week in November 2007 and commissioning a Blake memorial stained glass window in the church. If you wish to donate money for the window or make suggestions for festival week, please contact Reverend Timothy Peskett (frtim@zoom.co.uk).</p>
        <p>The Centre for Eighteenth-Century Studies at the University of York, with the support of Nottingham Trent University and the Blake Society, is hosting a three-day Blake at 250 conference from 30 July to 1 August 2007. Further details are available at the conference web site &lt;http://www.york.ac.uk/inst/cecs/conf/Blakehome.htm&gt;.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
