<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
 <idno>041-03</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><hi rend="b">BLAKE</hi> AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 2007-08</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>2007-08</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">41.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Sarah Jones</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Advisory Board</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D.W. Börrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Angela Esterhammer</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>C.S. Matheson</name>
              <name>Jennifer Davis Michael</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
              <name>G.A. Rosso</name>
              <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="2007/2008"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_41">
    <front>
      <pb id="p41-97-98" n="97-98"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.041.03.bqscan" rend="file">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            A Bibliography for the Study of<lb/>
            <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi><lb/>
            Book and<lb/>
            Exhibition<lb/>
            Reviews<lb/>
            VOLUME 41<lb/>
            NUMBER 3<lb/>
            WINTER 2007-08</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0001">
        <head>
          <title>CONTENTS</title>
        </head>
        <table id="contents" rows="12" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>A Bibliography for the Study of <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi><lb/><hi rend="i">By Justin Van Kleeck</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">100</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Jennifer Davis Michael, <hi rend="i">Blake and the City</hi><lb/><hi rend="i">Reviewed by Michael Ferber</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">125</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Jeremy Tambling, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night Thoughts</hi><lb/><hi rend="i">Reviewed by Wayne C. Ripley</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">127</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Jason Allen Snart, <hi rend="i">The Torn Book: UnReading William Blake’s Marginalia</hi><lb/><hi rend="i">Reviewed by Jennifer Davis Michael</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">129</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>[Robert C. Brandeis,] <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries</hi>: An Exhibition Selected from the Bentley Collection at Victoria University, Victoria University Library, Toronto<lb/><hi rend="i">Reviewed by C. S. Matheson</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">131</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>Magnus Ankarsjö, <hi rend="i">William Blake and Gender</hi><lb/><hi rend="i">Reviewed by G. A. Rosso</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">133</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particular</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi> by “B. Blake”<lb/><hi rend="i">By Morton D. Paley</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">135</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Corrigendum</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>To “Blake’s ‘Annus Mirabilis’: The Productions of 1795,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.2 (fall 2007)<lb/><hi rend="i">By Joseph Viscomi</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">135</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>ADVISORY BOARD</title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., University of Toronto, retired</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin, London</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, University of Trier</p>
        <p>Robert N. Essick, University of California, Riverside</p>
        <p>Angela Esterhammer, University of Zürich</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia</p>
        <p>Anne K. Mellor, University of California, Los Angeles</p>
        <p>Joseph Viscomi, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p>
        <p>David Worrall, The Nottingham Trent University</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p41-99" n="99"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>Michael Ferber is professor of English and Humanities at the University of New Hampshire. He has recently edited (and partly translated) the anthology <hi rend="i">European Romantic Poetry</hi> (New York: Pearson Longman, 2005) and completed the second edition of <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of Literary Symbols</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 2007). He may be reached at mferber@cisunix.unh.edu.</p>
        <p>C. S. Matheson teaches romantic literature and visual culture at the University of Windsor, Ontario. Her current projects on romantic spectatorship include a book on the invention of public art exhibition in the period (which does feature Blake) and a collaborative investigation, with Alex McKay, of the Claude mirror and constructions of landscape called “The Transient Glance” &lt;http://www.claudemirror.com&gt;.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Davis Michael (jmichael@sewanee.edu), professor of English at the University of the South in Sewanee, Tennessee, is the author of <hi rend="i">Blake and the City</hi> (Bucknell UP, 2006).</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley recently completed <hi rend="i">Samuel Taylor Coleridge and the Fine Arts</hi>, which will be published by Oxford in 2008.</p>
        <p>Wayne C. Ripley is an assistant professor at Winona State University. He is working on a project involving Blake, Young, and the tradition of devotional radicalism in the long eighteenth century.</p>
        <p>G. A. Rosso (rossog1@southernct.edu) has authored and co-edited a number of books and essays on Blake’s epic prophecies and their relation to the Bible, Milton, and British social history. He teaches English at Connecticut State University in New Haven.</p>
        <p>Justin Van Kleeck (jsvk13@vt.edu) is an adjunct assistant professor of English at Piedmont Virginia Community College in Charlottesville, Virginia.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Alexander S. Gourlay</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Department of English, Morey 410, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Sarah Jones sarah.jones@rochester.edu TELEPHONE: 585/275-3820 FAX: 585/442-5769</p>
        <p>Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451<lb/>
Email: meav@mail.rochester.edu</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720-1030<lb/>
Email: mpaley@berkeley.edu</p>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V 1A2 Canada</p>
        <p>Alexander S. Gourlay, Department of English, Rhode Island School of Design, 2 College Street, Providence RI 02903-2717<lb/>
Email: agourlay@risd.edu</p>
        <p>David Worrall, Faculty of Humanities, The Nottingham Trent University, Clifton Lane, Nottingham NG11 8NS UK<lb/>
Email: david.worrall@ntu.ac.uk</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the Department of English, University of Rochester. Subscriptions are $60 for institutions, $30 for individuals. All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be applied to the current volume. Addresses outside the US, Canada, and Mexico require a $20 per volume postal surcharge for airmail delivery. Credit card payment is available. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to Sarah Jones, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester NY 14627-0451. Back issues are available; address Sarah Jones for information on issues and prices, or consult the web site.</p>
        <p>Manuscripts are welcome in either hard copy or electronic form. Send two copies, typed and documented according to forms suggested in the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>, and with pages numbered, to either of the editors. No articles will be returned unless accompanied by a stamped self-addressed envelope. For electronic submissions, you may send a disk, or send your article as an attachment to an email message; please number the pages of electronic submissions. The preferred file format is RTF; other formats are usually acceptable.</p>
        <p>International Standard Serial Number: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is indexed in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, Humanities International Complete, Arts and Humanities Citation Index, Current Contents and the Bibliography of the History of Art. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 2008 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb id="p41-100" n="100"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title>ARTICLE</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>A Bibliography for the Study of <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Justin <name>Van Kleeck</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">
            <hi rend="i">Author’s note: This bibliography is also online in an expanded version—including reviews, which have been omitted from the print version because of space limitations—at the journal’s web site &lt;http://www.blakequarterly.org&gt;, where it will be updated yearly.</hi>
          </note>
          <p>THE intended purpose of this bibliography is to provide a resource for close study of Blake’s manuscript work <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi> through a multitude of possible approaches: bibliographical, textual, social reception, etc. In preparing this list, I have attempted to be as comprehensive as possible in terms of the date and nature of the materials included, but also selective about what is and is not most relevant to the study of this particular Blakean production.</p>
          <p>While in general I have tended to err on the side of liberality, I have followed several key guidelines in deciding what to include. The most important criterion is that the secondary work must be devoted to some component of <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi>, whether in its entirety (as in a monograph or article), in a distinct part (as in a book or dissertation chapter), or in the course of a close investigation along with perhaps one or two other works by Blake. Thus many critical works often considered fundamental to Blake studies in general do not appear here—e.g., Frye’s <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> or Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet against Empire.</hi> An item need not have been “published,” per se, but it must be available in some format from at least one institution (however easy or difficult obtaining the item might be). Unfortunately, papers presented at conferences passed through the critical sieve unless they later appeared in published form, due mainly to the fact that conference proceedings often do not leave detailed bibliographical trails. However, extensive monographs written by seasoned critics published by centuries-old scholarly presses do appear here alongside doctoral dissertations, master’s theses, and even a baccalaureate honors essay (these last two genres included mostly to show the ongoing activity related to <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi> at all levels of scholarship). I have also included those reviews of editions and monographs devoted to <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi>, largely because reviews often contain interesting arguments that are relevant to a study of the manuscript; for reviews of editions, I have cited those that focus particularly on the edited version of the manuscript. Materials may be in any format/medium—printed books and articles, videotapes, sound recordings, or librettos—as long as they satisfy the other criteria. Materials may be in any language; I have tried to identify the language when it is not English and, when possible, to provide an English translation.</p>
          <p>As for editions of Blake’s writings as a whole or of his poems exclusively, I have not, except in one case (see below), included those that provide only a selection of the <hi rend="i">VALA/Four Zoas</hi> manuscript text. Usually selected editions do not involve a fresh version of the text prepared in direct consultation of the manuscript. Indeed, many selections often derive in some way from previous complete editions prepared by other editors. Additionally, selections may allow for a study of some particular portion of what Blake wrote, but they do not allow for a fully informed engagement with the work as a textual whole. Moreover, tracking down every selected edition of Blake’s poetry, in every revision and/or reprint, was an over-whelming prospect too daunting at this point for this bibliographer. While the editions of W. H. Stevenson and Alicia Ostriker derive from the text of David Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, they do represent the manuscript text in its entirety—and each has been “edited” from Erdman’s original in a multitude of ways. I have made a single exception for John Sampson’s 1905 edition, with its 1913 revised companion. I have included Sampson’s edition(s) because, first, most other editors and scholars have pinpointed Sampson’s as the first “reliable,” scholarly edition of Blake’s writings, which makes his selected text of <hi rend="i">“The Four Zoas”</hi> more relevant, perhaps, than other selected versions, and second, D. J. Sloss and J. P. R. Wallis’s <hi rend="i">Prophetic Writings</hi> (finally published in 1926) originated as a companion/follow-up to Sampson’s edition of Blake’s poems. Weighing these two particulars, I felt that Sampson’s selected text deserved a place in the list. For all editions cited, I have recorded only the first edition’s full information and then, in my comments, noted years of later reprints, revised or not, <hi rend="i">except</hi> when the revision involved a change in the title (see, e.g., Keynes, Erdman, and Stevenson) or other publication details.</p>
          <p>My goal has been comprehensiveness, and for my bibliographical sleuthing I have used the following databases as the main tools to compile this list:
<list type="simple"><item><p>• The Modern Language Association (MLA) International Bibliography, 1926 to the present;</p></item><item><p>• The Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature (ABELL), 1922 to the present;</p></item><item><p>• The WorldCat/OCLC bibliography.</p></item></list>
G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> (1995), and subsequent checklists/updates published in this journal proved similarly helpful for uncovering additional items. Beyond these main resources, I consulted Bentley and Martin K. Nurmi’s <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography: Annotated Lists of Works, Studies, and Blakeana</hi> (Minneapolis: U of Minnesota P, 1964), which is occasionally cited in my comments. Further, I used the holdings of the University of Virginia Library, information obtained from personal contacts, and my own
<pb id="p41-101" n="101"/>
personal experience in the course of years of focused engagement with <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas.</hi> But I recognize that, however many “Wonders of labour” I might have performed, there will be at least a few(!) items I have missed. Thus, I welcome any additional citations—past, present, and future—from others. This bibliography is not complete in its current version; hopefully it may remain unfinished perpetually and continue to grow year by year, so that collaboration, as it were, can only make it stronger.</p>
          <p>I have attempted to provide annotations, based on my own reading and the resources just mentioned, to those entries that seemed to warrant or demand commentary beyond the simple citation. These annotations range in length, in many cases only clarifying the entry’s inclusion based upon bibliographical information contained in another source. In all of them, though, I have tried to focus on the nature of the work and its contents without my own personal spin—as much as this is possible in a <hi rend="i">selected</hi> and <hi rend="i">focused</hi> bibliography. Again, my goal is to build an informational clearinghouse of materials for a study of <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi>, not to highlight specific works as authoritative or especially recommended.</p>
          <p>The entries are organized by year, beginning with the first recorded mention of <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi> in William Michael Rossetti’s catalogue, part of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> of 1863, and ending in 2007 (though I have not done a full examination beyond 2006). Within years, the entries are then organized by author’s last name; those with no author identified are listed as “anonymous.” I have also tried to describe each entry further using these categories: edition, criticism (general or textual), review, biography, film, sound recording, musical score, and other.</p>
          <p>A note on the title of Blake’s work: I have given yet another title to Blake’s manuscript in the long history of its authorial and post-authorial existence. “<hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi>,” as I refer to it, represents to me a title that acknowledges the full genesis of the work, from its earliest stages as “<hi rend="i">VALA</hi>” (the title that still appears in every Night’s heading in the manuscript) to its latest authorial version as “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” (with “<hi rend="i">VALA</hi>” still present just below on the title page, though crossed out by Blake). The subtitle(s) make the situation even more complex, though, so I have truncated the work’s latest appellation, which serves more as a mere pointer to the original in all its complexity and uncertainty than as a summation of what it is and was and will be. I have not, finally, tried to codify my previous suggestion that “Zoas” may in fact be “Zoa’s”,<ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> since this possibility remains only a suggestion; I have used the common form of the title without apostrophe. <note id="n1">1. See Van Kleeck, “Blake’s Four . . . ‘Zoa’s’?” (2005).</note></p>
          <p>In conclusion, I would like to note that I have found perhaps most interesting the various periods of explosive activity involving <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi> that become quickly visible in this bibliography. Thus, we can see how more and more brave souls, critical and otherwise, have undertaken the task of working with and through Blake’s original—to many the most daunting production of his fiery artistic forge. The late 1970s up through the 1990s seem particularly prominent in this regard. Equally compelling is the changing nature of this activity, the appearance and reappearance or disappearance of specific topics of concern and methods of approach. In compiling this bibliography to aid others in their study of <hi rend="i">VALA/The Four Zoas</hi>, I myself have been able to learn a great deal about how we can continue to puzzle and marvel and quibble over the manuscript that Blake left us . . . and to “enter into” it if we dare.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1863</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Gilchrist, Alexander<lb/><hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, “Pictor Ignotus.” With Selections from His Poems and Other Writings.</hi> 2 vols. London: Macmillan and Co., 1863.</p>
            <p>Category: Biography</p>
            <p>Entry no. 7 in vol. 2, list 2 (“Uncoloured Works”); listed as “Vala, or the Death and Judgment of the Ancient Man: a Dream of Nine Nights; by William Blake” (2: 240). These lists were compiled by William Michael Rossetti.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1893</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ellis, E. J., and W. B. Yeats, eds.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake: Poetic, Symbolic, and Critical. Edited with Lithographs of the Illustrated “Prophetic Books,” and a Memoir and Interpretation.</hi> 3 vols. London: Bernard Quaritch, 1893.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Ellis and Yeats present “Vala” (their title) unveiled for the first time. They produce their “hybrid” text by printing the latest stages of Blake’s revisions, but also by changing the manuscript text at various points where they feel Blake failed to create “long resounding strong heroic Verse.” They report many of their emendations and provide some notes on the original text.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1905</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Sampson, John, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of William Blake: A New and Verbatim Text from the Manuscript Engraved and Letterpress Originals with Variorum Readings and Bibliographical Notes and Prefaces.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1905.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition (selections)</p>
            <p>Sampson’s is widely hailed as the first reliable edition of Blake’s writings. He provides selections from <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and the other epics. A revised version of the edition, with a different title but no changes to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, was published in 1913 (see below).</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p41-102" n="102"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1906</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ellis, Edwin J., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1906.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Ellis’s text of “Vala” is a reprint of that in his edition with Yeats (1893). In Ellis’s commentary, he expresses the same views as in the earlier edition regarding Blake’s use of traditional symbolism, mysticism, etc.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1913</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Sampson, John, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of William Blake: Including the Unpublished</hi> French Revolution <hi rend="i">Together with the Minor Prophetic Books and Selections from</hi> The Four Zoas, Milton, <hi rend="i">and</hi> Jerusalem. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1913.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition (selections)</p>
            <p>Revised version of the 1905 edition; no changes to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1918</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>“Catalogue of the John Linnell Collection of Highly Important Works by William Blake Obtained Direct from the Artist ....” London: Messrs. Christie, Manson &amp; Woods, 1918.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>Lot 206, recorded as “VALA: OR, THE DEATH AND JUDGMENT OF THE ANCIENT MAN: A DREAM OF NINE NIGHTS; by WILLIAM BLAKE, 1797” (28). A handwritten note next to the entry indicates that the manuscript was sold to “Parsons” (not “Pearson” as in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> p. 464) for £420.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1921</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey<lb/><hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William Blake.</hi> New York: Grolier Club of New York, 1921.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>Keynes revises Ellis and Yeats’s ordering of the manuscript and briefly describes each page’s designs and the first line of text (if any).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1924</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Plowman, Max<lb/>
“Blake’s Bible of Hell.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> (6 November 1924): 710.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“Suggests that it may be <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” (Bentley and Nurmi 321).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1925</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Writings of William Blake.</hi> 3 vols. London: Nonesuch P, 1925.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>This is Keynes’s first edition, following closely after his 1921 <hi rend="i">Bibliography.</hi> Keynes breaks new ground with “Vala, or The Four Zoas” by incorporating a large number of Blake’s revisions to the manuscript text in the edition text; his accompanying textual notes, though not extensive, also help fill in some of the details. While his inclusion of authorial revisions is selective, he presents a very full representation of the text in a format that is readable.</p>
            <p>Plowman, Max<lb/>
“Blake and Hayley.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> (30 April 1925): 300.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“The poem read to Hayley was probably <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” (Bentley and Nurmi 321).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1926</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Pierce, Frederick E.<lb/>
“Two Notes on Blake.” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 41 (1926): 169-70.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>One of the notes is on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Plowman, Max<lb/>
“Blake Drawings.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> (1 April 1926): 249.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“Who rubbed out part of the drawings in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> MS?” (Bentley and Nurmi 321).</p>
            <p>Sloss, D. J., and J. P. R. Wallis, eds.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Prophetic Writings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1926.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Sloss and Wallis’s edition was originally begun as a companion to Sampson’s 1905 edition, but various delays, both personal and political—such as World War I—pushed publication back to 1926. They look very closely, even more so than Keynes, at the bibliographical details of the <hi rend="i">VALA/Four Zoas</hi> manuscript, including the first and only recorded instance in an edition of “The Four Zoa’s” (i.e., with apostrophe) as Blake’s second title. Although their text is a “clean” version incorporating Blake’s final revisions, they have full footnotes to report textual details. Two interesting facets of their text are that they end Night I on p. 8, also including pp. 19-22; and they print Night VIIb (pp. 91-98) in an appendix.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p41-103" n="103"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1927</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> London: Nonesuch P, 1927.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>In this edition, Keynes uses the 1925 <hi rend="i">Writings</hi> text, but he arranges Blake’s writings thematically rather than chronologically as he did before (and does again later in his 1957 and following editions).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1929</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Lindsay, Jack<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake: Creative Will and the Poetic Image.</hi> 2nd ed. London: Fanfrolico P, 1929.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“Includes an essay on <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> not published in the 1st ed.” (according to the WorldCat citation).</p>
            <p>Wright, Thomas<lb/><hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. Olney: Thomas Wright, 1929.</p>
            <p>Category: Biography/criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 9 (1: 143-55) is a commentary on the poem, including an illustration of the Prester Serpent (manuscript p. 98) with names of persons and places attributed to specific parts, such as Verulam and Bacon to the head (1: 150).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1939</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Samuels, Jayne Newcomer<lb/>
“William Blake’s Use of Color Symbolism in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. State College of Washington, 1939.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1943</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Nitchie, Elizabeth<lb/>
“Blake’s ‘The Tiger.’” <hi rend="i">Explicator</hi> 1 (1943): item 34.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“Properly relates the fifth stanza to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” (Bentley and Nurmi 313).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1949</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Blackstone, Bernard<lb/><hi rend="i">English Blake.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1949.</p>
            <p>Category: Biography</p>
            <p>Ch. 5 (79-102) in part 1 (“Life and Works”) is on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1956</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr.<lb/>
“The Date of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 71 (1956): 487-91.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>“Evidence that ‘all of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> from the fourth Night on was written or transcribed in its present state after May, 1802.’ This dating makes the poem less of a workshop and more important in its own right” (Bentley and Nurmi 237).</p>
            <p>Margoliouth, H. M., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Vala: <hi rend="i">Blake’s Numbered Text.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1956.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Margoliouth undertakes a formidable task: “to present the text of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> as Blake made his fair copy of each Night before erasures, deletions, additions, and changes of order had brought it to the state in which we know it today as <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” (xi). Thus, he presents the text before most of Blake’s revisions, though some are included, Margoliouth’s main basis of exclusion being his recovery of the “earliest” text as suggested by Blake’s line numbers. Although at times his decisions about what to include are highly debatable, his effort to recover “<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>” is both laudable and very useful. As Margoliouth’s is a version of the early text, he prints much of Night I, Night VIII, and pp. 117-19 of Night IX in appendices. He prints in order Nights VIIa and VIIb (or “VII” and “VII <hi rend="i">bis</hi>”), arguing (for the first time) that the first and second “Night the Seventh” fit well together before Blake’s later revisions.</p>
            <p>Rudd, Margaret<lb/><hi rend="i">Organiz’d Innocence: The Story of Blake’s Prophetic Books.</hi> London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1956.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 2 (49-124) is on “<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” “This naïve, rather incoherent book sets out to prove that the ‘very wonderful story’ of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (which ‘form one long narrative’) is in intimate detail ‘Blake’s own psychological drama’. It may have been Miss Rudd’s refusal to consult <hi rend="i">any</hi> Blake scholarship during the writing of her book which allows her to conclude, <hi rend="i">inter alia</hi>, that ‘<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> has a simple, almost naive, coherence’” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> #2586).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1957</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Harper, George Mills<lb/>
“Symbolic Meaning in Blake’s ‘Nine Years.’” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 72 (1957): 18-19.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Complete Writings of William Blake with All the Variant Readings.</hi> London: Nonesuch P; New York: Random House Inc., 1957.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Revised version of the 1925 <hi rend="i">Writings</hi>, now in one volume instead of three.</p>
            <pb id="p41-104" n="104"/>
            <p>Raine, Kathleen<lb/>
“Blake’s ‘Cupid and Psyche.’” <hi rend="i">Listener</hi> 58 (21 November 1957): 832-35.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Raine argues that “Vala and Luvah [are] from Apuleius” (Bentley and Nurmi 325).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1958</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr.<lb/>
“The Failure of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Texas Studies in English</hi> 37 (1958): 102-13.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“Some detailed conclusions from a study of the manuscript as to how and why <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> went wrong” (Bentley and Nurmi 237).</p>
            <p>Miner, Paul<lb/>
“William Blake: Two Notes on Sources. (1) Blake’s Use of Gray’s ‘Fatal Sisters’ (2) A Source for Blake’s Enion?” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public Library</hi> 62 (1958): 203-07.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“Gray’s influence on <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> Night VIII, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>; a source for Enion in Drayton’s <hi rend="i">Poly-Olbion</hi>” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> #2229).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1961</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bloom, Harold<lb/><hi rend="i">The Visionary Company: A Reading of English Romantic Poetry.</hi> London: Faber and Faber, 1961.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Part 1, section 7, is “States of Being: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>”; a revised and enlarged edition of this book was published by Cornell UP (1971). Additionally, the section on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> was reprinted in <hi rend="i">Blake: A Collection of Critical Essays</hi>, ed. Northrop Frye (Englewood Cliffs: Prentice-Hall, 1966) 104-18.</p>
            <p>Rabinovitz, Rubin<lb/>
“Old Testament Influences in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. Columbia U, 1961.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Yasuda, Masayoshi<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> kara <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> e (1) [From <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (1)].” <hi rend="i">Kwanseigakuin Daigaku Eibeibungaku: Journal of the Society of English and American Literature, Kwanseigakuin University</hi> 11th series 6, no. 6 (November 1961): 15-32.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1962</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Anderson, William<lb/>
“A Study of Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. U of Texas at Austin, 1962.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Fowler, Lorraine Tulis<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Waste Land</hi>: Paths to Regeneration, the City of God.” Master’s thesis. Southern Methodist U, 1962.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1963</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: Vala <hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas: <hi rend="i">A Facsimile of the Manuscript, a Transcript of the Poem and a Study of Its Growth and Significance.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1963.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Bentley’s facsimile, originating as a dissertation, is almost overwhelming, both in its physical size, being a life-size reproduction of the manuscript with accompanying apparatus, and in the information that Bentley provides. Along with a transcription, extensive critical “study” of the poem’s “growth and significance,” and bibliographical tables of content and physical details (e.g., lines reused elsewhere, watermarks, etc.), Bentley’s black-and-white facsimile is the first and only one of its kind.</p>
            <p>Hill, Kathleen Balet<lb/>
“The Role of Orc as Redeemer: A Study of Orc as a Possible Redemptive Figure in the ‘Four Zoas’ of William Blake.” Master’s thesis. Columbia U, 1963.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1964</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Butlin, Martin<lb/>
“Blake’s ‘Vala, or The Four Zoas’ and a New Water-Colour in the Tate Gallery.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 106, no. 737 (1964): 381-82.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1965</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Abrahams, Cecil Anthony<lb/>
“An Annotated Index to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> of William Blake.” Master’s thesis. U of New Brunswick, 1965.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> With commentary by Harold Bloom. Garden City: Doubleday &amp; Co., Inc., 1965.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <pb id="p41-105" n="105"/>
            <p>Erdman’s first (nearly “complete”) version of Blake’s writings. In his version of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Erdman conflates text on pp. 7 and 143-44 and relegates Night VIIb to an appendix. The 1970 fourth printing, with revisions, was used by Stevenson (1971, 1989, 2007) and Ostriker (1977) for their own complete editions of Blake’s poems.</p>
            <p>Harper, George Mills<lb/>
“Apocalyptic Vision and Pastoral Dream in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Quarterly</hi> 64 (1965): 110-24.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Osborn, Winifred<lb/>
“Vates Ludens: William Blake’s ‘<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, sub specie ludi.’” Master’s thesis. Columbia U, 1965.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1966</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Anderson, William Davis<lb/>
“‘Awake Ye Dead’: A Study of Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen, The Four Zoas</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Diss. U of Texas at Austin, 1966.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>See also Anderson’s master’s thesis of 1962, focused solely on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> This dissertation presumably incorporates that work as a distinct part.</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake: Complete Writings with Variant Readings.</hi> Oxford: Oxford UP, 1966.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Revised version of the 1957 edition, now published by Oxford University Press. Revised versions of this edition, with the same title and still by Oxford, were published in 1971, 1972, 1974, 1976, and 1979; the 1979 edition is the last before Keynes’s death in 1982.</p>
            <p>Macdonald, Susan L.<lb/>
“The Symbolic Significance of Tharmas in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. Memphis State U, 1966.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Schulkind, Carole<lb/>
“The Structural Symbolism of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. Adelphi U, 1966.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1967</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Reid, Robert Lanier<lb/>
“A Study of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: 1) A Four-Fold Vision, 2) Tharmas and Architecture.” Master’s thesis. U of Virginia, 1967.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Stevenson, W.H.<lb/>
“Two Problems in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 1.3 (winter 1967-68): 13-16; continued in <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 1.4 (spring 1968): 6-8.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Stevenson presents the problems of the ending of Night I and the two Nights VII, giving his solutions based upon satisfactory readings in light of the textual evidence. These solutions later take form in his edition text: Night I ends on p. 8; Night VIIb is retained as part of the edition text (rather than appearing in an appendix) and follows Blake’s directions for reordering. He points out that since “the text is so pervaded with problems we do well to try to avoid conjectures involving Blake’s supposed or probable intentions where he did not make them explicit. We have to make such conjectures too often in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> without manufacturing them” (14).</p>
            <p>Sugnet, Charles<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Myth in Process.” Master’s thesis. U of Virginia, 1967.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1968</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Erdman, David V.<lb/>
“The Binding (et cetera) of <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Library</hi>, 5th series, 19 (1964 [1968]): 112-29.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Erdman’s article, ostensibly a review of Bentley’s Vala <hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas, contains his arguments about the manuscript (Blake intended it to remain an “illuminated manuscript”) and a wealth of textual “corrections” to Bentley’s transcription, all resulting from Erdman’s newfound concern “to perfect Blake’s text, particularly to recover the ‘illegible’ passages” (113).</p>
            <p>Kashiwagi, Toshikazu<lb/>
“‘The Four Zoas’ ni okeru Blake [Blake in ‘The Four Zoas’].” <hi rend="i">Koyasan Daigaku Ronso: Journal of Koyasan University</hi> 3 (1968): 1-14.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1969</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Beer, John<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Universe.</hi> Manchester: Manchester UP; New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, Inc., 1969.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Appendix 3 (343-52) is on “‘Vala, or The Four Zoas’, Text and Illustrations,” and includes commentary and descriptions of many of the designs.</p>
            <pb id="p41-106" n="106"/>
            <p>Erdman, David V.<lb/>
“A Temporary Report on Texts of Blake.” <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon.</hi> Ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld. Providence: Brown UP, 1969. 395-413.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>This is one of Erdman’s many reports on editions of Blake. In this article, he deals with errors in printed texts in the same manner he did with Bentley’s 1963 facsimile in “The Binding (et cetera) of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>” (1968); he covers <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> on 407-10.</p>
            <p>Nanavutty, Piloo<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">Materia Prima</hi> in a Page of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi>” <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon.</hi> Ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld. Providence: Brown UP, 1969. 293-302.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“The Circle of Destiny no Keisei: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night I no Bunseki [The Formation of the Circle of Destiny: An Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night I].” <hi rend="i">So Takeyuki Kyoju Kanrekikinen Bunshu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Essays and Studies in Honor of the Sixtieth Birthday of Professor So Takeyuki</hi>]. Kashiwa, 1969. 83-112.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night II ni okeru Cycle Images ni tsuite [Cycle Images in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night II].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 9 (1969): 86-98.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Wenger, A. Grace<lb/>
“Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth.” <hi rend="i">Explicator</hi> 27 (1969): item 53.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1970</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Katsura, Fumiko<lb/>
“Blake Shinwa Oboegaki—<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> wo megutte [Notes on Blake’s Mythology—On <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Kiyo: Shitennoji Joshidaigaku: Review of Shitennoji Women’s College</hi> no. 2 (1970): 32-46.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Laque, Carol Feiser<lb/>
“A Study of Organic Form in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. U of Cincinnati, 1970.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>McNeil, Helen T.<lb/>
“The Formal Art of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman and John E. Grant. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1970. 373-90.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Simonson, Paul<lb/>
“The Lost Traveler’s Dream: A Study of ‘The Four Zoas’ by William Blake.” Master’s thesis. Hartford Seminary Foundation, 1970.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> ni okeru Kozo to Giko no Ichikosatsu—Night the First wo Chushin to shite [A Survey of the Structure and Technique in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>—Centering on Night the First].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 10 (1970): 53-67.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1971</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Stevenson, W. H., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake.</hi> Longman Annotated English Poets. London: Longman Group Limited, 1971.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>In this edition, the text comes from Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose</hi> (1970), since—according to Stevenson—Blake’s text has been virtually settled by Erdman and Bentley. Stevenson’s main task, then, is to provide the first thoroughgoing set of annotations to Blake’s writings. As he puts it, he has “tried in this edition not to interpret or expound any ‘system’ in B.’s [Blake’s] works, but to give whatever information is necessary for the exposition of each poem or passage, so that the reader may be able to interpret more easily for himself” (xi). Thus, Stevenson becomes the first editor to make an intentional shift away from textual scrutiny to annotative/interpretive comprehensiveness. However, he does make a fair number of revisions to his base text (Erdman). In <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in particular, he orders Nights I and II in the same way as Sloss and Wallis, ending I on p. 8 (with pp. 19-22 added) and beginning II on p. 9, and he prints Nights VIIa and VIIb in their manuscript order (though with Blake’s revisions to VIIb) rather than relegating VIIb to an appendix.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“‘The Four Zoas’ to ‘Milton’ ni okeru Spectres no ichi kosatsu: Counterpart to Negation no mondai [A Study of Spectres in ‘The Four Zoas’ and ‘Milton’: The Problem of Counterpart and Negation].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 12 (1971): 140-58.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p41-107" n="107"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1972</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Evans, James C.<lb/>
“The Apocalypse as Contrary Vision: Prolegomena to an Analogical Reading of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Texas Studies in Literature and Language</hi> 14.2 (1972): 313-28.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Many of the problems in critical interpretations of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> arise from a duality inherent in the poem itself: it is simultaneously an account of an <hi rend="i">individual</hi> moving from restricted to totally free (imaginative) perception and a history of human consciousness, the former requiring a linear plot and the latter a moment of revelation (so that there is no prescribed progression) (314-15). Thus, “the persona of the author of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is dual: he is both a prophet to a culture and a more hermetic visionary” (315). Evans bases his “alternative principle of structural organization” for the poem on the Circle of Destiny.</p>
            <p>Opalenik, Mary Susan<lb/>
“The Dislocation of Energy in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. San Francisco State College, 1972.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Smith, Catherine F.<lb/>
“Pictorial Language in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> by Blake.” Diss. U of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1972.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Stevenson, Warren<lb/><hi rend="i">Divine Analogy: A Study of the Creation Motif in Blake and Coleridge.</hi> Salzburg Studies in English Literature: Romantic Reassessment 25. Salzburg: U of Salzburg, 1972.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 4 (114-47), “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: From Creation to Re-Creation.”</p>
            <p>Stilwell, Derek P.<lb/>
“The Shadow in Eternity: A Reading of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. Dalhousie U, 1972.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Tsuchiya, Shigeko<lb/>
“Vision no hizumi—‘Four Zoas’ o megutte [The Warp of Vision—On ‘The Four Zoas’].” <hi rend="i">Critica</hi> 16 (1972): 2-13.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1973</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bromberg, Pamela Starr<lb/>
“Blake and the Spectre of Milton.” Diss. Yale U, 1973.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“‘This dissertation attempts to study Blake’s poetic relationship with Milton’ in the <hi rend="i">Marriage, Europe, Vala</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> #A2743).</p>
            <p>Grant, John E.<lb/>
“Visions in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>: A Consideration of Some Pictures in the Manuscript.” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on</hi> The Four Zoas, Milton, Jerusalem. Ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1973. 141-202.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Grant examines Blake’s illustrations on pp. 2, 13, 19, 22, 25, 26, 43-76, 35, 37-42, and 117-40. He argues that while it is often possible to speak meaningfully about “early” and “late” alterations to the text, no similar principle extends to the pictures, nor is it possible to make <hi rend="i">a priori</hi> inferences about relationships between text and picture based on the critical (i.e., Bentley’s) belief that Blake moved from illustration to illumination in his later career (143).</p>
            <p>Hagstrum, Jean H.<lb/>
“Babylon Revisited, or the Story of Luvah and Vala.” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on</hi> The Four Zoas, Milton, Jerusalem. Ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1973. 101-18.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Much of Hagstrum’s discussion focuses on Luvah and Vala, who appear together mostly (indeed, almost exclusively) in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn, and Brian Wilkie<lb/>
“On Reading <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Inscape and Analogy.” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on</hi> The Four Zoas, Milton, Jerusalem. Ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1973. 203-32.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Marshall, Jerry<lb/>
“A Jungian Analysis of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Thesis.” Master’s thesis. Appalachian State U, 1973.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D.<lb/>
“The Figure of the Garment in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on</hi> The Four Zoas, Milton, Jerusalem. Ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1973. 119-39.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1974</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Gibb, Peter Lloyd<lb/>
“From Satire to Apocalypse in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. U of British Columbia, 1974.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <pb id="p41-108" n="108"/>
            <p>Hamilton, Lee T.<lb/>
“Energy and Archetype: A Jungian Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> by William Blake.” Master’s thesis. North Texas State U, 1974.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Lento, Thomas V.<lb/>
“The Epic Consciousness in Four Romantic and Modern Epics by Blake, Byron, Eliot, and Hart Crane.” Diss. U of Iowa, 1974.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Includes a chapter on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Mellor, Anne Kostelanetz<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Human Form Divine.</hi> Berkeley: U of California P, 1974.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 5 (165-213) is on “<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Blake’s Concept of Form, 1795-1810.”</p>
            <p>Phillips, Quitman E.<lb/>
“William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: His Vision of Artistic Growth and Purpose.” BA honors thesis. Harvard U, 1974.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Sanders, Jon Barry<lb/>
“The Desire of Man: A Reading of Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. U of Oregon, 1974.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Schotz, Myra Glazer<lb/>
“The Altering Eye: William Blake and the Art of Parallax, an Approach to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. Brandeis U, 1974.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1975</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>DiSalvo, Jackie<lb/>
“Blake Encountering Milton: Politics and the Family in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Milton and the Line of Vision.</hi> Ed. Joseph Anthony Wittreich. Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1975. 143-84.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Kaplan, Nancy A.<lb/>
“William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Rhetoric of Vision.” Diss. Cornell U, 1975.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Kobayashi, Keiko<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>—Blake ni okeru shisoteki hensen [<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>—The Development of Blake’s Thought].” <hi rend="i">Osaka Daigaku Daigakuin Eibungaku Danwakai: Osaka Literary Review</hi> no. 14 (1975): 14-26.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, A. W. J.<lb/>
“A History of the Composition of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as Revealed by a Study of the Surviving Manuscript.” Diss. U of Wales, Bangor, 1975.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Nurmi, Martin K.<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> London: Hutchinson &amp; Co., 1975.</p>
            <p>Category: Biography</p>
            <p>Ch. 7 (119-45) is on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Starer, Robert<lb/><hi rend="i">Images of Man.</hi> For soprano, mezzo-soprano, tenor, and baritone soloists, mixed chorus, flute (piccolo), horn, cello, harp, and percussion. Melville: MCA Music, 1975.</p>
            <p>Category: Musical score</p>
            <p>The music is accompanied by selected text from Blake’s poem.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“‘The Four Zoas,’ Night the Third no bunseki: Zoa-Emanation kankei no kaifuku e no mosaku [An Analysis of ‘The Four Zoas,’ Night the Third—A Search for the Restoration of the Zoa-Emanation Relationship].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 18 (1975): 40-48.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1976</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Benzel, Michael Arnold<lb/>
“Vision and Revision in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Evidence of the Manuscript.” Diss. U of Toledo, 1976.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Bullard, William Fleming<lb/>
“Embodied Semblances: A Comparative Study of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and D. H. Lawrence’s <hi rend="i">The Rainbow.</hi>” Diss. Boston College, 1976.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Gallant, Christine Condit<lb/>
“Regeneration through Archetype: William Blake’s Changing Myth in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. U of Minnesota, 1976.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Lindsay, D.<lb/>
“The Resurrection of Man: A Short Commentary on Night Nine of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">UCT Studies in English</hi> 6 (1976): 14-23.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <pb id="p41-109" n="109"/>
            <p>McClellan, Jane Martha<lb/>
“William Blake’s Concept of Man in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Diss. Florida State U, 1976.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Sugnet, Charles J.<lb/>
“The Role of Christ in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi> 3.2 (1976): 167-80.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1977</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ault, Donald<lb/>
“Incommensurability and Interconnection in Blake’s Anti-Newtonian Text.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 16 (1977): 277-303.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>This essay was reprinted in <hi rend="i">Essential Articles for the Study of William Blake, 1970-1984</hi>, ed. Nelson Hilton (Hamden: Archon Books, 1986) 141-73.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake Books: Annotated Catalogues of William Blake’s Writings in Illuminated Printing, in Conventional Typography and in Manuscript, and Reprints Thereof, Reproductions of His Designs, Books with His Engravings, Catalogues, Books He Owned, and Scholarly and Critical Works about Him.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>Bentley provides bibliographical information on the manuscript (along with practically all of Blake’s other “books” in various genres), which is also contained in Bentley’s earlier facsimile edition (1963).</p>
            <p>Bidney, Martin<lb/>
“Urizen and the Comedy of Automatism in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 56 (1977): 204-20.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>DiSalvo, Jacqueline Anne<lb/>
“War of Titans: Blake’s Confrontation with Milton; <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as Political Critique of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and the Genesis Tradition.” Diss. U of Wisconsin-Madison, 1977.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Lemieux, Gerard Alfred<lb/>
“The Mantle of Mystery: Its Growth from <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. Southern Illinois U, Carbondale, 1977.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Myers, Victoria<lb/>
“The Dialogue as Interpretive Focus in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 56 (1977): 221-39.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ostriker, Alicia, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> Penguin English Poets. Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1977.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Ostriker approaches editing Blake in a manner similar to Stevenson (1971), using Erdman’s 1970 <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose</hi> as the basis for her own edition. However, she turns to Keynes as an additional editorial model, especially when it comes to the arrangement and handling of Blake’s writings: she uses a similar set of editorial symbols in the text to represent Blake’s revisions. Highly attuned to the need for editorial precision, she is careful to distinguish Blake’s printed poems from his manuscript texts. She is equally aware, however, of the difficulties Blake’s poetry presents to readers, and so offers interpretive and explanatory notes in the back of her edition, along with a dictionary for various names, places, etc. A reprint of this edition, without revision, was published in 2004.</p>
            <p>Paananen, Victor N.<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Boston: Twayne Publishers, 1977.</p>
            <p>Category: Biography</p>
            <p>Ch. 8 (88-112) is on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Schotz, Myra Glazer<lb/>
“On the Frontispiece of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 10.4 (spring 1977): 126-27.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“‘The Four Zoas,’ Night the Fourth no bunseki: Enion no kaifuku o mezasu Tharmas no saku [An Analysis of ‘The Four Zoas,’ Night the Fourth: Tharmas’s Attempts to Restore Enion].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 23 (1977): 27-34.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“On the Alliance of Tharmas and Urizen in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Clue to the Role of Tharmas.” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 24 (1977): 1-16.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1978</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1978.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>For his text of “<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>”, Bentley uses a revised version of the transcription from his 1963 facsimile. Particularly noteworthy is that in this edition, Bentley has gone further than mere transcription by adding editorial punctuation and revising portions of text (with or without Blake’s directions)—all along with a version of the revision symbols in the text that appeared in the 1963 transcription. Added to many,
<pb id="p41-110" n="110"/>
and often extensive, footnotes, Bentley’s is a heavily compacted bibliographical version of the manuscript text.</p>
            <p>Brisman, Leslie<lb/><hi rend="i">Romantic Origins.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1978.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 6 (224-75), “Re: Generation in Blake,” includes a section on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> It was partially reprinted as “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: First Things” in <hi rend="i">Modern Critical Views: William Blake</hi>, ed. Harold Bloom (New York: Chelsea House Publishers, 1985) 145-57.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V.<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: New Text for Pages 5, 6, and 7, Night the First.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 96-99.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Erdman adopts Lincoln’s hypothesis (see below) about the text on these pages in relation to the fragments (pp. 143-44) and thus revises his edition text.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V.<lb/>
“Night the Seventh: The Editorial Problem.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 135-39.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Erdman adopts the solution to the Nights VII problem proposed by Mark Lefebvre (see below) and thus revises his edition text, conflating Nights VIIa and VIIb.</p>
            <p>Gallant, Christine<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1978.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Focuses on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> from the interpretive perspective of Jungian psychology.</p>
            <p>Glausser, Wayne Edward<lb/>
“Blake and the Daughters of Memory.” Diss. Yale U, 1978.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Glausser focuses on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> See also his article on a similar topic solely on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1985).</p>
            <p>Hilton, Nelson<lb/>
“The Sweet Science of Atmospheres in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 80-86.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Hirst, Désirée, and G. M. Matthews<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Long Poems.</hi> London: Audio Learning, 1978.</p>
            <p>Category: Sound recording</p>
            <p>Hirst and Matthews provide instructional material on this recording. Track A is entitled “Some Difficulties of Approach: <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Considered.”</p>
            <p>Hoagwood, Terence Allan<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and ‘The Philosophick Cabbala.’” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 87-90.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Kilgore, John<lb/>
“The Order of Nights VIIa and VIIb in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 107-13.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Kilgore points out two (overlapping) aspects of the “scholarly puzzle” of two Nights VII: 1) “the editorial problem of finding the least imperfect arrangement of the two Nights within the text of the poem”; and 2) “the interpretive problem of deciding what imaginative place each Night has in the poem as a whole” (107). He then argues for the conflation of Nights VIIa and VIIb based upon a supposed better “fit,” ignoring Blake’s directions to reorder VIIb but inserting it, in the original order, into VIIa at that Night’s original ending on p. 85.</p>
            <p>Lefebvre, Mark<lb/>
“A Note on the Structural Necessity of Night VIIb.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 134.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Lefebvre argues for the conflation of Nights VIIa and VIIb based upon better “fit”: follow Blake’s instructions for reordering VIIb and insert it into Night VIIa at that Night’s original ending on p. 85. This is the proposal that Erdman adopts and implements in his 1982 edition text.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Text of Pages 5, 6, and 7, Night the First.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 91-95.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Lincoln argues against Bentley’s view that text found on the fragments (pp. 143-44) represents later versions of corresponding text in Night I, returning instead to the previous opinion that the fragmentary text is earlier material. Erdman agrees and revises his text in the 1982 edition.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew<lb/>
“The Revision of the Seventh and Eighth Nights of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 114-33.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>In this article, Lincoln offers “a textual arrangement which will allow the two Nights [VII] to be read as a single and reasonably coherent narrative” (115). Since Blake left VIIb in the manuscript, Lincoln says that he was never committed to excluding it and feels that a coherent order can be formed by inserting all of VIIa between the transposed halves of VIIb (132).</p>
            <pb id="p41-111" n="111"/>
            <p>Lindsay, David W.<lb/>
“Prelude to Apocalypse: A Short Commentary on Night VIII of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> 70 (1978): 179-85.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Magno, Cettina<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> for Italy.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12.2 (fall 1978): 140-41.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Naschak, Bruce Stephen<lb/>
“William Blake and the Tradition of Inspired Poetry.” Master’s thesis. San Diego State U, 1978.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Naschak focuses on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in particular.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Fifth no bunseki—saikuru no aratana kaiten [An Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Fifth—A New Revolution of the Cycle].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 25 (1978): 131-37.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Four Zoas: <hi rend="i">The Design of a Dream.</hi> Cambridge: Harvard UP, 1978.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>The first monograph devoted entirely to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Wilkie and Johnson’s interpretation is based on their “basic premise about the poem’s firmness of meaning and its subtle but demonstrable coherence” (ix). Their case for this reading “rests mainly on internal evidence: the pattern of meaning, imagery, structure, and story that emerges when one reads the poem closely” (xiv). In their view, much of the difficulty of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> arises from its forbiddingly complex, non-contextualized verbal texture, which reflects how “Blake was trying something more than either ordinary discursive communication or (which is less obvious) other kinds of mythic or allegorical narrative” (2).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1979</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Kilgore, John Dodge<lb/>
“The Human Universal: Studies in the Structure of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. U of California, Irvine, 1979.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Murphy, Karleen Middleton<lb/>
“The Emanations of the Four Zoas: Ahania, Enion, Vala, Enitharmon.” Diss. U of Toledo, 1979.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1980</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Banerjee, Tilak<lb/>
“Pope’s Epic and the Hebraic Tradition from Thomson to Blake.” Diss. York U, 1980.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Includes a chapter on Blake and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (“Blake and the Prophet Hero”).</p>
            <p>Imamura, Yukiko<lb/>
“A Study of the Variant Versions of the Fall of Man in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. Kent State U, 1980.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>MacLean, R. L.<lb/>
“William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Consideration of the Text, Critical Estimates, Literary Background and Relationship to Blake’s Other Work, Together with a Reading of the Poem.” Diss. U of Edinburgh, 1980.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Mann, Paul<lb/>
“A Preface to William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. U of California, Santa Cruz, 1980.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Because “perception constitutes a world” in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and in the same sense “criticism would constitute (and not merely explain) a text,” Mann believes that “one’s task as a reader” of Blake’s work “is . . ., and in larger part than one might at first assume, to come to terms with the structures and goals of criticism itself” (iv).</p>
            <p>Okuma, Akinobu<lb/>
“Blake no ‘yottsu no Zoas’—genshi no seisei shigaku: Blake’s ‘The Four Zoas’—The Generative Poetics of Vision.” <hi rend="i">Kenkyu Kiyo, Saga Daigaku Kyoyobu: Journal of the Faculty of Liberal Arts, Saga University</hi> no. 12 (1980): 19-72.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Sixth no bunseki—Urthona no dokutsu [An Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Sixth—Urthona’s Cave].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 30 (1980): 1-7.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1981</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Butlin, Martin<lb/><hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. Studies in British Art. New Haven: Yale UP, 1981.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <pb id="p41-112" n="112"/>
            <p>Butlin gives very brief descriptions of sketches and other illustrations on the manuscript pages.</p>
            <p>Ginsberg, Allen<lb/><hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century Poetry—Allen Ginsberg.</hi> Boulder: Naropa Institute, 29 October 1981; 3, 5, 10 November 1981.</p>
            <p>Category: Sound recording</p>
            <p>These are recordings of Ginsberg lectures (individual dates each on its own cassette tape) focusing on, or dealing extensively with, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, as well as other works (in relation to this work and otherwise).</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew<lb/>
“Blake’s Lower Paradise: The Pastoral Passage in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 84 (1981): 470-78.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Mann, Paul<lb/>
“Editing <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Pacific Coast Philology</hi> 16.1 (1981): 49-56.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Mann discusses the resistance of Blake’s manuscript to (traditional) editing. According to Mann, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is “unfinished,” which “makes life hard for the editor, who believes he must produce a text as close to the author’s final intentions as possible” (50).</p>
            <p>Singh, Gurbhagat<lb/>
“Lacan, Lévi-Strauss and William Blake: A Note on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Literary Criterion</hi> 16.2 (1981): 56-65.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Starling, Roy<lb/>
“The Ellis and Yeats Edition of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>: Text and Commentary.” Diss. Florida State U, 1981.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Tsuchiya, Shigeko<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> dai nanaya—futatsu no bijon [<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night Seven—On the Two Visions].” <hi rend="i">Albion: Albion</hi> ns no. 27 (1981): 42-59.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Yoshihara, Fumio<lb/>
“‘Yogensho’ ni okeru enkan shinborizumu—<hi rend="i">Yottu no Zoas</hi> ni tsuite: Cycle Symbolism in the Prophetic Books—Part 2, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Gengo Bunka Ronshu, Nagoya Daigaku Sogo gengo Senta: Studies in Language and Culture, Language Center, Nagoya University</hi> no. 2 (1981): 59-73.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1982</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ackland, Michael<lb/>
“The Embattled Sexes: Blake’s Debt to Wollstonecraft in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 16.3 (winter 1982-83): 172-83.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> With commentary by Harold Bloom. Rev. ed. Berkeley: U of California P, 1982.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>This “complete” edition by Erdman derives from his first edition, <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose</hi> (1965), now including newly discovered texts and additional material. Of particular importance are Erdman’s two major revisions to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> text: his de-conflation of the text on pp. 7-8 and 143-44 and his conflation of Nights VIIa and VIIb into one “Night the Seventh” (following the discussion in the fall 1978 issue of <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>). A “newly revised” version of this 1982 edition was published in paperback in 1988 by Anchor-Doubleday; the only change to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> text is Erdman’s page numbering, which he alters in order to coincide with the pagination in his and Magno’s 1987 facsimile edition.</p>
            <p>Ide, Nancy Marie<lb/>
“Patterns of Imagery in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. Pennsylvania State U, 1982.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Loudon, Michael Douglas<lb/>
“The Story in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Guide to the Events of the Epic.” Diss. State U of New York at Buffalo, 1982.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Punter, David<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel and Dialectic.</hi> Amsterdam: Rodopi, 1982.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 4 (170-209) is on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, with the following sections: “Abstract and Concrete,” “The Fragmentation of Consciousness,” and “Mind and Body.”</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Eighth no bunseki [An Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Eighth].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 34 (1982): 1-9.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night VII (a) no bunseki—Los no jikohenkaku [An Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night VII
<pb id="p41-113" n="113"/>
(a)—Self-Reformation of Los].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 33 (1982): 37-45.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Whitehead, Fred<lb/>
“Visions of the Archaic World.” <hi rend="i">Sparks of Fire: Blake in a New Age.</hi> Ed. James Bogan and Fred Goss. Richmond: North Atlantic Books, 1982. 231-43.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“An attempt to ‘reconstruct . . . [<hi rend="i">Vala’s</hi>] plot by collecting and analyzing passages scattered throughout the ms’ [p. 232]” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> 419).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1983</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ackland, Michael<lb/>
“Blake’s Critique of Enlightenment Reason in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 19 (1983): 173-89.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Blondel, Jacques, ed. and trans.<lb/>
Vala, <hi rend="i">ou</hi>, Les Quatre Vivants; <hi rend="i">Annotations à divers ouvrages.</hi> Oeuvres de William Blake 4. Paris: Aubier-Flammarion, 1983.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>An edition (?) of the poem including both English and French text.</p>
            <p>Brown, James Boyd<lb/>
“The History of an Illusion: The Meaning of the Four Zoas in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. York U, 1983.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Cushing, James Byers<lb/>
“The Figure of the Poet: Self-Representation in Young, Blake, and Wordsworth.” Diss. U of California, Irvine, 1983.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Includes a chapter on Blake and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Deen, Leonard W.<lb/><hi rend="i">Conversing in Paradise: Poetic Genius and Identity-as-Community in Blake’s Los.</hi> Columbia: U of Missouri P, 1983.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 5 (123-65), “Priest and Poet, Serpent and Human Form, in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”</p>
            <p>DiSalvo, Jackie<lb/><hi rend="i">War of Titans: Blake’s Critique of Milton and the Politics of Religion.</hi> Pittsburgh: U of Pittsburgh P, 1983.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>DiSalvo deals extensively with <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in this book, the published version of her dissertation (1977).</p>
            <p>Dowdey, London, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas: The Torments of Love and Jealousy in the Death and Judgment of Albion the Ancient Man by William Blake.</hi> Chicago: Swallow P, 1983.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Dowdey’s “edition,” if one can use that word in its commonly understood sense, is a highly personal, unusual, and therefore compelling version of Blake’s manuscript. The prose translation of Blake’s (mostly) poetic text and the inclusion of Blakean illustrations from various other works—early and late, illuminated and not—most immediately distinguish Dowdey’s production, inspired in and by the spirit of Blake as poet and illuminator. Further, Dowdey at first takes a markedly anti-scholarly stance and encourages his readers to worry less about understanding what Blake says than about letting Blake’s vision inspire their own visions as they read and behold. Yet, in the accompanying appendices, Dowdey presents explanatory notes and other ancillary material that could have come directly from a traditional scholarly edition. All together, Dowdey’s illuminated text and its apparatus reveal the extent to which Dowdey has approached Blake in the spirit that Blake approached Milton, enacting, as it were, Blake’s citation on the title plate of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: “Would to God that all the Lords people were Prophets.”</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V.<lb/>
“Redefining the Texts of Blake (Another Temporary Report).” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17.1 (summer 1983): 4-15.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>Erdman’s corrections and changes to his text of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (as reflected in his 1982 edition) are on 7-8.</p>
            <p>Himy, Armand<lb/>
“Un Symbole de Blake: <hi rend="i">Le Sparagmos.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Bulletin de la Société d’Études Anglo-Américaines des XVIIe et XVIIIe Siècles</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Society of Seventeenth and Eighteenth-Century Anglo-American Studies</hi>] 16 (June 1983): 89-107.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In French.</p>
            <p>Lee, Judith<lb/>
“Ways of Their Own: The Emanations in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 50 (1983): 131-53.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Storch, Margaret<lb/>
“The ‘Spectrous Fiend’ Cast Out: Blake’s Crisis at Felpham.” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 44 (1983): 115-35.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>On <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi></p>
            <pb id="p41-114" n="114"/>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth no bunseki—keiji no joju [An Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth—Accomplishment of Revolution].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 35 (1983): 41-50.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Seventh (b) no bunseki—Vala no honsho [An Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Seventh (b)—The Nature of Vala].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 36 (1983): 29-36.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Webster, Brenda S.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology.</hi> Athens: U of Georgia P, 1983.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 6 (203-49) is on “<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1984</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Howard, John<lb/><hi rend="i">Infernal Poetics: Poetic Structures in Blake’s Lambeth Prophecies.</hi> Rutherford: Fairleigh Dickinson UP, 1984.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 11 (206-27), “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Epic Prophecy.”</p>
            <p>Kilgore, John<lb/>
“On Reading <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Some Basic Principles.” <hi rend="i">Yongo Yongmunhak</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and Literature</hi>] 30 (1984): 687-99.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Lagomarcino, Leslie Karen<lb/>
“Apocalyptic Art and William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: ‘Night the Ninth.’” Master’s thesis. U of Virginia, 1984.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Whitmarsh-Knight, David Edward<lb/>
“Structure as a Key to Meaning in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. U of New Brunswick, 1984.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1985</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Blanchard, George A.<lb/>
“Threefold Vision as Structural Vehicle in William Blake’s ‘The Four Zoas.’” Master’s thesis. George Mason U, 1985.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N.<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Intention and Production.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18.4 (spring 1985): 216-20.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>For Essick, the physical condition of the manuscript, with its deletions, erasures, marginal insertions, and designs, “immediately suggests” that it is “the signifier of an unrealized intention to produce the poem in some other form” (216). Especially helpful are his proposed three stages of manuscript composition/revision: “(1) a manuscript and production mockup for a poem (<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>?) intended for publication of text and designs as intaglio etchings/engravings . . ., tentatively dated c. 1796-1800; (2) a manuscript and production mockup for a poem (<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>?) intended for publication as a letterpress text accompanied by intaglio etched and/or engraved designs surrounding selected pages of text . . ., tentatively dated c. 1800-1804; (3) a working manuscript unrelated to any specific publication intentions (i.e., <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript as we know it today), tentatively dated c. 1804-1807” (219).</p>
            <p>Glausser, Wayne<lb/>
“The Gates of Memory in Night VIIa of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18.4 (spring 1985): 196-203.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Gori, Michela<lb/>
“Dalla visione al mito: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> di William Blake [From Vision to Myth: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> of William Blake].” Diss. U of Florence, 1985.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Italian.</p>
            <p>Kamusikiri, Sandra Darlene<lb/>
“‘A Building of Magnificence’: Blake’s Major Prophecies and Eighteenth-Century Conceptions of the Human Sublime.” Diss. U of California, Riverside, 1985.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Mann, Paul<lb/>
“The Final State of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18.4 (spring 1985): 204-15.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Mann’s purpose in considering Blake’s possible intentions for <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is to offer his view that “Blake might have been experimenting with a compromise between his customary copperplate methods and the strictures of commercial publishing, a more conventional means of production which could enable him to reach a wider audience than his copperplate method permitted.” Thus, if Mann’s theory is correct, “we would have to revise our sense of Blake’s project as an absolute rejection of normal publishing practice” (204). Particularly provocative is his suggestion that Blake may have received additional <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> copperplates from Edwards and used them for other purposes.</p>
            <p>Otomo, Mikaeru<lb/>
“William Blake no ‘Yonin no Zoas’ ni okeru chikara no byoshutsu ni tsuite: Description of Power in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi><pb id="p41-115" n="115"/>
or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dohto Daigaku Kiyo, Kyoyobu: Bulletin of Dohto University, General Education</hi> no. 4 (1985): 11-20.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> dai nanaya ni kansuru shomondai to doko [Issues and Trends in Recent Criticism of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night the Seventh].” <hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Reitaku University Bulletin</hi>] 39 (1985): 85-96.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Tsuchiya, Shigeko<lb/><hi rend="i">Bijon no hizumi: Blake no ‘Yonin no Zoa’</hi> [<hi rend="i">His Twisted Vision: Blake’s ‘Four Zoas’</hi>]. Kyoto, 1985.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1986</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ault, Donald<lb/>
“Re-Visioning <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality.</hi> Ed. Nelson Hilton and Thomas A. Vogler. Berkeley: U of California P, 1986. 105-39.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Berger, Susan<lb/>
“William Blake’s Perception of the Human Mind.” Master’s thesis. U of Iowa, 1986.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Deals with <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas and Jerusalem.</hi></p>
            <p>Erdman, David V.<lb/>
“Improving the Text of <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20.2 (fall 1986): 49-52.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Another report and errata list by Erdman for his edition; the corrections and changes to his <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> text are on 50.</p>
            <p>Ide, Nancy M.<lb/>
“Patterns of Imagery in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Méthodes quantitatives et informatiques dans l’étude des textes/Computers in Literary and Linguistic Research: En hommage à Charles Muller.</hi> Ed. Étienne Brunet. 2 vols. Travaux de linguistique quantitative 35. Geneva: Slatkine, 1986. 2: 495-505.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Lee, Judith<lb/>
“Scornful Beauty: A Note on Blake and Ariosto.” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 23.4 (1986): 34-38.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Lee discusses the influence of Ariosto’s <hi rend="i">Orlando furioso</hi> on Blake’s epic.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew<lb/>
“Blake and the Natural History of Creation.” <hi rend="i">Essays and Studies</hi> 39 (1986): 94-103.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Lincoln deals with <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and relationships to Milton—<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> in particular.</p>
            <p>Matsushima, Shoichi<lb/>
“Blake no ‘Yon Zoas’ [Blake’s ‘Four Zoas’].” <hi rend="i">Walpurgis ‘86, Kokugakuin Daigaku Gaikokugo Kenkyushitsu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Walpurgis ‘86, Periodical of Kokugakuin University</hi>] (1986): 35-47.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Otomo, Mikaeru<lb/>
“‘The Four Zoas’ no chikara no tokushitsu ni tsuite: Some Features of the Power in ‘The Four Zoas.’” <hi rend="i">Hokkaido Eigoeibungaku: English Literature in Hokkaido</hi> 31 (1986): 1-9.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Watanabe, Mitsuru<lb/>
“Senteki sekai kara mozaikuteki sekai e—‘yottu no Zoa’ to Blake no jikan [From a World of Line to One of Mosaic—‘The Four Zoas’ and Blake’s Time].” <hi rend="i">Osaka Daigaku Daigakuin Eibungaku Danwakai: Osaka Literary Review</hi> no. 25 (1986): 44-54.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1987</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ault, Donald<lb/><hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound: Re-Visioning Blake’s</hi> The Four Zoas. Barrytown: Station Hill P, 1987.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ault’s monumental (and quite forbidding) study is a “relentless interrogation of similarities and differences, of anomalous exclusions and inclusions, [that] emphasizes the positive function of a large number of textual details that have been previously disregarded by critics because these details 1) have been assumed to result from the ‘unfinished’ manuscript state of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> or 2) have appeared to be anomalies or discrepancies that interfere with, even contradict, traditional models of poetic coherence” (xi). “The extent of the revisions and rearrangements of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> text indicates that its narrative difficulties are part and parcel of Blake’s compositional/philosophical situation, not an obfuscation of it” (xii), so that Ault takes all Blake’s revisions as strategic gestures or psychological/ontological revisions. As these comments suggest,
<pb id="p41-116" n="116"/>
Ault does not deal extensively with the composition of the manuscript text but instead treats it mostly as an organic whole (of sorts), any inconsistencies or problems arising from Blake’s revisions being interpreted as meaningful. Of particular importance are Ault’s discussions of Blake’s unique narrative techniques: “perspectival transformation,” “aspectual interconnection,” “text as flight,” and “text as pattern.” Equally interesting are Ault’s marginal comments—references, elucidations, counter-perspectives, etc.</p>
            <p>Bowman, Clay M.<lb/>
“The Divine Family in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Comparison of the Divine Family Motif in Blake and the Kabbalah.” Master’s thesis. U of Houston, 1987.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Dawson, P. M. S.<lb/>
“Blake and Providence: The Theodicy of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20.4 (spring 1987): 134-43.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Haigney, Catherine<lb/>
“Reply to Andrew Lincoln.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21.2 (fall 1987): 77.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>A reply to Lincoln’s fall 1987 response to “Vala’s Garden in Night the Ninth” (spring 1987).</p>
            <p>Haigney, Catherine<lb/>
“Vala’s Garden in Night the Ninth: Paradise Regained or Woman Bound?” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20.4 (spring 1987): 116-24.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ide, Nancy M.<lb/>
“Image Patterns and the Structure of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20.4 (spring 1987): 125-33.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Contrary to most critics, Ide finds the powerful effect of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> coming not only from the narrative, but also from the relationships and repetitions of key images, so that “individual images in the <hi rend="i">Zoas</hi> can be seen as isolatable conceptual elements with identifiable [traditional] connotations for most readers” (125). Ide identifies 196 “image categories” (listed on 126) and then uses a computer program to generate frequency distributions across the text for each category.</p>
            <p>Lewis, Linda Marlene<lb/>
“Titanic Rebellion: The Promethean Iconography of Milton, Blake and Shelley.” Diss. U of Nebraska-Lincoln, 1987.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Examines <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost, The Four Zoas</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi>, with a chapter devoted to each.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew<lb/>
“Vala’s Garden.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21.2 (fall 1987): 77.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>A response to Haigney’s spring 1987 article.</p>
            <p>Magno, Cettina Tramontano, and David V. Erdman, eds.<lb/>
The Four Zoas <hi rend="i">by William Blake: A Photographic Facsimile of the Manuscript with Commentary on the Illuminations.</hi> Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 1987.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Magno and Erdman provide a facsimile of the manuscript derived from infrared photographs, thus revealing a wealth of detail not available in Bentley’s 1963 facsimile, though, unlike Bentley’s, their reproductions are much reduced in size from the original. Still, Magno and Erdman’s reproductions reveal much that previously had not been visible (especially if used along with a magnifying glass!); their various tracings in the introduction are equally helpful in this regard, as are the few color reproductions they include. Before the facsimile itself, the editors provide extensive and often illuminating commentary on each page’s designs, focusing on the visual narrative with relevant references to the text. Part of this narrative depends on their reordering of manuscript pages to follow Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry and Prose</hi>, here executed visually with the manuscript reproductions.</p>
            <p>Otomo, Mikaeru<lb/>
“Blake, ‘The Four Zoas’ no sekai to entoropi no hosoku: The Cosmic View in Blake’s ‘The Four Zoas’ and the Entropy Law.” <hi rend="i">Higashi Nippon Gakuen Daigaku Kyoyobu Ronshu: Higashi Nippon Gakuen Journal of Liberal Arts and Science</hi> no. 13 (1987): 17-27.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter<lb/>
“Final States, Finished Forms, and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20.4 (spring 1987): 144-46.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Contrary to virtually all other critical views, Otto finds “cogent thematic and contextual reasons to entertain the possibility at least that when Blake finally stopped working on the manuscript he believed that the form taken by the work [at that time] was the only one that the subject matter could assume,” i.e., “the (unfinished) form of the work embodies the poem’s insights about the nature of the fallen world and of fallen perception” (144).</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter<lb/>
“The Spectrous Embrace, the Moment of Regeneration, and Those Two Seventh Nights.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 23 (1987): 135-43.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <pb id="p41-117" n="117"/>
            <p>Pierce, John Benjamin<lb/>
“Blake’s Writing of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Study of Textual Development.” Diss. U of Toronto, 1987.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>See Pierce’s monograph, <hi rend="i">Flexible Design</hi> (1998).</p>
            <p>Rosso, George Anthony, Jr.<lb/>
“Blake’s Prophetic Workshop: Narrative, History, Apocalypse in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. U of Maryland, 1987.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>See Rosso’s monograph with the same title (1993).</p>
            <p>Singh, Charu Sheel<lb/>
“The Hindu Contexts of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and Walt Whitman’s <hi rend="i">Song of Myself</hi>: A Study of Primal Man Archetype.” <hi rend="i">Journal of Literature and Aesthetics</hi> 1.4 (September 1987).</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Suzuki, Masashi<lb/>
“Senso to Uzumaki: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Ni Okeru Chikara [War and Vortex: Power in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Eibungaku Kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi>] 64.1 (1987): 3-18.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1988</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Brooks, Harold F.<lb/>
“Blake and Jung: Blake’s Myth of the Four Zoas and Jung’s Picture of the Psyche.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Critical Miscellany</hi> 1.1 (1988): 47-74.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Brooks deals with <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, along with <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, in his comparisons of Blake and Jung.</p>
            <p>Fuller, David<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Heroic Argument.</hi> London: Croom Helm, 1988.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Most of ch. 2 (88-161), “Creation and Redemption and Judgement,” is on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Ide, Nancy Marie<lb/>
“Identifying Semantic Patterns: Time Series and Fourier Analyses.” <hi rend="i">Revue Informatique et Statistique dans les Sciences Humaines</hi> [<hi rend="i">Computing and Statistical Review in the Humanities</hi>] 24 (1988): 193-200.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>“A study of ‘images of labor’ and ‘pastoral images’ in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is said to show that ‘the pattern of image distribution in the <hi rend="i">Zoas</hi> is both <hi rend="i">rhythmic</hi> and <hi rend="i">simple</hi>’” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> 519).</p>
            <p>Pierce, John B.<lb/>
“The Shifting Characterization of Tharmas and Enion in Pages 3-7 of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 22.3 (winter 1988-89): 93-102.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>This material reappears in Pierce’s <hi rend="i">Flexible Design</hi> (1998).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1989</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ando, Kiyoshi<lb/>
“The Textual Problems of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1).” <hi rend="i">Jinmon-Kagaku Ronshu</hi> 43 (1989): 21-47; Part 2, <hi rend="i">Jinmon-Kagaku Ronshu</hi> 44 (1989): 1-27; Part 3, “The Textual Problems of Pages 5 and 6 of the MSS [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Tokai English Review</hi> 2 (1990): 1-19; Part 4, <hi rend="i">Jinmon-Kagaku Ronshu</hi> 45 (1990): 13-46.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>In Japanese. “‘The . . . textual confusion of Night the First is to be the major theme of this serial study’ .... Part 3 ‘also tries to re-evaluate the existing texts of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>’ (p. 1). Part 4 is concerned with pp. 7, 143, with a new transcript of pp. 5-7, 143-4” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books Supplement</hi> 338).</p>
            <p>Ide, Nancy M.<lb/>
“Meaning and Method: Computer-Assisted Analysis of Blake.” <hi rend="i">Literary Computing and Literary Criticism: Theoretical and Practical Essays on Theme and Rhetoric.</hi> Ed. Rosanne Potter. Philadelphia: U of Pennsylvania P, 1989. 123-41.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ide, Nancy M.<lb/>
“A Statistical Measure of Theme and Structure.” <hi rend="i">Computers and the Humanities</hi> 23.4-5 (August-October 1989): 277-83.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Luening, Otto<lb/><hi rend="i">Lines from “The First Book of Urizen” and “Vala, or, A Dream of Nine Nights.”</hi> SATB a cappella. New York: C. F. Peters Corp., 1989.</p>
            <p>Category: Musical score</p>
            <p>The music is accompanied by selected text from the two Blake poems.</p>
            <p>Mann, Paul<lb/>
“Finishing Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 22.4 (spring 1989): 139-42.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Mann responds to Otto’s “Final States, Finished Forms” (1987) in this discussion article, followed by Otto’s reply.</p>
            <p>Naylor, Kathryn L.<lb/>
“Blake’s Quest for Unity in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. St. Cloud State U, 1989.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <pb id="p41-118" n="118"/>
            <p>Otto, Peter<lb/>
“Is There a Poem in This Manuscript?” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 22.4 (spring 1989): 142-44.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Otto’s response to Mann’s “Finishing Blake,” the preceding discussion article.</p>
            <p>Pierce, John B.<lb/>
“The Changing Mythic Structure of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Study of the Manuscript, Pages 43-84.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 68 (1989): 485-508.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Stevenson, W. H., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> 2nd ed. Longman Annotated English Poets. London: Longman Group UK Limited, 1989.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Revised version of the 1971 edition without significant changes to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Stevenson does give a nod to the textual discussion over Blake’s manuscript in the fall 1978 issue of <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, and Erdman’s subsequent editorial revisions, but does not alter his text to go along with the revised Erdman text. Indeed, in this edition, the text is no longer “By | David V. Erdman” as it was in 1971.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1990</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bidney, Martin<lb/>
“Urizen and Orc, Cortés and Guatimozin: Mexican History and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> VII.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 23.4 (spring 1990): 195-98.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Freeman, Kathryn Sue<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Apocalypse According to Blake’s Sleeper.” Diss. Yale U, 1990.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>See Freeman’s monograph, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Nostos</hi> (1997).</p>
            <p>Hubley, Emily, dir.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blakeball.</hi> 1988. Hubley Studios. Pyramid Film &amp; Video, 1990.</p>
            <p>Category: Film</p>
            <p>An animated film (originally produced in 1988) based on Blake’s poem. According to the abstract in the WorldCat citation, it “explores the world of poet and painter William Blake using a baseball game’s nine innings as a metaphor for the nine nights of Blake’s poem.”</p>
            <p>Ima-Izumi, Yoko<lb/>
“Blake ni okeru byoki to jyoshei: Pickering kohon to <hi rend="i">Yon Zoa</hi>: Illness and the Women in Blake’s Pickering Manuscript and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Bungeigengo Kenkyu, Bungei Hen, Tsukuba Daigaku, Bungei Gengogakukei: Studies in Language and Literature: Literature: Institute of Literature and Linguistics, University of Tsukuba</hi> 19 (1990): 29-56.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Rosso, G. A.<lb/>
“History and Apocalypse in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Final Nights.” <hi rend="i">Spirits of Fire: English Romantic Writers and Contemporary Historical Methods.</hi> Ed. G. A. Rosso and Daniel P. Watkins. Rutherford: Fairleigh Dickinson UP, 1990. 173-88.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Traylen, Maryanne<lb/>
“‘Sol’ and ‘Luna,’ ‘Burn in water and wash in fire’: Some Instances of Contraries at Work in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Four Zoas, Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the Light of Jung’s Thought and His Alchemical Understanding in <hi rend="i">Mysterium Coniunctionis.</hi>” Diss. U of Wales, Swansea, 1990.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1991</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bizzaro, Patrick<lb/>
“The Symbol of the Androgyne in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and Shelley’s <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi>: Marital Status among the Romantic Poets.” <hi rend="i">Joinings and Disjoinings: The Significance of Marital Status in Literature.</hi> Ed. JoAnna Stephens Mink and Janet Doubler Ward. Bowling Green: Bowling Green State U Popular P, 1991. 36-51.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>De Luca, Vincent Arthur<lb/><hi rend="i">Words of Eternity: Blake and the Poetics of the Sublime.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1991.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 4 (“Narrative Sequences: Modes of Organization”), section 2 (113-24), “Interpolation, or the Text as Palimpsest: The Example of <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi>”</p>
            <p>Hibino, Mami<lb/>
“Blake no shi ni okeru kyoki: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> kenkyu: Madness in Blake’s Poetry—A Study of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Machikane Yama Ronso: Bungaku hen: Osaka Daigaku Bungakubu:</hi> [<hi rend="i">Machikane Yama Bulletin</hi>]<hi rend="i">: Literature: Faculty of Letters, Osaka University</hi> no. 25 (1991): 1-15.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter<lb/>
“The Multiple Births of Los in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">SEL: Studies in English Literature, 1500-1900</hi> 31.4 (1991): 631-53.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>The material in this article reappears in ch. 5 of his <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence</hi> (2000).</p>
            <pb id="p41-119" n="119"/>
            <p>Yogev, Michael<lb/>
“Covenant of the Word: The Bible in William Blake’s Late Prophetic Poems.” Diss. U of Washington, 1991.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1992</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ando, Kiyoshi<lb/>
“[A Study of Blake’s Manuscript of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in the British Library].” <hi rend="i">Journal of Science of Culture and Humanities</hi> 49 (1992): 63-89.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <p>Bidlake, Steven<lb/>
“Blake, the Sacred, and the French Revolution: Eighteenth-Century Ideology and the Problem of Violence.” <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 3.1 (1992): 1-20.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Focuses on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Cox, Stephen<lb/><hi rend="i">Love and Logic: The Evolution of Blake’s Thought.</hi> Ann Arbor: U of Michigan P, 1992.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Cox covers <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in ch. 9 (167-81), “The Ruins of <hi rend="i">The Zoas</hi>,” and ch. 10 (183-203), “Love among the Ruins.”</p>
            <p>Kang, Sun Koo<lb/>
“William Blake Yi <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> [A Survey of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Yongo Yongmunhak</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and Literature</hi>] 38 (1992): 453-76.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Korean, with a summary in English.</p>
            <p>Mounsey, C. F.<lb/>
“William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: A Reassessment of Its Implied Metaphysics.” Diss. U of Warwick, 1992.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1993</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Georgelos, Peter<lb/>
“Mother Outline: A Critique of Gender in Blake’s Aesthetics and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. U of Western Ontario, 1993.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Hobson, Christopher Z.<lb/>
“Unbound from Wrath: Orc and Blake’s Crisis of Vision in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">SEL: Studies in English Literature, 1500-1900</hi> 33.4 (1993): 725-54.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Richey, William<lb/>
“‘One must be master’: Patronage in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi>” <hi rend="i">SEL: Studies in English Literature, 1500-1900</hi> 33.4 (1993): 705-24.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Rosso, George Anthony, Jr.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Workshop: A Study of</hi> The Four Zoas. Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>According to Rosso, Blake’s narrative technique in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is one of <hi rend="i">kerygma</hi>, which aims actively to engage its readers so as to induce vision and transform them. Further, Blake conflates traditions, and also internal subjectivity and political history, to emphasize that internal redemption must extend out into social redemption for a true apocalypse to occur. Rosso’s book, the published version of his dissertation (1987), is the first devoted to the manuscript that includes a close look at its composition history as part of an interpretation.</p>
            <p>Vine, Steven<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry: Spectral Visions.</hi> Basingstoke: Macmillan P; New York: St. Martin’s P, 1993.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 6 (96-126), “Excesses of Joy and Grief: The Veil, Sexuality and Apocalypse in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1994</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Cox, Philip<lb/>
“‘Among the Flocks of Tharmas’: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and the Pastoral of Commerce.” <hi rend="i">Historicizing Blake.</hi> Ed. Steve Clark and David Worrall. Basingstoke: Macmillan P; New York: St. Martin’s P, 1994. 86-104.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Kruger, Kathryn Sullivan<lb/>
“Weaving the Word: The Metaphorics of Weaving and Female Textual Production.” Diss. U of Miami, 1994.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>On Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, as well as Tennyson.</p>
            <p>Lansverk, Marvin D. L.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Wisdom of Many, the Vision of One: The Proverbs of William Blake.</hi> New York: P. Lang, 1994.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 7 (131-60), “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Blake’s Vision of Ecclesiastes.”</p>
            <p>Romero, Milena<lb/>
“The Fourfold Circle of Jerusalem.” <hi rend="i">Textus: English Studies in Italy</hi> 7 (1994): 23-40.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Romero’s article on the numerological and symbolic significance of Jerusalem covers both <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <pb id="p41-120" n="120"/>
            <p>Smith, Elizabeth Leigh<lb/>
“William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Romantic Poetry in the Epic Tradition.” Master’s thesis. U of Houston, 1994.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1995</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ando, Eiko<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Blake’s Jesus.” <hi rend="i">Centre and Circumference: Essays in English Romanticism.</hi> Ed. Kenkishi Kamijima and Yasuo Deguchi. Tokyo: Kirihara Shoten for the Association of English Romanticism in Japan, 1995. 114-26.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr.<lb/>
“A Fifth Zoa.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 17.1-2 (1995): 25-28.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Freeman, Kathryn S.<lb/>
“Narrative Fragmentation and Undifferentiated Consciousness in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">European Romantic Review</hi> 5.2 (1995): 178-92.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Freeman argues that in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake revises traditional dream-vision narrative techniques in order to represent his most challenging idea: the contemporaneity of Eternity and the fallen world that appears to have been divided from it. He accomplishes this by making the “dream” that of the single authorial consciousness itself, in which the fallen characters become the narrators at times in order to emphasize the vulnerabilities of the fallen mind projecting/creating them. Thus, textual inconsistencies are resolved by Night IX, where a continuous narrative of dawning reintegration exposes the fragmentary and delusional perceptions of a divided consciousness that are found in the previous Nights. By making every aspect of existence within the poem the creation of a single “sleeping” consciousness, Blake suggests that human divinity resists all attempts to divide the human from the divine. Most of the content of this article is included in Freeman’s 1997 monograph.</p>
            <p>Lincoln, Andrew<lb/><hi rend="i">Spiritual History: A Reading of William Blake’s</hi> Vala <hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1995.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Lincoln’s thesis is that Blake begins <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> with a reinterpretation of history using Enlightenment-era methods of philosophy, sociology, and theology. Through several stages of revision, he moves first towards a (revised) history of Jesus that allows for the casting off of error and for brotherhood, then towards a particularly nationalistic myth; it is at this point that he abandons the poem. Although the poem is complex, to judge it as a “ruin” is a critical recoiling from, rather than engaging with, these complexities. Lincoln bases his interpretation upon the growth of the manuscript as he believes it occurred.</p>
            <p>Suh, Kang Mok<lb/>
“William Eui Yeoksa Dasi Sseugi: <hi rend="i">Ne Zoa Deul</hi> Ggajieui Han Ilgi [William Blake’s Re-Writing of History: A Reading up to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>].” Diss. Seoul National U, 1995.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>I believe this work to be in Korean rather than English.</p>
            <p>Wada, A.<lb/>
“The Evolution of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala/The Four Zoas</hi>: Its Formation, Collapse and Regeneration.” Diss. Durham U, 1995.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1996</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Baulch, David Monroe<lb/>
“‘Forms Sublime’: William Blake’s Aesthetics of the Sublime in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Diss. U of Washington, 1996.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Brachfeld, Jennifer<lb/>
“The State of the Union: Bi-Gendered Redemption in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. Florida Atlantic U, 1996.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Csikós, Dóra<lb/>
“Is He the Divine Image? Blake’s Luvah and Vala.” <hi rend="i">AnaChronist</hi> (1996): 162-84.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Richey, William<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Altering Aesthetic.</hi> Columbia: U of Missouri P, 1996.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 3 (75-109), “The Rise and Fall of Blake’s Classicism: <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1997</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Csikós, Dóra<lb/>
“Narrative Techniques in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">AnaChronist</hi> (1997): 29-38.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Csikós, Dóra<lb/>
“‘Urizen Who Was Faith and Certainty Is Changed to Doubt’: The Changing Portrayal of Urizen.” <hi rend="i">Hungarian Journal of English and American Studies</hi> 3.2 (1997): 131-59.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <pb id="p41-121" n="121"/>
            <p>Freeman, Kathryn<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Nostos: Fragmentation and Nondualism in</hi> The Four Zoas. Albany: State U of New York P, 1997.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Developing her earlier (1995) article on this subject, Freeman here presents Blake as deliberately and meticulously crafting <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in order to give an entirely cognizant mythic representation, albeit complex, of the human consciousness. The dream within a dream within a dream structure is the vehicle for Blake to dramatize the fallacies of fallen/fragmented consciousness. This structure also allows Blake to portray the progressive movement from dualism, a state of complete externalization of the divine self that is all things, to non-dualistic wholeness, when the universe and God are recognized as being one’s true center. Thus, Blake is able to show that wholeness is an ever-present, underlying reality that is simply not recognized by the various parts of the one eternal consciousness. Like Blake’s myth, then, existence is a quest towards wholeness in which the quester and the goal are the same thing; the distinction is mere illusion. According to Freeman, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is a representation of that mind as it goes on its quest to itself, and the poem’s complexity dissolves due to the freedom to backread such a perspective gives: linearity of narrative structure, like time itself, is an illusion. Freeman’s is a psychological reading drawing extensively on Eastern and Western sources.</p>
            <p>James-Hansen, Jeanne A.<lb/>
“The Universal Female: Female Characters as Catalysts in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. South Dakota State U, 1997.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1998</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Pierce, John B.<lb/><hi rend="i">Flexible Design: Revisionary Poetics in Blake’s</hi> Vala <hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas. Montreal and Kingston: McGill-Queen’s UP, 1998.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Pierce’s “essential argument is that the synoptic and synchronic tendencies of Blake’s poetics are the result of conscious revision and correction of an essentially diachronic narrative” in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> (xvii-xviii). He particularly highlights Blake’s changing of the poem’s subtitle to “The torments of Love &amp; Jealousy” as applying to each set of characters and to Blake’s (late) method of analogous or syncretistic characterization that focuses on such “torments.” Pierce is consistently and helpfully attentive to the development of the manuscript as he presents his argument.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">1999</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Baulch, David M.<lb/>
“Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Hypertext and Multiple Plurality.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 30.3 (1999): 154-60.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>The fact that Blake created a “multiple plural” (or redundancy) by adding “s” to the already plural Greek “zoa” suggests two interpretive possibilities: “Either the multiple plural is bad Greek or the manuscript that follows embodies what its title grammatically implies, many sets of four zoas” (154). The manuscript has not yet benefited from a hypertext version, so that its editorial history is one of extracting a single, coherent narrative from the tangle of revisions—this has in turn largely influenced its interpretive history. However, such a Newtonian imposition of singularity is directly opposed by Blake’s counter-Newtonian theme, of which the multiple plurality of the “zoas” is an intrinsic part. In contrast, “hypertext can preserve the integrity of the manuscript of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as a total of its narrative possibilities,” since hypertext allows for asynchronous and non-linear relationships—the many possible worlds of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> that constitute it.</p>
            <p>Hobson, Christopher Z.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Chained Boy: Orc and Blake’s Idea of Revolution.</hi> Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 1999.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 4 (151-210), “Rethinking Social Agency in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” This chapter incorporates Hobson’s article “Unbound from Wrath” in <hi rend="i">SEL</hi> (1993).</p>
            <p>Kang, Ok-Sun<lb/>
[“A Study of the Image of Father in William Blake’s Poems: Focusing on <hi rend="i">The Songs of Experience</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”] <hi rend="i">Yongo Yongmunhak</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and Literature</hi>] 45 (1999): 117-36.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Korean, with a summary in English.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2000</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Hobson, Christopher Z.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake and Homosexuality.</hi> New York: Palgrave, 2000.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 3 is on “Homosexuality, Resistance, and Apocalypse: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence: Love, Jealousy, and the Sublime in</hi> The Four Zoas. Oxford: Oxford UP, 2000.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Otto argues that rather than urging sublime transcendence (whether through the invocation of a transcendent or of an immanent power) in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake hopes to thwart it. Part of that effort takes place as “the poem deconstructs dominant cultural forms (religion, commerce, science, art) in order to uncover their ‘real’ content (the suffering body of Albion)” (345). However, this necessary precursor to “step[ping] forward into a living Eternity rather than a bodiless heaven” does not actually occur in the poem. Blake’s critique involves a
<pb id="p41-122" n="122"/>
conversation with Swedenborg, Young, and Locke, in which the poem’s text speaks as/for the spirit and the illustrations speak as/for the body.</p>
            <p>Sturrock, June<lb/>
“Urizen as Ceres in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth.” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 38.1 (2000): 50-58.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Valentine, Stephen James<lb/>
“The Clod and the Pebble: An Adaptation of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Master’s thesis. U of Virginia, 2000.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2001</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Kang, Ok-Sun<lb/>
[“William Blake’s Prophetic Poems and His Social Consciousness: Focusing on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”] <hi rend="i">Yongo Yongmunhak</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of English Language and Literature</hi>] 47 (2001): 755-73.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Korean, with a summary in English.</p>
            <p>Kruger, Kathryn Sullivan<lb/><hi rend="i">Weaving the Word: The Metaphorics of Weaving and Female Textual Production.</hi> Selinsgrove: Susquehanna UP, 2001.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 4 is on “The Loom of Language and the Garment of Words in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” See also her dissertation with the same title (1994).</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter<lb/>
“A Pompous High Priest: Urizen’s Ancient Phallic Religion in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 35.1 (summer 2001): 4-22.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Otto’s article includes and expands upon material in his <hi rend="i">Blake’s Critique of Transcendence</hi> (2000).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2002</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Lussier, Mark<lb/>
“‘Rest before Labour’: The Pre-Text/s of Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Romanticism on the Net</hi> 27 (2002). &lt;http://www.erudit.org/revue/ron/2002/v/n27/006563ar.html&gt;.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter<lb/>
“From the Religious to the Psychological Sublime: The Fate of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William Blake in Honor of John E. Grant.</hi> Ed. Alexander S. Gourlay. West Cornwall: Locust Hill P, 2002. 225-62.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Otto, Peter<lb/>
“A Sublime Allegory: Blake, Blake Studies, and the Sublime.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 43 (2002): 61-84.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Otto devotes much of his discussion to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Pritchard, Gwyn<lb/><hi rend="i">Enitharmon.</hi> For mezzo-soprano and piano. 1973 (revised 1984-85). Birmingham: Camerata, 2002.</p>
            <p>Category: Musical score</p>
            <p>The music is accompanied by selected text from Blake’s poem.</p>
            <p>Risden, E. L.<lb/>
“William Blake and the Personal Epic Fantastic.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Fantastic in the Arts</hi> 12.4 (2002): 417-24.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Risden’s article examines Blake’s treatment of personal epiphany in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi></p>
            <p>So, Tat Sang<lb/>
“Eternal Death in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. U of Dallas, 2002.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2003</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ankarsjö, Magnus<lb/>
“‘Bring Me My Arrows of Desire’: Gender Utopia in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss. Göteborg U, 2003.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Baulch, David M.<lb/>
“Time, Narrative, and the Multiverse: Post-Newtonian Narrative in Borges’s <hi rend="i">The Garden of the Forking Paths</hi> and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Comparatist</hi> 27 (2003): 56-78.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Csikós, Dóra Janzer<lb/><hi rend="i">“Four Mighty Ones Are in Every Man”: The Development of the Fourfold in Blake.</hi> Philosophiae Doctores 15. Budapest: Akadémiai Kiadó, 2003.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Hoshino, Eriko<lb/>
“<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, moshikuwa <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> Dai Ichiya ni okeru Tharmas to Enion no Kankei no Hokai—Gnosis teki Kenchi kara [The Disruption of Relations between Tharmas and Enion in Night the First in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>—From a Viewpoint of Gnosis].” <hi rend="i">Saitama Junshin Joshi Tanki Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Saitama Junshin Women’s Junior College</hi>] 19 (2003): 89-95.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>In Japanese.</p>
            <pb id="p41-123" n="123"/>
            <p>Pierce, John B.<lb/><hi rend="i">The Wond’rous Art: William Blake and Writing.</hi> Madison: Fairleigh Dickinson UP, 2003.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Ch. 4 is on “<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and the Archaeology of Writing.”</p>
            <p>Ripley, Wayne C.<lb/>
“Erdman’s Pagination of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 36.4 (spring 2003): 140-43.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Ripley gives an extremely helpful tabulation of page numbers in Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry and Prose</hi> and the Magno-Erdman facsimile (1987), pointing out how problematic the editorial renumbering of manuscript pages ends up being for both the editors and readers (hence the need for a table of correspondences).</p>
            <p>Rutland, Laura Ellen<lb/>
“Hindrance, Act, and the Scapegoat: William Blake, Kenneth Burke, and the Rhetoric of Order.” Diss. U of Tennessee, 2003.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Covers Blake’s three epics.</p>
            <p>Weir, David<lb/><hi rend="i">Brahma in the West: William Blake and the Oriental Renaissance.</hi> Albany: State U of New York P, 2003.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Along with Weir’s sustained focus on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, appendix B is a “Synopsis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,” which, the author says, “is intended mainly for novice students who need a rough guide to the poem” (133).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2004</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ankarsjö, Magnus<lb/><hi rend="i">Bring Me My Arrows of Desire: Gender Utopia in Blake’s</hi> The Four Zoas. Gothenburg Studies in English 87. Göteborg: Göteborg U, 2004.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>This is the published version of Ankarsjö’s 2003 dissertation.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2005</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Beer, John<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake: A Literary Life.</hi> Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005.</p>
            <p>Category: Biography</p>
            <p>Ch. 8 (109-21), “‘Vala’ and the Fate of Narrative Epic,” is devoted to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>Feldman, Travis<lb/>
“The Contexts and Production of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Towards a Theory of the Manuscript.” Diss. U of Washington, 2005.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Serres, Nicholas Gorman<lb/>
“Soteriology in the Poetry of William Blake: The Turn from Fall to Salvation in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Master’s thesis. U of Montana, 2005.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Tambling, Jeremy<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Night Thoughts.</hi> Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Ch. 4 (71-96), “Night Dreams: <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck, Justin<lb/>
“Blake’s Four . . . ‘Zoa’s’?” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 38-43.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck suggests that the mark resembling an apostrophe above “Zoas” in Blake’s added title on the title page most likely is an intentional punctuation mark by Blake, so that editions should include it or editors should at least provide some commentary upon it.</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck, Justin<lb/>
“‘Tenderness &amp; Love Not Uninspird’: Blake’s Re-Vision of Sentimentalism in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.2 (fall 2005): 60-77.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>According to Van Kleeck, Blake (characteristically) both criticizes and adopts for adaptation some of the key features of sentimentalism as a literary and a cultural phenomenon. Of particular importance are sentimentalism’s gender stereotypes and divisions these create between and within the sexes, producing a social “system” further fragmenting the fragmented identity of the Universal Man Albion. Blake’s re-vision of sentimentalism replaces a weakened/weakening sentimentality with inspired vision, the catalyst for true apocalypse that reunites the divided sexes at the poem’s end.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2006</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Ankarsjö, Magnus<lb/>
“Blake’s Four ‘Zoas’!” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 189-90.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Ankarsjö responds to Van Kleeck’s suggestion in “Blake’s Four . . . ‘Zoa’s’?” (2005) about the possible title apostrophe; he argues that it is not a punctuation mark (based, in part, upon a comparison to other apostrophes in illuminated works).</p>
            <pb id="p41-124" n="124"/>
            <p>Ankarsjö, Magnus<lb/><hi rend="i">William Blake and Gender.</hi> Jefferson: McFarland &amp; Co., 2006.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Includes a chapter on “The Gender Utopia of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” See also his <hi rend="i">Bring Me My Arrows of Desire</hi> (2004).</p>
            <p>Michael, Jennifer Davis<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake and the City.</hi> Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 2006.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism</p>
            <p>Includes a chapter on “Prophetic Labor and Creation of Space: Lambeth and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”</p>
            <p>Słomczyński, Maciej, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">Czterej Zoa: męki miłowania i zazdrości, gdy umarł i był osądzony Albion pradawny człowiek.</hi> Arcydzieła Literatury Światowej. Kraków: Zielona Sowa, 2006.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>A translation of the poem in Polish.</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck, Justin<lb/>
“‘mark ye the points.’” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.4 (spring 2006): 190-91.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck replies to Ankarsjö’s response (“Blake’s Four ‘Zoas’!”) regarding the possible title apostrophe with counterarguments in support of his original claim.</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck, Justin Scott<lb/>
“The Veils of <hi rend="i">VALA</hi>: A Critical Survey of Full Editions of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> Manuscript.” Diss. U of Virginia, 2006.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>Van Kleeck undertakes the first review of all (textually and/or imagistically) complete editions of Blake’s manuscript, focusing in particular upon the ways each editorial persona (or personae) influences the nature of his/her edition, both for good and for bad. Van Kleeck is also interested in what he perceives to be a recurring editorial <hi rend="i">discordia concors</hi> between subjective interpretation and “objective” textual editing. This tense harmony, in his view, proves to be equally problematic and fruitful in its effect upon the nature of editions, thus making the edited versions of Blake’s work at once “veils” and tools for new insight.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">2007</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Stevenson, W. H., ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> 3rd ed. Longman Annotated English Poets. Harlow: Pearson Education Limited, 2007.</p>
            <p>Category: Edition</p>
            <p>Revised version of the 1971/1989 editions without significant changes to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, though other important changes have been made since the second edition, such as the inclusion of the prose tracts <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> and <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, as well as a rearrangement of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> to accord with Blake’s ordering of the later copies.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">No Date or Ongoing</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Anon.<lb/>
“‘The Four Zoas,’ by William Blake. Add. 39764.” <hi rend="i">British Library Manuscripts Catalogue.</hi> &lt;http:// www.bl.uk/catalogues/manuscripts/HITS0001. ASP?VPath=html/33520.htm&amp;Search=39764&amp;Highlight=F&gt;.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>Online catalogue entry for the manuscript in the British Library.</p>
            <p>Eaves, Morris, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, eds.<lb/><hi rend="i">The William Blake Archive.</hi> &lt;http://www.blakearchive.org&gt;.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>Includes an electronic version of Erdman’s text.</p>
            <p>Hilton, Nelson, ed.<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake Digital Text Project.</hi> &lt;http://www.english.uga.edu/wblake/homel.html&gt;.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>Includes an electronic version of Erdman’s text.</p>
            <p>Ruegg, F. William<lb/>
“Blake’s ‘The Four Zoas’ Fetishized: An Experimental Hypertext.” &lt;http://www.lcc.gatech.edu/~broglio/eromantic/blakefetish.nassr.html&gt;.</p>
            <p>Category: Other</p>
            <p>An online version of the manuscript of sorts, presenting only a few images of manuscript pages along with some critical (and other) commentary and additional material.</p>
            <p>Whitmarsh-Knight, David Edward<lb/>
“William Blake’s ‘The Four Zoas’ Explained.” &lt;http://www.thefourzoas.com&gt;.</p>
            <p>Category: Criticism (textual)</p>
            <p>This is an online publication by the author based on research for his dissertation of 1984, which focused on textual development along with interpretation. He states, “Because this research seems not to have been read or noted by scholars in the field, I have been asked frequently to make the research more generally available.” The site also includes a similar analysis of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p41-125" n="125"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title>REVIEWS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Jennifer Davis Michael. <hi rend="i">Blake and the City.</hi> Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press, 2006. 235 pp., 14 b&amp;w illus. $55.00/£31.95, hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Michael <name>Ferber</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>THIS interesting and perceptive if somewhat uneven book repays careful reading. Its subject, the various cities Blake dwelled in and on (London, Jerusalem, Babylon, and Golgonooza), is large and important enough to warrant a booklength study. It is attentive to details, accurate in paraphrasing, and lucid and unpretentious in manner. It interprets chastely, for the most part, keeping close to the texts: simply by collating two or three scattered passages it often illuminates them all. It is up to date with Blake scholarship, and courteously engages with it intermittently throughout. It could serve as an advanced introduction to Blake, for graduate students, say, beginning a serious study of him; indeed I think the chapter on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> contains one of the clearest and most useful brief guides to that nine- or tenfold mess of a poem. The book also offers much of interest to scholars, both in little observations about individual passages or citations of historical contexts and in larger, if sometimes questionable, frameworks for conceiving whole works. It consistently grinds no particular theoretical ax, though it submits to the hegemony of “text”; it cites Bachelard and de Certeau a few times, but Derrida, Foucault, and Lacan are refreshingly absent, even as absent presences.</p>
          <p>Michael’s introduction canvasses Blake’s uneasy place in the romantic canon, and distinguishes his view of nature from Wordsworth’s. The contrast between natural and artifical, between rural and urban, is not found in Blake, she argues, because “all human environments are constructed, be they urban or rural, and the idea of a pristine nature does not even exist outside the human mind” (18). (I would have dropped “the idea of,” for as it stands the second clause is tautological.) She does not distinguish between rural and wild, and so the unexceptionable claim that humans construct the rural environment leaks into the highly debatable claim that they construct nature. But of course Blake did not usually distinguish them either, as we see right from the start in the contradiction between the opening line of the “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (“Piping down the valleys wild”) and the frontispiece that shows a flock of sheep reconstructing the wild by removing the grass. “All that appears external,” Michael says, “is for Blake internal” (16). This seems about right, but one substantial thread running through this book is “the physical city” (21), the real London, about which Michael comes up with some interesting data, new to me at least, and we may wonder how well this gritty given London intersects with the idealist or constructed city. This is a deep problem in Blake, of course, not just for Michael. She seems to think Blake has worked it all out consistently, whereas I think Blake often conflates collective social construction (by “Albion,” for instance) and individual idealist projection, even leaving aside his extreme claim that the not-human or “nature” is in the end only a projection of a fallen state of a human mind. In general, while she helpfully contrasts Blake’s ideas with Wordsworth’s, Swift’s, or others’, she seems to think within Blake’s horizon of thought; he always has the last word. This sort of empathy or ventriloquism can be useful and encouraging, and I know how hard it is to resist sounding Blakean when one has devoted the time that it takes to feel capable of writing well about him, yet it tempts one to neglect or finesse his real difficulties and contradictions.</p>
          <p>The conclusion of the introduction is a good summary of Blake’s life in London, his eight residences and their neighborhoods, and how things were changing, “ever building, ever falling.” Each of the four chapters that follow centers on a work and a theme or approach. The first deals with some of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> a through a recasting of the pastoral mode into a kind of urban “communal space.” It reminds us that there were quite a few parks, fields, and other open areas inside greater London, if not the City proper, so Blake did not have to escape London to enjoy some of the delights of rural life; the parks break down the country/city dichotomy. Nor does he distance himself from that life in his poems, which seem more intimate and engaged than both traditional, and Wordsworthian, pastoral. Michael thinks “Spring,” “Laughing Song,” and “Ecchoing Green” have an urban setting (47), though surely that is not something that was likely to occur to readers, even Londoners, familiar with the pastoral genre, and it is not clear what difference it makes in how we read each poem. More telling, I think, is her point that “Holy Thursday” of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> seems to have both an urban setting, like its Innocence counterpart, and a rural one, with its invocation of “land” and “fields” and “thorns” (49). Anticipating her approach to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the final chapter, which she pursues with a vengeance, Michael argues that some late copies, with their “elaborate frames . . . outside the designs,” “draw attention to the created quality of this pastoral world” (40-41) within a city. Her comments on several of the poems are often subtle and well worth pondering, though occasionally I was left unconvinced. In the “Introduction,” she writes, “the song appears to ‘fall’ from pure music to written text,” though the shift “reverses itself” as the song is offered to every child (43). Why “fall”? Is this still the effect of Edward Said’s mistake in <hi rend="i">Beginnings</hi> that “I stain’d the water clear” describes a fall, a metaphysical or spiritual stain, as if there were some purer way to make ink? She seems to want every conceivable meaning of “mark” to be operative in “London,” including “make a mark,” and allows the marks in both Ezekiel and Revelation to be part of the background of the poem, though I would have thought them mutually exclusive. But these are minor distractions from much that is rich and interesting.</p>
          <pb id="p41-126" n="126"/>
          <p>Her second chapter, on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, moves, as she says, from pastoral to georgic, being concerned with labor, the aesthetic labor of building Golgonooza and the degraded or enslaved labor of building the real London in time of war. I found this the most satisfying chapter, though perhaps the least ambitious or experimental in approach, both because its theme is so central to the poem and because, as I said, it includes a helpful tour of the poem. Chapter 3 argues that in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> the city appears more as an organism or body than as a construction of labor, while organic nature is described as works of art. It includes a brief history of organic metaphors for the city, mainly of the “body politic” sort, and some good remarks on just what “body” and “organic” mean in Blake’s usage. The final chapter, on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, dwells on the textuality of the city, and the difficulty of reading the multitude of signs in the real London as well as (and in much the same way as) in the composite text-and-designs of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> It includes a longish discussion of what Wordsworth says about London in <hi rend="i">The Prelude.</hi></p>
          <p>Let me say in passing that, given the intractable problem of writing usefully about Blake’s three long poems in fewer than 200 pages, Michael acquits herself surprisingly well. Neither <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> nor the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> chapter deals much with the main plots (hard to discern in the latter, in any case) nor the themes of love, jealousy, self-sacrifice, and brotherhood; while at times I was thus left a little frustrated, I can appreciate that she wanted to avoid having to examine the whole tangled mass of interconnected plots and themes, which would have required another hundred pages and risked wearying the reader with predigested commonplaces or endless minute particulars. Among the themes central to these poems, the one she chooses, the city, opens a gate (to borrow the metaphor) that leads to many revealing vistas. She leaves it largely to us to reintegrate these vistas into the poems’ larger structures and meanings.</p>
          <p>In her final chapter, Michael claims that a city, a real city such as London, is a text: it must be “‘read,’ in order to understand some meaning within it . . . and at the same time ‘written’s so as to create a meaning . . .” (161). Whatever may be said for this idea, it is now rather a commonplace. Since <hi rend="i">texte</hi> arrived from France over 40 years ago it has colonized every department of humanities and social sciences. Everything has become a text. Everything must be read, and, since meaning is indefinitely displaced and postponed, everything must be reread, reinterpreted, and rewritten endlessly. The ideology, as Melville would say, of a sub-sub-librarian. Over 30 years ago Paul de Man pronounced that “All wars are texts,” which led a group of Yale graduate students to pass out buttons saying “Veterans of Foreign Texts.” But no mockery stopped the tsunami of textuality. In recent years, I think, the tide has receded, for it turns out that some things are not very much like texts after all, and even if they were, we would have to make distinctions among city-texts, landscape-texts, war-texts, and so on, and would soon be left about where we were before the flood.</p>
          <p>Michael does not claim everything is a text, but in claiming that cities are texts she seems unaware of the history of “Theory” and its pretensions during the last 40 years, and to some of us who lived through them this innocence is a little annoying. Perhaps she has in mind a younger set of readers, who feel distant from all that, and will consider her metaphor (and more than metaphor) with fresh eyes. And it is true that cities are at least a little like texts, especially to a first-time tourist, and the comparison may strike illuminating sparks, as does her earlier comparison of the city to a body. With her usually steady attention to details, Michael is still a helpful guide, as when she discusses the four gates of Golgonooza or the relationship of the lyric “From Islington to Marybone” to the larger poem that contains it, but she plays this role less often in this chapter than in the earlier ones. She is after big concepts, and the biggest is the inverse of the city-as-text metaphor: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the text itself, is a city! (164). She is drawing from De Luca here, who likened <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to “a wall of words,” but she goes much further, comparing streets and canals to lines of poetry, shores and walls to borders of pages, quarters or districts to chapters, junctions and crossings to the four prefaces, and landmarks to the full-page designs (167-68). That, certainly, is not banal; I found it rather brave and charming, though over the top. She doesn’t do much with it, of course (how far could you take it?), content to let it widen our foreheads for a moment before moving on to other implications of the text taken as a city.</p>
          <p>She wants to show that Blake imagines or conjures up a reader of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> who is rather like a large-minded visitor to a large city, baffled at first, but willing to explore and contemplate the labyrinth until it takes meaningful shape, whether revealed (read) or created (written), and becomes a habitable home while the visitor becomes a citizen. If we can learn to be such readers we will know how to “converse” with other citizens, entering each other’s bosoms, and there-by continually rebuild the city. It is an attractive idea. It is Blake’s utopian vision of Jerusalem, and hard to resist, but whether Blake embodied this vision somehow in the form of his poem is quite another matter. I have my doubts. I grant that a reader of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> with Michael’s metaphor in mind might feel encouraged to plunge in, and I don’t underestimate the value of that state of mind, but her argument in this final chapter remains more a pep talk than a Baedeker, and after a while even the most hopeful reader will need the latter. In my experience, even after many years of reading <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and excellent commentaries on it such as Morton Paley’s, the walls of words remain discouraging barriers (we might call them wailing walls), the poetry is often clunky and clumsy, the narrative has little momentum or discernible direction, some passages are of adamantine obscurity, and the tone is often unpleasantly hectoring or jeremiahing. Though some sectors of it are wondrous and inspiring, the whole thing, if it is a city, is Babylonish or Knossian. I’ll revisit it from time to time, as I’ll revisit Michael’s interesting book, but I’ll keep my Athenian passport.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p41-127" n="127"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Jeremy Tambling. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night Thoughts.</hi> Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2005. x + 202 pp. £50.00/$85.00, hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Wayne C. <name>Ripley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>ANYONE looking for a close reading of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors, or Blake’s relationship to Edward Young, will be initially misled by the title of Jeremy Tambling’s recent study. While there is an interesting chapter on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> and Blake’s designs, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night Thoughts</hi> takes night as a metaphor and structuring device and should be seen, rather, as a successor to David Wagenknecht’s <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night: William Blake and the Idea of Pastoral</hi> (1973). But whereas Wagenknecht considered Blake’s conception of night within literary conventions and traditions, Tambling focuses on the wild topoi and discourses Blake associated with night and argues that Blake’s night thoughts disrupt identity and challenge rationality at its most fundamental levels. Tambling associates night thoughts with the typical Blakean imagery of shadows, shade, stars, forests, dreams, and most of all darkness—a word that, the reader is told several times, spreads over six pages in the concordance—and he suggests that such imagery presents a realm of madness, irrationality, sexuality, and heterogeneity. Since night thoughts challenge grand narratives, one may be reminded of Donald Ault’s idea of the non-Newtonian narrative in <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound</hi>, but it would be closer to Tambling’s point to think of classic descriptions of Beulah and Generation, concepts that one wishes Tambling had incorporated more, at least as an organizational device. As it is, Tambling has given us a poetics of Beulah that dares not speak its name.</p>
          <p>The initial chapters are organized around a nexus of night thoughts images pulled from Blake’s work as a whole, without consideration of chronology or development. Emulating his theme, Tambling moves stylistically in rhapsodic prose from one association to another. Sometimes his readings brilliantly illuminate unrecognized metaphoric patterns across Blake’s works; other times these associations lead the reader down a seemingly endless signifying chain. One likes to think that this learned, rambling style is intentional, since the specter of an older critical tradition wanders throughout the book, in which literary analysis was the occasion for wider rumination and reflection as much as for tenure and promotion. It is unfortunate that Tambling does not embrace his leanings toward this type of criticism more forthrightly, because he always seems to be wrestling with more than just Blake. These wider concerns emerge briefly in the preface, where Tambling acknowledges the influence of F. R. Leavis, “whose wrestlings with Blake in seminars held me fascinated” (vii). But something in Blake kept the great critic at bay, for while Leavis was “utterly committed, he also seemed to be held back from developing writing on Blake in a way which I have attempted to think further about it [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] in this book” (vii). The first chapter begins, accordingly, by tracing a genealogy of Leavis’s 1972 <hi rend="i">Nor Shall My Sword: Discourses on Pluralism, Compassion and Social Hope</hi>, through “daytime” use of Blake by the patriotic and progressive forces of twentieth-century Britain. For Tambling, the nationalistic Blake of the “Jerusalem” hymn and the Blake allied with optimistic and progressive humanism distort the complexity and irrationality always at work in Blake’s thought. As he will suggest in his conclusion, Tambling is just as ready to seize upon Blake as a symbol for Britain, but this dark Blake must always be a challenge to easy narratives of nationalism, urbanism, race, and empire.</p>
          <p>Challenging the easy political uses of Blake, Tambling offers Ugolino as the organizing figure for his conception of Blake’s night thoughts. Blake first drew a sketch of Ugolino between 1780 and 1785, and later employed the subject in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (1790), <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi> (1793), its revision <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi> (1820), and the Dante watercolors (1824-27). According to Dante, Ugolino devoured the dead flesh of his sons and grandsons in agonizing guilt and hunger when imprisoned in a tower, and, in the <hi rend="i">Inferno</hi>, he gnaws the head of his betrayer, the Archbishop Ruggieri. While the story itself possesses horrific ambiguities, the different contexts in which Blake employed the design add to the difficulty of its interpretation. In <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Ugolino appears on plate 16, which proclaims that the world is divided between the prolific and the devouring. In <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>, the illustration is recontextualized with the anticlerical recrimination “Does thy God O Priest take such vengeance as this?” (E 265).<ref target="n2" type="note">1</ref> As Tambling argues, Ugolino is both “a giant, embodiment of kinetic energy” and “the duality of creating and devouring” (6). Blake’s Ugolino shatters simple categories of thought, and his anguished state of starvation and grief embodies the contradictions of night thoughts, “where desire for the morning and its reason contrasts with night and its reason, which is inseparable from a non-differentiated madness and death” (6). <note id="n2">1. David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (New York: Anchor-Doubleday, 1988).</note></p>
          <p>As the ambiguous and tortuous symbol of Ugolino suggests, Tambling wants to move beyond a simple binary analysis of night and day to a place of tortured irrationality. As he writes, a central question in Blake’s night thought is “[w]hat enables distinguishing and naming discrete forms and identities?” (124). But while Tambling effectively uses words like “ghost” and “echo” to capture the transient uncertainty of the polysemous meanings found in night thoughts, methodologically he frequently bisects his night thought imagery into pairings of related but distinct concepts. Instead of the binary of day and night, there are actually two nights. One is unremittingly evil, and it is the night properly to be feared and escaped. Tambling doesn’t specify it as such, but this aspect of night should be glossed as Generation, Ulro, or Udan-Adan,
<pb id="p41-128" n="128"/>
which are always encroaching upon richly prolific Beulah. The other night, which gives us <hi rend="i">true</hi> night thoughts, is always in “shadow”—a nice Blakean doubling. Typified by Ugolino’s ordeal, this shadowed night represents prolific indeterminacy, producing meaning even as it undermines it. Madness and the other night thoughts imagery follow the same pattern of dual meanings. Both forms of madness “make identities pale, deranged” (123), but Tambling associates the latter with William Cowper’s wish to be, like Blake, “mad as a refuge from unbelief” (E 663). Because this wish appears to be identity affirming, however, Tambling must explain how creative madness can slip into the Urizenic abstractions associated with the Spectre and Nebuchadnezzar (146-47). The distinction between these subcategories is never absolute, and neither, it seems, can it be, since rationalism itself in night thoughts exists in a state of complicity with that outside of its boundaries, always “inseparable from the passion that fascinates it” (148).</p>
          <p>The creative instability of night thoughts is exemplified for Tambling in “The Tyger,” which he ties to “the voice of the Devil” in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and the claim that “Reason is the bound or outward circumference of Energy” (pl. 4, E 34). As this maxim suggests, reason and energy are never free from one another, but necessarily imply and require each other. This condition is typified by the Devil himself, who is caught within the very theological system he critiques, bound to the contrary views he denies (125). As a creator, Blake himself is in a similar position. He praises the virtues of the outline in opposition to abstraction, but “it is the line, the boundary, the limit which separates the inline from the outside line” (125). Yet this observation implies more for Tambling than “[w]ithout Contraries is no progression” (pl. 3, E 34). The outline not only creates the abstraction through exclusion but requires abstraction to define itself. In “framing” the Tyger, the creator (in all of its meanings) must delineate an outline out of the dynamic chaos of energy and reason. The line itself will negotiate between form and abstraction. For Tambling, these contradictions and complicities are at the essence of night-thoughts semiology. In “The Tyger,” they emerge in “the forests of the night”; in Dante, the “dark wood” (<hi rend="i">Inferno</hi> 1:1-3). In “Mad Song,” the narrator rejects the dawn, turning his
<q>
back to the east,<lb/>
From whence comforts have increas’d;<lb/>
For light doth seize my brain<lb/>
With frantic pain. (E 415-16)
</q>
As Tambling comments, “[f]or ‘Mad Song’, fulfilment of the lyrical, giving light, would give ‘frantic pain’. Night thoughts are preferred, Spring is rejected before it comes, and the light of Enlightenment rationality is a source of madness” (135).</p>
          <p>Despite their relatively obscure subject, Tambling’s chapters on Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, the illustrations, and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> are more accessible. In contrast to many Blake critics, he locates Young’s credentials not only in the context of the Graveyard school but also in the context of German romanticism and surrealism, citing André Breton’s 1924 “Manifesto of Surrealism”: “Young’s <hi rend="i">Nights</hi> are Surrealist from one end to the other” (44). By viewing Young in this context, Tambling conveys well the excitement, novelty, and utter strangeness that can be found in a work that critics often malign, and he also accurately sees night in Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> as “the moment when Lockean daytime passivity is broken and thoughts wander unlimited” (58). Tambling reads <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, the illustrations, and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in tandem with <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi>, which paraphrases Young in its final plate and suggests Blake’s lifelong interest in Young. Given the size and complexity of these works, the reading admittedly moves quite fast, but Tambling seizes effectively upon those moments of night thoughts that best reflect his analysis of Blake’s other works. He combines the standard line that <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript embodies its fundamental themes of splitting and division with his own notion of night thoughts. The manuscript poem is “an impossible dream” because “[n]ight thoughts presuppose splittings within the text, which argue not for an originary psychic split, but that there can be nothing but a split state to start with” (72). Like the meeting of reason and energy in the creation of the Tyger, the duplicitous nature of jealousy leads simultaneously to the division between Tharmas and Enion even while it binds Urizen and leads to Los’s binding of Orc. Because night thoughts are inherently fragmentary, Tambling leaves off his reading of the poem with Night Eight as Blake “moves away from night thoughts, to something more deliberate, by adopting figures from Christianity” (89). While Tambling never addresses this issue explicitly, the implication is that Edenic Christianity, at least as Blake understood it later in life, was part of the dawn, belonging to the world of day thoughts; as such, it would not be within Tambling’s focus.</p>
          <p>More problematic is the role gender plays within night thoughts. Resisting simple binaries makes it difficult to associate one gender with night thoughts, but Tambling oftentimes employs Blake’s patriarchal language uncritically, resulting in an inadvertent sexism that associates women with difference. It is in this element of night thoughts that the omission of Beulah is particularly damaging to Tambling’s argument. Beulah is a necessary place of repose in Blake’s later works, and it remains the highest state achievable by man after the fall from Eden. While the male characters march, fight, and proclaim, the women in Beulah do much of the labor in restoring Eternity. Neglecting these scenes in Beulah for moments like Enitharmon’s night in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, where the gender dynamics of night are laid out around the errors of female will (8), misrepresents the complex role of women in Blake’s thought, a role made more complex with the discovery of Blake’s Moravian heritage and its spiritual feminization of men. As Tambling explicates them, Blake’s plots invariably revolve around male protagonists, while females are doomed to be ephemeral, marginalized, and vilified. He reads, for example, Enitharmon into the “Nurse’s Song” of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>; the nurse’s true identity, he suggests, is disguised by her femininity
<pb id="p41-129" n="129"/>
(11). As Tambling observes, gender cast off from identity is a return to the Eternal Man, who contains both “feminine” and “masculine” portions (91). Gender destroys real identity, splitting “the fantasised identity seen as bisexual in Lacan’s mirror-stage” (11). But time and time again, the instability of identity is associated by Tambling with women and not men. Gender may be a fallen condition in Blake’s universe, but too often in Tambling’s argument, gender means femininity. In his interpretation of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas: The Torments of Love and Jealousy in the Death and Judgment of Albion the Ancient Man</hi>, jealousy exists only between men and women, since Blake follows Young in believing that jealousy, “in the context of male friendship, is controllable” (72). Observing that this maxim was not true for Blake and his relationship with Hayley, Tambling removes male jealousy from the realm of night thoughts by associating it with Urizen (72). This is odd, since Hayley is very much aligned with Satan and hermaphroditic imagery in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and the notebook poems. Yet if jealousy exists only sexually between men and women, one is at a loss to explain Tambling’s question whether the “torments” in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> subtitle refer to men alone, since females are “derivations of men” (92), which seems to translate to “men are tormented because women get jealous.” In an early scene between Los and Enitharmon, they are described as angry with one another, “Alternate Love &amp; Hate his breast; hers Scorn &amp; Jealousy” (9:24, E 305). As Tambling explicates the line, it shows that “in this ranking of qualities . . . it is worse to be the woman than the man” (73).</p>
          <p>If Tambling’s exploration of gender is problematic, his argument regarding night thoughts and their relationship to cities shows true innovation. As a scholar of Charles Dickens and Henry James, Tambling brings new light to London and the bewildering array of place-names in Blake’s later works: “Place names help to hold on to a past so wholly swept away as to seem never to have existed. To write the city through these names is to build it: it is the work of Golgonooza” (110). His pairing of “London” with the lyric on plate 27 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> illustrates well Blake’s awareness of the changing nature of his city and his efforts to preserve local histories in the swirl of physical and moral reform in the early nineteenth century. In Tambling’s account, the evolving city is the province of night thoughts since it reveals the acute “spatial” and “temporal” confusion of Blake’s historical moment (109): “[P]lace names no longer relating, or conferring identity, or recording what has disappeared, or changed, engender the other night, space of madness and of the ‘neuter’, the loss of self in the act of writing the city” (123).</p>
          <p>The final chapter, on the Dante illustrations, which are alluded to throughout the book, undertakes the ambitious task of reading the designs not only as emblems of London in the year 1824 but also as Blake’s engagement with Byron and Dickens. The former is more tenable, since Blake had dedicated <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> to Byron two years earlier and was likely aware of Byron’s 1824 death. Tambling pairs Dante and Byron in Blake’s mind as political exiles and reads in the illustrations mutual concerns of Blake and Byron regarding the poor and outcast. The association between Blake and Dickens, however, is far more speculative, and Tambling pines for the notion that Dickens may have read Blake. But the link between the authors becomes interesting when he compares Dickens’s experience of the city as a young man with Blake’s late in life. The developing metropolis in the nineteenth century in many ways destroys for Tambling the possibility of night thoughts by literally and figuratively abolishing the dangerous streets and thoughts outlined in Blake’s “London” through street expansion, gas lighting, and utilitarian surveillance.</p>
          <p>Having begun by dispensing with the patriotic uses of Blake in twentieth-century British history, Tambling ends his book by denouncing Peter Ackroyd’s biography of London<ref target="n3" type="note">2</ref> for using Blake to turn what was vibrant and alive into something that is “dead, finished, [and] knowable” (172). Ackroyd assumes the “constancy of places” (173), and the new city imagined by its planners is all day thoughts now for Tambling, creating an “information economy based on telematics, the apparent reverse of night thoughts in making information visible” (171). He finds London’s hope not in an ossifying fusion of the present and the past but in the vibrant multicultural streets of London, which tell new, local histories and introduce new night thoughts. <note id="n3">2. Peter Ackroyd, <hi rend="i">London: The Biography</hi> (London: Chatto &amp; Windus-Random House, 2000).</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Jason Allen Snart. <hi rend="i">The Torn Book: UnReading William Blake’s Marginalia.</hi> Selinsgrove: Susquehanna University Press, 2006. 213 pp., 22 b&amp;w illus. $48.50/£29.95, hardcover.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Jennifer Davis <name>Michael</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>SOME of Blake’s most trenchant and pithy comments come to us from the margins of the books he owned: “To Generalize is to be an Idiot,” or “If Morality was Christianity Socrates was The Savior” (E 641, 667). Thanks to the recovery and collection of these marginalia by such editors as Keynes and Erdman, students of Blake may and do quote from them as readily as from Blake’s self-published writings, as I have just done, focusing on their content at the expense of context. In doing so, we follow the example of Frye, Bloom, Thompson, Damon, and other leaders in the field. However, as Jason Snart argues in his new book, to extract these marginal interventions from their material context is to risk not only misreading the statements themselves, but also misinterpreting what books meant for Blake as a reader and printer.</p>
          <pb id="p41-130" n="130"/>
          <p>Snart’s thesis is that “Blake’s experience as a reader both informed and reflected his thinking about what books could do and be” (35). Therefore, the annotations do not express, or emerge out of, a preexisting theory (30). Rather, they embody a process of readerly engagement, which, Snart argues, is “flatten[ed]” or even eclipsed entirely when scholars treat all Blake’s textual productions as equivalent (31): for example, placing an annotation to Reynolds alongside a line from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Snart is interested in the marginalia not as products, but as process. While Snart’s book has some shortcomings and some underdeveloped points, its great value lies in its attention to the marginalia as material interventions in the books of others, leading to questions and hypotheses about scenes of reading, writing, and printing in Blake’s own illuminated poems, notably <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi></p>
          <p>Snart is not alone in focusing on marginalia in order to illuminate the practice of reading: H. J. Jackson has published two books in the past six years, <hi rend="i">Marginalia: Readers Writing in Books</hi> (2001) and <hi rend="i">Romantic Readers: The Evidence of Marginalia</hi> (2005). Snart acknowledges the first, broader study, not as a “source” but as “responding to many of the same developments in scholarship” (12). I mention Jackson’s latter book, however, because it throws into sharper relief the different ways in which she and Snart approach marginalia. While both seem to agree that annotation “synthesizes . . . the functions of reading and writing” (Jackson, <hi rend="i">Marginalia</hi> 90), Jackson maintains the sense of a coherent and preexisting philosophy that is solidified and confirmed by Blake’s reading practices. She cites his account, on a blank page of Reynolds’s <hi rend="i">Discourses</hi>, of his own annotations to Locke and Bacon (now lost), testifying to the consistency of his opinion over time. Blake, she concludes, “used his system of annotation to argue in favor of his own convictions, building up and defending a contrary position” (<hi rend="i">Romantic Readers</hi> 158). Repeatedly Jackson speaks of Blake’s “system” or “method” of annotation.</p>
          <p>Snart, on the other hand, characterizes all of Blake’s work as an “anti-system project.” The “UnReading” in his title “looks to avoid the conventional reading of marginalia for content in favor of asserting and maintaining their difficulty” (23). This approach requires that Snart resist the urge to make Blake coherent. Rather, he rewrites Los’s famous line from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (E 153) to read “I must not create a system, or be enslaved by another” (127): this appears, without comment, as the epigraph to chapter 4. Thus Snart participates in the post-Derridean and anti-Frygean practice of attending to the textual instabilities of Blake, in the tradition of Donald Ault (one of his dissertation supervisors, and a heavy influence) and Molly Anne Rothenberg. At the same time, his attention to the materiality of the marginalia and the physicality of Blake’s readerly interventions forms a bridge between a more abstracted deconstructionism and the material investigations of Michael Phillips and Joseph Viscomi into Blake’s book production.</p>
          <p>Before turning directly to the marginalia, Snart spends two chapters exploring what he calls Blake’s “anti-Newtonianism” and the tension between “fixity” and “fluidity” in his (or indeed any artist’s) work. While Snart acknowledges that Blake’s opposition to “Newton’s sleep” is often oversimplified (45), he himself falls prey to the convenient use of “Newtonian” to refer to a linear system of cause and effect, described in language that transparently reveals an objective reality (36-37). Indeed, the phrase “Newtonian narrative,” which Snart borrows from Ault, risks following in the path of the notorious “Orc cycle” as a critical commonplace. The second chapter, after helpful close readings of several plates from <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, focuses largely on “<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> as “a book about the impossibility of getting <hi rend="i">outside</hi> of the book one is writing” (96). While Paul Mann has already discussed <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> as “a book about books” (Mann 49), Snart explores the interpretive challenges posed not only by the book itself but also by the editorial impulse to pin “Urizen” down, to identify pictured figures as “Urizen,” as well as, inevitably, to decide the order in which to read the plates. The end of chapter 2 offers, rather awkwardly, a brief “Preludium” to Snart’s examination of the marginalia themselves. Here, as elsewhere, Snart tends to tell us repeatedly what he is doing, a likely residue of the dissertation that might well have been edited out of the published volume.</p>
          <p>Nonetheless, Snart makes a convincing case that Blake’s “composite art,” with its inclusion of competing and even contradictory evidence, poses a challenge to the univocal authority of a “Newtonian” text. The marginalia thus become another means of challenging that Newtonian singularity. By “unfinish[ing]” a “finished” text, “the qualities of completeness (unity), univocality (repression), and closure could be contested if not dismantled outright” (38). This analogy between annotated and illuminated books raises another question, however: did Blake view his marginalia as an artistic production, even a publication?</p>
          <p>Like Jackson, Snart cites Lavater’s final aphorism, which invites readers to “interline” and “set . . . mark[s]” as they read and then to show their annotations to others. For both critics, this directive suggests that “Blake did not annotate only as he read a volume for the first time” (Snart 161). Both also note the apparent addresses to a reader in the marginalia, as well as the signing of them as “Will Blake.” Snart further notes the “uncanny” production of an alternative “title page of sorts” in Blake’s annotations to Reynolds’s title page (152). While Blake de-centers the “original” text and often makes it difficult for the reader to ignore his comments, “rarely if ever has Blake defaced the original text to the point that it is unreadable” (150). Without the original, the sense of a contrary statement would be lost.</p>
          <p>While Jackson asserts that Blake circulated his annotated books as an “alternative form of publication” (<hi rend="i">Romantic Readers</hi> 169), Snart does not go so far.<ref target="n4" type="note">1</ref> Snart is more interested in integrating Blake’s experience as an annotator with his experience as an author and printer, suggesting, for example, that the
<pb id="p41-131" n="131"/>
“wall of words” V. A. De Luca notes on some pages of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (De Luca 218) represents a deliberate defense against the contesting voice of annotation (Snart 142-43). Snart shares with Jackson, however, a fascination with Blake’s use of pen to ink over his penciled notes, which Snart construes as evidence that Blake expected an audience to read them (132-33). <note id="n4">1. Morton Paley makes a case (266) for at least some of Blake’s annotations being intended for an audience, “fit . . . though few.”</note></p>
          <p>The strongest parts of Snart’s argument are those that stick closely to the marginalia themselves. Even where he briefly introduces topics for further study, as in the closing section, “Areas for Further Research,” he zeroes in on glaring gaps in our understanding of Blake’s annotation. The links to Blake’s own poetry and illuminated books, however, are not always as convincing. For instance, I am not persuaded that Urizen’s “trac[ing] . . . verses” in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is in any way connected to Blake’s tracing over his marginalia in pen (144). Moreover, <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, as I have suggested above, takes up an inordinate amount of space in a relatively brief book about marginalia.</p>
          <p>Despite these cavils, Jason Snart is to be commended for so acutely challenging the prevailing mode of reading the marginalia purely for content. Like the Santa Cruz Blake Study Group, whom Snart frequently cites and who first called attention to the distorting effect of typeset editions of Blake, Snart has shown the inadequacy of extracting marginalia from their context. He also calls attention to the alarming deterioration of many of the annotations, as pencil fades and pages crumble. We can only hope that someday some of these annotated pages might become part of the Blake Archive.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>De Luca, V. A. “A Wall of Words: The Sublime as Text.” <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality.</hi> Ed. Nelson Hilton and Thomas A. Vogler. Berkeley: U of California P, 1986. 218-41.</p>
            <p>Jackson, H. J. <hi rend="i">Marginalia: Readers Writing in Books.</hi> New Haven: Yale UP, 2001.</p>
            <p>---. <hi rend="i">Romantic Readers: The Evidence of Marginalia.</hi> New Haven: Yale UP, 2005.</p>
            <p>Mann, Paul. “<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> and the Horizon of the Book.” <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality.</hi> Ed. Nelson Hilton and Thomas A. Vogler. Berkeley: U of California P, 1986. 49-68.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. “William Blake and Dr. Thornton’s ‘Tory Translation’ of the Lord’s Prayer.” <hi rend="i">Prophetic Character: Essays on William Blake in Honor of John E. Grant.</hi> Ed. Alexander S. Gourlay. West Cornwall: Locust Hill P, 2002. 263-86.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>[Robert C. Brandeis.] <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries</hi>: An Exhibition Selected from the Bentley Collection at Victoria University, Victoria University Library, Toronto. 30 October-15 December 2006. Toronto: Victoria University, 2006. 36 pp., 36 b&amp;w illus. Canadian $15.00, paperback.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>C. S. <name>Matheson</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>As a student at Oxford I earned a bit of money working part-time in the college library. The hourly wage was small, but the labor wasn’t taxing, except for locking up and shutting down the lights in a long gallery reputedly haunted by the ghost of someone disappointed at Finals (a person, incidentally, who turned up well albeit wrinkled at a gaudy in my last term).</p>
          <p>But the shelving and the cataloguing and the reserve requests were really made tolerable by the possibility of an outing with the college librarian. Periodically the librarian would receive word that someone had donated his or her library to the college and then she—and sometimes to my delight she and I—would be dispatched to examine the books and carry away our selections. These alumni seemed to favor the environs of North Oxford, or else they had followed the Woodstock Road along a bit further and daringly settled in the Cotswolds. They inhabited similar houses—not architecturally similar of course, but eerily alike in their proportion of armchairs to reading lights, cretonnes to bookrests, and well-used dictionaries to presentation copies. In the librarian’s venerable Morris Minor we would travel at an unflappable 30 mph towards these quiet houses and their expectant libraries. I was always waiting for the bright moon to drop behind the cottage roof.</p>
          <p>These excursions were my first proper lesson in the deep autobiography that is serious book collecting. They taught me just how many layers of self are manifested in a library, and the extreme generosity of selves who can project their libraries forward into another sphere and towards another set of readers. I learned that bookshelves stand at the convergence of dense, humming lines of testimony: not just to a person’s subject and expertise and interests, but to his or her travels, experiences, consolations and connections; not just to the provenance of rare volumes, but the point at which a book’s passage through the world merges with the whole journey of a collector. A life lived with books can be wholly different from a career enacted through them. There are times when geomancy seems a more necessary science than bibliography.</p>
          <p>Now imagine how these issues are amplified when the collection in question is “one of the three most important Blake collections, institutional or private, formed in the second half of the twentieth century” (Robert Essick, quoted in the “Introduction”).
<pb id="p41-132" n="132"/>
And when the collector is not only our foremost Blake biographer (<hi rend="i">Stranger from Paradise</hi> [2001]), but a scholar whose work forms part of the superstructure of Blake studies. Here indeed is a “Web / Of Ages &amp; Generations, folding &amp; unfolding,” which is a rather more pleasant image when taken out of context. The books, paintings, manuscripts, drawings and artifacts brought together by G. E. Bentley, Jr., and E. B. Bentley over nearly six decades form a remarkable production in their own right. The works (more than 2500) parallel and embody Bentley’s meticulous reconstruction in his numerous books and articles of Blake’s associations, circles, and working practices. This is a collection that recreates the sociability and productivity—not to mention the dizzying interconnectivity—of the book and art worlds in Blake’s lifetime. Recently gifted to the E. J. Pratt Library of Victoria University at the University of Toronto, the Bentley collection was show-cased in the fall of 2006 through a fine exhibition curated and catalogued by chief librarian Robert C. Brandeis.</p>
          <p>The exhibition begins with the visage of Blake himself. A copy of Deville’s life mask, in which Blake’s habitual sweetness of expression was soured by the weight of the plaster, is paired with Schiavonetti’s engraving after the Phillips portrait, a print used as the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> in 1808. It is an apposite choice, not only because it answers our wish to greet Blake himself, but also for the many layers of reproduction and transmission manifested in these works. Everything follows from a desire to translate the imaginative faculty.</p>
          <p>The first movement of the exhibition shows the range of Blake’s graphic production, from sketch and manuscript to engraving on copper and wood to relief etching. It’s instructive to see three electrotypes—“London,” “Infant Sorrow,” and “The Divine Image”—from the 16 made after Gilchrist’s c. 1861 electrotype copies of Blake’s plates. There are three sets of these electrotype copies now extant, and I feel rather subdued when I think of <hi rend="i">printing from them</hi> in Bentley’s seminar. Blake’s designs for and after the work of other artists (including the wonderful engraved portrait of Lavater, beaky and exacting as a Renaissance princeling) ready us for the exquisite Virgil illustrations and the magisterial <hi rend="i">Dante</hi> and <hi rend="i">Job</hi> suites that fill the South Gallery. The latter is a splendid 1826 “proof” copy on India paper. A pencil drawing in the “Visionary Heads” mode—representing Prince Arthur or perhaps an unusually svelte Henry VIII—and an autograph riddle manuscript penned on the verso of a proof of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi> direct us to the calligraphic vigor of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> Copy M of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, one of the collection’s greatest treasures, consists of <hi rend="i">A Song of Liberty</hi> printed, as the catalogue describes, “on one sheet forming four pages with the first page left blank” (9). Together with copy L (in the collection of Robert Essick), this work provides important evidence that the <hi rend="i">Song</hi> was not just the tailpiece of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, but may have been intended for distribution as a separate pamphlet.</p>
          <p>Copy M of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> dramatizes a tendency within the Bentley collection as a whole to illuminate artists and audiences,
            <figure n="Bentleys1.41.3.bqscan" rend="file"><figTranscr>
              William Blake<lb/>
              &amp; His
            </figTranscr></figure><figure n="Bentleys2.41.3.bqscan" rend="file"><head>E. B. Bentley and G. E. Bentley, Jr., at the reception to mark the opening of the exhibition.</head><figDesc>Photographs courtesy of Alex McKay.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p41-133" n="133"/>
issues of production and reception in the period. The professional sphere that Blake (periodically) inhabited is embodied in the exhibition through the work and biographies of some of Blake’s key associates: Cumberland, Flaxman, Fuseli, Linnell, Stothard, and Tresham. These six men, or alternatively, “Men who occupied the sixth chamber,” appear here as artists in their own right as well as patrons, readers, or peers. Sometimes of course these roles converged, as in the case of Cumberland, whose literary manuscripts, scrapbooks, and sketches live alongside books embellished with engravings by Blake. Linnell is represented by an oil portrait sketch of Mrs. George Stephen (wife of a solicitor consulted by Linnell over the Blake estate), a kindly, intimate image that seems consistent with Linnell’s handling of Blake himself. Stothard’s tender watercolor <hi rend="i">Infancy</hi> (c. 1802) makes the sharp dealing of the Canterbury Pilgrims affair seem almost impossible. And Tresham’s oil painting <hi rend="i">Anthony and Cleopatra</hi>, executed for Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, calls up the aspirations and disappointments of a whole decade of British art.</p>
          <p>The Bentley collection is both an entity and the emanation of a distinguished scholarly collaboration. As a “working library” in its richest sense, one that documents the material and spiritual labor of the subject, the biographer, and the collectors, its relocation to the Pratt Library at Victoria University in Toronto seems very appropriate. Here it is in close proximity to an important holding of Coleridge materials and the Northrop Frye papers, not to mention Douglas Martin’s portrait of Frye composedly levitating. And here the lines of the collection are extended magnetically towards a new set of readers, scholars, and students. William Blake and His Contemporaries was opened in late 2006 with a gala reception, memorable on many counts, not the least for hearing a university president quote “When the morning stars sang together” rather than the passages of Job more habitual to administrators. But what struck me most forcibly was that the qualities that converge in successful collecting—knowledge and insight, judgment and good fortune—also shape the community one collects in turn. In a life lived with books the notion of provenance, like the “little lovely Allegoric Night” in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, may be “stretchd abroad, expanding east &amp; west &amp; north &amp; south.”</p>
          <note type="unreferenced" place="footer"><hi rend="i">Editors’ note: Information on ordering the catalogue is available at</hi> &lt;<hi rend="i">http://library.vicu.utoronto.ca/libpubs.htm</hi>&gt;.</note>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Magnus Ankarsjö. <hi rend="i">William Blake and Gender.</hi> Jefferson: McFarland &amp; Co., 2006. × + 210 pp. $32.00/£20.50, paperback.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>G. A. <name>Rosso</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>IN this well-meaning book, Magnus Ankarsjö struggles with the complex and intractable issues of sex and gender in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Seeking to refute the argument that Blake was anti-feminist, Ankarsjö declares that he will “dismantle the claims that define Blake as condescending towards the female sex” (2). His goals are to demonstrate that there is much more positive “gender interactivity” in these poems than critics realize and that in them “Blake presents a gender utopia with a vision of complete equality between the sexes” (3, 2). With the burden of proof on his shoulders, Ankarsjö seeks to trace a “clear line of development” in Blake’s portrayal of gender in the epics, but, in his attempt to manage the irreducible complexity of the narratives and of the sexual forces that energize them, he fixates on what he calls Blake’s “single-minded idea” of achieving an apocalypse of gender equality through a unitary symbol, one that is realized only in the final plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (3,6). Despite the book’s detour into history that briefly explores Blake’s affiliations with Protestant dissent, English Jacobinism, and 1790s feminism, Ankarsjö’s primary claim is that because <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is the culminating version of Blake’s mythological system, we must read each poem from the vantage of the entire canon (6, 124, 189). He thus ends up reading from a teleological perspective that simplifies Blake’s myth and the central role of gender within it.</p>
          <p>Besides this methodological limitation, Ankarsjö does not sufficiently develop his conceptual vocabulary or provide adequate scholarship on the issues that interest him. In the first chapter, “Apocalypse, Utopia and Gender,” he devotes only a couple of pages to each of his key concepts, relying on Morton Paley’s <hi rend="i">Apocalypse and Millennium</hi> (1999) and Nicholas Williams’s <hi rend="i">Ideology and Utopia in the Poetry of William Blake</hi> (1998) for his understanding of these terms. And in a move that he repeats several times, Ankarsjö misreads Blake’s text and takes selected passages out of context to serve his argument. For example, he cites the following bleak passage from <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as an “anticipation of the utopian society” (15):
<q>
For when he came to where a Vortex ceasd to operate<lb/>
Nor down nor up remaind then if he turnd &amp; lookd back<lb/>
From whence he came twas upward all. &amp; if he turnd and viewd<lb/>
The unpassd void upward was still his mighty wandring<lb/>
The midst between an Equilibrium grey of air serene<lb/>
Where he might live in peace &amp; where his life might meet repose (72:16-21, E 349)
</q><pb id="p41-134" n="134"/>
We are told that these lines anticipate utopia because they describe Urizen’s journey as an “‘upward,’ and forward progressive movement” (15). In the context of Night 6, however, as Urizen explores the “dens” of his rational cosmology, he attempts to order chaos by “throwing his venturous limbs into the Vast unknown” and building “a road immense” from “void to void” (E 349), echoing Satan’s journey in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> Further, Urizen seeks to rebuild the fallen world by making himself king and commanding that “all futurity be bound in his vast chain,” thus “Gaining a New Dominion” (73:19-24, E 350). Ankarsjö’s positive interpretation of the passage thus excludes crucial counter-information.</p>
          <p>Ankarsjö is on firmer ground in terms of gender, a topic he obviously has read and thought seriously about. He follows Helen Bruder’s example in <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1997) and seeks to recontextualize Blake’s handling of gender while opposing previous feminist critiques. Although he tends to make bogeywomen out of Anne Mellor and Alicia Ostriker, focusing primarily on their work from the early 1980s, his analysis of Blake in the context of French feminism and the work of Judith Butler is insightful and suggestive. But while chapter 2, “Blake’s Radical Context,” does offer feminist-historical analysis of Blake’s early work, it too remains undeveloped. Citing work by Keri Davies on the important role of Joseph Johnson’s bookshop in making Blake’s work available to a female audience (52-53), Ankarsjö discusses potentially important connections between William Blake and Mary Hays, but the link is tenuously explored and superficially analyzed. We learn that both writers question the “governing paradigm of Enlightenment reason” by emphasizing passion, and that in Hays’s <hi rend="i">The Victim of Prejudice</hi> (1799) the two main characters are described by her as “[a]nimated . . . by one heart and one mind” and thus resemble, according to Ankarsjö, “the male-female togetherness” of Blake’s epics (57). Closer textual and deeper historical analyses are needed to establish specific and viable connections.</p>
          <p>In the final three chapters, on the epics, Ankarsjö puts aside the feminist-historical approach to pursue the structural development of Blake’s female characters. His focus on gender interactivity is relevant and important, but Ankarsjö again tends to misread and take things out of context. For example, in the book’s central and longest chapter (on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>), he states that criticisms of Vala as negative are wrong for two reasons: one, she is absent from most of the poem and two, when she reappears in Night 9, she becomes “the most important character at the inception of the apocalypse” and so “ends the poem as a more positive character” (69). Although Vala does end the poem on a more positive note, these claims downplay her complicity in dividing Luvah in Night 2 and disregard her affiliation with the destructive activity of “the Shadowy Female” and Rahab in Nights 7 and 8. Similarly with Enitharmon: Ankarsjö calls her “the most persistently evil of the four female characters” (72), but claims that she also ends positively because she helps Los take down “the crucified body of Christ” in Night 8. “It is essential to notice here that Los and Enitharmon . . . do this together,” he writes, because it represents the “male-female co-operation” that enables them to “launch the apocalypse of the concluding Night” (77). But, again, this reading ignores context. In fact, there are two versions of taking down the crucified body, and both emphasize states of terror and despair. In the first, only Los takes down the body and then he and Jerusalem, not Enitharmon, bring it to the sepulcher (110 [106]:14-15, E 379). In the second version, the narrator says that Los and Enitharmon take the body down and that “Jerusalem wept . . . two thousand Years” (114 [110]:30-33, E 385). Blake makes clear that what the actors share in the scenes of crucifixion and entombment is an overwhelming and historically catastrophic doubt, not hope of eternal life. This imagery is repeated nearly verbatim at the beginning of Night 9, suggesting that Blake’s apocalypse opens on a note of despair that complicates a purely utopian perspective.</p>
          <p>Similar problems also detract from Ankarsjö’s treatment of gender and utopia in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, despite his valiant effort to bring attention to this crucial aspect of Blake’s apocalypse. Ankarsjö shows that gender interactivity is more positive in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> than in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and that Ololon “has no equal in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” for creating actions with positive consequences (124). But he again makes several assertions that are not supported by the text or that reduce narrative complexities. The most important, Ololon’s final “reunion” with Milton, is crucial to his thesis. Ankarsjö says that <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> “must be read as a development” (155) toward <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and beyond <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> because it contains a “single representation” of gender unity (154), even though it stops short of apocalyptic merger: “Blake leaves the two main characters standing at the threshold, just about to enter the gender utopia of Eden” (157). But he does not tell us that Ololon ends by questioning whether she and Milton are “Contraries” and that her final union is with “Jesus the Saviour” (42:11, E 143). Ankarsjö is aware that female subsumption into the male may not be a feminist ideal, and he quotes Judith Butler’s <hi rend="i">Gender Trouble</hi> to the effect that masculine and feminine cannot both be represented when “the masculine constitutes the closed circle of the signifier and signified” (155-56n18), but he simply asserts that Blake shows otherwise. The same problem occurs in the chapter on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, where the issue is even more important since this is, he claims, where Blake’s gender utopia is fully achieved. Of the incorporation of Jerusalem (or Brittannia) into Albion’s bosom at the end of the epic, Ankarsjö announces that “Blake has erased all gender differentiation” and achieved the “complete absence of gender” (188, 189).</p>
          <p>Some of the best recent feminist criticism of Blake questions the value of this erasure. Two challenging essays, both available but ignored by Ankarsjö, are particularly relevant in this regard. In “‘A Garment dipped in blood’: Ololon and Problems of Gender in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,”<ref target="n5" type="note">1</ref> Betsy Bolton gives a
<pb id="p41-135" n="135"/>
more nuanced and critical account of gender in the poem, arguing that while Blake’s humanism seeks to transcend sexual division, he “does <hi rend="i">not</hi> succeed in writing beyond the sexes: the female remains within the structure of his prophecies as a degraded or an invisible term” (83). And especially importantly for Ankarsjö’s reading, she claims that Ololon and Milton do not reunite but instead remain at odds, and that the figure she does merge with, “One Man Jesus the Saviour,” sublates her identity: “this One Man seems to be grounded in a vanished female figure whose return to inanimate matter lends sacrificial strength to the prophet” (97). This is not to say that Bolton’s reading is the correct one, but it does deserve scrutiny, especially since her approach has been extended in important ways by other scholars, especially Claire Colebrook. In “Blake and Feminism: Romanticism and the Question of the Other,”<ref target="n6" type="note">2</ref> Colebrook argues that Blake develops a positive theory of sexual difference, one which “dynamically sustains each term <hi rend="i">in relation</hi>” (4). She reads the ending of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as more complex and ambivalent than does Ankarsjö, contending that in Albion’s union with Jerusalem Blake recognizes the essential relation of two terms which are “never fully . . . integrated” (6). Colebrook asserts that Blake’s portrayal of unity actually includes a dimension of otherness: “Blake . . . exploits the fact that Albion is specifically ‘man’ insofar as he needs to reinclude his female emanation; it is <hi rend="i">this</hi> aspect of Blake’s figuring of gender which . . . sustains an essential recognition of alterity” (7). These creative, subtle readings show that Blake can be placed in productive dialogue with recent feminist theory and literary scholarship. <note id="n5">1. <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 36.1 (spring 1997): 61-101.</note><note id="n6">2. <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 34.1 (summer 2000): 4-13.</note></p>
          <p>The appearance of Ankarsjö’s <hi rend="i">William Blake and Gender</hi> comes at an auspicious moment of renewed feminist interest in Blake’s work. A recent collection, <hi rend="i">Women Reading William Blake</hi>,<ref target="n7" type="note">3</ref> contains another solid essay by Colebrook, situating Blake in both feminist and literary history, and other essays that fill in contexts explored less fully by Ankarsjö, although his interest in Mary Hays and Blake remains a promising and unexplored connection. Along with Janet Warner’s novel <hi rend="i">Other Sorrows, Other Joys</hi> (2003) and Marsha Keith Schuchard’s <hi rend="i">Why Mrs. Blake Cried</hi> (2006), <hi rend="i">Women Reading William Blake</hi> indicates that the trend in feminist Blake scholarship is historical and biographical, with attention focused on Blake’s wife Catherine and women in Blake’s circle, including Ann Flaxman, and on his relation to contemporary women writers such as Joanna Baillie, Mary Robinson, Charlotte Smith, and Mary Tighe. Ankarsjö had the right idea at the right time, and his effort to uncover a more feminist humanism in Blake’s work is laudable, but his study appears somewhat reductive in the light of resurgent feminist scholarship. <note id="n7">3. Ed. Helen P. Bruder (Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2007).</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title>MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title><hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi> by “B. Blake”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>As is well known, Williak Blake exhibited three pictures at the Royal Academy exhibition of 1808. These are listed in the exhibition catalogue as “311 Jacob’s dream,—vide Genesis, chap. xxviii, ver. 12”; “439 Christ in the sepulcher, guarded by angels”; and “477 The Last Judgment.”<ref target="n8" type="note">1</ref> There is a peculiarity about the listing of the third that has been silently corrected in Blake scholarship. It seems indeed trivial, involving only one letter. The artist’s name is given as “B. Blake.” <note id="n8">1. <hi rend="i">The Exhibition of the Royal Academy MDCCCVIII.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Royal Academy catalogues were probably produced quickly and with little proofreading. Getting a letter wrong was nothing out of the ordinary. The miniature painter John Hazlitt’s name was, for example, given as “T. Hazlitt” in the catalogue of 1802 in conjunction with Hazlitt’s portrait of Samuel Taylor Coleridge.<ref target="n9" type="note">2</ref> However, there is an important difference here. There was in 1802 no exhibiting painter named T. Hazlitt, while John Hazlitt had exhibited every year from 1788 through 1801. The public could easily guess the real name of the artist who showed the Coleridge portrait and three others. In contrast, Benjamin Blake was the name of a painter of landscapes and of game who exhibited “View at Dumford, near Amesbury” (171) in 1808, and whose address is given in the catalogue as 37 Broad Street, Soho.<ref target="n10" type="note">3</ref> (William Blake’s address is correctly given as 17 South Molton Street, Oxford Street.) As the Royal Academy did not act as an agent for selling paintings, providing the artist’s address was a way for prospective buyers to gain contact, and so giving the wrong artist’s name for <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi> was, though unintentional, a professional disservice. It is also an indication of how obscure Blake was as he entered what Alexander Gilchrist was to call his “Years of Deepening Neglect.” <note id="n9">2. See my <hi rend="i">Portraits of Coleridge</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1999) 28.</note><note id="n10">3. Some details about B. Blake, but not the confusion about <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi>, are given in appendix 2, “Blake Residences,” in G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 2nd ed. (New Haven: Yale UP, 2004) 737. By 1811, when B. Blake showed “View at Great Dunford, Wiltshire” (<hi rend="i">The Exhibition of the Royal Academy MDCCCXI</hi>, 146), his address was Great Dunford, near Salisbury.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-41-3-0009">
        <head>
          <title>CORRIGENDUM</title>
        </head>
        <p>In “Blake’s ‘Annus Mirabilis’: The Productions of 1795,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 41.2 (fall 2007): 52-83, illus. 28b is identified in both the text and caption (65, 66) as <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy C, plate 3. It is in fact plate 7 of copy E, and the credit should be to the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</p>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>Joseph <name>Viscomi</name></docAuthor>
        </byline>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
