<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
 <idno>26.1.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Börrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>E.B. Bentley</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Srigley</name>
              <name>Joan K. Stemmler</name>
              <name>Julia M. Wright</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <front>
      <pb id="p26-1-2" n="1-2"/>
        <div1 id="cover">
            <figure n="cover.026.01.bqscan" rend="file">
                <figTranscr>Blake<lb/>
                    AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
                    VOLUME 26<lb/>
                    NUMBER 1<lb/>
                    SUMMER 1992</figTranscr>
            </figure>
        </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="12" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>
            	  <hi rend="b">
              		<hi rend="i">Contents</hi>
            	  </hi>
          		</title>
       		  </head>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">ARTICLES</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="26.1.srigley">The Sickness of Blake’s Rose</ref><lb/> by Michael Srigley</cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="26.1.stemmler">“Undisturbed above once in a Lustre”: Francis Douce,
                            George Cumberland and William Blake at the Bodleian Library and
                            Ashmolean Museum</ref><lb/> by Joan K. Stemmler</cell>
            <cell>9</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="26.1.designs">A New Color Print from the Small Book of Designs</ref><lb/> Martin
                            Butlin</cell>
            <cell>19</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="26.1.sketches">Two Newly Identified Sketches for Thomas Commins’s <hi rend="i">An Elegy</hi> and Further Rediscovered Drawings of the 1780s</ref><lb/>
                            Martin Butlin</cell>
            <cell>21</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="26.1.wright">“Empire is no More”: Odin and Orc in <hi rend="i">America</hi></ref><lb/> Julia M. Wright</cell>
            <cell>26</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="26.1.bentley">Blake’s Elusive Ladies</ref><lb/> E. B. Bentley</cell>
            <cell>30</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="26.1.paley">Corrections to the Blake Trust <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></ref><lb/> Morton
                            D. Paley</cell>
            <cell>34</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
            	<ref type="article" issue="26.1.satan">Satan Arousing the Rebel Angels</ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="26.1.subscription">Blake’s <hi rend="i">Subscription Rates Rise</hi></ref>
            </cell>
            <cell>35</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p><hi rend="b">Cover</hi>: William Blake, “Lady Macbeth and the <corr type="emend">Sleeping</corr>
                    Duncan.” <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1992 Copyright Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p26-3" n="3"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="i">CONTRIBUTOR’S NOTES</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">MARTIN BUTLIN</hi> retired as Keeper of the Historic British
                    Collection at the Tate Gallery in June 1989. He is author of <hi rend="i">The
                        Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (Yale UP, 1981), and other
                    works on Blake and J. M. W. Turner.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">E. B. BENTLEY</hi> has lived and traveled with William Blake and G.
                    E. Bentley, Jr. for forty years. She collects children’s books, and is
                    currently working on nineteenth-century emblem books for children and acting as
                    a research assistant to G. E. Bentley.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">MORTON D. PALEY</hi> is the editor of the new Blake Trust edition of
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
        <p><hi rend="b">MICHAEL SRIGLEY</hi>, Professor of English at the University of
                    Uppsala in Sweden, is finishing a full-length study on Pope’s <hi rend="i">Essay on Man</hi>, which includes a chapter on Pope’s
                    expressed interest in Pythagorean metempsychosis.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JOAN K. STEMMLER</hi>, an independent scholar in Washington, D.C.,
                    is doing research and teaching in the history of art in England in the
                    eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JULIA M. WRIGHT</hi> is a third year doctoral student in English
                    Literature at the University of Western Ontario. Her research interests include
                    English and Irish literature of the Romantic period, and she is currently
                    working on her dissertation on Blake.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0003">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="i">EDITORS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editors:</hi> Morris Eaves, University of Rochester, and Morton D.
                    Paley, University of California, Berkeley.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Bibliographer:</hi> Detlef W. Dörrbecker, Universität
                    Trier, West Germany.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Review Editor:</hi> Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia,
                    Athens.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Associate Editor for Great Britain:</hi> David Worrall, St.
                    Mary’s College.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Production Office:</hi> Morris Eaves, Department of English,
                    University of Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Telephone:</hi> 716/275-3820.<lb/><hi rend="b">Fax:</hi> 716/442-5769.</p>
        <p>Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA
                    94720.</p>
        <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker, Universität Trier, FB III Kunstgeschichte,
                    Postfach 3825, 5500 Trier, West Germany.</p>
        <p>Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA
                    30602.</p>
        <p>David Worrall, St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill, Waldegrave Road,
                    Twickenham TW1 4SX, England.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0004">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="i">INFORMATION</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Managing Editor:</hi> Patricia Neill</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the
                    sponsorship of the Department of English, University of Rochester.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Subscriptions</hi> are $50 for institutions, $25 for individuals.
                    All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer
                    issue. Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be applied to
                    the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and Mexico)
                    require a $8 per volume postal sur-charge for surface mail, a $18 per volume
                    surcharge for air mail delivery. U.S. currency or international money order
                    necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications
                    to Patricia Neill, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of
                    Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627.</p>
        <p>Many <hi rend="b">back issues</hi> are available at a reduced price. Address
                    Patricia Neill for a list of issues and prices.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Manuscripts</hi> are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented
                    according to the forms suggested in <hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, to
                    either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester,
                    Rochester, NY 14627; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of
                    California, Berkeley, CA 94720. Only one copy will be returned to authors.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">International Standard Serial Number:</hi> 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is <hi rend="b">indexed</hi> in the
                    Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern
                    Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language
                    and Literature, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical
                        Bibliography</hi> (ed. David V. Erdman et al.), American Humanities Index,
                    the Arts and Humanities Citation Index, and Current Contents.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">The Sickness of Blake’s Rose</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Michael <name>Srigley</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>Blake’s poem, <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> is probably one of the
                    best-known, best-loved and yet, as I hope to show, least understood poems in the
                    English language. Its popularity is due to its apparent simplicity and to its
                    generous ambiguity. When students are asked to give their own impressions of the
                    poem, their responses are usually vague and various. It is about love or beauty
                    undergoing corruption; it is about the frailty of goodness or the destructive
                    power of time. All the interpretations have in common a general sense of
                    something beautiful being defiled or desecrated. A similar variety of
                    interpretation within the same limits is found in literary criticism. One of the
                    most elaborate interpretations is offered by Kathleen Raine. She suggests that
                    the key to the poem is to be found in the tale of Psyche and Eros in
                    Apuleius’ <hi rend="i">The Golden Ass</hi>, which Blake is known to have
                        admired.<ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> The mysterious
                    “invisible worm” of the poem is traced to Eros as the invisible
                    winged serpent whom Psyche will marry according to the Oracle of Apollo. David
                    Erdman approaches the meaning of the poem through Blake’s illustrations
                    to it, and finds both markedly erotic.<ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> In
                    one illustration, a worm “extends a curved phallic body out from the
                    flower centre and about the human form of the Rose.” The girl’s
                    face “registers desperation and we see the sharp proboscis of the worm
                    turning out from below her dress as about to attack her.” Despite the
                    phallic imagery and the suggestions of incipient rape, Erdman interprets both
                    the etchings and the poem as basically optimistic; their message, he concludes,
                    is that “life is mortal.” He also finds a sign of hope in the
                    upraised arms of one of the girls: it indicates that “a worm hidden in
                    secret may be reborn as a boy or girl.” <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
                        Kathleen Raine, Blake and Tradition, 2 vols. (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP,
                        1968) 2: 199-201.</note><note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The Illuminated Blake, annotated by David V.
                        Erdman (Garden City, NJ: Anchor P/Doubleday, 1975) 81-82.</note></p>
        <p>It is not my purpose to criticize or dismiss such interpretations of <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi>; each of them in its own way throws some light on the
                    poem’s ‘intention,’ to use the Renaissance term. Rather, I
                    wish to suggest that there is an alternative approach to a lyric such as this,
                    one that concentrates on the details of the poem and seeks to elucidate
                        them.<ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> As various, more recent studies of
                    Blake’s deceptively simple poems have shown, they are often richly
                    complex and repay close analysis. <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> belongs to
                    this category. Kathleen Raine has written that <q> Blake’s obscurities
                        are never vague; they are hard, precise, and insoluble until we have the key
                        to their meaning; then they vanish altogether.<ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref><note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Paul Robinson, “What Psychology Won’t
                            Explain” in Michigan Quarterly Review (1980): 45-46.</note><note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Kathleen Raine, Blake and Antiquity
                            (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1977) 12.</note></q> I believe this is true in particular of certain obscurities in <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi>, not least the nature of the nocturnal “invisible
                    worm” which causes the sickness of the Rose. 
                </p>
        <p>First the poem itself: <q> O Rose, thou art sick!<lb/> The invisible worm<lb/>
                        That flies in the night,<lb/> In the howling storm,<lb/> Has found out thy
                        bed<lb/> Of crimson joy:<lb/> And his dark secret love<lb/> Does thy life
                        destroy. </q> In a draft of this poem, the ‘his’ of the
                    penultimate line is replaced by ‘her.’ This indicates that in
                    Blake’s mind the invisible worm could be of either sex. Further
                    information about the worm can be gleaned from the poem. It is invisible, it
                    flies by night in a howling storm, and it seeks out the Rose as the object of
                    its “dark secret love.” Its love is in some way surreptitious; as
                    the imagery of the poem suggests it is sexual; and as we learn from the final
                    line it is destructive. It causes the Rose to become sick. Let us look more
                    closely at the various meanings of the word <hi rend="i">worm.</hi></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">The Worm</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Among the more normal meanings of this word listed in the Oxford English
                        Dictionary, there are two figurative ones that might throw some light on
                        Blake’s “invisible worm.” According to one (II. 1) it
                        is “a grief or passion that preys stealthily on a man’s heart
                        or torments his conscience (like a worm in a dead body or a maggot in
                        food),” with examples from 900 A.D. onwards. Alternatively (II.b), it
                        is defined as “a whim or ‘maggot’ in the brain; a
                        perverse fancy or desire; a streak of madness or insanity, often <hi rend="i">wild worm.</hi>” This figurative worm is the embodiment
                        of some powerful human feeling that preys stealthily on the mind and causes
                        a form of abnormality. Behind these figurative meanings lies a long
                        tradition of various nocturnal wormlike spirits that can travel to a human
                        being and induce some form of abnormal state. It is to this tradition that
                        Blake’s “invisible worm” belongs. These invisible
                        spirits, known as <hi rend="i">lares</hi> or <hi rend="i">larvae</hi>, are
                        mentioned by St. Augustine in his <hi rend="i">Civitas Dei</hi> (Ix. ix.
                        Loeb ed.) and became part of the demonic lore inherited by the Middle Ages
                        and the Renaissance. Boccaccio in his influential iconographical work, <hi rend="i">De deis gentium</hi> (1472, p. 295a) states that these spirits
                        were created by Morpheus, the deity of dreams, as phantasms which according
                        to popular belief “invade the sleeping and weigh down on them,
                        pressing and oppressing the senses.” In the form of incubi and
                        succubi they visited sleeping persons, causing them to have vivid erotic
                        dreams. In the 12th Book of <hi rend="i">Orlando Furioso</hi>, Orlando is
                        described as being pursued by a phantom copy of his Angelica. This phantom
                        is called “notturne larve,” a nocturnal ghost or spirit that
                        haunts lovers. A similar incident occurs in Spenser’s <hi rend="i">Faerie Queene</hi> (I.i.34 ff) when Archimago employs two magical flies
                        to <pb id="p26-5" n="5"/> deceive the Red Cross Knight. One fly is sent to
                        procure a lascivious dream from Morpheus, while the other becomes a phantom
                        copy of Una which attempts to seduce the Knight and arouse him sexually.
                        These nocturnal spirits travel to men or women and cause them to have erotic
                        dreams that can result in orgasm. In a learned commentary on Genesis
                        published in 1601, Benedictus Pererius gave the standard view of what are
                        today called ‘wet dreams’: <q> when men are polluted by
                            nocturnal seed, a succubus-demon is there, acting through a body of air
                            in the form of a woman.<ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref><note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Pererius, <hi rend="i">Commentarium et
                                    Dusoputationem in Genesim</hi> (1601), v. I, p. 387, col. b,
                                para. 64.</note></q> We can now understand why Blake could vacillate about the gender of the
                        “invisible worm.” If it was visiting a man it would be the
                        female succubus, and a male incubus if visiting a woman. We can therefore
                        deduce that the Rose in the final version of the poem stands for a young
                        woman being visited by a male incubus in the form of an “invisible
                        worm.”</p>
          <p>The idea of the “wild worm” infecting the mind of a person and
                        a nocturnal <hi rend="i">larva</hi> fused in the seventeenth century, when
                        the meaning of <hi rend="i">larva</hi> as ghost, skeleton, or mask, was
                        extended by biologists to include grub or maggot, a meaning which the word
                        “worm” also once had (O.E.D. under “worm,” 5).
                        To obtain some idea of how Blake may have visualized the “worm/That
                        flies by night,” let us now consider a seventeenth-century engraving
                        found in a work that Blake almost certainly knew. This is the <hi rend="i">Lumen de lumine</hi> (1652), the alchemical allegory written by Thomas
                        Vaughan, brother of the metaphysical poet, Henry Vaughan. As Raine has
                        suggested, this allegorical vision of Thalia revealing the secrets of
                        alchemy to an adept in the depths of the earth is a major inspiration of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi> Blake would certainly
                        have been interested in the emblematic engraving which opens <hi rend="i">Lumen de lumine</hi>, as well as in the commentary on it in the main
                        text. The central panel of the engraving shows an oval of illuminated ground
                        surrounded by darkness. In the center is an altar with a candle on it
                        signifying <hi rend="i">Lumen Naturae</hi>, the Light of Nature. An Angel
                        with raised sword and a ball of thread is seen to the left, while to the
                        right a blindfolded man is groping his way towards the surrounding darkness
                        designated <hi rend="i">Regio Phantastica</hi>, the Region of Fantasy.
                        Awaiting to seize him there are various winged creatures including basilisks
                        and winged serpents or worms with coiled tails. As we learn from
                        Vaughan’s commentary on this scene, the blindfolded figure being
                        initiated into the mysteries of alchemy will stray into the monstrous region
                        of fantasy unless he accepts the protection of the Angel and uses the thread
                        of Ariadne to guide him through the labyrinth of the alchemical <hi rend="i">opus.</hi> His goal is both above and below him. Above is the <hi rend="i">Mons Magorum Invisibilis</hi>, the Invisible Mountain of the
                        Magicians. Below is a large winged dragon with its tail in its mouth, the
                        alchemical <hi rend="i">ourobouros</hi> enclosing a heap of gold on which a
                        child is sitting and the inscription <hi rend="i">Non nisi parvilis</hi>,
                        intimating that only as children can we enter the Kingdom of Heaven.
                        Concerning the basilisks and winged worms that infest the Region of Fantasy,
                        Vaughan has this to say: in gaining access to the caverns of the Invisible
                        Mountain where the secrets of alchemy are to be discovered, great care must
                        be taken because <q> they are very dangerous places after Night, for they
                            are haunted with Fires, and other strange Apparitions, occasion’d
                            (as I am told by the Magi) by certaine spirits, which dabble
                            lasciviously with the sperm of the world, and imprint their Imaginations
                            on it, producing many times fantastic, and monstrous Generations.<ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref><note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Thomas Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Lumen de
                                    Lumine</hi> in <hi rend="i">The Works of Thomas Vaughan</hi>,
                                ed. Alan Rudrum (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1984) 317, 643-48.</note></q> It is these monstrous productions of sexual imagination that are shown
                        flying in the dark as basilisks and worms or snakes, seeking to waylay the
                        candidate during his maze-like initiation into <hi rend="i">the Mysteries of
                            this my</hi> &lt;<hi rend="i">Thalia’s</hi>&gt; <hi rend="i">Schoole.</hi><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> As the
                        alchemists repeatedly claimed, sexual abstinence was a prime requirement for
                        accomplishing the Work; the basilisks and winged worms therefore represent
                        erotic temptation to the practitioner of alchemy. As we shall see, these
                        nocturnal spirits were believed to be created from a special sperm created
                        during erotic dreams or imaginings. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Vaughn
                            310, 435-36.</note></p>
          <p>It has been necessary to investigate this highly taboo area of human belief
                        in order to discover the lost context of a poem like <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose.</hi> It was precisely such an investigation into the taboos
                        surrounding sex in his own age that Blake undertook. It is well-known that
                        he regarded the Pauline Christian attitude towards sex as unhealthy and as
                        the cause of much abnormality. It warped the natural sexuality of young men
                        and women; it corrupted family life; and it led to prostitution and venereal
                        disease. Through enforced celibacy it was also the cause of much sexual
                        prurience in the Church itself. In his poetry, Blake frequently attempted to
                        expose this diseased attitude to sex, and some of the key passages will be
                        cited later. The point I wish to make here is that <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose</hi>, far from being a vaguely romantic evocation of the
                        susceptibility of beauty to corruption, is in fact a detailed analysis of
                        the causes of the sexual malady of Blake’s times. Its general
                        diagnosis can now be summarized. The “invisible worm” is the
                        embodiment of the sexually heated fantasies of a male, traveling by night
                        through the “howling storm” of erotic passion to the woman
                        being imagined and desired by the solitary lover. To understand this strange
                        idea of what can be called telepathic sexual intercourse between a man and a
                        woman who are physically apart, we must now consider the writings of someone
                        who inspired both Vaughan and Blake. This is the sixteenth-century physician
                        and alchemist, Paracelsus.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Paracelsus and Invisible Illnesses</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Blake left it on record that the two figures to whom he was most indebted
                        were the mystic, Jakob Boehme, and the physician, Paracelsus. In <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, he claims that
                        “any man of mechanical talents may from the writings of Paracelsus or
                        Jacob Behmen produce ten thousand <pb id="p26-6" n="6"/> volumes of equal
                        value with Swedenborg’s.”<ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
                        In a verse letter to John Flaxman of 1800 he again mentions Paracelsus and
                        Boehme as sources of inspiration, claiming that they have actually appeared
                        to him.<ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> Discussing the influence of
                        Paracelsus on Blake, S. Foster Damon has suggested that the paramount
                        importance given by Blake to the human imagination derives ultimately from
                            Paracelsus.<ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> This is true also of
                        the negative power of the human imagination when uncontrolled or distorted
                        by wrong desire. What a man imagines, he becomes, declared Paracelsus in his
                            <hi rend="i">Archidoxis</hi>, which would have been available to Blake
                        in the English translation of 1656.<ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
                        This applies both to the use of the creative imagination and of a diseased
                        imagination. Paracelsus’ fullest treatment of uncontrolled
                        imagination as the cause of various psychological or physical diseases is
                        his <hi rend="i">De Causis et Origine Morborum Invisibilium</hi>, originally
                        published in German in 1565 in <hi rend="i">Opera Omnia</hi>, and reissued
                        in Geneva in 1658 in Latin translation.<ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Leaving aside for the moment the question of whether Blake was
                        acquainted with this work, I shall first give an account of its relevant
                        portions. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Complete Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey
                            Keynes (London; New York, Toronto: Oxford UP, 1966) 158.</note><note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Keynes 799</note><note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi>
                            (1979), ed. by S. Foster Damon, under “Paracelsus.” See
                            also Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study
                                of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford, 1970)
                            passim, for parallels between the thought of Paracelsus and
                            Blake.</note><note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> The Archidoxes of Magic by Paracelsus</hi>, transl. by R.
                            Turner (London, 1656); 2nd ed. 1975 (London: Askin Publlishers, 1975)
                            introd. by Stephen Skinner.</note><note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> All quotations are from the ed. of
                            1656.</note></p>
          <p>As the title of the book indicates, it deals with the causes and origin of
                        invisible diseases. Among these Paracelsus includes diseases born of the
                        imagination, and these he covers in Book III of <hi rend="i">De
                            Origine.</hi> When uncontrolled the human imagination was shameless and
                        obstinate and gave rise to many human ills.<ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> This was particularly so in illnesses deriving from an
                        overactive sexual fantasy. It is this fantasy that creates a false sperm
                        from which incubi and succubi are produced. More particularly, this false
                        sperm or “corrupted salt” is <q> born of the imagination in
                            Amor Heroes &lt;solitary sex&gt;. What is this love? It is none
                            other than when someone creates a woman in his mind through the power of
                            fantasy, and making love with her satisfies his love. From this act
                            results the ejaculation of a useless, feeble sperm incapable of
                            generating children. From this sperm, however, incubi and succubi are
                            created. (<hi rend="i">Iam vero sperma hoc, ita productum,
                                eximaginatione in amore Hereos natum est. Quid vero iste amor est?
                                Nihil aliud, quam quod sibi aliquis per phantasiam in animo foeminam
                                fingit, &amp; cum hac re habendo, amorem suum exsatiat. Unde surdi
                                quo-que fatui spermatis exitus est, quod ad liberorum generationem
                                ineptum est. Exillo tamen spermate</hi> Incubus <hi rend="i">&amp;</hi> Succubus <hi rend="i">gignuntur</hi>).<ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref><note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> De Causis</hi> 128, in <hi rend="i">Opera
                                    Omnia.</hi></note><note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> De Causis</hi> 120.</note></q> The adulterated sperm produced by the erotic imagination is carried off
                        by nocturnal spirits (<hi rend="i">per nocturnos spiritus</hi>), and
                        “hatched into serpents, worms (<hi rend="i">vermes</hi>), toads and
                        similar impure creatures,” including as Paracelsus also says
                        basilisks. They pass from the heated imagination of one person to the person
                        being imagined. This can explain acts of black magic. For example, <q> if a
                            man has a strong and evil imagination, and wishes to injure another,
                            such beings are always ready to hand to lend a helping hand for the
                            accomplishment of his purpose.<ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref><note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Franz Hartmann, <hi rend="i">Paracelsus: Life and Prophecies</hi> (New York: Rudolph Steiner
                                Publications, 1973) 92.</note></q> The <hi rend="i">larvae</hi> used for such a transmission <q> can only
                            act upon men if the latter make room for them in their minds. A healthy
                            mind is a castle that cannot be invaded without the will of its master;
                            but if they are allowed to enter, they excite the passions of men and
                            women, they create cravings in them, they produce bad thoughts which act
                            injuriously upon the brain; they sharpen the animal instinct and
                            suffocate the moral sense.<ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref><note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Hartmann 93.</note></q> In a passage from <hi rend="i">Philosophia Saqax</hi>, Paracelsus
                        describes how this transmission takes place: <q> Spirits desire to act upon
                            &lt;a person’s imagination&gt;, and they therefore often
                            make use of his dreams for the purpose of acting upon him. During sleep
                            the sidereal man may by the power of the imagination be sent out of the
                            physical form, at a distance to act for some purpose. No place is too
                            far for the imagination to go, and the imagination of one man may
                            impress that of another, wherever it reaches.<ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref><note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Hartmann 112.</note></q> The same idea is found in another passage: <q> One man may communicate
                            his thoughts to another with whom he is in sympathy, at any distance
                            however great it may be, or he may act upon the spirit of another person
                            in such a manner as to influence his actions after the latter awakens
                            from his sleep, and in this way he may even injure the health of the
                            latter, and upon this law of Nature is based the possibility of
                            witchcraft and sorcery.<ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref><note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Hartmann 213-14.</note></q> In these various excerpts from the writings of Paracelsus are to be
                        found, I believe, either the main source of or a striking analogue to ideas
                        used by Blake in <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose.</hi> The poem is essentially a
                        distillation of the Paracelsan teaching concerning the transmission at a
                        distance of passionate imaginings from one person to another, as found
                        primarily in <hi rend="i">De Origine morborum invisilibum</hi> but also
                        referred to in other works by Paracelsus. The sickness of the Rose has been
                        caused by the fantasizing of a lonely young man as he conjures up an image
                        of a woman and imagines making love to her. From the ethereal sperm produced
                        by this act of erotic imagination, an “invisible worm” is
                        created which flies through the tempestuous night from the lover to the
                        beloved. As an expression of his “dark secret love” it carries
                        out an act of violation on the young woman. It is for this reason that Blake
                        speaks of this form of love as destructive. 
                    </p>
          <p>The role of the young lover in the drama evoked in <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose</hi> is concealed, but it comes out clearly in a passage in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, describing the erotic
                        experiences of a young girl and youth as each lies alone in bed: <q> The
                            moment of desire! The moment of desire! The virgin<lb/> That pines for
                            man shall awaken to enormous joys<lb/> In the secret shadows of her
                            chamber: the youth shut up from<lb/> The lustful joy shall forget to
                            generate and create an amorous image<lb/> In the shadows of his curtains
                            and in the folds of his silent pillow.<ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref><note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Keynes 194.</note></q> The girl is awakening from a powerful erotic dream, while the young
                        man, deprived of natural “lustful joy,” conjures up in his
                        solitude “an amorous image” of the desired woman. The two
                        halves of the passage are joined by a colon, perhaps suggesting that the
                        sexual climax of the girl and the erotic imaginings of the young man are
                        interrelated and simultaneous. Her pining for a man travels to him as
                        “an amorous <pb id="p26-7" n="7"/> image”; his longing for her
                        travels to the girl to become her partner in the sexual dream. As in <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> with its “dark secret love,”
                        their loves are conceived in “secret shadows” and in
                        “the shadows of his curtains.” Here for Blake lies the
                        unnatural character and essential sickness of their love. It is also
                        unnatural in that the youth “shall forget to generate.” This
                        may echo the observation of Paracelsus that erotic imaginings lead to a form
                        of sterile sperm that is incapable of producing children. The young man,
                        condemned by the Christian norms of society to living in unnatural celibacy,
                        is compelled to create “a woman in his mind through the power of
                        fantasy,” as Paracelsus wrote.</p>
          <p>The sickness in the love of the boy and girl is traced by Blake to religion.
                        In lines that immediately follow those we have just discussed, Blake writes
                        in fierce irony about monastic celibacy and its effects: <q> Are not these
                            the palaces of religion, the rewards of continence;<lb/> The
                            self-enjoyings of self-denial? why dost thou seek religion?<lb/> Is it
                            because acts are not lovely that thou seekest solitude<lb/> Where the
                            horrible darkness is impressed with reflections of desire?<ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref><note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Keynes 194.</note></q> Enforced continence leads to sexual sickness in the form of
                        narcissistic “self-enjoyings of self-denial” in darkness and
                        solitude. This abuse of sexuality is seen by Blake as epidemic in quality
                        and as spreading almost as a viral infection to all young love. Here again
                        his conception of the “self-enjoyings of self-denials” found
                        at the heart of the celibate Church is remarkably close to
                        Paracelsus’ view. In his treatise on plagues, <hi rend="i">De
                            pestilate</hi>, Paracelsus draws attention to the dangers of convents,
                        monasteries, and houses of prostitution, because in such places a lascivious
                        and evil imagination is especially active, and great quantities of sperma
                        are there collected by evil spirits, and that sperma contains a powerful
                        Mumia which may be extracted, and transformed into evil things.<ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref><note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Hartmann 124.</note></p>
          <p>From the revulsion towards sexuality inculcated by the Church arises a
                        psychic pestilence that is destroying the Garden of Love. Its victims are
                        named in <hi rend="i">The Sunflower</hi>: <q> Youth pined away with
                            desire,<lb/> And the pale Virgin shrouded in snow.<ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref><note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Keynes 215.</note></q> As William J. Keith has rightly suggested, the individuals in this poem
                        and in <hi rend="i">Vision of the Daughters of Albion</hi> are varieties of
                        Ovid’s Narcissus, but it is important to stress that for Blake their
                        self-consuming, sickly narcissism was imposed on them by the puritanical
                        norms of a superficially Christian society.<ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref><note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> William J. Keith, “The
                            Complexities of Blake’s Sunflower: An Archetypal
                            Speculation,” in <hi rend="i">Blake: A Collection of Critical
                                Essays</hi>, ed. by Northrop Frye (Englewood Cliffs, NJ:
                            Prentice-Hall, 1966) 58.</note></p>
          <p>This interpretation of <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> and of related poems
                        by Blake rests on the assumption that Blake was conversant with
                        Paracelsus’s strange ideas concerning invisible diseases and
                        telepathic infection. As we have seen, Blake himself claimed to have been in
                        direct contact with the spirits of Paracelsus, Boehme, Milton and other
                        discarnate entities, but such a claim is treated today with skepticism.
                        Eliminating then direct communication with the spirit of Paracelsus as the
                        source of Blake’s information about invisible diseases, there is the
                        possibility that Blake read <hi rend="i">De Origine</hi> in the Latin of the
                        1658 edition. It is know that by 1803 Blake could read both Latin and Greek,
                        and that his Greek was as fluent as that of “an Oxford
                            scholar.”<ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> Unfortunately, it
                        is not known when Blake began learning these languages. There remains the
                        possibility that Blake could have learnt Paracelsus’s teachings about
                        invisible diseases from people in his circle of friends who were interested
                        in such matters. In her forthcoming work entitled <hi rend="i">Men of
                            Desire: Swedenborg, Blake and Illuminist Freemasonry</hi>, Marsha Keith
                        Schuchard investigates, among other things, the keen interest in Paracelsus,
                        Swedenborg and in Cabalism in the circles that Blake frequented. She has
                        generously allowed me to make use of some of her findings.<ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref><note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Keynes 821.</note><note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> The information and quotations contained
                            in the following paragraph documenting the interest in Paracelsus in the
                            eighteenth century were kindly supplied to me by Dr.
                        Schuchard.</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Paracelsus in the Late Eighteenth Century</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>In the <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Ancient and Modern Books</hi> (1787) listed
                        as available in the London bookshop of John Denis, Dr. Schuchard notes the
                        following items: <list type="simple"><item><p># 4945 Auriolus Phillipus Theophrastus, his five Books of the
                                    Causes of Invisible Diseases, <hi rend="i">manuscript, fairly
                                        wrote</hi></p></item><item><p># 4927 <hi rend="i">Paracelsi Opera Omnia</hi> (1662)</p></item><item><p># 5241 <hi rend="i">Paracelsus his Archidoxes</hi> (1660)</p></item></list> John Denis was the English agent for the distribution of
                        Swedenborg’s works in England. Schuchard has also examined a handlist
                        “Catalogue of the Library of Richard Cosway,” now in the
                        Huntington Library. Cosway, painter and mystic, was a lifelong friend of
                        Blake’s. The Catalogue contains the following works by Paracelsus in
                        English translation: <hi rend="i">On the Nature of Things</hi> (1650 and
                        1674); <hi rend="i">New Light of Alchymy</hi> (1674); <hi rend="i">The
                            Supreme Mysteries of Nature</hi> (1656); <hi rend="i">Philosophy
                            Reformed</hi> (1657). The catalogue does not list Cosway’s
                        collection of occult manuscripts. A catalogue of the library of the artist,
                        Philippe Jacques de Loutherbourg, now in the Victoria and Albert Museum,
                        includes under item 136 a number of books by Paracelsus. Like Cosway, de
                        Loutherbourg was a Freemason and a follower of Swedenborg, and probably
                        known to Blake. Schuchard points out that interest in Paracelsus was also
                        widespread in a wider circle of Swedenborgian Freemasons. Such figures as
                        Manoah and Ebenezer Sibly, General Charles Rainsford and Dr. Sigismund
                        Bacstrom all possessed private libraries of occult literature, and refer to
                        Paracelsus in their published writings and manuscripts.</p>
          <p>It is clear then that in the final decades of the eighteenth century
                        Paracelsus continued to be read and studied and that his teachings
                        interested the members of the occult circles that Blake frequented. The
                        printed works of Paracelsus were still available in private libraries and
                        for sale in John Denis’s bookshop in and about the year 1787. It is
                        of particular interest that <pb id="p26-8" n="8"/> in that year Denis had
                        for sale a manuscript English translation of Paracelsus’s <hi rend="i">De Origine morborum invisilibium</hi>, the very work which, as
                        I claim, Blake was influenced by when he came to write <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose</hi> only a few years later. Blake and his wife joined the
                        Swedenborgian Society in 1789, and it is reasonable to assume that Blake
                        frequented John Denis’s bookshop. The copies of Swedenborg’s
                            <hi rend="i">Heaven and Hell</hi> and <hi rend="i">Divine
                            Providence</hi> in English translation which Blake procured in 1789 and
                        1790 were published by John Denis.<ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
                        Even if Blake had not read the English translation of Paracelsus’s
                            <hi rend="i">De Origine</hi> available in Denis’s bookshop, there
                        were a number of Swedenborgians and other esotericists close to Blake who
                        were interested in Paracelsus, as Schuchard has documented, and who could
                        have supplied him with the requisite information about its ideas. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Information about Denis’s role in
                            the publication of these two works of Swedenborg was kindly supplied by
                            Dr. Schuchard.</note></p>
          <p>In whatever exact way Blake may have acquired knowledge of
                        Paracelsus’s <hi rend="i">De Origine</hi>, it seems to me clear this
                        work played a significant part in the genesis of <hi rend="i">The Sick
                            Rose</hi> and that an awareness of its ideas illuminates the central
                        drama of the poem. It enables us to understand more exactly the nature of
                        the invisible worm that flies by night, the urge that drives it through the
                        storm, and why its love is destructive. It also throws light on one of
                        Blake’s major preoccupations: the blighting effect on young people of
                        the Church’s condemnation of sexuality as sinful by nature. Because
                        of this condemnation, sexual attraction does not lead to sexual union, nor
                        does it result in generation. It leads only to solitary, imagined sex which
                        Blake sees as enfeebling and as sick and sterile. The poem is therefore an
                        expression in a powerfully compressed and suggestive form of Blake’s
                        conviction that the Church’s condemnation of sexuality as
                        intrinsically shameful has caused a widespread social and psychological
                        sickness. It leads to the breaking of the marriage bond, to prostitution, to
                        venereal disease, and to a fevered eroticism that is essentially unhealthy.
                        It manifests as a destructive “dark secret love” instead of
                        Oothoon’s “lovely copulation” in bright daylight. It is
                        furtive instead of open. <hi rend="i">The Sick Rose</hi> not only forms an
                        integral part of Blake’s attack on negative Christian attitudes
                        towards human sexuality, but it is remarkable for its specific diagnosis of
                        the illness that this attitude has brought about. Using traditional demonic
                        lore but above all the ideas of Paracelsus, Blake suggests that the human
                        imagination when unregulated is able to create a strange psychic cloud of
                        pollution hovering over society and infested by the weird creatures of
                        erotic longing. It is these in the form of the “invisible
                        worm,” the spectral <hi rend="i">vermis</hi> of Paracelsus’s
                            <hi rend="i">De Origine</hi>, that travel telepathically from person to
                        person bearing erotic infection. As Blake wrote “He who desires but
                        acts not, breeds pestilence.”<ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref><note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Keynes 151.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-9" n="9"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">“Undisturbed above once in a Lustre”: Francis Douce, George
                        Cumberland and William Blake at the Bodleian Library and Ashmolean
                        Museum</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Joan K. <name>Stemmler</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>When Francis Douce died on 5 April 1834, he bequeathed to the Bodleian Library
                    almost all the printed books, coins, prints, and manuscripts he had
                        collected.<ref target="n28" type="note">1</ref> Sir Frederic Madden believed
                    that in “leaving them to the Bodleian he consigns them to neglect and
                    oblivion!” where they would “sleep on . . . undisturbed above once
                    in a lustre by some prying individual of antiquarian celebrity.”<ref target="n29" type="note">2</ref> On the 150th anniversary of the bequest, an
                    exhibition and catalogue celebrated the rich deposit, now divided between the
                    Bodleian Library and the Ashmolean Museum. Through Douce’s antiquarian
                    activities, he met and corresponded with a number of similarly-minded
                    individuals; the letters were bequeathed to the British Museum and in 1930 given
                    to the Bodleian Library.<ref target="n30" type="note">3</ref> Of interest to
                    this art historian was a pattern revealed in these sources of direct and
                    indirect contacts between Douce and the life-long friends, George Cumberland and
                    William Blake. Although I was well acquainted with Cumberland<ref target="n31" type="note">4</ref> and Blake, Douce’s connections with these men
                    were only marginally known to me<ref target="n32" type="note">5</ref> until I
                    explored selected sections of the Bodleian catalogues, Douce’s collected
                    letters, his notebooks, especially his “Collecta,” his portfolios
                    and his lists and notes relating to proposed publications in the archives at the
                    Ashmolean Museum.<ref target="n33" type="note">6</ref><note id="n28"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For his history, Last Will and Testament, and
                        the start and history of the development of his manuscript collection, see
                            <hi rend="i">The Douce Legacy, An exhibition to commemorate the 150th
                            anniversary of the bequest of Francis Douce (1757-1834)</hi> (Bodleian
                        Library, Oxford, 1984) vii-xiii, 13, 15, 130-139, hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">DL</hi> with the page number.</note><note id="n29"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 15, 17, 18 for Madden’s <hi rend="i">Journal</hi> and a letter to Sir Thomas Phillipps.</note><note id="n30"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 130.</note><note id="n31"><hi rend="s">4</hi> In initial research, I relied on Clementina
                        Black, ed., <hi rend="i">The Cumberland Letters, Being the Correspondence of
                            Richard Dennison Cumberland and George Cumberland between the Years 1771
                            and 1784</hi> (London: M. Secker, 1912); C. F. Bell, ed., <hi rend="i">Annals of Thomas Banks, Sculptor, Royal Academician</hi> (Cambridge:
                        Cambridge UP, 1938), hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">Annals</hi>; Geoffrey
                        Keynes, “Some Uncollected Authors XLIV. George Cumberland,
                        1754-1848,” <hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi> 19 (1970): 32-65,
                        hereafter cited as “Uncollected Authors”; Gerald E. Bentley,
                        Jr., <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of George Cumberland</hi> (New York:
                        Garland Publishing Co., 1975), hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>; Gerald E. Bentley Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969), hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">BR</hi> with the page number. Also consulted was the Cumberland
                        correspondence, formerly in the British Museum where it was cited in the
                        literature as British Museum Additional Manuscripts, B.M. Add. MSS. 36,495 -
                        36,497, June 1785-94, and now in the British Library, hereafter cited as
                        B.L. Add. MSS with number. I wish to thank the British Library for their
                        kind permission to quote from these manuscripts.</note><note id="n32"><hi rend="s">5</hi> In “Uncollected Authors” 35-36,
                        Douce is mentioned briefly in connection with the Cumberland correspondence
                        now in the British Library. In Bentley’s valuable bibliographies and
                        records published in regard to Blake and Cumberland the name Douce is also
                        mentioned.</note><note id="n33"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Preliminary lists of the bequest were made by
                        A. C. Madan, “Rough Catalog of Douce Prints and Summary
                        Guide,” Vol. I, 1915-16; G. R. Scott, “A Catalogue of the
                        Collections in Portfolio of Engravings . . .,” Vol. II, Feb-July 1916
                        [R.6.260]. A printed catalogue was made by [H. O. Coxe, with Henry Symonds,
                        Arthur Brown], <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Printed Books and Manuscripts
                            bequeathed by Francis Douce Esq. to the Bodleian Library</hi> (Oxford:
                        Oxford UP, 1840 [R.6.92]), hereafter cited as 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue.</hi> The correspondence, MSS. Douce d. 20-29, d. 32, d. 39,
                        extending from 1788 to 1834 was consulted. Three small notebooks of
                        purchases, the “Collecta,” MS. Douce e. 66, 1803-1810; e. 67,
                        1811-1823; e. 68, 1824-1834, the socalled “Diary of Antiquarian
                        Purchases” were consulted, along with the typed transcript [R6.91],
                        hereafter cited as TS. “Collecta.” I wish to thank the
                        Bodleian Library for their permission to publish material from these
                        sources. I owe thanks to the librarians in Duke Humphrey’s Library at
                        the Bodleian Library for their attentive help, and especially to Clive
                        Hurst, Head of Special Collections at the Bodleian Library, who confirmed
                        and corrected where necessary some of my readings of the passages in the
                        “Collecta” and in the typescript by comparing my citations
                        with the original notebooks. The Ashmolean holdings are of prints and
                        manuscripts formerly at the Bodleian Library which, judged to be primarily
                        of artistic rather than literary interest, were transferred to the
                        University Galleries in 1863; in 1915, another exchange occurred, so that
                        more fine prints and drawings came to the Department of Prints and Drawings
                        at the Ashmolean. In the Ashmolean Archives are notebooks, manuscripts and
                        miscellaneous material on art, the Douce Bequest, The Bell Bookcase, 3
                        Boxes. I would like to thank the Ashmolean Museum for their permission to
                        publish material from this source. My thanks also go to the Assistant
                        Keepers in the Department of Prints and Drawings in the Ashmolean Museum,
                        Dr. John Whiteley and Dr. Catherine Whistler and to the Print Room
                        Supervisior, Dr. Bernadette Nelson, for their patient and generous
                        help.</note></p>
        <p>This paper will show when and how these three individuals, first only loosely
                    connected through location and developing common interests, finally came into
                    closer contact by the 1800s. Though we know that in Douce’s collection at
                    his death there were two books of illuminated printing by Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> Copy B with the separate plate,
                    “Our End is come,” and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> Copy I,
                    plus the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> Copy H and a third state of the
                        <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>,<ref target="n34" type="note">7</ref>
                    a 1794 purchase which will be discussed below has not been previously noted,
                    Blake’s <hi rend="i">For Children: the Gates of Paradise.</hi> Douce
                    likewise collected some of Cumberland’s books, but more important is the
                    revelation of the way Douce used Cumberland as one of his resources for
                    information about the visual arts. Campbell Dodgson called Douce a bibliophile
                    and collector of woodcuts of advanced taste.<ref target="n35" type="note">8</ref> I suggest that Cumberland, in his appreciation of early woodcuts
                    and the work of Giulio di Antonio Bonasone<ref target="n36" type="note">9</ref>
                    and in his advocacy of Blake, both personally and through his books, played a
                    role in forming that taste. This essay also offers corroborating information to
                    that recently published by Joseph Viscomi.<ref target="n37" type="note">10</ref>
                    With his suggestion that Isaac D’Israeli, a close friend and
                    correspondent of Douce, bought in 1834 part of George Romney’s collection
                    of books in illuminated printing by Blake, Viscomi focuses interest on new ways
                    of understanding how Blake’s books were produced and collected,
                    illuminating the “tenuousness of our assumptions regarding patronage and
                    the earliest modes by which illuminated books were produced and
                        disseminated.”<ref target="n38" type="note">11</ref> In the Douce
                    bequest, a hitherto unpublished network of relationships reveals more
                    information about practices of selling and collecting books and prints during
                    the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Douce B. 790, Arch. A. d. 22, <hi rend="i">The Book of
                        Thel</hi>, ?1786-1803; Douce MM. 834, Arch. G. d. 53, <hi rend="i">The
                            Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, 1790-93, as in <hi rend="i">DL</hi>
                        89-90. For information on these holdings, see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books: Annotated Catalogues of William Blake’s
                            Writings</hi> . . . (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977) 57, 118-128,
                        133-138, 285-298, hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">BB</hi> with page number.
                        See <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 658, #553, for the Douce 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> 32, where only <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> are listed, and to which the other books should be added.
                        For the impression, 1A, “Our End is come,” bound in with <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate
                            Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP,
                        1983) 30, hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">SP.</hi> For <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, see Essick <hi rend="i">SP</hi> 63,
                        impression 3D.</note><note id="n35"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Woodcuts of the Fifteenth Century in the Ashmolean Museum, with
                            notes of similar prints at the Bodleian</hi>, ed. Campbell Dodgson
                        (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1929) 6.</note><note id="n36"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The first catalogue of Bonasone (fl. 1531-74)
                        was written by Cumberland (see note 30 below). Cumberland and his
                        contemporaries spelled Bonasone with a terminal <hi rend="i">i</hi> which I
                        retain for their writings.</note><note id="n37"><hi rend="s">10</hi> “The Myth of Commissioned Illuminated
                        Books: George Romney, Isaac D’Israeli, and “ONE HUNDRED AND
                        SIXTY designs . . . of Blake’s,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23
                        (1989): 48-74.</note><note id="n38"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Viscomi 65.</note></p>
        <p>Douce and Blake were both born in 1757, Cumberland three years earlier.<ref target="n39" type="note">12</ref> Socially, Douce’s family was more
                    highly placed than that of the middleclass Cumberland or the artisan Blake. All
                    three were younger sons, a position affecting their education and income: in the
                    1770s, Douce was admitted as an attorney of the King’s Bench, Cumberland
                    worked at the Royal Exchange Assurance Office in London, finally earning
                    £60 per annum,<ref target="n40" type="note">13</ref> and Blake served his
                    apprenticeship with James Basire, the engraver for the Society of Antiquaries.
                    Cumberland was admitted as a student at the Royal Academy in 1772, an expression
                    of his true interests.<ref target="n41" type="note">14</ref> In their third
                    decade, the three men approached the world of books and prints from different
                    directions. Douce was said to have made his first purchase of an antique coin at
                    age 10.<ref target="n42" type="note">15</ref> Elected as a Fellow of the Society
                    of Antiquaries by 1779, he tried to devote himself to literary and antiquarian
                    pursuits as much as possible. Blake was said to have frequented print-shops and
                    auction sales as a boy. He aspired to be a painter and poet: his first
                    exhibition at the Royal Academy was reviewed by Cumberland. Upon the death of
                    his father in 1784, he went into a brief partnership with James Parker as an
                    engraver and printseller, after which he began to make his own books and
                    reproductive engravings for others. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Unless
                        otherwise noted, I draw the following material on Douce and Blake from the
                        “Introduction” in <hi rend="i">DL</hi> and from <hi rend="i">BR.</hi></note><note id="n40"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Black (see note 4 above) 24, 85.</note><note id="n41"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> Bibliography</hi> 49, according to the MS. list of Students
                        Admitted to the Royal Academy.</note><note id="n42"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 22, #34.</note></p>
        <p>Cumberland had an omnivorous interest in learning and in writing; by 1780 he
                    reported to his brother that he had met some “Geniuses and Men of
                        Science.”<ref target="n43" type="note">16</ref> By 1784, he knew and
                    wrote on behalf of the sculptor, Thomas Banks, and through him met Richard
                    Cosway, and, later, Thomas Johnes and Horne Tooke.<ref target="n44" type="note">17</ref> In 1784, Cumberland came into a £300 inheritance, releasing
                    him from his fourteen years of “servitude” <pb id="p26-10" n="10"/> at the Royal Exchange.<ref target="n45" type="note">18</ref> Devoting himself
                    to experiments in printing and practical ways of self-publishing, he probably
                    shared this knowledge with Blake. Traveling several times to the continent,
                    Cumberland met Baron de Murr in Nuremberg and the librarian of the Grand Duke of
                    Tuscany in Florence, experiences he later recorded in his book <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> of 1796.<ref target="n46" type="note">19</ref>
                    Settling in Italy by 1788, away from the “cold weather and cold
                    receptions” given to his unorthodox family in England,<ref target="n47" type="note">20</ref> he cultivated friends like John Irvine in that
                    “school of real students in sculpture and painting” in Rome.<ref target="n48" type="note">21</ref> He established lifelong relationships with
                    dealers and gem-cutters of Rome, collecting gems, books, prints and information.
                        <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Black 267.</note><note id="n44"><hi rend="s">17</hi><hi rend="i"> Annals</hi> 25, 56, 57; Black 307. For a full account of Johnes
                        and his connections with Cumberland and Blake, see Morton D. Paley,
                        “Thomas Johnes, ‘Ancient Guardian of Wales,’”
                            <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 2 (1969): 65-67, hereafter cited as
                        “Johnes.”</note><note id="n45"><hi rend="s">18</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36, 494, fol. 225, as cited
                        in “Uncollected Authors” 32.</note><note id="n46"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> Thoughts on Outline, Sculpture, and the System that guided the
                            ancient artists in composing their figures and groupes: Accompanied with
                            free remarks on the practice of the moderns, and liberal hints cordially
                            intended for their advantage. To which are annexed twenty-four designs
                            of classical subjects invented on the principles recommended in the
                            essay by George Cumberland</hi> (London, 1796) 27, hereafter cited as
                            <hi rend="i">Thoughts.</hi></note><note id="n47"><hi rend="s">20</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,496, fols. 16, 17, 31 July
                        1788, to his Mother. Cumberland went to Italy with the abused wife and
                        children of his former landlord, making a monetary settlement arranged by
                        John Flaxman with her former husband. B.L. Add. MSS. 36,495, fol. 372, 10
                        May 1788, from Mrs. E. Cumberland, “I am now your own for you have
                        paid dearly for me.”</note><note id="n48"><hi rend="s">21</hi><hi rend="i"> Thoughts</hi> 10; George Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Outlines from
                            the Antients, exhibiting their principles of composition in figures and
                            basso-rilievos taken chiefly from inedited monuments of Greek and Roman
                            sculpture.</hi> With an introductory essay (London, 1829) iv.</note></p>
        <p>Douce began in 1779 a correspondence with Richard Twiss, a wealthy older fellow
                    antiquary, traveler and miscellaneous writer, from which we gain an insight into
                    Douce’s early concern with collecting.<ref target="n49" type="note">22</ref> Twiss mentions in 1788 Mr. Edwards, Mr. Raspe, Mr. Marchand,
                    bookseller, cataloguer and gem-cutter respectively,<ref target="n50" type="note">23</ref> as men in whom Douce would take an interest. The Edwards brothers,
                    James and John, opened their Pall Mall book-shop in 1784. Jean Hagstrum suggests
                    that Blake probably knew the shop and that he may have seen there medieval
                    prayer books, like the Bedford Book of Hours.<ref target="n51" type="note">24</ref> In 1788, Blake is said to have discovered how to print illuminated
                    books using relief-etched plates.<ref target="n52" type="note">25</ref> In the
                    same year Douce makes one of his major purchases, an illuminated book of hours
                    printed in Paris in 1505.<ref target="n53" type="note">26</ref> No connection is
                    claimed between Douce and the two others at this time, but all express from
                    different perspectives their interest in similar fields. <note id="n49"><hi rend="s">22</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, Bushhill, Edmonton and other
                        addresses, 1779-1806; <hi rend="i">DL</hi> 122, #179; <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Bibliography.</hi></note><note id="n50"><hi rend="s">23</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 3, 18 October 1788;
                        fol. 7, 26 November 1788; fol. 8, 7 December 1788. Douce also corresponds
                        with Ritson, Steevens, and Edwards in this period, and later was in frequent
                        contact with the Cosways.</note><note id="n51"><hi rend="s">24</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake: Poet and Painter</hi> (Chicago: University of
                        Chicago P, 1964) 31-33; David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against
                            Empire: A poet’s interpretation of the history of his own
                            times.</hi> 3rd rev. ed. (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1977) 130,
                        507.</note><note id="n52"><hi rend="s">25</hi> For a full explanation of Blake’s
                        process of relief-etching, see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake,
                            Printmaker</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1980) chapter 3.</note><note id="n53"><hi rend="s">26</hi> The purchase was made at the sale of Thomas
                        Pearson in April of 1788. Douce CC 290(3), <hi rend="i">DL</hi>
                    135.</note></p>
        <p>The French Revolution causes Cumberland to return to England in 1790, settling
                    first in Lyndhurst, near Southhampton, and then moving to Bishopsgate near
                    Windsor Great Park by 1794.<ref target="n54" type="note">27</ref> Cumberland has
                    the Edwards’ shop bind his books; Douce also patronizes the Edwards in
                    1790, buying printed books and two manuscripts from the catalogue.<ref target="n55" type="note">28</ref> Blake, working in London all this time,
                    publishes in 1789 <hi rend="i">The Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
                        Book of Thel</hi>; by 1790, his imagination fired by the Revolution, he
                    finishes some plates of his <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> By
                    1795 he makes eight more books, prints color-prints, and does much reproductive
                    engraving. In the same year, Richard Edwards, the younger brother of the
                    booksellers, asks Blake to make drawings and engravings for an edition of
                    Young’s <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">27</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,496, fols.
                        184, 199; B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fols. 298, 299, 12 May 1794,
                        Bishopsgate.</note><note id="n55"><hi rend="s">28</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fols. 59, 60, 19
                        October 1791; <hi rend="i">DL</hi> 136.</note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Cumberland also publishes three books:<ref target="n56" type="note">29</ref>
                        he mentions on 17 January 1792 that he has laid his work before “one
                        of our first rate London Collectors, a Dignitary of high literary character
                        who unites to a great fortune great knowledge in all that is worth knowing
                        or having” and has had it approved.<ref target="n57" type="note">30</ref> The work, <hi rend="i">Some Anecdotes of the life of Julio
                            Bonasoni</hi>, published by 17 February 1793,<ref target="n58" type="note">31</ref> is dedicated to Sir William Hamilton who may have
                        been the “London Collector.” By 6 March over half these books
                        were sold.<ref target="n59" type="note">32</ref> Douce purchases
                        Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Bonasoni</hi> by November 1793, as we know
                        from a letter of thanks from Andrew Lumisden, who borrowed the book of
                        Douce: “I return you, with many thanks, Cumberland’s anecdotes
                        of the life of Bonasoni.”<ref target="n60" type="note">33</ref>
                        Cumberland visits Johnes, a patron of Banks and Stothard, between May and
                        July 1794, and dedicates in 1796 a “really beautiful book,”
                            <hi rend="i">An Attempt to Describe Hafod</hi>, describing the residence
                        in Wales.<ref target="n61" type="note">34</ref> Johnes uses the
                        Edwards’ Pall Mall bookshop for more than antiquarian purchases: he
                        sends Cumberland a halibut in care of Edwards.<ref target="n62" type="note">35</ref> At the same time, Cumberland and Blake are in very close touch
                        as Blake engraves for Cumberland eight plates dated 1794 and 1795 for <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline.</hi><ref target="n63" type="note">36</ref>
                        Two preserved letters from Blake to Cumberland in 1795 and 1796 show the
                        strength and familiarity of this relationship.<ref target="n64" type="note">37</ref> Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> was
                        inventoried in Douce’s bequest but he did not purchase it until
                            1818.<ref target="n65" type="note">38</ref><note id="n56"><hi rend="s">29</hi> See “Uncollected Authors”
                            57-65, for the complete bibliography, to which information from <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> 3-36, and G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
                            “Cumberland Bibliography Addenda,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
                            11 (1977): 128 should be added.</note><note id="n57"><hi rend="s">30</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fols. 109, 110,
                            27 January 1792.</note><note id="n58"><hi rend="s">31</hi><hi rend="i"> Some Anecdotes of the life of Julio Bonasoni, a Bolognese
                                artist, who followed the styles of the best schools in the sixteenth
                                century. Accompanied by a catalogue of the engravings, with their
                                measures, of the works of that tasteful composer. And remarks on the
                                general character of his rare and exquisite performances. To which
                                is prefixed, a plan for the improvement of the Arts in England</hi>
                            (London, 1793), hereafter cited as Bonasoni; B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497,
                            fols. 234, 235, 17 Feb. 1793, Richard Cumberland to George Cumberland;
                            fol. 236, 27 Feb. 1793, Charles Long to Cumberland.</note><note id="n59"><hi rend="s">32</hi> In a letter from Cumberland’s
                            bookseller, W. Lucas, B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fol. 241, 11 March
                            1793.</note><note id="n60"><hi rend="s">33</hi> MS. Douce d. 20, fol. 52, 30 November
                            1793.</note><note id="n61"><hi rend="s">34</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fols. 300, 301,
                            ?29 May 1794, and 318, 28 July 1794, from Johnes to Cumberland. A. C.
                            Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London: 1906) 12,
                            notes that Stothard decorated the library of Hafod. See also <hi rend="i">Annals</hi> 120; “Johnes” 66-67;
                            “Uncollected Authors” 58.</note><note id="n62"><hi rend="s">35</hi> B.L. Add. MSS. 36,497, fol. 318, 28 July
                            1794.</note><note id="n63"><hi rend="s">36</hi><hi rend="i"> Bibliography</hi> 15-17.</note><note id="n64"><hi rend="s">37</hi><hi rend="i"> The Letters of William Blake with related Documents</hi>,
                            3rd ed., ed. Geoffrey Keynes (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1980) 5, 6; 6
                            December 1795 and 23 December 1796.</note><note id="n65"><hi rend="s">38</hi> 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>(note 6
                            above), where it is listed as C. subt. 180; see <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> 17 for Cumberland’s withdrawal of the book
                            from the market and his subsequent public sales of it between 1804 and
                            1815. See note 115 below for details.</note></p>
          <p>By 6 August 1792, Twiss is in Paris buying for Douce.<ref target="n66" type="note">39</ref> However, in a hastily scrawled letter of 25 August
                        1792, Twiss recounts his relief at his escape from Paris, with his head
                        still affixed to his body and not on a pike: “The Lord have mercy on
                        the two thousand English now in Paris!”<ref target="n67" type="note">40</ref> Blake’s close associates, the Swiss artist, Henry
                        Fuseli, and Joseph Johnson, the publisher and bookseller, plan to go to
                        France as well in the same year, but are deterred by the events of the
                        Terror. The name Fuseli is mentioned in connection with another facet of
                        Douce’s interest in natural science: Twiss had begun sending to Douce
                        unhatched pupae, describing in detail the butterflies which would emerge,
                        including information on mounting the specimens. Among the books about which
                        he tells Douce is one by Fuseli’s brother, “‘Fuesleis
                        [sic] les insectes de la Suisse’, 4<hi rend="s">to</hi>, with 55
                            Col.<hi rend="s">d</hi> plates.”<ref target="n68" type="note">41</ref> On 2 September 1794, Twiss mentions “the book of
                        directions for insects from johnson” at St. Paul’s Churchyard,
                        indicating that Douce already has it.<ref target="n69" type="note">42</ref><note id="n66"><hi rend="s">39</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 44.</note><note id="n67"><hi rend="s">40</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 45.</note><note id="n68"><hi rend="s">41</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fol. 55, 9 April
                            [?August] 1794. See Eudo Mason, <hi rend="i">The Mind of Henry Fuseli:
                                Selections from his Writings with an Introductory Study</hi>(London:
                            Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1951) 358, for a listing of Johan H.
                            Fuseli’s review of his translation of a book by his brother, J.
                            C. Fuseli, in the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> 21 (May 1795):
                            523. Mason mistakenly gives the title as <hi rend="i">Archives of
                                Etymology</hi>, but it should be Fuessly’s <hi rend="i">Archives of Entomology, containing the History, or ascertaining the
                                Characters and Classes of Insects not hitherto described,
                                imperfectly known, or erroneously classified</hi> (London: Joseph
                            Johnson, 1795) 523-24. The original designs were by Schellenberg.</note><note id="n69"><hi rend="s">42</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fols. 68, 69, 2
                            September 1794.</note></p>
          <p>Despite these indications that Douce had a marginal knowledge of Fuseli and
                        Johnson, figures well known to Blake, the first mention of the name of Blake
                        in connection with that of Douce occurs in a letter from Twiss to Douce on
                        13 September 1794.<ref target="n70" type="note">43</ref> Blake had printed
                            <hi rend="i">For Children: Gates of Paradise</hi>, “Published by
                        William Blake #13 Hercules Building Lambeth and J. Johnson St. Paul’s
                        Churchyard” by 1793.<ref target="n71" type="note">44</ref> In a
                        letter to Douce whose first two paragraphs deal with exchanges of books and
                        with entomology, Twiss mentions the book in the third paragraph. <q> . . . a
                            lady here has just shown me . . . two curious works of Blake No. 13
                            Hercules Build[ing] Lambeth. One “the gates of Paradise”,
                            16 etchings. 2 A <hi rend="s">mo</hi> the other “Songs of
                            innocence” printed [crossed out] colours. I suppose the man to be
                            mad, but he draws very well. have [you] anything by him?<ref target="n72" type="note">45</ref></q> Douce underlines this last question in red ink, a habit he had
                        initiated in the 1780s to emphasize passages which <pb id="p26-11" n="11"/>
                        interested him in letters he received. Douce must have commissioned Twiss to
                        obtain the mentioned books, because in Twiss’s next letter, we find
                        underlined in red ink <hi rend="i">Saturday, next, 27th.</hi><q> On Saturday, next, 27th, any time after 12 o’clock, if you will
                            be so good as to send to the Black Bull Holborn, you will find there
                            ready, your Barbuth, Monffot, 3 [?impastein] Donovans insects<hi rend="s">t</hi> [?Jere] Taylors, Mandeville on Stews, &amp; my
                            Curtis insects &amp; Blakes Paradise, and also a very curious <hi rend="i">Caterpillars</hi>, which will produce next May Linnaeus <hi rend="i">Phalena Pudebunda.</hi><ref target="n73" type="note">46</ref></q> This hitherto unnoted and unmentioned copy of <hi rend="i">For
                            Children: Gates of Paradise</hi> must not have been kept by Douce as it
                        does not appear to be in the Bodleian Library now.<ref target="n74" type="note">47</ref><note id="n70"><hi rend="s">43</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 70<hi rend="s">r</hi>. In April of 1991, when I did my research at the Bodleian
                            Library, Mr. J.A. Brister kindly offered help to me by showing me his
                            corrected transcript of the “Collecta” and by mentioning
                            to me his rememberance of a reference to Blake in the Douce
                            correspondence. His sharing of this recollection led me to look for and
                            find the Blake material mentioned in this paper. Mr. Brister’s
                            death in June marks not only a personal deprivation for his colleagues
                            but a loss for scholars in this area.</note><note id="n71"><hi rend="s">44</hi> See <hi rend="i">BB</hi> 185-193, for
                            details about <hi rend="i">Gates.</hi></note><note id="n72"><hi rend="s">45</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, 13 September 1794,
                            fol. 70<hi rend="s">v</hi>.</note><note id="n73"><hi rend="s">46</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, 25 September 1794,
                            fol. 72<hi rend="s">r</hi>.</note><note id="n74"><hi rend="s">47</hi> This book is not listed in the
                            unreferenced 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue.</hi> See Gerald E. Bentley
                            Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement: Being New Materials Relating
                                to the Life of William Blake Discovered Since the Publication of
                                Blake Records</hi> (1969) (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1988) 85, hereafter
                            cited as <hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi>, where five copies, none in the
                            Bodleian, are listed. Copy A, now in the Library of Congress, Lessing G.
                            Rosenwald Collection, is the only known proof copy. While in the hands
                            of W. E. Moss, six copies of Copy A were printed in perhaps 1942 of
                            photographic reproductions; I infer one of these is the one mentioned as
                            at the Bodleian Library (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 185, 192, 193).</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland makes contacts with other collectors, noting in the <hi rend="i">Anecdotes of Bonasoni</hi> that he knows the exquisite collection of
                        the Rev. Mr. Cracherode. <q> I lately, saw in the portfolios of Mr.
                            Cracherode, a print of a battle of naked men, ten or twelve figures, in
                            folio, well preserved, with a label, on which was written, Antionio
                            Pollojolo [sic] opus.<ref target="n75" type="note">48</ref><note id="n75"><hi rend="s">48</hi><hi rend="i"> Bonasoni</hi> 34, 66, referring to what is probably a
                                copy of Anthonio Pollaiuolo, <hi rend="i">Battle of the Nudes</hi>,
                                B.001.</note></q> Clayton Mordaunt Cracherode, the reclusive London collector who
                        bequeathes his collection to the British Museum in 1799,<ref target="n76" type="note">49</ref> has interests similar to those of Douce. On 12 May
                        1795, Douce receives this invitation, “Mr. Cracherode presents his
                        complements to Mr. Douce, and will be very happy to see him on Thursday
                        next, at any time that may be convenient to him from eleven to two
                            o’clock.”<ref target="n77" type="note">50</ref> In a Douce
                        manuscript of unknown date, the “Curiosities of Engraving or
                        Anecdotes of Prints,” he mentions Cracherode’s copy of
                        “Cupid and Psyche by A Venetian &amp; Cumberland’s opinion of
                            it.”<ref target="n78" type="note">51</ref> Thus, while there is
                        no hard evidence that Douce knows Cumberland and Blake personally, their
                        paths are certainly parallel and perhaps touch. <note id="n76"><hi rend="s">49</hi><hi rend="i"> Dictionary of National Biography.</hi></note><note id="n77"><hi rend="s">50</hi> MS. Douce d. 20, fol. 61, 12 May 1795,
                            Queen’s Square.</note><note id="n78"><hi rend="s">51</hi> “The Curiosities of Engraving or
                            Anecdotes of Prints,” 103, Box 2, Bell Bookcase, Douce Bequest
                            1834, Department of Prints and Drawings, Ashmolean Museum, hereafter
                            cited as “Curiosities.”</note></p>
          <p>By 1793 D’Israeli and Douce were on friendly terms, D’Israeli
                        writing to Douce from Exeter. D’Israeli, preparing a new addition of
                        the second volume of <hi rend="i">Curiosities of Literature</hi>, asks Douce
                        on 24 July for corrections and improvements.<ref target="n79" type="note">52</ref> On 2 September 1794, D’Israeli mentions Dyer’s
                        catalogue which is “pretty bulky;” it has 300 pages and
                        consists of 1186 works.<ref target="n80" type="note">53</ref> As of 14
                        September 1793, Douce apparently does not yet own the catalogue.<ref target="n81" type="note">54</ref> Again on 25 June 1796,
                        D’Israeli reminds Douce that “Dyer is preparing a rich and
                        voluminous Catalogue.”<ref target="n82" type="note">55</ref><note id="n79"><hi rend="s">52</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fols. 1, 2.</note><note id="n80"><hi rend="s">53</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fols. 3, 4.</note><note id="n81"><hi rend="s">54</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fols. 5, 6.</note><note id="n82"><hi rend="s">55</hi> MS. Douce d. 33, fols. 22,
                        23.</note></p>
          <p>In Exeter by 1783, Gilbert Dyer advertised a catalogue of his library, an
                        example of the beginning of circulating libraries; by 1811, Dyer was selling
                        libraries as large as 2600 items for several thousand pounds.<ref target="n83" type="note">56</ref> This method of sales from
                        “Retailers of libraries by Marked Catalogues,” as well as from
                        “Sellers of books by the Hammer” was prevalent at the
                            time.<ref target="n84" type="note">57</ref> Dyer’s importance
                        here is in connection with a sale of a Blake book to Douce, as we shall see
                        below. <note id="n83"><hi rend="s">56</hi> For Dyer, 1743-1820, see Ian
                            Maxted, “‘4 rotten cornbags and some old books’:
                            The Impact of the Printed Word in Devon,” in Robin Myers and
                            Michael Harris, eds. <hi rend="i">Sale and Distribution of Books, from
                                1700</hi> (Oxford: Oxford Polytechnic Press, 1982) 66, 69n74.</note><note id="n84"><hi rend="s">57</hi> See Gwyn Walters, “Early Sale
                            Catalogues: Problems and Perspectives,” in Myers and Harris 118
                            (note 56 above), quoting Richard Gough (1735-1809), “Father of
                            British Antiquity.”</note></p>
          <p>Twiss gossips with Douce in a letter of 17 April 1797 that “Caleb Wms
                        is married to the Rights of Woman for sure,” referring of course to
                        William Godwin and Mary Wollstonecraft.<ref target="n85" type="note">58</ref> He mentions that he expects at his home Thomas Holcroft and
                        his daughter who plays the piano well.<ref target="n86" type="note">59</ref>
                        With these references, Twiss displays his knowledge of the radical circle
                        with which Blake was connected and, at the same time, indicates that Douce
                        would be interested in learning about them.<ref target="n87" type="note">60</ref> Douce’s politics and religion are summarized in the
                        Bodleian catalogue: a Deist, he was “A Radical in politics, his
                        watchwords were Liberty and Justice, and his hero was Napoleon.”<ref target="n88" type="note">61</ref><note id="n85"><hi rend="s">58</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 96.</note><note id="n86"><hi rend="s">59</hi> MS. Douce d. 39, fol. 97<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 8 January 1796.</note><note id="n87"><hi rend="s">60</hi> Erdman <hi rend="i">Prophet</hi> 38-39,
                            154, 156, 159, describes this circle, mentioning in particular the
                            friendship among James Barry, Thomas Holcroft and William Godwin. He
                            notes the dinners in Johnson’s rooms where Fuseli, Godwin,
                            Holcroft, and Blake were present, and he is certain Blake must have been
                            acquainted with the Society for Constitutional Information, revived by
                            Hollis and Tooke, who in turn is Cumberland’s friend. According
                            to William St. Clair, <hi rend="i">The Godwins and the Shelleys: The
                                Biography of a Family</hi> (London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1989) 163,
                            Godwin was introduced to Blake 26 May 1796.</note><note id="n88"><hi rend="s">61</hi> As cited in <hi rend="i">DL</hi> 8,
                            9.</note></p>
          <p>In 1799, at the death of both his father and mother, Douce has £3000
                        settled on him, expanding his ability to purchase books, prints,
                        manuscripts, and coins.<ref target="n89" type="note">62</ref> The artist
                        James Barry, a familiar of Godwin and Holcroft, is known to Douce by 1800:
                        D’Israeli invites Douce to dine, proposing also to ask Barry and
                        “Dr. Grant, a friend of Fuseli.”<ref target="n90" type="note">63</ref> Douce records that in 1800 and 1801 he bought from Barry his
                        letters to the “dilettanti society” and to the “society
                        of arts”; he also lent books to Barry during the same period.<ref target="n91" type="note">64</ref> In April 1807, Douce bought drawings
                        by Barry at his sale.<ref target="n92" type="note">65</ref> Blake, by 1800
                        in Felpham for three years, also indicated a renewed interest in Barry at
                        this time, recording in outrage that “While Sr Joshua was rolling in
                        Riches Barry was Poor &amp; unemployd except by his own Energy.”<ref target="n93" type="note">66</ref><note id="n89"><hi rend="s">62</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> ix.</note><note id="n90"><hi rend="s">63</hi> For Barry, see <hi rend="i">DL</hi> 3-5,
                            which cites MS. Douce d. 33, fol. 152.</note><note id="n91"><hi rend="s">64</hi> MS. Douce e. 69, fols. 4, 5; Douce e.
                            74, 1800.</note><note id="n92"><hi rend="s">65</hi> TS. “Collecta” 21, #5 (MS.
                            Douce e. 66, fol. 20<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note><note id="n93"><hi rend="s">66</hi> In Blake’s Annotations to <hi rend="i">The Works of Sir Joshua Reynolds</hi>, ed. Edward Malone
                            (London, 1798), as in David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete
                                Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (New York:
                            Doubleday, 1988) 636.</note></p>
          <p>A closer connection between Cumberland and Douce emerges in 1798, when
                        Cumberland prints <hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar: An
                            African Tale</hi>, a disguised satire critical of the Pitt
                        administration, a book of which Mr. Erskine “deemed it dangerous,
                        under Mr. Pitt’s maladministration, to publish.”<ref target="n94" type="note">67</ref> Keynes names Mr. Horne Tooke and Mr.
                        Douce as Cumberland’s supporters, Tooke having made Cumberland read
                        the Manuscript through the whole way in one sitting,<ref target="n95" type="note">68</ref> and Douce buying the book.<ref target="n96" type="note">69</ref> Johnes, friend of Cumberland and patron of Stothard
                        and Banks, sends Douce digitalis seeds before 1805.<ref target="n97" type="note">70</ref> The names of Stothard, Westall and Flaxman, mutual
                        acquaintances of Cumberland and Blake, appear frequently in Douce’s
                        writings. <note id="n94"><hi rend="s">67</hi> “Uncollected
                            Authors” 60-61. See also <hi rend="i">Annals</hi> 126-27, for
                            Banks’s introduction to Erskine in 1798. Thomas Erskine
                            (1750-1823), Lord Chancellor of England, defended Thomas Paine in 1792
                            and John Horne Tooke in 1794.</note><note id="n95"><hi rend="s">68</hi> “Uncollected Authors”
                            60-61.</note><note id="n96"><hi rend="s">69</hi> 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> where
                            it is listed as C.476.</note><note id="n97"><hi rend="s">70</hi> MS. Douce d. 21, fol. 12.</note></p>
          <p>By the middle of 1801 Cumberland has to leave the London area in search of a
                        less expensive place to live; moving to Sussex, he leaves his possessions in
                        the care of his old friend, the sculptor Banks, with instructions to sell
                        over 1120 prints and 195 books through Mr. Thomas Philipe.<ref target="n98" type="note">71</ref> Thomas Dodd, whose name will appear in
                        Douce’s book of purchases, is one of the purchasers of some of
                        Cumberland’s collection at the sale which took place before 14 August
                            1802.<ref target="n99" type="note">72</ref> In the matter of collecting
                        prints, Dodd, who began issuing sale catalogues in 1806,<ref target="n100" type="note">73</ref> would seem to be important in a new kind of
                        acquisition on the part of Douce. Douce begins in 1803 to keep the
                        “Collecta” and Dodd’s name begins to show up with
                        increasing frequency as a source for prints in Douce’s list of
                            acquisitions.<ref target="n101" type="note">74</ref> For instance, Douce
                        purchases from Dodd in March 1805 anonymous woodprints of a “man
                        drawing a woman sleeping,” <pb id="p26-12" n="12"/> and “Women
                        bathing”: the first seems related to an Albrecht Dürer woodcut
                        and the second to a rare reproduction of a Dürer drawing.<ref target="n102" type="note">75</ref> Dürer’s name appears in
                        June 1805, with the purchase of “Alb. Durer’s triumph of
                        Maximilian compleat.”<ref target="n103" type="note">76</ref><note id="n98"><hi rend="s">71</hi><hi rend="i"> Annals</hi> 140-42. Bell identified the print and
                            book-seller Thomas Philipe in Frits Lugt, <hi rend="i">Les Marques de
                                Collections de Dessins &amp; D’estampes</hi> (Amsterdam,
                            1921) 457, #2451. For Philipe, see also Walters 121 (note 57
                            above).</note><note id="n99"><hi rend="s">72</hi> For the sale and the vicissitudes
                            surrounding it, see <hi rend="i">Annals</hi> 151, 153, 171. Another sale
                            by Cumberland is recorded by Frits Lugt, <hi rend="i">Repertoire des
                                Catalogues des Ventes Publiques, 1660-1825</hi> (The Hague: Martinus
                            Nijhoff, 1938) in 1803, #6616, 28 May 1803, London “A Gentleman
                            Leaving Town to reside in the Country,” conducted by
                            Phillips.</note><note id="n100"><hi rend="s">73</hi> Walters 121.</note><note id="n101"><hi rend="s">74</hi> TS. “Collecta” 5,
                            December 1803; 8 May 1804, 10 October 1804 (MS. Douce e. 66, fol. 3<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 5<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 7<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note><note id="n102"><hi rend="s">75</hi> TS. “Collecta” 12 (MS.
                            Douce e. 66, 9<hi rend="s">v</hi>). This probably refers to the woodcut
                            B. 149 (160), <hi rend="i">Draftsman Drawing a Nude in the Manual of
                                Measurement</hi>, as in Walter E. Strauss, ed. <hi rend="i">Wood-Cuts and Wood Blocks of Albrecht Dürer</hi> (New York:
                            Abaris, 1980) [SW 204]. The drawing, <hi rend="i">Women’s
                                Bath</hi>, reproduced in <hi rend="i">The Complete Drawings of
                                Albrecht Dürer</hi>, vol. I, ed. Walter E. Strauss (New York:
                            Abaris, 1974) 142 [SD 1493/4], was copied. See Campbell Dodgson,
                            “Rare Woodcuts in the Ashmolean Museum—I,” <hi rend="i">The Burlington Magazine</hi> 63 (1930): 21-24, who notes
                            among Douce’s collection of Dürer and copies of
                            Dürer in the Ashmolean the “rare <hi rend="i">Women’s Bath</hi>, reproducing in reverse
                            Dürer’s drawing of 1496,” but does not mention the
                                <hi rend="i">Draughtsman.</hi></note><note id="n103"><hi rend="s">76</hi> TS. “Collecta” 13, June
                            1805 (MS. Douce e. 66, fol. 10<hi rend="s">v</hi>), perhaps referring to
                            what is listed by Bartsch as <hi rend="i">The Triumph of Emperor
                                Maxmillian</hi>, B. 139 (154), <hi rend="i">The Great Triumphal
                                Car</hi>, 1522, [SW 188]. See Dodgson 21, for the “not very
                            early (seventeenth century?) copy of the portraits of Maximilian
                            I” in the Douce collection.</note></p>
          <p>From 1807 to 1811, Douce serves as Keeper of the Department of Manuscripts in
                        the British Museum. Unlike Cumberland, who wrote and published several
                        books, Douce published, in addition to many submissions to the Society of
                        Antiquaries, only one important book, his 1807 <hi rend="i">Illustrations of
                            Shakspeare</hi>, with one section on the Morris Dance, and, in 1833, the
                        study on The Dance of Death.<ref target="n104" type="note">77</ref><note id="n104"><hi rend="s">77</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 65; <hi rend="i">Illustrations of Shakspeare, and
                                of ancient manners: with dissertations on the clowns and fools of
                                Shakspeare; on the collection of popular tales entitled Gesta
                                Romanorum; and on the English morris dance</hi>, 2 vols. (London:
                            Longman, 1807).</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland’s sons, George Jr. and Sydney, move to London in 1808;
                        their father recommends that they look up well-placed men, including in his
                        list of names that of Mr. Douce.<ref target="n105" type="note">78</ref> The
                        young men, also liaisons to Blake, stay briefly at the home of Robert
                        Cromek, who in 1807 employs Blake to draw the illustrations for
                        Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi><ref target="n106" type="note">79</ref> Douce’s present and future friends are interested in
                        the book: Dawson Turner, whose correspondence with Douce begins in 1821,
                        mentions the “1st edition of Blake’s Blair’s
                        Grave” which he wants.<ref target="n107" type="note">80</ref> Among
                        Dodd’s papers is Cromek’s Prospectus for <hi rend="i">The
                            Grave</hi>, along with a brief biography of Blake.<ref target="n108" type="note">81</ref> Douce, however, appears not to have purchased <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi><note id="n105"><hi rend="s">78</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 209.</note><note id="n106"><hi rend="s">79</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 209. For Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> and
                            Blake’s involvment, see Robert N. Essick and Morton Paley, <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> “<hi rend="i">The
                                Grave”: A study with facsimile</hi> (London: Scolar Press,
                            1982).</note><note id="n107"><hi rend="s">80</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 5; <hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi> 72.</note><note id="n108"><hi rend="s">81</hi> A favorable comment on the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> is quoted by Bentley from the microfilm of B.L. Add. MS.
                            33,402, fol. 153, the papers of Thomas Dodd (<hi rend="i">BR</hi>171n4).
                            The Prospectus from B.L. Add. MS. 33,397, fol. 144, is reproduced in <hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi> 35, 36.</note></p>
          <p>Douce’s bequest to the Bodleian Library also includes the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809 accompanying Blake’s
                            exhibition.<ref target="n109" type="note">82</ref> Bentley says that the
                        catalogues were “issued in unlabelled greyish-Blue wrappers . . . to
                        the ‘Fit audience . . . tho few’ who paid <hi rend="i">2s.6d.</hi> to see Blake’s exhibition in 1809-10.”
                        Different from the undistributed ones, two mistakes in those issued
                        catalogues are corrected by Blake’s hand, leading Bentley to
                        conjecture that its possessors must have seen the exhibit in person. There
                        is, however, no mention in Douce’s “Collecta” of Blake
                        in 1809-10: even though Douce owned a corrected catalogue, whether he was
                        one of the few who saw the exhibition is unknown. <note id="n109"><hi rend="s">82</hi><hi rend="i"> BB</hi> 134-136, Copy H.</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland’s name begins to appear as one of Douce’s sources of
                        information in his small, but undated, note-book of queries.<ref target="n110" type="note">83</ref> The first letter from Cumberland in
                        the Douce correspondence is from Culver Street, Bristol, where Cumberland
                        finally settles in 1807. Between 1809 and 1834, Douce receives from
                        Cumberland at least 52 letters, touching not only on artistic matters, but
                        on radical political ones as well.<ref target="n111" type="note">84</ref> On
                        17 April 1809, Cumberland sends to Douce a mold of an Egyptian Torso, the
                        first of several gifts.<ref target="n112" type="note">85</ref><note id="n110"><hi rend="s">83</hi> MS. Douce e. 62, 22<hi rend="s">v</hi>;
                            e. 63, 9<hi rend="s">v</hi>.</note><note id="n111"><hi rend="s">84</hi> MS. Douce d. 21, 1; d. 22, 14; d. 23,
                            1; d. 24, 7; d. 25, 8; d. 26, 8; d. 27 11; d. 32, 3. See below for one
                            collected letter in <hi rend="i">MS.</hi> Douce d. 25 actually from
                            George Cumberland, Jr., not George Cumberland, Sr.</note><note id="n112"><hi rend="s">85</hi> MS. Douce d. 21, fol. 221.</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland writes often to Blake about publishing his new method of engraving
                        without ever persuading him, and in 1810 Cumberland jots in his notebook:
                        “communicated to Douce my Plans of engraving [omitted] publish them
                        in Nicholson.”<ref target="n113" type="note">86</ref> Continuing to
                        keep in touch with Douce, he gives Douce some prints of old little
                            Masters.<ref target="n114" type="note">87</ref> After selling his
                        Bonasone prints to the British Museum,<ref target="n115" type="note">88</ref> he replies to a Douce letter with information relative to
                        Cennino Cennini and Baron de Murr, topics mentioned in the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>: in the same letter he thanks Douce for his
                            <hi rend="i">Morris Dance.</hi><ref target="n116" type="note">89</ref>
                        The following year, Douce buys a Bonasone print of <hi rend="i">Elysium</hi>, perhaps spurred by Cumberland’s own interest in this
                            artist.<ref target="n117" type="note">90</ref> Systematically, although
                        with inaccurate orthography, Douce recorded in 1811 and 1812 purchases and
                        exchanges of books dealing with the history of art and prints, including
                        “Winckelman sur les arts. In exchange Priestley,” “De
                        Murr hist des graveurs. Deboffe,” and “Bartch’s [sic]
                        ‘Peintre graveur’ of Deboffe.”<ref target="n118" type="note">91</ref> There is a rhythmic sequence between the letters
                        and the note-books: Douce asks questions of Cumberland, Cumberland responds,
                        Douce underlines significant passages in red ink and subsequently purchases
                        the referenced object, recording it in the “Collecta.” The
                        implication is that Douce gains information from Cumberland and follows up
                        on his advice. In July 1812, Cumberland writes mentioning the loss of Horne
                        Tooke, their mutual friend.<ref target="n119" type="note">92</ref> Although
                        Cumberland uses phrases suggesting person to person contact with
                        Douce—“when we meet” or “we will talk
                        over,” other letters indicate that he fails to see Douce on visits
                        made to London.<ref target="n120" type="note">93</ref> In the next year,
                        Cumberland calls on Blake, Cosway and Stothard.<ref target="n121" type="note">94</ref><note id="n113"><hi rend="s">86</hi> For this correspondence see Gerald E.
                            Bentley Jr. and Martin Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi>
                            (Minneapolis: U of Minnesota Press, 1964) 63, citing Cumberland’s
                                <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> for 1810, B.L. Add. MSS. 36,520A, fols.
                            14-16. William Nicholson’s <hi rend="i">Journal of Natural
                                Philosophy, Chemistry and the Arts</hi> was the intended
                            publication.</note><note id="n114"><hi rend="s">87</hi> TS. “Collecta” 45,
                            February 1811, #3 (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 1<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note><note id="n115"><hi rend="s">88</hi> Lugt, <hi rend="i">D’estampes</hi> 55 (note 71 above), says the sale was
                            1811.</note><note id="n116"><hi rend="s">89</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 45, 8 April
                            1811.</note><note id="n117"><hi rend="s">90</hi> TS. “Collecta” 49, June
                            1812, #7 (MS. Douce e. 67, 5<hi rend="s">v</hi>). This print is probably
                            the one now in the Ashmolean: D.IT 10.Roy., B.xv.139.101, <hi rend="i">Love caught in the Elystan Fields and bound to a tree</hi>, 1563,
                            Giulio Bonasone, inventore.</note><note id="n118"><hi rend="s">91</hi> TS. “Collecta” 47,
                            December 1811, #5; 49, June 1812, #10; 50, July 1812, #12, (MS. Douce e.
                            67, fols. 3<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 6<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 6<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note><note id="n119"><hi rend="s">92</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 100, 15 July
                            1812.</note><note id="n120"><hi rend="s">93</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 46<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 8 April 1811; MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 82<hi rend="s">r</hi>,
                            10 February 1812; fol. 142, 26 December 1813.</note><note id="n121"><hi rend="s">94</hi> “Uncollected Authors”
                            46.</note></p>
          <p>In January 1813, Cumberland answers a question regarding an edition of
                        Boccaccio in English of 1634,<ref target="n122" type="note">95</ref> by
                        spring, Cumberland sends Douce his “Tales.”<ref target="n123" type="note">96</ref> In the “Collecta,” Douce enters:
                        “Mr. Cumberland gave me two curious Engl. editions of Bocaccio and of
                        the Q. of Navarre’s tales.”<ref target="n124" type="note">97</ref> By April, Douce appears to have bought the Tales.<ref target="n125" type="note">98</ref> Cumberland mentions to Douce his
                        plans for a publication and his trust in the print-seller Colnaghi.<ref target="n126" type="note">99</ref> Douce seems to have offered his help,
                        as Cumberland says he will be guided entirely by Douce’s advice in
                        regard to a publisher.<ref target="n127" type="note">100</ref> This letter
                        ends: “God bless you &amp; keep you from Despotism,” one of
                        several allusions to their mutual aversion to the present political state.
                        In Douce’s “Curiosities of Engraving,” Cumberland is
                        mentioned twice in connection with prints by Bonasone: there are references
                        “to Cumberland’s letter to me of the 10th April 1813”
                        and to a page number in Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Bonasoni.</hi><ref target="n128" type="note">101</ref><note id="n122"><hi rend="s">95</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 110<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 19 January 1813.</note><note id="n123"><hi rend="s">96</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fols. 117, 118, 28
                            March 1813.</note><note id="n124"><hi rend="s">97</hi> TS. “Collecta” 53, March
                            1813, #8 (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 9<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note><note id="n125"><hi rend="s">98</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 119<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 20 April 1813.</note><note id="n126"><hi rend="s">99</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fols. 117, 118, 28
                            March 1813.</note><note id="n127"><hi rend="s">100</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 120<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 12 April 1813.</note><note id="n128"><hi rend="s">101</hi> “Curiosities” 23, 71
                            (note 51 above).</note></p>
          <p>This relationship becomes more intense in 1814. Cumberland must have sent his
                        manuscript to Douce, because he writes a letter apologizing for careless
                        errors in it due to hasty writing; the errors have been corrected by
                        Douce’s exacting scholarship.<ref target="n129" type="note">102</ref>
                        In the same letter, Cumberland begins to renew his descriptions of his
                        collection of instructional prints, incorrectly called “the Tarocchi
                        Cards of Mantegna.”<ref target="n130" type="note">103</ref> These
                        were owned by other Englishmen of the period, including Douce;
                        Cumberland’s is one of the earliest extant sets. Cumberland mentions
                        specific ones, describing his “ancient plates” of the
                        “Prima Causa” and “an old half naked man and a
                            dog.”<ref target="n131" type="note">104</ref> Douce, interested
                        in playing cards, soon sees <pb id="p26-13" n="13"/> Cumberland’s
                        collection, copying into his “Curiosities of Engraving” <q>
                            Some Account of the 8° volume containing 50 prints by Boticello
                            [sic] or Maldivi mentioned in p. 43, and now, June 1814, in the
                            collection of Geo. Cumberland Esq. who lent me the book.<ref target="n132" type="note">105</ref></q> Douce goes on to describe the book in great detail. <note id="n129"><hi rend="s">102</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 162, 8 May 1814.</note><note id="n130"><hi rend="s">103</hi> See Arthur M. Hind, <hi rend="i">Early
                                Italian Engraving</hi>, Vol. I (London: Quaritch Ltd., 1938) 221-40
                            for “Tarocchi cards”; Cumberland’s set at the Royal
                            Academy is the E Series. For illustrations of Cumberland’s
                            prints, including the <hi rend="i">Prima Causa</hi>, see Jay Levenson,
                            Konrad Oberhuber, and Jacquelyn L. Sheehan, <hi rend="i">Early Italian
                                Engravings from the National Gallery of Art</hi>, Exh. Cat.,
                            Washington, 1973, 81-157, esp. #66.</note><note id="n131"><hi rend="s">104</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 163<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 8 May 1814.</note><note id="n132"><hi rend="s">105</hi> “Curiosities”
                            47-57.</note></p>
          <p>The “Curiosities of Engraving” contains extensive notes and
                        plans for a book treating the subject of prints, but Douce’s
                        painstaking efforts never came to fruition, as his work was already
                        superseded by the now standard reference book on prints, Bartsch’s
                            <hi rend="i">Le Peintre-Graveur.</hi><ref target="n133" type="note">106</ref> Revelatory of Douce’s careful method of research and
                        annotation are notes on the back of a duplicate of a Bonasone print still in
                        the Bodleian Portfolio, <hi rend="i">The Triumph of Love.</hi><ref target="n134" type="note">107</ref> The Bodleian print bears the
                        following notations on its verso: “Bartsch XV.141, No. 106, See
                        Cumberland p. 75 No 200 The Elysium of Lovers, Felsina Pittrice di Malvasia,
                        1st vol, p. 75.” <note id="n133"><hi rend="s">106</hi> I thank Dr.
                            John Whiteley for this observation. Adam von Bartsch, [1757-1821], <hi rend="i">Le Peintre-Graveur</hi>, 21 vols., Vienna: 1803-1821; see
                            now <hi rend="i">The Illustrated Bartsch</hi>, ed. Walter L. Strauss
                            (New York: Abaris Books, 1980).</note><note id="n134"><hi rend="s">107</hi> Douce Portfolio, W.2.3c.70, <hi rend="i">The Triumph of Love.</hi> A better version of the same
                            print, also from Douce’s collection, now is in the Ashmolean
                            Museum, D.IT 10.Roy., B.xv.141.106, <hi rend="i">The Triumph of
                                Love</hi>, 1545, “Bonahso.”</note></p>
          <p>A poignant and uncharacteristic selfpity breaks from Cumberland in a letter
                        in December 1814. The previous May, Cumberland had written: “If you
                        get the Bartsch book I would like to see it when I get to town.”<ref target="n135" type="note">108</ref> Finally, in December, evidently
                        having tried to obtain the book of Colnaghi, he asks for the loan of
                        Douce’s Bartsch since he has no answer from the bookdealer. <q> [Y]ou
                            have a thousand choice things to amuse you with, and live in the midst
                            of everything you want, while I am chained to a Rock among Savages.<ref target="n136" type="note">109</ref><note id="n135"><hi rend="s">108</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 161, 1 May
                                1814.</note><note id="n136"><hi rend="s">109</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 180<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 18 December 1814.</note></q> By Christmas, the Bristol exile thanks Douce for finding the 4 volumes
                        of the Italian Schools by Bartsch, saying that George Junior will pay
                            him.<ref target="n137" type="note">110</ref> Cumberland received his
                        Bartsch in January and in a point by point refutation justifies in a letter
                        to Douce his own 1793 <hi rend="i">Bonasoni</hi>, denying this egotistical
                        German’s account of the beginning of printing.<ref target="n138" type="note">111</ref><note id="n137"><hi rend="s">110</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 183<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 25 December 1814.</note><note id="n138"><hi rend="s">111</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fols. 186, 187, 5
                            January 1815.</note></p>
          <p>Cumberland also advises Douce, this time about Giambattista della Porta. <q>
                            [I] think if you ever do find him he will be a fragment—for no
                            other reason will people part with such singular things—&amp;
                            these sort of books of Physiognomy I have generally found
                                mutilated.”<ref target="n139" type="note">112</ref><note id="n139"><hi rend="s">112</hi> MS. Douce d. 22, fol. 183<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 25 December 1814, referring to the Italian
                                physiognomist who wrote <hi rend="i">De humana physiognomonia</hi>
                                in 1586.</note></q> In September 1815, Douce finds and buys “Porta’s
                            physognomia”<ref target="n140" type="note">113</ref> and, in
                        April 1816, buys from Smith “Bonasoni’s Gods.”<ref target="n141" type="note">114</ref> The last entry in December 1818
                        includes “Cumberl. outlines” indicating that Douce finally
                        purchased Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline.</hi><ref target="n142" type="note">115</ref><note id="n140"><hi rend="s">113</hi> TS. “Collecta” 63, #4
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 20<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note><note id="n141"><hi rend="s">114</hi> TS. “Collecta” 66, #17
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 24<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note><note id="n142"><hi rend="s">115</hi> TS. “Collecta” 76, #14
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 32<hi rend="s">v</hi>). My thanks to Mr. Hurst
                            for confirming this reading in the original MS. fol. 32<hi rend="s">v</hi>. Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Outlines of the
                                Ancients</hi> (see note 21 above) was not published until 1829 so
                            the entry must refer to his earlier book, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
                                Outline.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Although one surviving letter indicates continuing contact, correspondence
                        between Cumberland and Douce falls off somewhat between 1815 and 1821, as
                        Cumberland readies his book for publication.<ref target="n143" type="note">116</ref> He says “I dread the [illeg.] of printing” and
                        notes that “[t]ruth speaking is a dangerous habit here.” Not
                        until 1827 will the book, <hi rend="i">An Essay on the utility of collecting
                            the best works of the ancient engravers of the Italian School</hi>, be
                            published.<ref target="n144" type="note">117</ref><note id="n143"><hi rend="s">116</hi> MS. Douce d. 23, fol. 82, 6 May
                            1818.</note><note id="n144"><hi rend="s">117</hi> See “Uncollected
                            Authors” 49-50, for details of the negotiations with Robert
                            Triphook as publisher and that it was finally sold in 1827 by three
                            other booksellers, including Colnaghi. <hi rend="i">An Essay on the
                                utility of collecting the best works of the ancient engravers of the
                                Italian School, accompanied by A Critical Catalogue, with
                                interesting anecdotes of the engravers, of a chronological series of
                                rare and valuable prints, from the earliest practice of the art in
                                Italy to the year 1549, now deposited in the British Museum and
                                Royal Academy</hi> (London, 1827).</note></p>
          <p>Financial necessity leads Cumberland to dispose of his other Italian
                        engravings, including the Tarocchi Cards, to the Royal Academy.<ref target="n145" type="note">118</ref> In July 1820, Douce notes that
                        “Smith gave me cast of Cumberland’s (now his)
                            hermaphrodite.”<ref target="n146" type="note">119</ref> Yet, in
                        the midst of his own need, one of Cumberland’s more endearing but
                        aggravating traits, his ceaseless intercession on behalf of his friends and
                        relatives, is revealed.<ref target="n147" type="note">120</ref> In an
                        undated letter,<ref target="n148" type="note">121</ref> he asks Douce to
                        recommend his son’s <hi rend="i">Spanish Lives</hi>, Douce scratches
                        in the margin, “Nothing but self, self &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> from
                        all my worthy friends.” George Jr. had returned to London from Lisbon
                        in 1815; <hi rend="i">Views in Spain and Portugal</hi> was published by
                            1820.<ref target="n149" type="note">122</ref><note id="n145"><hi rend="s">118</hi><hi rend="i"> Annals</hi> 58.</note><note id="n146"><hi rend="s">119</hi> TS. “Collecta” 82, #16
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, 38<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note><note id="n147"><hi rend="s">120</hi> Instances showing this abound in his
                            correspondence. Francis Greenacre, <hi rend="i">The Bristol School of
                                Artists: Francis Danby and Painting in Bristol, 1810-1840</hi>, Exh.
                            Cat., City Art Gallery, Bristol, 4 September-10 November 1973, no.
                            98-99, 250, alludes to this trait, noting that Sir Thomas Lawrence and
                            Stothard were the main contacts through whom Cumberland, after moving to
                            Bristol, helped almost every English artist.</note><note id="n148"><hi rend="s">121</hi> MS. Douce d. 29, n.d., fol. 190<hi rend="s">r</hi>, addressed to Kensington Square, where Douce lived
                            from 1821 to 1825, proposed here as written probably shortly after
                            1821.</note><note id="n149"><hi rend="s">122</hi> See “Uncollected
                            Authors” 48.</note></p>
          <p>Dawson Turner writes to Docue in the spring of 1821.<ref target="n150" type="note">123</ref> Turner had earlier directly contacted Blake; on 9
                        June 1818, Blake sent him a price list for some illuminated books.<ref target="n151" type="note">124</ref> D’Israeli too is interested
                        in Blake: on 7 January 1819, he writes to Dyer that “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. D’Israeli wants as soon as possible a copy of
                        Blake’s Young.”<ref target="n152" type="note">125</ref> T. F.
                        Dibdin, a Douce correspondent,<ref target="n153" type="note">126</ref> whose
                            <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi> provide recollections of Douce, recalled
                        that Blake visited him in the summer of 1816 to talk about the minor poems
                        of Milton; he subsequently purchases from Blake a copy of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi><ref target="n154" type="note">127</ref> Dibdin
                        too was aware of Dyer’s library, commenting in 1810 on a catalogue,
                        saying that it contains twenty thousand volumes.<ref target="n155" type="note">128</ref> Blake had become famous enough to be included in
                            <hi rend="i">A Biographical Dictionary of the Living Authors of Great
                            Britain and Ireland.</hi><ref target="n156" type="note">129</ref>
                        Despite this fame and evidence of direct and indirect contacts between Blake
                        and Douce’s friends, Douce and Blake do not seem to have met after
                        the possible contact at Blake’s exhibit. <note id="n150"><hi rend="s">123</hi> MS. Douce d. 23, fol. 240, 3 April 1821.</note><note id="n151"><hi rend="s">124</hi><hi rend="i"> BB</hi> 118-120.</note><note id="n152"><hi rend="s">125</hi><hi rend="i"> BR Supp.</hi> 73, quoted from a photocopy of the MS in
                            Pierpont Morgan Library.</note><note id="n153"><hi rend="s">126</hi> See MS. Douce d. 32, from 1808 to
                            after 1832 for these letters.</note><note id="n154"><hi rend="s">127</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 242-243; Viscomi, citing <hi rend="i">Reminiscences
                                of a Literary Life</hi> (London, 1836) 2: 787.</note><note id="n155"><hi rend="s">128</hi> Maxted 66n74 (see note 56
                            above).</note><note id="n156"><hi rend="s">129</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 244.</note></p>
          <p>Blake too had to sell his collection of prints about the same time, Colnaghi
                        handling the sale.<ref target="n157" type="note">130</ref> In April 1821
                        Douce records the purchase of “Blake’s marr of heaven &amp;
                        hell Dyer,”<ref target="n158" type="note">131</ref> referring to Copy
                        B of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> now at the Bodleian
                            Library.<ref target="n159" type="note">132</ref> That by
                        “Dyer” is meant Gilbert Dyer, the bookseller to Dibdin and
                        D’Israeli, seems certain.<ref target="n160" type="note">133</ref><note id="n157"><hi rend="s">130</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 276, 395. Records about the sale have been
                            lost.</note><note id="n158"><hi rend="s">131</hi> TS. “Collecta” 86, #4
                            (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 40<hi rend="s">v</hi>); <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
                            289.</note><note id="n159"><hi rend="s">132</hi> See note 7 above.</note><note id="n160"><hi rend="s">133</hi> See Viscomi 56n29 for “Bentley
                            has not identified Dyer, other than to suggest “(George?)
                            Dyer,” by which he probably means the poet (1755-1841) (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 289). Perhaps “Dyer” was the
                            “honest, worthy, painstaking bookseller, the brother of the late
                            Rev. Mr. Dwyer,” whom Dibdin mentions in <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi> (1: 194). Essick suggests Charles George Dyer, a
                            London printseller, noting that Bentley withdraws his tentative earlier
                            suggestion that the seller may have been the author George Dyer (<hi rend="i">SP</hi> 30). Bentley notes there is no London bookseller by
                            the name of Dyer and speculates correctly that D’Israeli’s
                            Dyer is Douce’s Dyer (<hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi>
                        73n3).</note></p>
          <p>Correspondence from “G. Dyer” to Douce begins in 1805, with a
                        note in which Dyer thanks Douce for a favorable account of his book’s
                            principles.<ref target="n161" type="note">134</ref> From Dyer’s
                        description of how he had to trace the names of our Rivers, Hills, Vallies
                        and Towns in an etymological search, the book must be <hi rend="i">A
                            restoration of the ancient modes of bestowing names on the rivers,
                            hills, vallies, plains, and settlements of Britain; recorded by no
                            ancient, nor explored by any modern author</hi> . . ., Exeter, printed
                        for G. Dyer, 1805.<ref target="n162" type="note">135</ref> Dyer also
                        encloses “the set of Adam,” indicating that Douce was now
                        making purchases of him. In September 1808, Douce had dealings with Dyer;
                        his name continues to appear yearly in Douce’s note-book of
                            purchases.<ref target="n163" type="note">136</ref> Dyer, like other
                        Exeter booksellers, probably had agents in London so that he could
                        conveniently make purchases these;<ref target="n164" type="note">137</ref>
                        dealing with him would have been easy. It is not far-fetched to suppose that
                        Dyer may have purchased Blake books at the Colnaghi sale, <pb id="p26-14" n="14"/> given that he knew that collectors like Douce, D’Israeli
                        and Dibdin were interested in the artist. This adds to our information
                        regarding the wide-ranging practices of bookselling and collecting proposed
                        by Viscomi. <note id="n161"><hi rend="s">134</hi> MS. Douce d. 21, 15
                            December 1805, fol. 60.</note><note id="n162"><hi rend="s">135</hi> As determined from the <hi rend="i">National Union Catalog.</hi></note><note id="n163"><hi rend="s">136</hi> TS. “Collecta” 28, Sept.
                            1808, between #9 and #10 (MS. Douce e. 66, fol. 28<hi rend="s">v</hi>).
                            Thereafter, between 1808 and 1821, Dyer’s name appears 22 times
                            at least one a year.</note><note id="n164"><hi rend="s">137</hi> Maxted 66.</note></p>
          <p>Seven letters and a gift come from Cumberland in 1824, as Douce enters in the
                        “Collecta,” “Mr. Cumberland gave me 3 antique
                            pastes.”<ref target="n165" type="note">138</ref> The name of the
                        gem-maker Tassie, whom Cumberland first championed in <hi rend="i">Thoughts
                            on Outline</hi>, occurs in Douce’s list of acquisitions in 1805.
                        Cumberland considered Tassie a preeminent gem-maker of ancient and modern
                        copies: Tassie had made molds and paste reproductions of some of
                        Cumberland’s and Cracherode’s collection.<ref target="n166" type="note">139</ref> In 1824, Cumberland, responding to a question from
                        Douce about Tassie’s processes, tells Douce to make inquiries of
                        Tassie as to how he makes his gems: “He will show you as he showed
                        me.” Cumberland ends with “God send you a speedy
                            Settlement.”<ref target="n167" type="note">140</ref> This last
                        wish may indicate the reason for Cumberland’s renewed interest in
                        Douce. Douce was involved at the time in negotiations related to settling
                        the estate of Nollekens from which Douce eventually inherited enough money
                        to enable him to collect on a greater scale than before. <note id="n165"><hi rend="s">138</hi> TS. “Collecta” 95, January 1824 (MS.
                            Douce e. 68, fol. 1<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note><note id="n166"><hi rend="s">139</hi><hi rend="i"> Thoughts</hi> 25, 29. At the Scottish National Portrait
                            Gallery there is a unique copy of a “Manuscript Catalogue”
                            by Tassie called “Tassie Gems MS. Supplement to Raspe.”
                            Filled with 2889 entries of gems, it lists multiple examples of
                            reproductions by Tassie of gems taken from Cumberland’s
                            collection and at least one from Cracherode’s, #550. My thanks to
                            Miss Helen Watson who kindly assisted me.</note><note id="n167"><hi rend="s">140</hi> MS. Douce d. 24, fols. 210, 211, 20
                            January 1824.</note></p>
          <p>The next month, Cumberland, visiting his sick brother, Richard, at Driffield,
                        writes a long letter to Douce, referring to the disposition of his print
                        collection, which he says are “out to good pasture in the Academy and
                        the Museum.”<ref target="n168" type="note">141</ref> Noting that he
                        received from Irvine in Rome a copy of the book of Cennino Cennini’s
                            <hi rend="i">Treatise on Painting</hi> published at Rome 1821 by G.
                        Tambroni, he tells Douce that the first notice about it appeared in his <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline.</hi><ref target="n169" type="note">142</ref> Douce also owns Cennino’s <hi rend="i">Treatise</hi>,<ref target="n170" type="note">143</ref> and the subject
                        of priority of knowledge becomes a disputed topic, as Cumberland shows by a
                        querulous comment. <q> You say you had Cennino di Cennini before I wrote
                            about him— that is news, as I believe and know he was never
                            printed till very lately—perhaps you have a copy of the
                            Manuscript which De Murr of Augusburg [sic], the Jesuit, told me 40 yrs
                            ago he never saw and gave me the clue to find it? . . .<ref target="n171" type="note">144</ref></q> The next year, Cumberland tries unsuccessfully to see Douce three
                        times. <note id="n168"><hi rend="s">141</hi> MS. Douce d. 24, fol. 315, 3
                            December 1824.</note><note id="n169"><hi rend="s">142</hi> For Cennino, see Joan K. Stemmler,
                            “Cennino, Cumberland, Blake and Early Painting
                            Techniques,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 17 (1984): 145-48.</note><note id="n170"><hi rend="s">143</hi> See 1840 <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>,
                            C. 548, Cennini, Trattato, Giuseppi Tambroni, 8°, Roma,
                            1821.</note><note id="n171"><hi rend="s">144</hi> MS. Douce d. 25, fol. 41<hi rend="s">v</hi>, 9 March 1825.</note></p>
          <p>In 1824 or 1825, Douce purchases Blake’s print of Canterbury Pilgrims
                        from Hurst and Robinson for £3/3/2.<ref target="n172" type="note">145</ref> It is a third state, made between 1810 and 1820, now
                        deposited in the Ashmolean Museum.<ref target="n173" type="note">146</ref> A
                        steady correspondence about Cumberland’s Runic ring which he sent to
                        Douce results in the publication in <hi rend="i">Archaeologia</hi> in 1827
                        by Douce of a “Dissertation on the Runic Jasper Ring belonging to
                        George Cumberland, Esq. of Bristol.”<ref target="n174" type="note">147</ref><note id="n172"><hi rend="s">145</hi> It is listed twice in TS.
                            “Collecta” 97, November 1824, (Douce MS. e. 68, fol. 2<hi rend="s">v</hi>), “Blake’s print of Canterbury
                            pilgrimage. Hurst,” and TS. “Collecta” 98, March
                            1825, #6 (Douce MS. e. 68, fol. 3<hi rend="s">v</hi>),
                            “Blake’s Canterbury Pilgr. Hurst &amp; Robins.”
                            This is probably a double entry, as there is but one state in the
                            Ashmolean Museum. Douce had noted in TS. “Collecta” 91,
                            April 1822 (MS. Douce e. 67, fol. 45<hi rend="s">r</hi>) that he now
                            bought of Hurst &amp; Robinson, formerly Woodburne. The price is in
                            pencil on the verso.</note><note id="n173"><hi rend="s">146</hi> See <hi rend="i">SP</hi> 60-89,
                            especially 63 for Canterbury Pilgrims, Ashmolean impression numbered
                            3D.</note><note id="n174"><hi rend="s">147</hi> MS. Douce d. 29, n.d., fol. 191. This
                            letter should be given a t.a.q. of 20 January 1824 because it logically
                            precedes MS. Douce d. 24, fol. 210, 20 January 1824 in its subject. See
                            also <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> 5 (<hi rend="i">Archeologia</hi> 21
                            [1827]: 119-27); “Uncollected Authors” 36, for the
                            information that Stothard broke the ring.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s name appears in a letter to Douce not sent by George
                        Cumberland, but by his son, George Cumberland Jr. Taking on his
                        father’s role as advocate, the younger Cumberland writes on 14 June
                        1826: <q> If you call upon M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Blake The Artist you will
                            see a very fine work of his just published but not in the Shops. I
                            mention it for that reason if you can recommend it to notice you will
                            oblige.<lb/> Yours very truly<lb/> G. Cumberland J<hi rend="s">r</hi><ref target="n175" type="note">148</ref><note id="n175"><hi rend="s">148</hi> MS. Douce d. 25, fol. 194,
                                Glo’ster Cottage, Old Brompton.</note></q> Of interest is the fact that George Junior assumes a knowledge by Douce
                        of the address of Blake which may suggest that the two had met face to face.
                        The elder Cumberland follows up on this subject in January 1827. Referring
                        to “a great original,” he continues: <q> . . . and so is Blake
                            who has lately published a strange and clever book of Job in 22 plates
                            all line engravings as ever I saw—but I think it a bad education
                            not to say I [illeg.] to represent as he has done, the Creator as an old
                            man with a long beard whether by Rafael or him.<ref target="n176" type="note">149</ref><note id="n176"><hi rend="s">149</hi> MS. Douce d. 26, fols. 8<hi rend="s">r</hi>, 21 January 1827.</note></q></p>
          <p>Blake writes a grateful letter to Cumberland on 12 April 1827, in which he
                        mentions the tiny copper card plate Cumberland had given him to
                            ornament.<ref target="n177" type="note">150</ref> After Blake’s
                        death on 12 August 1827, Cumberland writes to his widow Catherine that
                        “latterly I have not only been unable to continue Collecting but have
                        even sold all I had Collected—yet still preserving all I possessed of
                        his graver.”<ref target="n178" type="note">151</ref> Douce, in
                        contrast, seems not to have valued the later work of Cumberland or Blake,
                        since he purchases neither Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Essay</hi> nor
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job.</hi> In 1827, Douce notes that “R.
                        Stothard gave me a cast of a compartment of a sculptured chest in G.
                        Cumberland’s possn (or fragments of one),” an indication of
                        the value to Douce of Cumberland’s scattered former possessions.<ref target="n179" type="note">152</ref> Continuing to purchase books and
                        prints brought to his attention by Cumberland, he acquires by 1829
                        DeMurr’s own copy of “Nuremb. library” and at the sale
                        of the collection of Sir Thomas Lawrence buys more prints by Bonasone.<ref target="n180" type="note">153</ref><note id="n177"><hi rend="s">150</hi> “Uncollected Authors”
                            51.</note><note id="n178"><hi rend="s">151</hi> “Uncollected Authors”
                            53; Keynes 172, 25 November 1827 (see note 37 above).</note><note id="n179"><hi rend="s">152</hi> TS. “Collecta” 103,
                            January 1827, #6 (MS. Douce e. 68, fol. 7<hi rend="s">r</hi>).</note><note id="n180"><hi rend="s">153</hi> TS. “Collecta” 110, June
                            1829, #4; 113, May 1830, #3 (MS. Douce e. 68, fol. 13<hi rend="s">v</hi>).</note></p>
          <p>At Douce’s death in 1834, Cumberland, along with D’Israeli,
                        Turner and others, is remembered in Douce’s will with a ring, valued
                        at five guineas.<ref target="n181" type="note">154</ref> The printed
                        portraits of Cowper, Cumberland, Holcroft, Tooke, Barry, Bewick, Cosway,
                        Fuseli and Richard Brothers, are among the 634 which Douce assembled during
                        his lifetime.<ref target="n182" type="note">155</ref> However, there is no
                        representation among either the portraits of painters and engravers or those
                        of remarkable characters, of the one whose work is now the most famous,
                        William Blake. <note id="n181"><hi rend="s">154</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 13, 14.</note><note id="n182"><hi rend="s">155</hi> As listed in Scott, Vol. II, fols.
                            76-96 ff. (note 6 above) and found in Portfolios, PO. 135, New Bodleian,
                            Room 132, numbered 43, 44, 87, 176, 204, 211, 230, 246, 479.</note></p>
          <p>Thomas Dodd, the now retired printseller and auctioneer, was given the task
                        of writing the catalogue of Douce’s prints.<ref target="n183" type="note">156</ref> In 1835, commenting on the pages in <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> where Cumberland praised Blake for his
                        “facsimiles of my originals,” Dodd said “Mr
                        Cumberland’s inventions in outline as far as his hand hath been
                        concerned in them is not in unison with his ideas—. . . However, some
                        few of the accompanying pieces are etch’d by <hi rend="i">W.
                            Blake</hi>, which are decidedly more correct than those produced by the
                            author.”<ref target="n184" type="note">157</ref> Of
                        Cumberland’s Bonasone catalogue, it was the opinion of Dodd that the
                        author possessed only the “slightest knowledge of engravings by early
                        italian artists” and that his catalogue of old prints was
                        “vague, erroneous and ridiculous.”<ref target="n185" type="note">158</ref><note id="n183"><hi rend="s">156</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 17. Found inadequate and never printed,
                            Dodd’s handwritten Catalogue of the Prints &amp; Drawings, c.
                            1836-40, the “Fair Copy” of the catalogue with notes and
                            indexes by Douce, is now in the Douce Room at the Ashmolean Museum as
                            Mr. John Whiteley kindly showed me.</note><note id="n184"><hi rend="s">157</hi> Cited in <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 56 and
                                <hi rend="i">BR Supp.</hi> 12, from British Library, Add. MS.
                            33,398, fol. 257.</note><note id="n185"><hi rend="s">158</hi><hi rend="i"> Bibliography</hi> 12.</note></p>
          <p>In the same year, the remainder of Cumberland’s collection was sold by
                        auction in London at Christie &amp; Manson: <pb id="p26-15" n="15"/> among
                        the books listed were DeMurr’s <hi rend="i">Bibliotheque de
                            Peinture</hi>, Malvasia’s <hi rend="i">Felsina Pittrice</hi>,
                        Tambroni’s <hi rend="i">Trattato</hi>, Bartsch’s <hi rend="i">Italian School</hi>, and Vasari’s <hi rend="i">Vite di
                            Pittori</hi>, books from which he liberally dispensed information to his
                        fellow antiquarians and friends.<ref target="n186" type="note">159</ref>
                        Sadly, he was forced to sell too the productions of his old friend, William
                        Blake. Living frugally in Bristol, Cumberland died at age 94, still writing
                        letters exploring his new interests and supporting friends to the end.<ref target="n187" type="note">160</ref><note id="n186"><hi rend="s">159</hi><hi rend="i"> A Catalogue of the Collection of Books on Art, Antique
                                Bronzes, Terra Cottas, and Coins, the property of George Cumberland,
                                Esq.</hi>, Christie &amp; Manson, St. James’s Square,
                            London, 1835.</note><note id="n187"><hi rend="s">160</hi> For the Bristol years, see Greenacre
                            (note 120 above).</note></p>
          <p>The Bodleian Library’s body of archival material bequeathed by Douce
                        deserves more than the quinquennial wakening predicted for it by Sir
                        Frederic Madden when he said it would be disturbed but once in a lustre.
                        Lustre reverberates with lustrous, a term we might apply to Douce’s
                        bequest, for its reflected light shines into darker corners of other
                        histories, illuminating them. My sympathies for Cumberland, a good-hearted
                        and expansive gentleman, and my particular interest in Blake, led me to
                        concentrate on them. Thus additional information about Blake’s <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi> was uncovered, the way in which Douce
                        drew upon Cumberland’s knowledge was brought to light, and three new
                        letters in which Blake is mentioned were found. Other of Douce’s
                        letters from his wide circle of friends which I “disturbed”
                        are equally fascinating and informative. Douce’s careful annotations,
                        scrupulous scholarship, meticulous cataloguing, and most of all, concern for
                        what we today call cultural history,<ref target="n188" type="note">161</ref>
                        make his legacy to us particularly useful in discovering more about
                        interactions among persons of learning in the eighteenth century. <note id="n188"><hi rend="s">161</hi><hi rend="i"> DL</hi> 64.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-19" n="19"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A New Color Print from the Small Book of Designs</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Ahitherto unrecorded color-printed copy of the design on plate 20 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> has turned up in a British
                        private collection.<ref target="n189" type="note">1</ref> The new discovery
                        can be shown to have come from the second copy of the socalled “Small
                        Book of Designs” and confirms recent discoveries made about the
                        color-printed designs by Robert Essick and Joseph Viscomi. It will perhaps
                        be helpful to draw these discoveries together and examine their
                        implications. <note id="n189"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Henry Wemyss of
                            Sotheby’s, London, kindly informed me about this work, allowed me
                            to inspect it, and supplied the photograph.</note></p>
          <p>In the first place it is clear that the new print is a second pull of the
                        parallel design in the first copy of the Small Book of Designs in the
                        British Museum.<ref target="n190" type="note">2</ref> The coloring is
                        identical though somewhat thinner, with the tone of the uncovered paper
                        showing through in places. Essick has shown that, in the case of the Large
                        Book of Designs, three of the duplicates are second pulls from the first
                        copy in the British Museum, B262: <hi rend="i">Albion Rose, The Accusers of
                            Theft, Adultery, Murder</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea
                            Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, B284, 285, and 286.<ref target="n191" type="note">3</ref> To these Viscomi has added <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi>, B267, and the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, B264, and Ted Gott has
                        added <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> plate 21, B281.<ref target="n192" type="note">4</ref> It is not always easy to make such assertions; at best most
                        comparisons have to be made between a good color reproduction and an
                        original. However, in the case of the Large Book of Designs it seems that,
                        in fact, every case in which there is a duplicate, in other words every
                        design except for plate 14 from <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, is a repeated pull
                        from the same coloring.<ref target="n193" type="note">5</ref><note id="n190"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The
                                Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven, CT: Yale
                            UP, 1981) 134, no. 260 <hi rend="i">6.</hi> References to this catalogue
                            in the rest of this article will be given in the form “B260 <hi rend="i">6.</hi>”</note><note id="n191"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The
                                Separate Plates of William Blake</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP,
                            1983) 25 no. 1B, 32 no. 2E, and 44 no. 1B, respectively.</note><note id="n192"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Joseph Viscomi, “The Myth of
                            Commissioned Illuminated Books: George Romney, Isaac D’Israeli,
                            and ‘ONE HUNDRED AND SIXTY designs . . . of
                            Blake’s,’” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989):
                            72n38; Martin Butlin and Ted Gott, <hi rend="i">William Blake in the
                                Collection of the National Gallery of Victoria</hi> (National
                            Gallery of Victoria, 1989) 110-11, both works reproduced in
                            color.</note><note id="n193"><hi rend="s">5</hi> There is an old color reproduction of
                            262 <hi rend="i">4</hi> in Laurence Binyon, <hi rend="i">The Engraved
                                Designs of William Blake</hi> (London and New York: Benn Press,
                            1926) pl. 49, which can be compared with B265 in the Tate Gallery, or
                            the color reproduction of B265 (pl. 338) can be compared with B262 <hi rend="i">4</hi> in the British Museum.</note></p>
          <p>Viscomi has also demonstrated that the design from plate 5 of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> in the second copy of the Small Book of Designs was from
                        the same printings as that in the first. To this can be added the new
                        discovery and, almost certainly, the second pull of plate 3 of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (c.f., B260 <hi rend="i">9</hi> and B261 <hi rend="i">4</hi>). As Viscomi (72n38) also points out, even a partial <figure n="MHH.plate20.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"><head>1. “‘O Revolving Serpent,’ Plate 20 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,”
                                1796.</head><figDesc>Color-printed relief etching finished in pen and water color,
                                5.6 × 10.3 cm. Private collection, Great Britain.</figDesc></figure> duplication in the color printing means that both copies of the
                        Large Book of Designs and of the Small Book of Designs must have been
                        basically prepared at the same time, whenever the final finishing in pen and
                        water color may have been done.</p>
          <p>This conclusion, so obvious once made, makes my suggestion that the two Small
                        Books of Designs were printed in 1794 and 1796 respectively invalid.
                        Moreover, if one can accept the date 1796 for the second copy of the Small
                        Book of Designs, this invalidates my suggestion that the books of designs
                        were intermediary between the use of color printing in Blake’s
                        illuminated books and the totally independent large color-printed designs of
                            “1795.”<ref target="n194" type="note">6</ref> This theory
                        made some sense in the conceptual and technical development of
                        Blake’s use of color printing but is certainly not essential for
                        Blake’s development; indeed, the experiments in the books would have
                        been sufficient to produce the independent large prints. Whether one can
                        rely on Blake’s dates with regard to his color prints is another
                        question. It has already been shown that a number of the
                        “1795” prints were actually executed in 1804 or 1805.<ref target="n195" type="note">7</ref> Moreover, Viscomi suggests that the
                        1796 date, created by altering the “1794” on the title page of
                            <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (B260 <hi rend="i">1</hi> and B261 <hi rend="i">1</hi>) was done late in Blake’s career, when he added the
                        framing lines and verses characteristic of the second copy of the Small Book
                        of Designs. By this time Blake could well have wished to establish an
                        “ideal” date for the separate designs. <note id="n194"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Martin Bultin, “The Evolution of
                            Blake’s Large Color Prints of 1795,” in Alvin H.
                            Rosenfeld, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake; Essays for S. Foster
                                Damon</hi> (Providence, RI: Brown UP, 1969) 114-15.</note><note id="n195"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Martin Butlin, “A Newly
                            Discovered Watermark and a Visionary’s Way with his
                            Dates,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 15 (1982): 101-03; Martin Butlin,
                                “<hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>:
                            Some Minor Additions,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 17 (1984): 159;
                            Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">Tate Gallery Collections: Volume Five:
                                William Blake 1757-1827</hi> (London: Tate Gallery, 1990) 83, 90 no.
                            28, and 92 no. 29.</note></p>
          <p>The framing lines and verses characteristic of the second copy of the Small
                        Book of Designs are also a feature of the newly discovered print. The design
                        has been cut out of the original sheet of paper, leaving no margins, but by
                        good fortune much of the original sheet remains, cut up but stuck to the
                        sheet of cardboard onto which the design is also stuck. From these fragments
                        it can be seen that, like most of the other designs identified as coming
                        from the second copy of the Small Books of Designs, there were two pen-drawn
                        framing lines and a text, similarly inscribed with double inverted commas at
                        the beginning and end of each line as follows:</p>
          <q> “O revolving serpent”<lb/> “O the Ocean of Time and
                        Space” </q>
          <p>I leave it to other scholars to explain the significance of the second line
                        and its relevance, if appropriate, to the <pb id="p26-20" n="20"/> Arlington
                        Court picture, B803. It is generally assumed that Blake himself added these
                        inscriptions when he issued the second copy of the Small Book of Designs.
                        They seem to be in the same ink as the framing lines, which, as Viscomi
                        points out, are very close to those added to <hi rend="i">All Religions are
                            One</hi> Copy A, and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                            Experience</hi> Copy R, presumably at the time that they were sold to
                        John Linnell.<ref target="n196" type="note">8</ref><note id="n196"><hi rend="s">8</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977) 85-86 and 420. In addition,
                            Viscomi has kindly let me know of his conclusions concerning these,
                            copies, to be set out in his forthcoming book. Incidentally, the two
                            designs from the second copy of the Large Book of Designs in the Tate
                            Gallery, B264 and 265, also have framing lines similar to those that
                            characterize the second copy of the Small Book of Designs.</note></p>
          <p>Another characteristic of some of the designs from the second copy of the
                        Small Book of Designs is a small page number in the top right-hand corner.
                        These are found on B261 <hi rend="i">3, 6, 7</hi>, and <hi rend="i">9.</hi>
                        A similar number, in this case “16,” is found on the newly
                        discovered design. The other numbers so far discovered are
                        “9,” “13,” “20” and
                        “22.” This suggests that there may be ten more designs still
                        awaiting rediscovery, a very exciting prospect. There are, of course, 23
                        designs in the first copy of the Small Book of Designs but the two books
                        cannot have been identical: three designs from the second copy, B261 <hi rend="i">9, 10</hi>, and <hi rend="i">11</hi>, are of subjects not found
                        in the first copy.</p>
          <p>The possibility of missing designs is reinforced by the fact that four of the
                        designs from the second copy show stab holes from a former binding, B261 <hi rend="i">2, 5, 6</hi> and <hi rend="i">8</hi>;<ref target="n197" type="note">9</ref> the absence of such stab holes on other designs can
                        be accounted for by the trimming of the paper. This binding must have been
                        done before the second copy was dispersed. The early history of some of the
                        designs is not known but B261 <hi rend="i">1</hi> was given by Mrs. Blake
                        (who died in 1831) to Frederick Tatham, B261 <hi rend="i">5</hi> belonged to
                        Samuel Palmer’s cousin John Giles, while B261 <hi rend="i">3</hi>
                        seems to have belonged to John Varley who, as will be shown, also owned the
                        newly discovered design. <note id="n197"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Bentley
                            357.</note></p>
          <p>Other inscriptions, not by Blake, give the early provenance of this work.
                        There are two references, apparently in the same hand, reading
                        “Drawing of Blake’s given to A White by M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>
                        Varley March 31 1856” and “Original Drawing by Blake/See
                        Rossettis “Life and Works of Blake” (the inscription lacks the
                        closing quotation mark for “Life and Works of Blake”). After
                        the first of these two inscriptions but in a different hand are the words
                        “evidently printed in oil and touched with colour afterwards.”
                        There is also the number “8623.”</p>
          <p>A. White is presumably the Adam White who, according to inscriptions on the
                        back of a counterproof of the Visionary Head of <hi rend="i">Wat Tyler</hi>
                        (B740), was given that drawing by J. W. Lowry; the drawing had originally
                        “belonged to Varley the artist whose wife was Miss Lowry.”
                        White also owned a number of other Visionary Heads (B711, 712, 718, 736, and
                        760), one of which, <hi rend="i">Pindar and Lais the Courtesan</hi>, now in
                        the Harris Museum and Art Gallery, Preston (B711) is inscribed, in similar
                        fashion to the new color print, “Adam White from M<hi rend="s">r</hi>
                        [or more likely “M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>”] Varley.” In
                        addition one copy of the fourth state of the engraving by Blake and John
                        Linnell after Linnell’s portrait drawing of Wilson Lowry is inscribed
                        “To Adam White with J.W. Lowry’s regards 1854.”<ref target="n198" type="note">10</ref><note id="n198"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Essick 204, no. 4M.</note></p>
          <p>The Miss Lowry who married Varley was his second wife, Delvalle (born c.
                        1797-1800), the daughter of Varley’s friend Wilson Lowry (1762-1824)
                        and his second wife Rebecca Delvalle (1761-1848) whom he married in 1796.
                        Delvalle married Varley in 1825. The Blake connection was strengthened by
                        the fact that Wilson Lowry had engraved a number of the plates for Abraham
                        Rees’ <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia</hi>, 1820, for which Blake also
                        executed seven plates, one page being made up of engravings by both
                            artists.<ref target="n199" type="note">11</ref><note id="n199"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Essick 207-08. For help in unravelling
                            the family relationships of the Varleys and the Lowrys I am indebted to
                            my former colleague Anne Lyles; see also C. M. Kauffman, <hi rend="i">John Varley (1778-1842)</hi> (London: Batsford and Victoria and
                            Albert Museum, 1984) 58 and 132.</note></p>
          <p>The mid nineteenth-century owner of this design was Sir Joseph Nöel
                        Paton, RSA (1821-1901); it was probably he who added the inscription about
                        the technique of the print. Through his father he became an admirer of
                        Blake’s work, both his poetry and his designs, at an early age, and
                        some of this influence remained with him throughout his life. As he said,
                        his father taught him to “put the <hi rend="i">thought before the
                            thing</hi>, and encouraged me in perpetual scribblings at <hi rend="i">subjects</hi>, instead of obliging me to copy <hi rend="i">objects.</hi>” Even a late work like <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>
                        of 1889-91 still reflects the influence of Blake both in the pose, close to
                        that of the <hi rend="i">Dance of Albion</hi>, and in the bearded old man
                        type used for <hi rend="i">Ezekiel.</hi><ref target="n200" type="note">12</ref> In 1845 Paton won a premium for the competition for the
                        decoration of the new Houses of Parliament and in 1847 and 1849 came his two
                        large pictures of fairy subjects, the works for which he is probably best
                        known, <hi rend="i">The Reconciliation of Oberon and Titania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Quarrel of Oberon and Titania</hi>, both now in the
                        National Gallery of Scotland. He also painted such subjects as <hi rend="i">The Spirit of Religion</hi> (for the Houses of Parliament) and the <hi rend="i">Pursuit of Pleasure</hi> of 1855. He became an Associate of the
                        Royal Scottish Academy in 1847 and a full member in 1850. He was appointed
                        Her Majesty’s Limner for Scotland in 1865 and was knighted in 1867.
                        He also published two volumes of verse. He knew Millais (an associate of the
                        Rossettis in Preraphaelite days), Ruskin and the brothers David and William
                        Bell Scott, these being further links with the circle of Blake admirers in
                        the middle of the nineteenth century. It is nice to be able to identify at
                        least one work by Blake that he owned. <note id="n200"><hi rend="s">12</hi>
                            For this particular work, and Sir Nöel Paton in general, see
                            David and Francina Irwin, <hi rend="i">Scottish Painting at Home and
                                Abroad 1700-1900</hi> (London: Faber, 1975) 288-95; see also the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Bibliography.</hi></note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <pb id="p26-21" n="21"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Two Newly Identified Sketches for Thomas Commins’s <hi rend="i">An Elegy</hi> and Further Rediscovered Drawings of the
                            1780s</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Three typical pen and wash drawings of the 1780’s, two on one sheet of
                        paper, have turned up in the United States. Two seem to be related to Thomas
                        Commin’s <hi rend="i">An Elegy</hi>, while the other appears to be an
                        independent composition.<ref target="n201" type="note">1</ref><note id="n201"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I am indebted to Henry Wemyss of
                            Sotheby’s, London, for letting me know of the existence of the
                            drawings in the United States and for letting me have
                            photographs.</note></p>
          <p>In my catalogue I listed, as number 98, a “Sketch for Thomas
                        Commins’s ‘An Elegy,’” the only evidence for
                        which was the fact that it was in possession of Messrs. Robson in 1913.<ref target="n202" type="note">2</ref> The newly identified sheet of drawings
                        may be this work, but the two drawings are different enough from
                        Blake’s finished engraving for the identification to have been easily
                        missed in 1913; if so, there is a further drawing waiting to be discovered.
                            <note id="n202"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Martin Butlin. <hi rend="i">The
                                Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven, CT: Yale
                            UP, 1981) 38 no. 98, the engraving repr. pl. 103. In the rest of this
                            article references to my catalogue are given in the form
                            “B98.”</note></p>
          <p>Blake designed and engraved the frontispiece for Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, published in 1786. The engraving itself is
                        inscribed “W.Blake del<hi rend="s">t</hi>. &amp; sculp<hi rend="s">t</hi>.” (the identification of the final raised letter <figure n="Commin.Elegy.Frontispiece.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"><head>1. Frontispiece to Thomas Commin’s <hi rend="i">An
                                    Elegy</hi>, 1786.</head><figDesc>Hand-tinted etching and engraving, 17.3 × 13.8 cm.,
                                British Museum, London.</figDesc></figure> is not altogether clear). Below the design are four lines of
                        verse, arranged in two columns: <q> The shatter’d bark from adverse
                            winds<lb/> Rest in this peaceful haven finds<lb/> And when the storms of
                            life are past<lb/> Hope drops her anchor here at last. </q> Below is the
                        publisher’s imprint: “Published July 1. 1786 by J. Fentum N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 78 Corner of Salisbury Street, Strand” (on the
                        British Museum copy the final word is almost lost through the wearing of the
                        paper; it is reconstructed here on the basis of the imprint at the head of
                        the music itself).</p>
          <p>The engraved design shows a young man leaping out of an anchored boat towards
                        a young woman and child, presumably his family, awaiting him on the shore;
                        behind are trees and what appears to be a cliff (illus. 1). The design is
                        framed by a border of palm fronds, forming an upright oval. (The British
                        Museum copy is colored by <pb id="p26-22" n="22"/><figure n="Commins.Elegy.AltDesign.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"><head>2. Alternative design for Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>
                                c. 1786.</head><figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil on paper, cut irregularly, approx 34.0
                                × 26.5cm. Private collection, U.S.A.</figDesc></figure> hand, but a relative lack of subtlety, and in particular the way
                        in which the color runs over the edges of the forms in the framing oval,
                        suggests the work of an amateur, not Blake himself.)</p>
          <p>The full title of Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, at the head of
                        the first of five pages of music (printed on three sheets of paper), is
                        “AN ELEGY / set to Music by / THO<hi rend="s">s</hi>: Commins,/
                        Organist of Penzance, Cornwall./LONDON./Printed &amp; sold by J. Fentum,
                            N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 78, corner Salisbury S<hi rend="s">t</hi>..,
                        Strand.” The verses accompanying the music run (with a long
                        “s” used whenever appropriate): <q> Sigh not ye winds as
                            passing o’er the Chambers of the dead ye fly,<lb/> Weep not ye
                            dews for these no more shall ever weep, shall ever sigh.<lb/> Why mourn
                            the throbbing heart at rest<lb/> How still it lies within the
                            breast<lb/> Why mourn since death presents us peace,<lb/> And in the
                            grave our sorrows cease.<lb/><lb/> [The last two lines are repeated,
                            followed by the first two lines]<lb/><lb/> The shatter’d Bark
                            from adverse winds<lb/> Rest in this peaceful Heaven finds<lb/> And when
                            the storms of Life are past<lb/> Hope drops her Anchor here at
                            last.<lb/><lb/> [The last two lines are repeated]. </q><figure n="Commins.Elegy.Sketch.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"><head>3. Sketch for Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, c. 1786
                                (verso of illus. 2).</head><figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil on paper, cut irregularly, approx 26.5
                                × 34.0 cm. Private collection, U.S.A.</figDesc></figure> It is noticeable that in the song text the
                        “shatter’d Bark” finds rest in a peaceful
                        “Heaven” whereas in the lines below the frontispiece rest is
                        found in a peaceful “Haven”; this last is closer to what Blake
                        illustrates in his engraving.</p>
          <p>The recto of the rediscovered sheet of drawings shows a much varied version
                        of the engraved design, in reverse (illus. 2). An older, bearded man gets
                        out of the boat in a considerably less agile fashion, looking apprehensively
                        over his shoulder the while; two angels await him on the shore, and there
                        are trees behind. The composition is again an upright oval, within a roughly
                        drawn outline. The presence of the angels gives a greater feeling of Heaven
                        than in the engraving.</p>
          <p>This however is absent from the drawing on the reverse, in which a young man
                        has just finished rowing his boat into a small creek or haven (illus. 3).
                        There are no figures on the shore. Again there are trees behind but of a
                        totally different kind. The composition is an oblong. In the lower
                        right-hand quarter of the drawing there is what may be the beginnings of an
                        oval composition which would have continued to the right over the cut edge
                        of the existing paper. This drawing presumably preceded the one on the
                        recto, before even the format of the final engraving had been
                        determined.</p>
          <p>Another rediscovered drawing in the same American collection, and apparently
                        sharing the same provenance, is similar in style and, like the two drawings
                        here related to Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, datable to the
                        early or mid seventeen eighties (illus. 4). It shows three groups of figures
                        in what seems to be Heaven. Three bearded men float in the air just to the
                        left of center, facing the spectator, and another group of three figures,
                        one old, two young, float on the right facing two middle-aged dark-bearded
                        men who soar up from the left. In general character, and in the long flowing
                        robes ending in scroll-like folds, the drawing resembles the group of pen
                        and ink drawings illustrating scenes from the Old Testament, B112-4 in my
                        catalogue.</p>
          <p>Various inscriptions together with an attached piece of paper bearing a
                        printed title on the back of the first drawing indicate that it comes from
                        the collection of Henry Cunliffe “of the South Kensington
                        Museum.” Two inscriptions in ink are similar in handwriting <pb id="p26-23" n="23"/> and in the mistakes they embody to inscriptions on
                        other drawings that belonged to Henry Cunliffe, B69, 113, 119<hi rend="s">A</hi>, 144, 190 and 650. The inscription to the right reads “A
                        Sketch by William Blake. Obit 12 Aug. 1828/For a Biog<hi rend="s">Y</hi> of
                        B. see Cunninghams British Painters.” The reference is to Allan
                        Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters,
                            Sculptors, and Architects</hi>, first published in 1830 and again, with
                        a more balanced account of Blake, the same year; this is the source for the
                        mistaken date of Blake’s death (actually 1827). The inscription to
                        the left reads “Purchased at Sothebys in a Lot/28 Ap. 1862.”
                        Again there is a mistake: the anonymous sale, but one long identified as
                        being of works from the collection of Frederick Tatham, took place on the
                        29th of April.</p>
          <p>A further inscription, in pencil and running along the left-hand side of the
                        drawing, reads “From the Collection of Henry Cunliffe/of the South
                        Kensington Museum.” To the left of this is a printed title, “A
                        Man getting out of a Boat, two angels standing by him,/trees in the
                        background, <hi rend="i">in water-colours</hi>, with a Sketch/in pencil of a
                        man rowing a boat on the back.” This can be identified as coming from
                        the catalogue of the sale at Sotheby’s on 11 May 1895 of, inter alia,
                        “. . . A Series of Drawings by W. Blake, The Property of the Late
                        Henry Cunliffe, Esq.. ..”; the title is that of lot 105, bought by
                        Keppel for sixteen shillings.</p>
          <p>The works from the Cunliffe collection in the 1895 sale comprise, as well as
                        four lots by other artists, 10 lots containing works attributed to Blake,
                        numbers 96 to 105 (plus an india proof impression of the portrait by Linnell
                        of Blake), but none of the more important illuminated books that passed to
                        Henry Cunliffe’s nephew Walter, grandfather of the present Lord
                        Cunliffe. With the reappearance of these two sheets of drawings it seems
                        that one can now identify all the drawings in the 1895 sale and, in turn,
                        those purchased by Henry Cunliffe in 1862.</p>
          <figure n="AnEncounterinHeaven.26.1.bqscan" rend="file">
            <head>4. “An Encounter in Heaven,” c. 1780-85.</head>
            <figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil on paper, approx 30.5 × 40.5 cm.
                            Private collection, U.S.A.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>The 10 lots containing Blakes consist of 13 works in all, 12 drawings and one
                        print, although not every individual work is described and even those that
                        are described are often described in fairly vague terms. Certain lots can be
                        identified straightaway: 96, “A Group of Five Figures (one on
                        Horseback), a town in the background with mountains in the distance, the man
                        and woman in the centre are supposed to represent Blake and his Wife, <hi rend="i">a highly finished drawing in indian ink, apparently intended to
                            illustrate some story</hi>” is the finished drawing finally
                        identified in 1978 as an illustration to Robert Bage’s <hi rend="i">Hermsprong</hi>(B682); 97, “PESTILENCE. An allegorical design in
                        water colours of five figures and corpses” is B190, the version of
                        the much repeated composition later, like the <hi rend="i">Hermsprong</hi>
                        illustration, in the collections of William and George Bateson; 100,
                        “The Canterbury Pilgrims, the original drawing by Blake from the
                        picture to reduce the subject to the size of his plate, <hi rend="i">in
                            pencil</hi>” is B654, which was bought in at the 1895 sale,
                        eventually passed to the Hon. Merlin Cunliffe and now belongs to the British
                        Museum; 101, “Jane Shore doing Penance, <hi rend="i">highly finished
                            in watercolours, varnished</hi>” is B69, now in the Tate Gallery;
                        102, “Queen Emma walking over the red hot plough-shares,”
                        similarly described, is B59, in a private collection; 103, “The Witch
                        of Endor raising Samuel, <hi rend="i">spirited drawing in
                        water-colours</hi>” is B144, now in the New York Public Library; 104,
                        “Good and Evil Spirits contending for the possession of a Child, <hi rend="i">an allegorical subject in water-colours</hi>” is,
                        despite the medium given in the catalogue, the version of the large color
                        print of “1795” formerly in the collection of Mr. &amp; Mrs.
                        John Hay Whitney, B324.</p>
          <p>This leaves lots 98 and 99, which together with lots 103 and the rediscovered
                        lot 105 were bought by Keppel, apparently the New York dealer Frederick
                        Keppel, whose son David gave B119A, a drawing of <hi rend="i">Goliath
                            cursing David</hi>, to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, in 1914;
                        Frederick himself had bequeathed an impression of <hi rend="i">The
                            Accusers</hi> to the same museum in October 1913.<ref target="n203" type="note">3</ref> The only other recorded purchase of a Blake by
                        Keppel apart from those at this sale was at Sotheby’s on 8 July 1895
                        when he bought lot 125, <hi rend="i">Death on a Pale Horse</hi>, <pb id="p26-24" n="24"/> now in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge (B517). In
                        addition, in about 1919-20 his firm owned the separate color-printed design
                        from plate 12 of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> now in the Pierpont Morgan
                        Library, New York (B261 <hi rend="i">10</hi>), and also a copy of the
                        title-page to <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi><ref target="n204" type="note">4</ref><note id="n203"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The
                                Separate Plates of William Blake</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP,
                            1983) 33 no. 3D.</note><note id="n204"><hi rend="s">4</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977) 162.</note></p>
          <p>Lot 98 is described as “A Sketch in sepia of Angels with spirits of
                        women approaching them; and two other Sketches.” Lot 99 was “A
                        Group of Six Greek Warriors, <hi rend="i">in pen and ink</hi>; and a fine
                        impression of the Child of Nature, after C. Borckhardt, by W. Blake, <hi rend="i">fastened together at the corners.</hi>” It is tempting
                        to identify the drawing of eight airborne figures, which seems to have the
                        same provenance as lot 105, definitely bought by Keppel, as the main work in
                        lot 98, the “Sketch in sepia of Angels with the spirits of women
                        approaching them.” This allows for the habitual inaccuracy of
                        descriptions in sale catalogues, particularly from as long ago as 1895: at a
                        very quick look two of the figures on the right just could be women!</p>
          <p>Two further drawings with typical Cunliffe inscriptions on the back are
                        otherwise unaccounted for in the 1895 sale: B113, <hi rend="i">The Elders of
                            Israel receiving the Ten Commandments (?)</hi>, and B119A, <hi rend="i">Goliath cursing David</hi>, already mentioned as having belonged to
                        David Keppel. This last, again allowing for a fair laxity in description,
                        could, given the round shields carried by three of its six figures, be the
                        “Group of Six Greek Warriors” of lot 99. Assuming one of the
                        undescribed drawings in lot 98 to be B113, <hi rend="i">The Elders of
                            Israel</hi> . . ., one further work remains to be discovered and,
                        conveniently, one of the drawings reported in my last article on
                        rediscovered Blakes seems to fit the gap.<ref target="n205" type="note">5</ref> This is the sketch for <hi rend="i">Joseph’s Brethren
                            bowing before him</hi> discovered by David Bindman in Berlin which also,
                        David Bindman tells me, bears the typical Cunliffe inscription
                        “Purchased in a Lot at Sothebys 28 April 1862 HC“”
                        together with “A Sketch by William Blake Obit 12 August 1828./In
                        Cunninghams Lives of British Painters Ch.1 Blake”; there is also an
                        inscription matching the pencil inscription on the drawing for
                        Commins’s <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, “From the collection of
                        Henry Cunliffe of the South Kensington Museum.” <note id="n205"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Martin Butlin, “Six New Early Drawings by
                            William Blake and a Reattribution,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23
                            (1989) 110-11, repr. fig. 6.</note></p>
          <p>It is of course tempting to equate any known drawing one can find with those
                        that one knows to be missing, but at least the total number of works now
                        matches up and, although I have been caught out making similar
                        identifications in the past that have subsequently proved to be inaccurate,
                        it is at least for the present a working hypothesis that we now have all the
                        drawings sold by Henry Cunliffe in 1895. One can also venture further and
                        see how these 12 drawings fit with the only 12 works to have been bought by
                        Toovey in the Frederick Tatham sale held at Sotheby’s on 29 April
                        1862, some of which can quite definitely be shown to have been in Henry
                        Cunliffe’s collection. The lots bought by Toovey were as follows:
                        161, “The Original reduced Drawing of the Canterbury Pilgrimage, from
                        which he [Blake] engraved his plate,” lot 100 in 1895, B654; 170,
                        “A Pestilence, and other designs, <hi rend="i">in indian
                        ink</hi>,” six works in all, of which the named work was lot 97 in
                        1895, B190; 171, “Queen Emma walking over the red hot Ploughshares,
                        and Jane Shore doing Penance, <hi rend="i">both highly finished in
                            colours</hi>,” lots 102 and 101 respectively in 1895, B59 and 69;
                        175, “The Witch of Endor raising the Spirit of Samuel, <hi rend="i">in colours</hi>,” lot 103 in 1895, B144; 182, “An
                        Allegorical Subject - A Man holding a Child, with a chained demon issuing
                        from a fiery abyss, <hi rend="i">highly finished in colours</hi>,”
                        lot 104 in 1895, B324; and 184, “A Design, apparently intended in
                        illustration of a tale, <hi rend="i">highly finished in indian
                        ink</hi>,” lot 96 in 1895, B682. Lot 195 was also bought by Toovey,
                        “Another set” of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                            Experience</hi> “wanting three plates,” the posthumous
                        Copy i still in the Cunliffe collection. The five unidentified works in lot
                        170, all described as being “<hi rend="i">in indian ink</hi>,”
                        can therefore be equated with the following five works sold in 1895: 98,
                        “A Sketch in sepia of Angels . . . and two other Sketches,”
                        three works in all; 99, “A Group of Six Greek Warriors, <hi rend="i">in pen and ink</hi>,” sold with the print of the “Child
                        of Nature”; and 105, “A Man getting out of a Boat . . . <hi rend="i">in watercolours</hi>, with a Sketch in pencil of a man rowing a
                        boat on the back.” Q.E.D.!</p>
          <p>After all this supposition it should be easy enough to say something about
                        “Henry Cunliffe of the South Kensington Museum.” But, despite
                        the helpfulness of the present Lord Cunliffe and of Ronald Parkinson and his
                        colleagues at the Victoria and Albert Museum, as the South Kensington Museum
                        is now known, there seems to be very little information. The present Lord
                        Cunliffe’s great-great-uncle Henry Cunliffe was born in 1827 and died
                        in 1883, apparently in Germany; he is buried in the family plot at Headly in
                        Surrey. He was, typically for a number of mid nineteenth-century Blake
                        collectors, primarily a bibliophile and left his collection of books to his
                        favorite nephew Walter Cunliffe. Unfortunately, there is no record of a
                        Henry Cunliffe at the V &amp; A either in the diaries of Sir Henry Cole,
                        the famous director from its beginnings until 1873 (but there is mention of
                        an Edward Cunliffe), nor is he mentioned in the Precis and Board Minutes
                        between 1863 and 1877. (Just to confuse matters, Sir Francis Philip
                        Cunliffe-Owen, who lived from 1828 until 1894, did work at the Victoria
                        &amp; Albert Museum, having owed his first post in the Science &amp; Art
                        Department to the recommendation of his elder brother Lieutenant Colonel
                        Henry Charles Cunliffe-Owen [1821-67] who, in the course of a mainly
                        military career had been connected with the Great Exhibition of 1851 and was
                        also inspector of Art Schools under the Board of Trade; in 1857 Francis
                        CunliffeOwen became deputy general-superintendent at the South Kensington
                        Museum under Sir Henry Cole, in 1860 assistant director, and in 1873, in
                        succession to Cole, full director. In the 1850s and 1860s the Cunliffe-Owens
                            <pb id="p26-25" n="25"/> called themselves Owen, which further
                        distinguishes them from our Henry Cunliffe.<ref target="n206" type="note">6</ref><note id="n206"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For the Cunliffe-Owens see the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Biography.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Two further pen and wash drawings of the 1780s, listed in my catalogue as
                        untraced and not reproduced there, have turned up recently. B139, called <hi rend="i">The Bed of Death</hi> and cataloged as untraced since the sale
                        at Christie’s on 15 July 1957, has re-emerged and been reproduced in
                        the catalogue for the Christie’s sale of 9 July 1991, Lot 86. This
                        has been reproduced and discussed by Robert N. Essick in the last issue of
                            <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 25 (1992) 148, fig. 4. Whether the drawing
                        really shows a death bed seems unlikely, and it is certainly not related,
                            <hi rend="i">pace</hi> my catalogue entry, to my numbers B137 verso and
                        138. (The 1991 Christie’s catalogue also reproduces, at lot 85, the
                        Visionary Head of <hi rend="i">Jonathan</hi> in its present state; it was
                        previously reproduced, unrestored, in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> following its
                        sale at Christie’s on 9 July 1985.<ref target="n207" type="note">7</ref><note id="n207"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the
                            Marketplace 1985,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 20 (1986) repr. p. 16,
                            fig. 3.</note></p>
          <p>The other rediscovered drawing, <hi rend="i">Lady Macbeth approaching the
                            Sleeping Duncan</hi> (illus. 5) is much more exciting.<ref target="n208" type="note">8</ref> Its position in my catalogue, as B249, is too late;
                        rather, as hinted at in my entry, it should be placed earlier as one of the
                        pen and wash drawings of about 1785. The full medium is pen and wash over
                        pencil on laid paper watermarked “JWHATMAN.” As well as the
                        usual grey wash there is some brown along the draperies down the back of
                        Lady Macbeth and below her left hand. The paper seems to have been trimmed
                        all round, cutting the inscription “Blake,” perhaps a
                        signature, in the lower right-hand corner. The drawing illustrates the
                        passage from act II, scene ii of <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>, where Lady
                        Macbeth describes how <q> I laid their daggers ready,<lb/> He could not miss
                            ’em. Had he not resembled<lb/> My father as he slept, I had
                            done’t </q> This is in fulfillment of Macbeth’s
                        suggestion, in act I, scene vii, that he should use the daggers belonging to
                        Duncan’s two chamberlains, made drunk by Lady Macbeth, so that it
                        would look as if they had committed <figure n="LadyMacbeth.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"><head>5. “Lady Macbeth and the Sleeping Duncan,”
                                c.1785.</head><figDesc>Pen and grey and brown washes over pencil, on paper, trimmed,
                                32.7 × 42.6 cm. Thos. Agnew &amp; Sons, Ltd,
                                London.</figDesc></figure><figure n="LadyMacbeth.verso.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"><head>6. Verso of “Lady Macbeth and the Sleeping Duncan,”
                                c. 1785.</head><figDesc>Pencil with some brown wash on paper, trimmed, 32.7 ×
                                42.6 cm. Thos. Agnew &amp; Sons, Ltd, London.</figDesc></figure><pb id="p26-26" n="26"/> the deed. Blake shows Lady Macbeth with the daggers
                        standing over the sleeping Duncan, who has gone to bed with his crown on.
                            <note id="n208"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Andrew Wyld of Thos. Agnew &amp;
                            Sons, Ltd, told me about the drawing in London, let me examine it and,
                            again, supplied photographs. I am most grateful to my friends among art
                            dealers and auctioneers in keeping me informed about works by Blake as
                            they turn up.</note></p>
          <p>On the reverse there is a variant in pencil alone of the same composition,
                        inscribed, again in the lower right-hand corner, “Lady Macbeth/King
                        Duncan” (illus. 6). Also on the reverse, with the paper to be seen as
                        an upright with the left-hand edge at the bottom, is a slightly inclined
                        profile facing right, just possibly a study for the profile of Lady Macbeth.
                        On the reverse she stands on the right, leaning over Duncan in a much more
                        threatening manner than on the recto; he lies as before except that his left
                        arm seems to lie across his chest. Pentimenti on the recto show that Lady
                        Macbeth was originally in the same stooping position as on the verso; Blake
                        also drew her in an intermediary position before finally adopting the
                        present upright stance. The drawings therefore are a particularly
                        interesting example of how Blake improvised his compositions. Some of the
                        forms of the recto have come out on the verso, perhaps because it was drawn
                        with the paper laid on a dirty surface, and some of the brownish wash also
                        appears on the reverse, presumably as the result of an accident.</p>
          <p>The drawing, which is listed by William Rossetti as indicated in my entry,
                        seems to be one of the items in lot 165 in the Tatham sale at
                        Sotheby’s on 29 April 1862, “Lady Macbeth and Duncan, Angels
                        conducting the Souls of the Just to Paradise, &amp;c. <hi rend="i">in
                            indian ink</hi>,” four items in all, bought by Palser for
                        thirteen shillings; the lot comes among other drawings that can be
                        identified as pen and wash drawings of the 1780s. The recent history of the
                        drawing is no clearer than was indicated in my entry; all that can be said
                        is that it has recently turned up in the trade. Rossetti’s dismissive
                        description, “Not carried far beyond the outline. Ordinary”
                        seems far from the mark. In fact the drawing is one of the most dramatic and
                        boldly drawn of this whole group.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Empire is no More”: Odin and Orc in <hi rend="i">America</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Julia M. <name>Wright</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Orc appears in a number of Blake’s poems, but his character in <hi rend="i">America</hi> (1793) is uniquely drawn. A howling, flaming
                        figure in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794) and a chained infant in <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen</hi> (1794), the Orc of <hi rend="i">America</hi> is described in a wealth of detail that is matched only by
                            <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (1797).<ref target="n209" type="note">1</ref> The details that are provided, however, differ. In both <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">America</hi>, for instance,
                        Orc claims that his spirit can leave his chained body, but the Orc of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> represents his spirit as “A Worm
                        compelld” (80.31), while that of <hi rend="i">America</hi> chooses
                        figures of power: <q> on high my spirit soars;<lb/> Sometimes an eagle
                            screaming in the sky, sometimes a lion,<lb/> Stalking upon the
                            mountains, &amp; sometimes a whale I lash<lb/> The raging fathomless
                            abyss, anon a serpent . . .<lb/> On the Canadian wilds I fold. (1.12-17)
                        </q> These figures have been associated with various sets of symbols of
                        power, as Rodney M. Baine suggests that the shapes are all images of regal
                        power over nature (130), while David V. Erdman identifies some of the
                        animals as revolutionary emblems (259). Although the female later claims
                        that Orc courts her in these shapes, they are quite violent in Orc’s
                        speech: the shapes are “screaming,” “stalking,”
                        “lashing,” and, by “folding,” encircle and bind,
                        like the serpent of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi> The Orc
                        of <hi rend="i">America</hi> thus chooses a diversity of shapes that are not
                        only unbound but associated with aggressive power. This characterization of
                        Orc is reinforced and elaborated through allusions to Norse mythology that
                        can be used to explore the complexity of this revolutionary figure as he is
                        constructed in <hi rend="i">America.</hi><note id="n209"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I cite the dates on Blake’s title
                            pages rather than rehearse bibliographical debates regarding the dating
                            of these texts.</note></p>
          <p>In his discussion of the first quarter of the Preludium, Harold Bloom writes
                        that “The mythic world suggested is the Northern one of Odin and
                        Thor, the Eddic literature known to Blake through Mallet’s <hi rend="i">Northern Antiquities</hi> . . . and the poems and translations
                        of Thomas Gray” (118). Bloom emphasizes the references to iron, and
                        his identification of the female as the daughter of a Thor-like smith
                        (118-19), while Erdman finds in the action of the poem an allusion to Paul
                        Henri Mallet’s explanation of human sacrifice “as a harvest
                        rite” (251). Both <hi rend="i">America</hi> and Blake’s notes
                        for his designs for the 1790 edition of Gray’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> indicate a knowledge of Gray’s free translation of an
                        Icelandic lay, <hi rend="i">The Descent of Odin</hi>, and a familiarity with
                        Norse mythology that extends beyond <pb id="p26-27" n="27"/> that poem.
                        Blake’s notes, for instance, refer to “The Serpent who girds
                        the Earth” (680), which is not mentioned in Gray’s poem, as
                        well as “The Serpent &amp; the Wolvish Dog. two terrors in the
                        Northern mythology” (680), which recall Orc’s form as a
                        serpent and the “eternal Wolf” (9.2). Orc, moreover, like Lok
                        in Gray’s <hi rend="i">Descent</hi>, is riveted by a “tenfold
                        chain” (1.12; Gray 65), as has been noted by Mark Schorer (406n) and
                        Erdman (262n).<ref target="n210" type="note">2</ref> While critics have
                        indicated the Norse background for this poem and others by Blake, however,
                        there are close correspondences between <hi rend="i">America</hi>’s
                        Orc and Odin that have not been addressed. <note id="n210"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See Erdman (262n) and Schorer (405-06n) for other
                            correspondences between Gray’s translation and Blake’s
                            poetry.</note></p>
          <p>In asserting that he can transform his spirit into the shapes of a whale, a
                        serpent, an eagle, and a lion, Orc evokes a distinguishing feature of Odin.
                        In the <hi rend="i">Ynglinga Saga</hi>, Snorre Sturlason writes that Odin
                        “could transform his shape: his body would lie as if dead, or asleep;
                        but then he would be in shape of a fish, a worm, a bird, or beast”
                        (11), the four categories of Orc’s avatars.<ref target="n211" type="note">3</ref> The <hi rend="i">Heimskringla</hi>, of which the <hi rend="i">Ynglinga Saga</hi> is the first part, was not published in an
                        English translation until 1844, although the closeness of Sturlason’s
                        description of Odin’s transformative abilities to Orc’s
                        description of his metamorphic powers invites speculation that Blake had
                        access to unpublished or as yet unidentified information. Through
                        Mallet’s <hi rend="i">Northern Antiquities</hi>, however, which
                        “is almost certainly Blake’s source for Norse
                        mythology” (Bloom 441), Blake would have had access to a more general
                        knowledge of the saga, since it is both discussed and paraphrased in that
                        work. Bishop Percy’s translation of Mallet’s text was
                        published in 1770, and it notes Odin’s ability to transform his shape
                        and to travel widely: “[Odin] persuaded his followers that he could
                        run over the world in the twinkling of an eye, that he had the direction of
                        the air and tempests, that he could transform himself into all sorts of
                        shapes” (83). Like Mallet’s Odin, Orc merely claims such
                        abilities; there is no narratorial authority for Orc’s
                        transformations in <hi rend="i">America</hi>, as there is in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> In eighteenth-century antiquarian discourse, Odin
                        is persistently constructed as a confidence-man rather than a god, a human
                        being whose rhetorical and poetic abilities allowed him to convince his
                        followers, through speech alone, that he was a god.<ref target="n212" type="note">4</ref><hi rend="i">America</hi> is the only poem of the early 1790s in which Orc
                        is articulate, and he not only speaks, but speaks eloquently in a voice that
                        “shook the temple” (5.7) and “In thunders ends”
                        (7.1). In Odin and <hi rend="i">America</hi>’s Orc, then, we have two
                        compelling orators who claim to have the ability to change their shape and
                        travel widely. There are, however, even closer correspondences between the
                        language with which Mallet describes Odin and that with which Blake
                        describes Orc in <hi rend="i">America.</hi><note id="n211"><hi rend="s">3</hi> In eighteenth-century terms, these
                            classifications are legitimate: the whale was referred to as a fish well
                            into the nineteenth century.</note><note id="n212"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See, e.g., Lemprière and Mallet.
                            Odin is identified as a poet by Lemprière (417) and Mallet (83),
                            the inventor of poetry by Mallet (83), and the inventor of writing by
                            both Warton (xx) and Mallet (83).</note></p>
          <p>Odin is the “God of War” (Mallet 91), and it is as such that he
                        excites “terror” (Mallet 84) and bears the epithet,
                        “The terrible and severe God” (Mallet 91), recalling the
                        persistence with which Orc is associated with forms of the word
                        “terror,” and his appearance “like the planet
                        red” (5.2), which is named for the Roman god of war, Mars.<ref target="n213" type="note">5</ref> Odin, as a martial deity, is called
                        upon by his devotees to embolden them in battle, and Percy’s
                        translation of Mallet makes this point in language that appears in <hi rend="i">America</hi>, noting that “[Odin] often descended to
                        intermix in the conflict himself, to inflame the fury of the
                        combatants” (92). Orc’s inspiration of the American rebels is
                        repeatedly described in terms of flame: “And the flame folded roaring
                        fierce within the pitchy night / Before the Demon red, who burnt towards
                        America . . . gath’ring thick / In flames as of a furnace on the land
                        from North to South” (12.8-9, 12.11-12). This depiction of Orc as
                        flaming appears elsewhere in Blake’s works, but other details
                        regarding Orc’s non-inflammatory participation in the revolution do
                        not. In paraphrasing the <hi rend="i">Ynglinga Saga</hi>, Mallet writes that
                        Odin was a great warrior who “inspired his enemies with such terror,
                        that they could not describe it better, than by saying he rendered them
                        blind and deaf; that he would appear like a wolf all desperate” (84).
                        Mallet’s combination of “terror,” battle, a wolf,
                        blindness, and difficulty with hearing, occurs in the reaction of
                        Albion’s Angel to Orc’s speech: “Loud howls the Eternal
                        Wolf! . . . / America is darkned; and my punishing Demons terrified . . .
                        clouds obscure my aged sight” (9.2-3, 9.12). <note id="n213"><hi rend="s">5</hi> It is the martial Odin that appears in
                            Blake’s other works by name (<hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> 3.30;
                                <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 25.52-53; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                            83.19). Sotha, linked to Odin in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
                            (1795), also appears in a canceled plate for <hi rend="i">America</hi>(b.21). This additional connection between Odin and <hi rend="i">America</hi> is suspect, however, because of the question
                            of dating, since <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> was printed two years
                            after <hi rend="i">America</hi>, and the date of the canceled plate is
                            unknown.</note></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">America</hi>, Blake constructs an Orc that specifically
                        recalls the Norse god: both are associated with the shape of a wolf during
                        war, “inflame” warriors, blind opponents, have remarkable
                        oratorical abilities, and claim to possess extraordinary powers that allow
                        them to change shape and journey extensively. Why, then, does <hi rend="i">America</hi> have an Orc who echoes Mallet’s Odin in so many
                        specifics while, for instance, the contemporaneous <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                        does not? The answer, I would argue, lies in the difference between the
                        political situations that are represented. Unlike <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                        and the other poems in which Orc appears, <hi rend="i">America</hi> is
                        concerned specifically with oppression as imperial rule—and so is
                        Mallet’s discussion of Odin. Mallet indicates that Odin was
                        considered a nationalist hero in material available to him: <q> Several
                            learned men have supposed that a desire of being revenged on the Romans
                            was the ruling principle of his whole conduct. . . . He had no other
                            view, according to them, in running through so many distant kingdoms,
                            and in establishing with so much zeal his sanguinary doctrines, but to
                            spirit up all nations against so formidable and odious a power. This
                            leaven, which he left in the bosoms of the northern people, fermented a
                            long time in secret; but the signal, they add, once given, they all fell
                            as it were by common consent upon this unhappy empire; and after many
                            repeated shocks, entirely overturned it. (82-83) </q> “Stiff
                        shudderings shook the heav’nly thrones” (16.16): Odin inspires
                        rebels to overthrow the Roman Empire, the “enemies of universal
                        liberty” (Mallet 82), while Orc inspires rebels to overthrow the
                        British Empire, crying, “Empire is no more” (6.15).</p>
          <p>A poet who inflamed the rebels that freed Northern Europe from Roman <pb id="p26-28" n="28"/> rule, Odin appears to be an ideal figure with which
                        to affiliate the articulate Orc who inflames the rebels that free the
                        American colonies from British rule. Mallet’s Odin, however, is more
                        complex than this. According to eighteenth-century antiquarians, Odin was
                        not a Norse god, nor even a Northern European, but an exile from Asia
                        (Warton xx; Bell 233) who escaped into Northern Europe after participating
                        in a failed Scythian revolt against the Romans (Mallet 79). Mallet maintains
                        that Odin’s real name was Sigge, and vilifies him for imposing a
                        violent religious and political system on Northern Europeans through deceit
                        and violence: Sigge assumed the name of the deity Odin, “a title so
                        proper to procure him respect among the people he meant to subject,”
                        and “marched towards the north and west of Europe, subduing, we are
                        told, all the people he found in his passage” (80).
                        “[A]mbitious” (80), Mallet’s Odin is not only a
                        catalyst for the expulsion of the Roman Empire from Northern Europe, but a
                        conqueror of Northern Europe himself, and Mallet only offers the
                        characterization of Odin as an anti-imperialist hero in order to refute
                        it.</p>
          <p>Blake’s allusions to Mallet’s Odin, an anti-imperial conqueror,
                        can thus provide a schema through which to address two questions raised by
                            <hi rend="i">America:</hi> why is the champion of the oppressed in the
                        Prophecy depicted raping the female in the Preludium? And why are indigenous
                        Americans so thoroughly removed from the Prophecy’s conflict? (By
                        “Prophecy,” I mean the text within <hi rend="i">America</hi>
                        that is labelled as such, rather than the whole work.) While critics have
                        legitimated the rape, and so sustained Orc’s status as the
                        poem’s hero, Blake’s language suggests both violence and
                        illicit conquest: “[Orc] siez’d the panting struggling
                        womb” (2.3).<ref target="n214" type="note">6</ref> While the female
                        is not explicitly identified with Amerindians, she declares herself to be
                        the proprietor of American land (2.10),<ref target="n215" type="note">7</ref> and Erdman suggests that, in the illustration for plate 1, she
                        “appears in her American Indian form” (259). Viewing this
                        “daughter” (1.1) as a representative of the aboriginal peoples
                        would, moreover, be consistent with the iconography of loyalist engravings,
                        in which, as Stephen C. Behrendt points out, Britannia is represented as a
                        matriarch and her “‘daughter’ [is] the emblematic
                        American Indian” (32). The evidence linking the female with the
                        Amerindians is tenuous, but it is congruous with a parallel between the
                        female and this elided group to which I wish to draw attention. There
                        exists, I would suggest, a homomorphism between the situations of the
                        American revolutionaries, Orc, and Mallet’s Odin, in terms of their
                        relationships to martial power, a homomorphism in which the female occupies
                        the same position as the Amerindians, and the Northern Europeans, in being
                        the object of violence and conquest for a revolutionary figure who fights on
                        behalf of the oppressed. Wars between the colonists and the first nations
                        began before the American Revolution, and continued in the context of the
                        Revolution, since most of the aboriginal peoples of the northeast, including
                        the Iroquois Confederacy and the Delaware, sided with the British. The
                        revolutionaries were thus in the ideologically contradictory position of
                        trying to conquer one group while crying for liberty from another. Orc is
                        placed in a similarly contradictory position, identifying himself with
                        animals engaged in violent activities and seizing another against her will,
                        and then speaking on behalf of the oppressed Americans of European descent.
                            <note id="n214"><hi rend="s">6</hi> The rape has been described as
                            “desire fulfilling itself” (Doskow 176), “patriots
                            . . . making love to good earth” (Erdman 261), and Orc’s
                            attempt to “give his voice, and his passion, to silent
                            nature” (Bloom 120). More recently, Michael Ferber has
                            acknowledged the problem of “identifying the actions of the
                            American colonists . . . with a violent act” (95), but resolves
                            it by characterizing the rape as “a reclamation of the usurped
                            land by those who deserve her” (96). This reclaimed
                            “land,” however, complains at the end of the Preludium of
                            “eternal death” (2.17), “limb rending pains”
                            (2.15), “howling pains” (2.16), and
                            “torment” (2.17), and the bard of the canceled lines
                            echoes her “cry” (2.6) with “sick &amp; drear
                            lamentings” (2.21). The only reference to joy is limited to the
                            womb—“It joy’d” (2.4), not
                            “she,” or “he” for that matter. Even if the
                            rape has positive consequences, as fertilization or as the release of
                            the female’s voice, the act itself is one of violence and
                            conquest, and the final lines of the Preludium draw attention to the
                            negative implications of that violence, not a justification of
                            it.</note><note id="n215"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The phrase, “my American
                            plains” (2.10), could be used to identify the female as a
                            personification of those plains (see, e.g., Doskow and Erdman), but the
                            detail that concerns me is the word “my”: whether the
                            plains are external to her body or are tropologically equated with it,
                            she asserts that they are hers.</note></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">America</hi>, through the figure of Odin, Blake narrows the
                        scope of his rebel to anti-imperial rebellion, a focus that is not
                        especially relevant to the other works in which Orc appears. Like Odin,
                        Orc’s colonists liberate a nation from imperial rule, but it is a
                        nation that they have themselves “siez’d.” Thus, in his
                        celebration of the American Revolution, Blake, like Mallet, does not elide
                        the investment of the revolutionaries in violence and conquest, the violence
                        and conquest through which they, like Mallet’s Odin, gained the
                        ground from which they fought against their own subjugation to imperial
                        rule. Orc’s violence does not erode the legitimacy of the rebellion,
                        against Urthona or Albion’s Angel, and need not be legitimized as a
                        means to that end, but stands as a reminder that to engage the struggle for
                        power is to be contaminated by the means of that struggle.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Works Cited</title>
            </head>
            <p>Baine, Rodney M. <hi rend="i">The Scattered Portions: William
                                Blake’s Biological Symbolism.</hi> Athens, GA: privately
                            printed, 1986.</p>
            <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “‘This Accursed Family’:
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and the American
                            Revolution.” <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century</hi> 27 (1986):
                            26-51.</p>
            <p>Bell, John. <hi rend="i">Bell’s New Pantheon.</hi> 1790. 2 vols.
                            New York: Garland, 1979. Vol. 2.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman. Rev. ed. Toronto: Doubleday,
                            1988.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic
                                Argument.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1963.</p>
            <p>Doskow, Minna. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">America:</hi>
                            The Story of a Revolution Betrayed.” <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Studies</hi>8 (1979): 167-86.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire.</hi> Rev.
                            ed. Garden City: Doubleday, 1969.</p>
            <p>Ferber, Michael. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and the
                            Birth of Revolution.” <hi rend="i">History and Myth: Essays on
                                English Romantic Literature.</hi> Ed. Stephen C. Behrendt. Detroit:
                            Wayne State UP, 1990. 73-99.</p>
            <p>Gray, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Descent of Odin.</hi> 1768. <hi rend="i">The Works of Thomas Gray in Prose and Verse.</hi> Ed. Edmund Gosse.
                            4 vols. New York: AMS P, 1968. 1: 59-65.</p>
            <p>Lemprière, John. <hi rend="i">Classical Dictionary of Proper Names
                                Mentioned in Ancient Authors Writ Large.</hi> 1788. 3rd ed. New
                            York: Routledge, 1984.</p>
            <p>Mallet [Paul Henri]. <hi rend="i">Northern Antiquities.</hi> Trans.
                            Bishop Percy. 1770. Additional notes and text by I. A. Blackwell.
                            London: Bohn, 1859.</p>
            <pb id="p26-29" n="29"/>
            <p>Schorer, Mark. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Politics of Vision.</hi>
                            New York: Holt, 1946.</p>
            <p>Snorre Sturlason. <hi rend="i">Ynglinga Saga. Heimskringla: The Norse
                                King Sagas.</hi> Trans. S. Laing. 1844. Rev. ed. New York: Dutton,
                            1951. 7-43.</p>
            <p>Warton, Thomas. “Of the Origin of Romantic Fiction in
                            Europe.” 1774. <hi rend="i">The History of English Poetry.</hi> 3
                            vols. Additional Notes by Ritson, Ashby et al. London: Tegg, 1840. 1:
                            i-lvi.</p>
            <p>All quotations of Blake’s writings are taken from Erdman’s
                            edition, and will be from <hi rend="i">America</hi> unless otherwise
                            noted; quotations of the poetry will be cited by plate and line number,
                            and references to the prose will be cited by page number.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <figure n="Tarot.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"/>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <pb id="p26-30" n="30"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="Blake.Stothard.26.1.bqscan" rend="file">
            <head>1. Blake’s engravings of Stothard’s designs for <hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi>
                            (1782), in the British Museum (reproduced from the photograph supplied
                            by Robert N. Essick and used in his <hi rend="i">Separate Plates of
                                William Blake</hi> [1983]).</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s Elusive Ladies</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>E. B. <name>Bentley</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <q> The angels keep their ancient places<lb/> Turn but a stone, and start a
                        wing!<lb/> ’Tis ye, ’tis your estrangèd faces<lb/> That
                        miss the many-splendored thing.<ref target="n216" type="note">1</ref><note id="n216"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Francis Thomson, “The Kingdom of
                            God,” stanza 4.</note></q>
          <p>Two engravings executed on one plate by William Blake in 1782 have long been
                        known and mentioned and speculated about, but the book for which they were
                        intended has never been clearly identified. It has even been suggested that
                        the book was never published. The engravings I am dealing with are inscribed
                            “<hi rend="i">A Lady in the full Dress, &amp; another in the
                            most fashionable Undress now worn</hi>” and “<hi rend="i">The Morning Amusements of her Royal Highness the Princess Royal &amp;
                            her 4 Sisters</hi>” (illus 1). These two designs after Thomas
                        Stothard are to be found in the British Museum Print Room. A copy of the
                        book in which the engravings appeared has not been discovered, but I believe
                        that a small volume in the Huntington Library provides very clear
                        indications of what we should seek and therefore increases the likelihood of
                        turning up a copy of the ephemeral book in which the prints were
                        published.</p>
          <p>Those who search for Blake engravings have long known from Gilchrist’s
                        biography of the existence of engravings after Thomas Stothard of
                        “two frontispieces to Dodsley’s <hi rend="i">Lady’s
                            Pocket Book</hi>—‘The morning amusements of H.R.H. the
                        Princess Royal and her four sisters’ (1782), and ‘A Lady in
                        fulldress’ with another ‘in the most fashionable undress now
                        worn’ (1783).”<ref target="n217" type="note">2</ref> Gilchrist
                        does not specify where he had noticed these illustrations, and the reference
                        to “1783” would appear to be an error. In <hi rend="i">Thomas
                            Stothard, R.A.</hi>, A. C. Coxhead said the prints were designed by
                        Stothard for <hi rend="i">The Lady’s Magazine</hi>, but he does not
                        name any engraver. He based his list on the designs by Stothard which were
                        to be found in the Print Room of the British Museum but confessed that he
                        had not been able to find any copy of the magazine with all the plates
                        intact and implied that he had not found Stothard’s designs of either
                        “Morning Amusements” or “A Lady in full dress”
                        in <hi rend="i">The Lady’s Magazine.</hi><ref target="n218" type="note">3</ref><note id="n217"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life
                                of William Blake</hi>, “<hi rend="i">Pictor
                            Ignotus</hi>,” 2 vols. (London and Cambridge: Macmillan and Co.,
                            1863) 1: 51 and 2: 259.</note><note id="n218"><hi rend="s">3</hi> A. C. Coxhead, <hi rend="i">Thomas
                                Stothard, R.A.</hi> (London: Bullen, 1906) 42-47.</note></p>
          <p>In 1912, Archibald G. B. Russell listed the two Stothard designs with Blake
                        named as the engraver and joined Gilchrist in attributing them to <hi rend="i">The Lady’s Pocket Book</hi> (edited by Dodsley),
                        repeated Gilchrist’s 1782 and 1783 dates, and declared that
                        “The numbers for 1782 and 1783 contain frontispieces engraved in line
                        by Blake aftter Stothard.” This last assertion was simply taken from
                        Gilchrist and was not based on the discovery of these
                        “numbers.” He added that the two plates printed side by side
                        on a single sheet were in the Robert Balmanno collection of
                        Stothard’s works in the Print Room of the British Museum and noted
                        that the periodical “is not to be found in the British Museum and the
                        writer has been unable to meet with it elsewhere.”<ref target="n219" type="note">4</ref><note id="n219"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Archibald G. B. Russell, <hi rend="i">The Engravings of William Blake</hi> (London: Grant Richards, Ltd.,
                            1912) 142.</note></p>
          <p>Geoffrey Keynes in his 1921 bibliography of Blake also located the elusive
                        ladies in the publication named by Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">The Lady’s
                            Pocket Book</hi>, and added the imprint information inscribed <pb id="p26-31" n="31"/><figure n="Titlepage.LadiesPocketBook.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"><head>2. Title page of <hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite Pocket
                                    Memorandum-Book</hi> for 1780 (1779), courtesy of the Henry
                                E.</head><figDesc>Huntington Library.</figDesc></figure> on the engraving: “<hi rend="i">The Morning Amusements of
                            her Royal Highness the Princess Royal &amp; her 4 Sisters. Published by
                            J. Johnson . . . Nov</hi><hi rend="s">r</hi> I, 1782 <hi rend="i">Stothard del Blake Sc.</hi>”<ref target="n220" type="note">5</ref> Keynes tried to solve the problem introduced by the Johnson
                        imprint for the design intended for a Dodsley publication by supposing that
                        the publication was “Edited by Dodsley for J. Johnson 1782,”
                        but he confessed that he had never been able to find the elusive
                        “volume.” He did not say why he thought it was edited by
                        [James] Dodsley for Johnson. <note id="n220"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Geoffrey
                            Keynes, <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William Blake</hi> (New York: The
                            Grolier Club, 1921) 226.</note></p>
          <p>Upon becoming a reader at the Bodleian Library (1953) and the British Museum
                        [Library] (1958), my first tasks were prolonged by fruitless searches for
                            <hi rend="i">The Ladies/Lady’s Pocket Book</hi> and variations
                        upon the title. When Bentley and Nurmi published their bibliography, they
                        reviewed previous findings about the Pocket Book, added that the Rosenwald
                        collection contained a proof impression of “The Morning
                        Amusements” design, speculated that the publication may have been a
                        descendant of Robert Dodsley’s <hi rend="i">The Ladies New Memorandum
                            Book</hi><figure n="Prints.LadiesPocketBook.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"><head>3. The two facing prints in <hi rend="i">The Ladies New and Polite
                                    Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi> for 1780 (1779), courtesy of the
                                Huntington Library.</head></figure> for 1758, and suggested that Gilchrist’s Dodsley must have
                        been Robert’s (1703-64) brother James (1724-97).<ref target="n221" type="note">6</ref><note id="n221"><hi rend="s">6</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., &amp; Martin K.
                            Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: University
                            of Minnesota Press, 1964) 136.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, the descendent of <hi rend="i">A Blake
                            Bibliography</hi>, lists the work as “UNTRACED.” The entry
                        offers as “prime evidence [that the <hi rend="i">Pocket Book</hi>
                        existed] the two plates on one leaf in the BMPR”: <q> 1. <hi rend="i">‘The Morning amusements of her Royal Highness the Princess
                                Royal &amp; her 4 Sisters.’ ‘Stothard del.’,
                                ‘Blake sc.’, ‘Published by J. Johnson S<hi rend="s">t</hi> Paul’s Church Yard, Nov<hi rend="s">r</hi> I.1782’.</hi> (Design size: 12.6 × 9.6cm).
                            (Proofs are also in the Royal Academy [before title] and the Rosenwald
                            Collection.)<lb/><lb/> 2. <hi rend="i">‘A Lady in the full Dress,
                                &amp; another in the most fashionable Undress now worn.’
                                ‘T.S. del’, ‘W.B. sc’</hi> (design size:
                            6.5 × 9.6 cm). (A proof with only Blake’s name is in the
                            Royal Academy.)<ref target="n222" type="note">7</ref><note id="n222"><hi rend="s">7</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977) 591.</note></q></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> lists nine works with variations of the
                        Gilchrist title which had proved not to be the book with the plates engraved
                        by Blake after Stothard or to contain illustrations which might fit the
                        titles given on those in the Print Room, and also comments: “The
                        title was casually used, and Stothard signed a receipt of 11 April 1795 for
                        ‘sixteen guineas [<hi rend="i">for</hi>] two drawings for
                        Lady’s [Pocket Book <hi rend="i">del</hi>]
                            Maggazien.’”<ref target="n223" type="note">8</ref><note id="n223"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The receipt is in Princeton University
                            Library (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 592).</note></p>
          <p>Robert N. Essick has not only diligently joined in the search but also has
                        assisted searchers to identify what they were seeking by his meticulous
                        descriptions of the impressions in the Royal Academy, the British Museum and
                        the Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C. and by
                        reproductions of the two designs which have proved so elusive.<ref target="n224" type="note">9</ref> Like Coxhead, he looked vainly in <hi rend="i">The Lady’s Magazine</hi>, and he notes the paradox of
                        placing an engraving bearing a Johnson imprint in a magazine published by G.
                        G. J. and J. Robinson. <note id="n224"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Robert N. Essick,
                                <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake</hi> (Princeton:
                            Princeton University Press, 1983) 239-41 and figures 108-09. They are
                            omitted from his <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book
                                Illustrations</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991), because he
                            excludes “plates probably executed for publication in books but
                            known only through separate impressions” (vi).</note></p>
          <p>I cannot claim that the hunt was strongly publicized. When Shelley M. Bennett
                        published <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard: The Mechanisms of Art Patronage in
                            England Circa 1800</hi>, she cited Coxhead’s descriptions of our
                        elusive ladies in relation to the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine.</hi> She
                        also cited Bentley and Essick and said Essick doubts the book was ever
                        published and Bentley lists the book as “untraced.”<ref target="n225" type="note">10</ref><note id="n225"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Thomas
                                Stothard</hi> (Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1988) 65-66.
                            The “1778 volume” of “<hi rend="i">The Ladies
                                Comlete Pocket Book</hi>” which she locates in the
                            “British Library (P.P. 2469 cl [I])” is, according to the
                            British Library Catalogue, for 1769, not
                        “1778.”</note></p>
          <pb id="p26-32" n="32"/>
          <p>Many librarians are amused by my searches and others try to remind me that
                        this is a search for very “ephemeral stuff.” I have long
                        realized that it would probably be by serendipity if the book with
                        Blake’s and Stothard’s illustrations were ever found, but I
                        have clung to my conviction that it would turn up some time, some where.
                        Over the years I have looked for a <hi rend="i">Lady’s Pocket
                            Book</hi> in collections in India, China, Australia, New Zealand, Hong
                        Kong, Japan, Taiwan, Guatemala, Algeria, Austria, France, Germany, England,
                        Canada, the United States, and elsewhere. At the Bodleian in July 1991, I
                        checked the microfiche copy of the <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century Short
                            Title Catalogue</hi> without success. In the late autumn I looked for
                        the title at the Lilly Library in Bloomington, Indiana, and the Spencer
                        Library in Lawrence, Kansas. The librarians were eager to help find a <hi rend="i">Ladies Pocket Book</hi>, and there was even a lead or two to
                        follow. Alas, the ladies continued to be elusive.</p>
          <p>Recently, at the Huntington, I was looking for a book entitled <hi rend="i">My Ladies Casket</hi>, and that put me in mind of the old quest. In the
                        card catalogue there was an entry which aroused a flicker of hope, so I
                        called up the book.</p>
          <p>This is the title of the book which came to my trembling hand: <q> THE |
                            LADIES | NEW AND POLITE | Pocket Memorandum-Book, | For the Year of our
                            Lord 1780. | Being the Twentieth of King George III, the | Twenty-ninth
                            of the New Style in Great | Britain, and Bissextile or Leap-Year. |
                            Embellished with a beautiful Copper-Plate, representing | His Royal
                            Highness Prince WILLIAMHENRY as a | NAVAL OFFICER on board the FLEET;
                            also the most | elegant and genteel FULL DRESS and UNDRESS worn. |
                            CONTAINING, | [2 columns: column 1:] I. A Useful Memorandum | Book,
                            &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. | II. Table of Interest from one | Pound to
                            one Thousand. | III. Holidays, Birth-Days, | and other remarkable Days
                            in 1780. | IV. Good natured Credulity. | A Fable. | V. Experiment on the
                            Pro- | perties of Colours in im- | bibing the Rays of the Sun. | VI.
                            Anecdotes and enter- | taining Moral Essays. [Column 2:] VII. Curious
                            Descriptions in | Natural History. | VIII. Select Pieces of Poe- | try,
                            by the most admired | Wits. | IX. The most esteemed New | Songs, sung at
                            Vauxhall, |Ranelagh, the Theatres, | and Catch Club. | X. New Country
                            Dances | for 1780. | XI. Marketing Tables, Rates | of Hackney Coachmen,
                            | Chairmen, &amp;c. &amp;c. [End of columns.] | LONDON: | Printed for
                            J. JOHNSON, No. 72, St. Paul’s Church-yard. | [<hi rend="i">To be
                                continued annually. Price One Shilling.</hi>] &lt;Huntington:
                            429524&gt; (illus. 2) </q></p>
          <p>This publication is an excellent candidate for what has been so long sought.
                        The title of the second print in it, ‘a Lady in the newest full
                        Dress, and another in the most fashionable Undress,’ is remarkably
                        similar to Blake’s ‘A Lady in the full Dress, and another in
                        the most fashionable Undress now worn.’ The style of the lettering is
                        also remarkably similar. J. Johnson is the publisher for both the Blake
                        engraving and this “1780” edition. The format of the fashion
                        images is the same in both plates, with the ‘full Dress’
                        figure on the right and the ‘Undress’ figure on the left. The
                        size of Blake’s plate for the “1783” edition and that
                        for “1780” is the same, while the royal scenes are the same
                        height and clearly intended to be folded when bound into the book.</p>
          <p>It is a very small book (12.2 high x 7.6 cm wide) with tattered boards only
                        barely hanging on, and the engravings are very close in size to the Blake
                        prints in the British Museum.</p>
          <p>There are two anonymous plates engraved by Page, the platemarks are invisible
                        (frame for the images 9.5 × 6.5 and 9.5 × 6.5), the first of
                            “<hi rend="i">A Lady in the newest full Dress, and | another in
                            the most fashionable Undress</hi>” and the other of “<hi rend="i">His Royal Highness</hi> Prince William Henry, | <hi rend="i">Their MAJESTY’s Third</hi> Son, <hi rend="i">in his naval Uni- |
                            form, on board the</hi> Prince George, <hi rend="i">attended | by</hi>
                        Admiral Digby” (illus. 3).</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">CONTENTS</hi>; Titlepage (p. 1); Simple Interest at 5 1. per
                        Cent. from 1 Pound to 1000 (p. 2); Laws at Quadrille (pp. 3-4); Good Natured
                        Credulity. A Fable (pp. 4-6); Entertainment [experiments, anecdotes,
                        &amp;c] (pp. 6-11); Rules to be observed respecting Hackney Coachmen (p.
                        12); Memorandums for the beginning of the Year 1780 [largely blank, to be
                        filled in] (pp. [13-15]); Memorandum pages for January 1780-December 1780
                        (pp. [15-120]); The Pride of Rank and Opulence abased, a story (pp.
                        121-126); Select Pieces of Poetry [from Sheridan, Isaac Watts, &amp;c] (pp.
                        127-140); New Songs (pp. 140-144). <hi rend="i">N.B.</hi> There is a
                        catchword on the last page, strongly implying that there is a gathering or
                        more missing from the Huntington copy. The missing pages should contain the
                        New Country Dances and the Marketing Tables, &amp;c.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">COLLATION:</hi> 12° in sixes: A-M<hi rend="s">6</hi>; 12
                        gatherings.</p>
          <p>This volume has been used very sporadically by a contemporary for notes,
                        appointments, &amp;c., e.g., Friday January 28th: “M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Sawbridge and F. Sawbridge set out for Hackney”; there
                        are repeated other references to Mr. Sawbridge, to Weston and Hackney and
                        Portland Place.</p>
          <p>The Huntington pocket book arrived in 1973 with 50 similar items. There must
                        be many others still in existence. The nature of the publication strongly
                        suggests that there were issues for other years, and other copies for this
                        and other years must be extant.</p>
          <p>Having found a book which fits with the Johnson name, the illustration of
                        “FULL DRESS and UNDRESS now worn,” I’m convinced we
                        have found the correct series. <hi rend="i">The National Union Catalog</hi>
                        and the British Library catalogue supplements were rapidly consulted with no
                        new discoveries. Searches in the various computer listings were followed
                        eagerly. Through RLIN, the on-line Research Libraries Information Network, I
                        located and saw at the Folger Shakespeare Library <q> THE | LADIES | NEW AND
                            POLITE | Pocket Memorandum-Book, | For the Year of our Lord 1778. | . .
                            . | Embellished with a beautiful Copper-Plate, representing the NINE
                            LIVING MUSES of GREAT BRITAIN, | in the Temple of Apollo, viz. Miss
                            Carter, Mrs. | Barbauld, Mrs. Montagu, Mrs. Angelica Kauffman, | Mrs.
                            Macauley, Miss More, Mrs. Lenox, Mrs. Grif- | fifths, and Mrs. Sheridan.
                            | Also the MOST ELEGANT | and GENTEEL FULL DRESS and UNDRESS worn. | . .
                            . | LONDON: | Printed for J. JOHNSON, No. 72, St. Paul’s
                            Church-year [1777]. | [<hi rend="i">To be continued annually. Price One
                                Shilling</hi>] </q></p>
          <p>And the on-line <hi rend="i">ESTC</hi> (1992) directed me to an edition for
                        1789 in the <pb id="p26-33" n="33"/> John Johnson Cellection in Bodley: <q>
                            THE | LADIES | NEW AND POLITE | Pocket Memorandum-Book, | For the Year
                            of our Lord 1789. | . . . | Embellished with a beautiful Copper-Plate,
                            representing | two Ladies in the most fashionable Dresses now worn; |
                            also an elegant Engraving of Somerset-Place from the | Water [<hi rend="i">missing in the Bodley copy</hi>]. | . . . | LONDON: |
                            Printed for J. JOHNSON, . . . [1788]. </q></p>
          <p>We now know that an annual publication entitled <hi rend="i">The Ladies New
                            and Complete Pocket Memorandum-Book</hi> was published by Joseph Johnson
                        beginning as early as 1777 and continuing at least through 1788. Of the
                        three copies now located, for 1778, 1780, and 1789, those for 1778 and 1780
                        certainly have two images engraved on one plate designed so that the printed
                        sheet could be folded, leaving the prints to face one another, like
                        Blake’s, and that for 1789 apparently did so (the second engraving
                        announced on the title page is missing from the Bodley copy). Each of the
                        three editions offers fashion illustration, two of them using the same
                        wording as in Blake’s engravings: “Full Dress and Undress
                        worn.” The two illustrations of royalty (1780, 1783) and the one of
                        the muses of Apollo (1778) show a related interest in elegant subjects.</p>
          <p>Now we know we should be looking for a copy of the memorandum book for the
                        year 1783, since presumably such annuals were published before the new year
                        so that they could be sold in time for use on 1 January. The November 1782
                        date in the imprint of Blake’s plate fits such a pattern. I am
                        convinced that copies will turn up and will continue my pursuit.</p>
          <p>What we should expect to find is this: <q> THE | LADIES | NEW AND POLITE |
                            Pocket Memorandum-Book, | For the Year of our Lord 1783. | Being the
                            Twenty-third of King George III, and the | Thirty-second of the New
                            Style in Great Britain. | Embellished with a beautiful Copper-Plate,
                            representing The Morning Amusements of Her Royal Highness | the Princess
                            Royal &amp; Her 4 Sisters; also a Lady | in the FULL DRESS &amp;
                            another in the Most Fashionable UNDRESS now worn. | CONTAINING, | [<hi rend="i">2 columns</hi>: column 1:] I. A Useful Memorandum | Book,
                            &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. II. Table of Interest . . . [<hi rend="i">End
                                of columns.</hi>] LONDON: | Printed for J. JOHNSON, No. 72, St.
                            Paul’s Church-yard [1782]. | [<hi rend="i">To be continued
                                annually. Price One Shilling.</hi>]<lb/><lb/><hi rend="i">COLLATION</hi>: 12° in sixes: A-N<hi rend="s">6</hi>; 12.2 × 7.6 cm. </q></p>
          <p>There has to be a <hi rend="i">Ladies New and Polite Pocket
                            Memorandum-Book</hi> . . . for 1783 . . . Printed for J. JOHNSON waiting
                        for us somewhere.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <pb id="p26-34" n="34"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Corrections for the Blake Trust <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <figure n="Jerusalem.26.1.bqscan" rend="file"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Corrections in the transcription of Blake’s
                                    text:</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>P. 250, 72:50. There should not be a gap between the sixth and seventh
                            words of text, which should read: <q> South Fenelon </q></p>
            <p>The first part of the inscription in the design (transcribed on the
                            second line of commentary) should read: <q> Continually Building.
                                Continually Decaying </q></p>
            <p>P.295, 98: 45: the Coventet of Jehovah should read: <q> the Coventet
                                Jehovah </q></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Corrections in editorial matter:</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <table rows="38" cols="3">
              <row>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="b">Page/line</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="b">now reads</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="b">should read</hi>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>9, 19 down</cell>
                <cell>have been existed</cell>
                <cell>have existed</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>14, 2 up</cell>
                <cell>41 [46]</cell>
                <cell>46 [41]</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>15, 15 down</cell>
                <cell>34 [48]</cell>
                <cell>38 [34]</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>126, 15 up </cell>
                <cell>Hammer</cell>
                <cell>Hammer’</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>127, 2 up</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Jerusalem’</hi>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>130, 8 up</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Raine</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>(<hi rend="i">Raine</hi></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>131, 11 down</cell>
                <cell>end</cell>
                <cell>and</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>142, 9 down</cell>
                <cell>Circumcising</cell>
                <cell>‘Circumcising</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>147, top</cell>
                <cell>[plate no. missing]</cell>
                <cell>12</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>150, 3 up </cell>
                <cell>Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi></cell>
                <cell>Raine (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>164, 11 up</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">21</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">20</hi>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>168, 23 down</cell>
                <cell>constrasts</cell>
                <cell>contrasts</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>173, 5 up</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">betewen</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">between</hi>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>193, 22 down</cell>
                <cell>47: 7-11</cell>
                <cell>48: 7-11</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>194, 7 down</cell>
                <cell>41 [47]</cell>
                <cell>41 [37]</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>195, 12 down</cell>
                <cell>Gray</cell>
                <cell>Grey</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>204, 22 up</cell>
                <cell>36 [40]</cell>
                <cell>40 [36]</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>207, 6 down</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Symbols</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Symbols</hi> 454)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>210, 5 up</cell>
                <cell>Liberty’, <hi rend="i">MHH</hi></cell>
                <cell>Liberty’ (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>211, 13 down</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Death</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>Death</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>217, 22 up</cell>
                <cell>They</cell>
                <cell>‘They</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>219, 19 up</cell>
                <cell>(69: 43).</cell>
                <cell>(69: 43).)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>231, 3 up</cell>
                <cell>Mesrach</cell>
                <cell>Meshach</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>11 up</cell>
                <cell>I shall</cell>
                <cell>shall I</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>239, 10 down</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">345</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell><hi rend="i">345</hi>)</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>240, 4 down</cell>
                <cell>superstititions</cell>
                <cell>superstitions</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>255, 5 up</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">3</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">5</hi>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>256, bottom</cell>
                <cell>Church.</cell>
                <cell>Church’</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>256, bottom</cell>
                <cell>Beer, <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi></cell>
                <cell>Beer (<hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi></cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>269, 13 up</cell>
                <cell>Bath-Rabbin</cell>
                <cell>Bath-rabbim</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>274, 10 up</cell>
                <cell>86: 22</cell>
                <cell>86: 32</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>281, 22 down</cell>
                <cell>40</cell>
                <cell>41</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>291, 6 down</cell>
                <cell>Night and Ninth</cell>
                <cell>Night the Ninth</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>293, 16 down</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">99</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">97</hi>
                </cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>295, 8 up</cell>
                <cell>wihch</cell>
                <cell>which</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>299, 18 up</cell>
                <cell>
                  <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
                </cell>
                <cell><hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>’</cell>
              </row>
              <row>
                <cell>300, 8 up</cell>
                <cell>Manuscript.</cell>
                <cell>Manuscript.’</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Corrections to the placement or line references of
                                    notes:</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>P. 193: n. to 40 [36]: 20 refers to line 21</p>
            <p>P. 200: n. to 43 [38]: 55 refers to line 54</p>
            <p>P. 204: n. to line 15 belongs on p. 181, after the first sentence of the
                            note to 32 [46]: 15 there</p>
            <p>P. 227: n. to 60: 17 refers to line 18</p>
            <p>P. 245: n. to 69: 29 refers to lines 28-9</p>
            <p>P. 246: n. to 69: 69: 31-2 refers to lines 30-1</p>
            <p>P. 246: n. to 69: 39 ought to precede n. to line 41</p>
            <p>P. 255: n. to 74: 51-3 ought to precede n. to line 55</p>
            <p>P. 280: n. to 80: 1 refers to 80: 1-3</p>
            <p>P. 281: n. to 89: 47 refers to lines 46-7 n. to 89: 23-4 refers to lines
                            24-7</p>
            <p>P. 288: n. to 93: 10 refers to 1-18, and in line 5 of the note reference
                            is to line 18, not line 17, of text</p>
            <p>P. 292: n. to 96: 9 refers to lines 8-9 and 17</p>
            <p>P. 293: n. to 97: 14 should precede n. to line 15</p>
            <p>P. 295: n. to 98: 45 should precede n. to lines 46-53</p>
            <p>Three books to which reference is made in the editorial apparatus should
                            be added to the list of <hi rend="i">Works Cited</hi>:</p>
            <p>David Fuller. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Heroic Argument.</hi> London:
                            Croom Helm, 1988.</p>
            <p>Morton D. Paley. <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination.</hi> Oxford:
                            Clarendon Press, 1970.</p>
            <p>Joanne Witke. <hi rend="i">William Blake and Human Imagination.</hi>
                            London: Croom Helm, 1986.</p>
            <p>For their contributions to this list of corrections, I am indebted to Dr.
                            David Fuller (University of Durham), Professor John E. Grant (University
                            of Iowa), Professor Terence Hoagwood (Texas A &amp; M University), and
                            Mr. Thomas L. van der Voort (Alexandria, Virginia).</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-35" n="35"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <figure n="but536.1.wc.01" rend="db"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">Satan Arousing the Rebel Angels</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Blake’s 1808 watercolor, <hi rend="i">Satan Arousing the Rebel
                            Angels</hi>, from the series of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
                        illustrations commissioned by Butts, has been reproduced by dust-grain
                        gravure, a rarely used continuous-tone process similar to aquatint, by Hugh
                        Stoneman at the Print Centre, London. Dust-grain gravure was developed in
                        the nineteenth century for monochromatic printing. This is the first time it
                        has been used to produce a print in color, requiring three plates. Each
                        print is extensively colored by hand after printing.</p>
          <p>Blake’s <hi rend="i">Satan</hi> is being issued in the Victoria &amp;
                        Albert Museum’s Masterprints series, which also includes several
                        other reproductions, by various media, of works from the National Collection
                        of British Watercolours in the V&amp;A. The prints are issued in certified,
                        hand-numbered editions of 575 and range in price from $300 to $475. <hi rend="i">Satan Arousing the Rebel Angels</hi> (image size 20.5 inches
                        × 15.5 inches, on a sheet approx. 30.5 by 24.5 inches) is listed at
                        $475. It is being made available to <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>’s
                        subscribers for $425, including shipping. Send orders to V&amp;A
                        Masterprints, 48 South Molton Street, London W1Y2JU; telephone 071-499-5582;
                        fax 071-491-9985.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-35" n="35"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake<hi rend="i">’s Subscription Rates Rise</hi></title>
          </head>
          <p>Due to the rising production and postage costs, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> is
                        raising its subscription rates. For individuals, the rate increase begins
                        with volume 26, 1992-93. Institution rates will rise for volume 27, 1993-94.
                        The new rates are as follows: <table rows="4" cols="2"><row><cell>Individuals:</cell><cell>$25/year</cell></row><row><cell>Institutions:</cell><cell>$50/year</cell></row><row><cell>Postal surcharges:</cell><cell>Surface: $8</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>Airmail: $18</cell></row></table></p>
          <p>New advertising rates: <table rows="3" cols="2"><row><cell>Half-page ad:</cell><cell>$100</cell></row><row><cell>Full-page ad:</cell><cell>$140</cell></row><row><cell>Inserts:</cell><cell>$125</cell></row></table></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
