<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
	<idno>30.3.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1996/7</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1996/97</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">30.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Hilda Hollis</name>
              <name>Marc Kaplan</name>
              <name>Deborah McCollister</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1996/97"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_30">
    <front>
      <pb id="p30-65-66" n="65-66"/>
        <div1 id="cover">
          <figure n="cover.030.03.bqscan" rend="file">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
                      AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
                      VOLUME 30<lb/>
                      NUMBER 3<lb/>
                      WINTER 1996/97</figTranscr>
          </figure>
        </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="10" cols="2">
          <row>
          	<cell>	
        	  <head>
          		<title>CONTENTS</title>
        	  </head>
        	</cell>
    	  </row>		
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Article</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.3.kaplan"><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and the Origins of Patriarchy</ref><lb/><hi rend="i">by Marc Kaplan</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">68</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Review</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.3.dorrbecker">Veils, Infinity, a Roof, and “One thought” in
                            Contemporary Art: A Note on Four Exhibitions</ref><lb/><hi rend="i">by D. W. Dörrbecker</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">82</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Minute Particulars</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.3.hollis">Seeing Thel as Serpent</ref><lb/><hi rend="i">by Hilda Hollis</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">87</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="30.3.mccollister">The Seduction of Self-Abnegation in <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi></ref><lb/><hi rend="i">by Deborah McCollister</hi></cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">90</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Newsletter</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
            	<ref type="article" issue="30.3.jah"><hi rend="i">Jah Wobble Inspired by Blake</hi></ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="30.3.armand"><hi rend="i">Armand Hammer Museum Exhibition of the Boydell Shakespeare Gallery</hi></ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="30.3.net"><hi rend="i">New Issue of</hi> Romanticism on the Net</ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="30.3.notebook"><hi rend="i">Blake’s Notebook Facsimile Available</hi></ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="30.3.romantic"><hi rend="i">Romantic Circles Web Site</hi></ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="30.3.carolinas"><hi rend="i">Call for Papers: Carolinas Symposium on British Studies</hi></ref>, 
            	<ref type="article" issue="30.3.correction"><hi rend="i">Correction: Blake Archive URL</hi></ref>
            </cell>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="i">95</hi>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p30-67" n="67"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>D. W. Dörrbecker teaches in the department of art history at the
                    University of Trier. He began to publish on Blake in 1975, and his recent
                    efforts include the Blake Trust edition of <hi rend="i">The Continental
                        Prophecies.</hi></p>
        <p>Hilda Hollis is writing her thesis on George Elliot and Mikhail Bakhtin with the
                    support of a SSHRCC Doctoral Fellowship at McMaster University. She has
                    published essays in <hi rend="i">Milton Studies</hi> and <hi rend="i">Various
                        Atwoods</hi>, and has an article forthcoming in <hi rend="i">Victorian
                        Poetry.</hi></p>
        <p>Marc Kaplan teaches at Pepperdine University and Santa Monica College in Los
                    Angeles. Formerly a screenwriter, he authored the script which became the film
                        <hi rend="i">Fast Break</hi> (Columbia Pictures, 1979). A previous article
                    on Blake, “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: The Metaphysics of
                    Gender,” appeared in <hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century Contexts</hi> in
                    1995.</p>
        <p>Deborah McCollister is Professor of English at Dallas Baptist University. Recent
                    publications include articles on Wilde, Bunyan, and Tennyson. A current project
                    is a tour for students and friends to Christian and literary <corr type="emend">sites</corr> in southern
                    England, a happy task which she hopes to repeat every few years.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>EDITORS</title>
        </head>
        <p>EDITORS: Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</p>
        <p>BIBLIOGRAPHER: G. E. Bentley, Jr.</p>
        <p>REVIEW EDITOR: Nelson Hilton</p>
        <p>ASSOCIATE EDITOR FOR GREAT BRITAIN: David Worrall</p>
        <p>PRODUCTION OFFICE: Patricia Neill, Department of English, University of
                    Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627</p>
        <p>MANAGING EDITOR: Patricia Neill<lb/> TELEPHONE 716/275-3820<lb/> FAX
                    716/442-5769<lb/> PRODUCTION OFFICE EMAIL: pnpj@dbv.cc.rochester.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Morris Eaves</hi>, Department of English, University of Rochester,
                    Rochester NY 14627<lb/> Email: meav@dbv.cc.rochester.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Morton D. Paley</hi>, Department of English, University of
                    California, Berkeley CA 94720<lb/> Email: mpaley@uclink4.berkeley.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</hi>, 246 MacPherson Avenue, Toronto, Ontario M4V
                    1A2. The University of Toronto declines to forward mail.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Nelson Hilton</hi>, Department of English, University of Georgia,
                    Athens, GA 30602<lb/> Email: nhilton@uga.cc.uga.edu</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">David Worrall</hi>, St. Mary’s College, Strawberry Hill,
                    Waldegrave Road, Twickenham TW1 4SX England<lb/> Email:
                    worralld@maiInt.smuc.ac.UK</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>INFORMATION</title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="i">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY</hi> is published under the
                    sponsorship of the Department of English, University of Rochester.</p>
        <p>SUBSCRIPTIONS are $50 for institutions, $25 for individuals. All subscriptions
                    are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue.
                    Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be applied to the 4
                    issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and Mexico)
                    require an $8 per volume postal surcharge for surface, an $18 per volume
                    surcharge for air mail delivery. U.S. currency or international money order
                    necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications
                    to Patricia Neill, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of
                    Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627.</p>
        <p>BACK ISSUES are available at a reduced price. Address Patricia Neill for a list
                    of issues and prices.</p>
        <p>MANUSCRIPTS are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to forms
                    suggested in <hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, to either of the editors:
                    Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627;
                    Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA
                    94720.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL STANDARD SERIAL NUMBER: 0160-628x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is indexed in the Modern Language
                    Association’s International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research
                    Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography</hi>
                    (ed. David V. Erdman et al.), American Humanities Index, Arts and Humanities
                    Citation Index, Current Contents and the <hi rend="i">Bibliography of the
                        History of Art.</hi></p>
        <p>Cover illustration: Verena Immenhauser, “Untitled,” a figural
                    veil/a veiled figure, executed in preparation of the installation shown at
                    Berne, Switz. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1996 Copyright
                        Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <pb id="p30-68" n="68"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and the Origins of Patriarchy</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Marc <name>Kaplan</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>“O Albion why wilt thou Create a Female Will?” Los wails in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 30:31.<ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> The term
                    “Female Will” here makes its first appearance in Blake’s
                    poetry, though for years critics have used it retroactively to explicate prior
                    works, because it ties together so many of the sinister actions of the women
                    characters of the earlier poetry.<ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Critics
                    who elaborate on Blake’s notion of the Female Will usually make the case
                    that Blake does not intend a criticism of actual women by the term, but rather
                    of nature and Natural Religion, or else that his criticism is not of
                    woman’s empowerment but of the perverse exercise of that power. On the
                    other hand, feminist readings like those of Susan Fox and Anne K. Mellor have
                    pointed out that Blake seems uneasy about <hi rend="i">any</hi> display of
                    willfulness on the part of the female, and that he almost invariably portrays
                    such situations negatively, while simultaneously idealizing female
                    self-sacrifice as embodied in characters like Ahania and Oothoon.<ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is no exception to this latter rule. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> David V. Erdman and Harold Bloom, eds., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> (New York:
                        Doubleday, 1988) 176. Subsequent references to this text will be designated
                        by <hi rend="i">E</hi> followed by the page number. Plate and line numbers
                        will accompany the page numbers where appropriate.</note><note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Lengthy critical works on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are few, probably due to the difficulty of the poem,
                        which presumes a thorough familiarity with Blake’s earlier poetry.
                        Most studies remain at the level of establishing the epic’s coherence
                        and making it scrutable. Such works include Morton D. Paley’s <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1983), Minna
                        Doskow’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Jerusalem</hi> (East
                        Brunswick, N.J.: Associated University Presses, 1982), Joseph
                        Wicksteed’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Jerusalem</hi>
                        (London: Trianon Press, 1953), a work that has been criticized for its
                        eccentric and erroneous interpretations, and Joanna Witke’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Epic: Imagination Unbound</hi> (London:
                        Croom Helm, 1986). Works dealing with gender in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        include Thomas D. Frosch’s <hi rend="i">The Awakening of Albion</hi>
                        (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1974), discussed in the text, and Brenda
                        Webster’s <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology</hi>
                        (Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1983). Webster contends: “The
                        chief psychological problem posed by the poem is how to reconcile the
                        father, Albion, with the son, Los. The difficulty is their mutual suspicion
                        and hatred, which are linked for their desire for exclusive possession of
                        the mother, Jerusalem.” As the argument of this chapter indicates, I
                        agree with Webster that the poem’s central struggle is that of son
                        against patriarch and patriarchy, but disagree with her implication that
                        Blake is unconscious of his poem’s theme.</note><note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Susan Fox, “The Female as Metaphor in
                        William Blake’s Poetry,” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 3
                        (1977): 508-13, and Anne K. Mellor in “Blake’s Portrayal of
                        Women,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16 (1982-83): 148-55, advance the
                        basic propositions involving Blake’s sexism around which subsequent
                        debate has revolved. Alicia Ostriker in “Desire Gratified and
                        Ungratified: William Blake and Sexuality,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16
                        (1982-83): 156-65, concurs with Fox and Mellor that in Blake’s ideal
                        universe “to be female is to be dependent” (162) and notes
                        that “In <hi rend="i">Milton and Jerusalem</hi> . . . female figures
                        are either powerful or good; never both” (162-63). Other works which
                        deal with Blake’s sexual politics include Webster, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology</hi> (see above) and her article,
                        “Blake, Women and Sexuality” in Donald Ault, Mark Bracher and
                        Dan Miller, eds., <hi rend="i">Critical Paths: Blake and the Argument of
                            Method</hi> (Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press, 1987): 204-24;
                        Margaret Storch, <hi rend="i">Sons and Adversaries: Women in Blake and D.H.
                            Lawrence</hi> (Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 1991); and
                        Diana Hume George, <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell
                        University Press, 1980). Webster, Storch and George constitute a wing of
                        Blake criticism that is both Freudian and at times feminist as well, but
                        George, ostensibly using the same Freudian paradigms and often looking at
                        the same poems as Storch and Webster, comes to an almost opposite judgment
                        of Blake. Both Webster and George see Blake’s views as similar to
                        those of Freudian radicals like Norman O. Brown, but whereas George
                        champions Brown’s and Blake’s revolutionary sexual ethos,
                        Webster finds such strategies dangerous and regressive, and Storch, after
                        Webster, has a similar view. David Punter, “Blake, Trauma and the
                        Female,” <hi rend="i">New Literary History</hi> 15 (1984): 475-90,
                        suggests that the trauma of Oothoon in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
                            of Albion</hi> is really the projected displacement of the trauma felt
                        by Blake and males in general at a time when gender roles were in flux.
                        Nelson Hilton in “An Original Story” in <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality</hi>, Hilton and Thomas
                        Vogler, eds., (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1986) 69-104,
                        provides one of the most interesting recent defenses of Blake and <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, making the argument that Blake’s eye (his
                        text) saw more than his heart knew—a familiar poststructuralist
                        strategy, but Hilton’s knowledge of the background material on Mary
                        Wollstonecraft (see n15) helps him fashion a convincing case.</note></p>
        <p>There is more to the above statement of Los than the sexism that might
                    immediately meet the eye, however. Los clearly implies that the evil Female Will
                    is the creation of Albion, the fallen patriarch of British civilization, and not
                    something brought about by woman herself. Los later reiterates, “O Albion
                    why didst thou a Female Will Create?” (56:43, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 206). A
                    close scrutiny of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> reveals, I believe, that Blake
                    offers a perceptive critique of masculine gender-roles without a similar
                    rethinking of the role of the female.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> criticizes male power as it is embodied in the
                    structures of a society specifically identified by the poet as <hi rend="i">patriarchal.</hi> This term has for Blake many of the same pejorative
                    connotations as it does for contemporary feminist discourse: in both instances,
                    “patriarchal” connotes an oppressive masculinist system that
                    perpetuates itself through the definition and control of <hi rend="i">property.</hi></p>
        <p>The word “patriarch” and other terms derived from it appear but a
                    single time in Blake’s work prior to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, an
                    incidental reference in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> to “a throne
                    &amp; a pavement / Of precious stones surrounded by twenty four venerable
                    patriarchs” (123:35, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 393). In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, however, Blake uses the terms eight times, each time in a
                    highly significant context. It first appears in the prose section “To the
                    Jews” that precedes chapter 2 (27, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 171): “Was
                    Britain the Primitive Seat of the Patriarchal Religion?” Blake here <pb id="p30-69" n="69"/> means Patriarchal Religion to be taken in a double
                    sense: as referring both to the eternal truths of the Judeo-Christian culture
                    and to the degenerated Natural Religion which is the actual practice of that
                    same culture. It becomes clear that Blake identifies the patriarchal element in
                    that heritage with its fallen or erroneous aspect when he links patriarchy to
                    Druidism a few lines later: “Your Ancestors derived their origin from
                    Abraham, Heber, Shem, and Noah, who were Druids: as the Druid Temples (which are
                    the Patriarchal Pillars &amp; Oak Groves) over the whole Earth witness to this
                    day” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 171). Druidism is the prehistoric form of
                    Natural Religion; in one quatrain of the poem that follows the prose on plate
                    27, Blake addresses the “Spectre of Albion”: <q> Is this thy soft
                        Family-Love<lb/> Thy cruel Patriarchal pride<lb/> Planting thy Family
                        alone<lb/> Destroying all the World beside.<lb/> (27:76-80, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 173) </q></p>
        <p>The criticism of patriarchy enters <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> proper further on
                    in chapter 2, when the twelve sons of Albion corroborate their father’s
                    fall by “Rearing their Druid Patriarchal rocky Temples around his
                    limbs” (46:14, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 196). Later, Jerusalem hears the
                    Divine Voice asking “Wilt thou make Rome thy Patriarch Druid”
                    (61:50, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 212). Jerusalem subsequently laments the death of
                    her beloved “Along the Valley of Destruction, among these Druid Temples /
                    Which overspread all the Earth in patriarchal pomp &amp; cruel pride”
                    (79:66-67, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 235). Urthona, the Eternal form of Los,
                    characterizes himself as acting “Against the Patriarchal pomp and
                    cruelty, labouring incessant” (83:4, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 241). Finally,
                    in the apocalyptic burst of song that concludes the work, the poet exultantly
                    asks “Where is the Tree of Good &amp; Evil that rooted beneath the cruel
                    heel / of Albions Spectre the Patriarch Druid!” (98:47-48, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 258). The return of humankind to the unfallen state is clearly
                    linked to the abolition of patriarchy.</p>
        <p>Blake does not stop at mere condemnation of patriarchy; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> contains the poet’s most sophisticated analysis of
                    institutionalized masculinism. The critique of conventional masculine roles and
                    authority figures is a consistent theme in Blake’s poetry from early on.
                    Helen Bruder, in “The Sins of the Fathers: Patriarchal Criticism and <hi rend="i">The Book Of Thel</hi>,”<ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
                    finds Blake already engaged in a critique of patriarchy in <hi rend="i">The Book
                        of Thel</hi>, one of the first illuminated books, in which she describes the
                    poet as “exclaiming against the patriarchal fetishizing of the hymen as
                    an oppressive curb to an erotics of mutual delight” (156). She likewise
                    finds the poet preaching against phallocentrism in the creation of a
                    “young woman (Thel) who is so unimpressed by . . . displays of the
                    phallus” (156). The anti-phallocentrism, the attack on conventional (that
                    is, Urizenic) masculinity, and the repudiation of repression and virginity are
                    indeed constant preoccupations of Blake’s writing and art. But Bruder is
                    in error to say that the presentation of these themes in themselves constitutes
                    “a neglected feminist dimension to Blake’s long-acknowledged
                    radicalism” (147). A critique of masculinity is not per se a critique of
                    gender, and an insistence on woman’s sexual freedom is not necessarily a
                    feminist position when that erotic freedom is, as it is so often in
                    Blake’s myth, the only new freedom that the poet will allow his female
                        characters.<ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is perhaps the most dramatic example of the true
                    character of Blake’s sexual politics: never has the poet’s
                    condemnation of traditional masculine authority in the form of patriarchy been
                    more overt and forceful, yet Blake’s solution to the problem in no way
                    presumes an increase in female empowerment. <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
                        Helen Bruder, in <hi rend="i">Historicizing Blake</hi>, Steve Clark and
                        David Worrall, eds. (New York: St. Martin’s, 1994) 147-59.</note><note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Nor am I convinced by Bruder’s attempts
                        to establish a counter-tradition of Blake criticism that vindicates the
                        poet’s radical feminism. The authors she cites, like Bruder herself,
                        make a case for Blake as an opponent of phallocentrism and a champion of
                        woman’s sexual freedom, but not a case for the poet as an advocate of
                        genuine female empowerment. Vernon E. Lattin, in “Blake’s Thel
                        and Oothoon: Sexual Awakening in the Eighteenth Century” in <hi rend="i">The Literary Criterion</hi> 16 (1981): 11-24, notes the way
                        “Blake speaks very clearly about the centrality of woman’s
                        sexual awakening as the way of vision” (12) and finds Oothoon, unlike
                        Thel, gaining liberation “by confronting her desire” (22);
                        Lattin doesn’t consider the extent to which female sexual license
                        benefits male power structures. K. D. Everest, in “Thel’s
                        Dilemma” in <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 37 (1987): 193-208,
                        similarly describes the way “nominal virtue in Thel is gradually
                        subverted by an insurgent sexuality of superb energy and abandonment”
                        (206). Catherine L. McClenahan, in “‘No Face Like the Human
                        Divine?’: Women and Gender in Pickering Manuscript,” in G. A.
                        Rosso and Daniel P. Watkins, eds., <hi rend="i">Spirits of Fire: English
                            Romantic Writers and Contemporary Historical Methods</hi> (London:
                        Associated University Presses, 1990) 189-208, demonstrates how Blake shares
                        Wollstonecraft’s critique of sexual modesty, but fails to note that
                        the rationality that Blake so dislikes is the fundamental principle of
                        Wollstonecraftian feminism. Another of McClenahan’s arguments, that
                        Blake learned subversive techniques and voices from marginalized woman
                        writers, sounds suspiciously like the exploitative appropriation of feminine
                        characteristics that Alan Richardson has termed a
                        “colonization” of the feminine and found to be typical of male
                        romantic writers as a group (see n17). David G. Reide, in “The
                        Symbolism of the Loins in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” in <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi>
                        21 (1981): 547-64, convincingly shows how the poem rates Blake’s
                        contempt for “mere genital sexuality” (549), and Elizabeth
                        Langland in “Blake’s Feminist Revision of Literary Tradition
                        in ‘The Sick Rose’” in Donald Ault, Mark Bracher and
                        Dan Miller, eds., <hi rend="i">Critical Paths: Blake and the Argument of
                            Method</hi> (Durham, NC and London: Duke Univ. Press, 1987) 225-43,
                        demonstrates how that poem’s ironic language exposes the
                        speaker’s violation of the rose by phallic psychological projections;
                        as noted in the text however, anti-phallocentrism does not automatically
                        constitute feminism.</note></p>
        <p>The critique of patriarchy advanced by Blake in his final epic is, however, in
                    many ways strikingly similar to the argument of feminist historian Gerda Lerner
                    in her contemporary <pb id="p30-70" n="70"/> study, <hi rend="i">The Creation of
                        Patriarchy.</hi><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Lerner maintains that
                    the control by males of women’s sexual behavior and reproductive capacity
                    is the very cornerstone of our civilization. She contends that this
                    appropriation occurred prior to the institution of private property, and in fact
                    was the very foundation of private property (in Western history, Lerner locates
                    this event during the period of the early Sumerian and Mesopotamian
                    civilizations, 2200-1800 B.C.). Later, male subjugation of woman’s
                    sexuality resulted in class structure, and finally in slavery, the ultimate
                    commodification of the human (well underway by the time of the Babylonian Code
                    of Hammurabi, 1752 B.C.). According to Lerner, men in the earliest societies
                    were divided into classes relative to the amount of
                    “wealth”—potentially fertile women - over whom they had
                    hegemony. In this same historical period, men divided all women into two groups,
                    one “respectable” or “honorable,” meaning under the
                    protection of a male, and the other “not respectable,” meaning
                    unattached to a male. The two kinds of women were frequently distinguished by
                    the presence or absence of a veil, the wearing of which denoted the
                    “good” woman and also marked this “honorable” woman
                    as an article of property, which accounts for her protected status.
                    Male-dominated society moved toward an increasingly abstract and increasingly
                    masculine idea of God, culminating finally in the invisible-but-male Hebrew
                    deity, who ordains that the expression of woman’s sexuality for other
                    than reproductive purposes is sinful (Lerner places the beginning of the writing
                    of the Book of Genesis in the tenth century B.C., but believes the stories
                    within it to be parts of an oral myth several centuries older). <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Gerda Lerner, <hi rend="i">The Creation of
                            Patriarchy</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1986), 8-10. The
                        pages indicated present a summary of Lerner’s argument and indicate
                        chapters in which points are elaborated further.</note></p>
        <p>Lerner’s theory is frankly, admittedly, speculative. Her work has drawn
                    criticism for what has been deemed a too-willful projection of contemporary
                    feminist polemic onto a body of inconclusive (and inadequately researched)
                    empirical evidence.<ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> However damaging such
                    criticism may be to Lerner’s credibility as a historian, it in no way
                    lessens the value of her work as an instrument for the interpretation of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, for Blake’s poem, avowedly mythic and even
                    anti-empirical in its construction of history, is openly polemical.
                    Blake’s epics retain an engagement with literal history by virtue of the
                    poet’s implicit belief that utopian fantasy, by the suggestion of
                    unrealized human possibilities, can provoke real change in the social/political
                    world (in this respect, the poet’s strategy remains unchanged since the
                        <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>). <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi>
                        Scholar Sarah B. Pomeroy, writing in the <hi rend="i">New York Times Book
                            Review</hi>, 20 April 1986, voices the common concerns of
                        Lerner’s critics when she complains of Lerner’s
                        “subordination of principles of historical investigation to feminist
                        politics.” She objects to Lerner’s construction of “a
                        grandiose paradigm demonstrating the continually deteriorating position of
                        women.” Pomeroy takes Lerner to task for grouping “societies
                        as different as the Sumerians, Babylonians, Assyrians, Amonites, Hebrews and
                        Greeks as though they existed on a historical continuum and evolved from one
                        another,” and she complains that Lerner is led into some crucial
                        misunderstandings because of her dependence on works in translation and
                        secondary sources. In a review in <hi rend="i">History: Reviews of New
                            Books</hi> (Jan.-Feb. 1987 [66-67]), however, it is precisely
                        Lerner’s “intellectual boldness, her bluntness and penchant
                        for polemic” that Bernard Essen praises. Calling her work
                        “vastly ambitious and admirable, even heroic,” Essen goes on
                        to laud Lerner for “her flair for theorizing and generalizing,
                        sometimes outrageously,” which would serve equally well as a
                        description of Blake at his best.</note></p>
        <p>Lerner traces the development of patriarchy in a historical sequence. Blake in
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> displays a remarkable anticipation of the
                    initial stages of Lerner’s model. Blake, like Lerner, locates the
                    beginning of “fallen” history in the patriarchal suppression and
                    control of women’s sexual behavior. He develops a notion implicit in
                    Lerner’s model into a cardinal point of his myth: the destructive
                    dualisms of Western thought, which the poet has been bent on exposing ever since
                        <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, are in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> revealed to be rooted in the primal separation of women into
                    two camps, “good” (chaste) women and whores. The division of
                    females into good women and bad women provoked the development of the moral code
                    that Blake hates, with its radical separation of good and evil, heaven and hell,
                    holy and profane, pure and defiled. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the initial
                    moment of this separation is depicted in Albion’s separation of the
                    “good” woman Vala, who is actually sinister, from the
                    “bad” Jerusalem, whose only sins are her sexual openness and her
                    capacity for self-sacrifice. The veil of Vala is perhaps the poem’s
                    central trope; it becomes in Blake’s hands the symbol of everything that
                    separates humankind from its salvation. In the end, Jerusalem and Vala are
                    rejoined as a “whole” woman, Brittannia.</p>
        <p>The latter stages of Lerner’s model, however, diverge from and even oppose
                    Blake’s vision. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake would replace the
                    patriarchy with a (male) brotherhood bonded by a covenant. The covenant of
                    brothers is indeed a part of Lerner’s structure, but for her it
                    represents not the overthrow of patriarchy, but its ultimate consolidation.
                    Blake’s ideal brotherhood, in which women are shared among the brothers,
                    contains all the qualities to which Lerner objects. Further, Blake
                    doesn’t appropriate female procreativity outright, but in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, as in his earlier poetry, he denigrates
                    “merely” natural and biological creation and seeks to subsume it
                    under a “higher” creativity, that of artistic inspiration, a
                    quality which is portrayed as decisively masculine, because it involves the (for
                    Blake) quintessentially masculine ability to organize a “female”
                    and passive perceptual world.</p>
        <p>Lerner’s sequential model of patriarchal history has as its culmination
                    the production of a type of metaphorical construct that in her view has
                    fundamentally distored all Western thought. She describes this body of tropes as
                    configuring “the symbolic devaluing of women in relation to the
                    divine” (10). For Blake in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, this hierarchical
                    relationship <pb id="p30-71" n="71"/> is not considered a metaphor, but rather
                    the principle by which the poet’s mythic universe is organized; it is
                    ultimately the one element in the Blakean cosmos that seems <hi rend="i">not</hi> to be trope, but a categorical imperative. The devaluing of the
                    feminine is everywhere implicit in Blake’s construction of the
                    relationship of masculine self to female Emanation, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> concludes with a vision of a post-apocalyptic world in which
                    this hierarchy of self and Emanation is still firmly in place. Blake’s
                    vision is anti-patriarchal while still being hierarchically masculinist. In
                    contemporary terms, Blake has made gender-as-a-social-construction identical
                    with gender-as-essence. This is precisely the sort of transformation of a
                    metaphor into a fundamental principle of existence which Blake in other
                    situations recognizes immediately as Natural Religion.</p>
        <p>Having struck a tone critical of Blake, let me rush momentarily to his defense.
                    It would be disingenuous to take Blake to task for not meeting the standards of
                    a later era in his treatment of gender, or to suggest that he was in some way
                    worse on the issue than most other writers of the time (in fact, I am going to
                    imply the opposite). To single Blake out for special personal condemnation would
                    indeed undermine any sort of feminist argument predicated upon a belief in the
                    socially-constructed nature of attitudes about gender. The purpose of this essay
                    then, is not to establish Blake’s sexism (that has been done by Fox,
                    Mellor and others) or even to criticize it, so much as to demonstrate what a
                    crucial role the notion of gender-hierarchy plays in the form and functioning of
                    Blake’s visionary cosmos. If it proves impossible in this analysis to
                    suppress an occasional note of late-twentieth-century dismay, it is only because
                    the poet <hi rend="i">does</hi> reject so many of the attitudes of his era that
                    encounters with his sexist formulations, even after repeated readings, are
                    always slightly startling. The fact that gender seems to be an exception to a
                    general rule perhaps tells us less about Blake than about his and our
                    culture.</p>
        <p>However, if gender inequality is accepted as an organizing principle in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, I believe the poem can be rescrutinized to yield up
                    new insights. Blake’s sexism is no less intricately imaged than the other
                    parts of his myth, and his depiction of female characters, while by contemporary
                    standards perhaps less progressive than other parts of his artistic world, is no
                    less powerful. Indeed, I will imply below that, as with Picasso in our own era,
                    these female portraits represent some of the most intensely rendered of
                    Blake’s “Visionary Forms Dramatic” precisely because of the
                    anxiety they inspire in the poet.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>I</title>
          </head>
          <p>The patriarch whose fall and redemption are the subject of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is Albion, Blake’s Universal Man. His fall was
                        also described in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, but there the Zoas
                        themselves (the components of Albion’s unfallen self) took center
                        stage. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the Zoas are relatively minor
                        players, and the focus is on Albion himself, his sons and daughters, and
                        Jerusalem, “the Emanation of the Giant Albion,” as the
                        poem’s title informs us. The first half of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> deals with Albion’s fall into “Eternal
                        Death.” One of the most important models for the story of
                        Albion’s fall is the Book of Job, which Blake in fact illustrated
                        near the end of his life. Like Albion, Job is a patriarch who loses his
                        family and then has it restored to him. S. Foster Damon, in his book on the
                        Job engravings, maintains that Blake’s images interpret the Job story
                        as an internal, psychological drama: Job doesn’t lose his children to
                        physical catastrophe, rather he loses their affection and respect due to his
                        self-righteous morality.<ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> operates on a similarly psychological level:
                        when Albion’s Spectre and Emanation come to the Divine Humanity
                        saying “We alone are escaped” (43:29, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                        191), a direct reference to Job 1:15, they are not fleeing a massacre (as in
                        the Bible story), but rather from Albion’s own darkened psyche and
                        the fallen world it generates around itself, “Albions darkning
                        [r]ocks” (43:28, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 191). For Blake, as always,
                        psychology constitutes geography. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> S.
                            Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> (Providence: Brown
                            University Press, 1966) 3. This has become the generally accepted
                            interpretation of the Job engravings. The Job series is also linked to
                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> by the “Druid” trilithons
                            (Blakean symbols of Natural Religion) that appear in both sets of
                            illustrations.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> begins with the fall of Albion already in
                        progress. The Divine Vision calls out: <q> return Albion! return!<lb/> Thy
                            brethren call thee, and thy fathers, and thy sons,<lb/> Thy nurses, and
                            thy mothers, thy sisters and thy daughters<lb/> Weep at thy souls
                            disease, and the Divine Vision is darkend:<lb/> (4:10-13, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 146) </q> Albion, like Job, has lost his family and been
                        afflicted with disease. The problem, ironically, is patriarchy: in seeking
                        to hold and protect his family, Albion has in fact lost them spiritually,
                        because of his tyrannical possessiveness. Albion’s specific error is
                        to hide his Emanation from the Divine Humanity—that is, to restrict
                        her sexual favors to him alone, the act which Lerner theorized was the
                        crucial first move in the creation of patriarchy (the Emanation in this poem
                        has characteristics of both a wife and a daughter). With this event,
                        jealousy comes into the world: “So spoke Albion in jealous fears,
                        hiding his Emanation” (4:33, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 147).</p>
          <p>So <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> begins <hi rend="i">in medias res</hi>, as
                        does a classical epic. The fall of Albion will be recapitulated throughout
                        the poem. In asserting patriarchal control, Albion has lost control; his
                        sons, the products of patriarchy, now control England while Albion lies
                        helpless in a dream of Eternal Death. The illustration at the bottom of
                        plate 9 shows the fallen Albion prostrate on the ground.<ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> As Erdman notes, however, Albion’s <pb id="p30-72" n="72"/> eyes are open, leading us to believe that his
                        stupor is self-willed. The next plate depicts the fallen rule of
                        Albion’s sons, who are characterized by Morton Paley as “the
                        objects of [Albion’s] aggression disguised as justice”<ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>: <q> And this is the manner of the
                            Sons of Albion in their strength<lb/> They take the Two Contraries which
                            are calld Qualities, with which<lb/> Every Substance is clothed, they
                            name them Good &amp; Evil<lb/> From them they make an Abstract, which
                            is a Negation<lb/> (10:7-10, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 152-53) </q><note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The reference is to Copy D, as reproduced
                            in David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden
                            City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1974) 288. All plate numbers refer to the <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> reproduction. In other copies, Blake
                            changed the order of some of the plates in chapter 2. The order in the
                            reproduction in <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> corresponds to the
                            order in <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi></note><note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">The
                                Continuing City</hi> 221.</note></p>
          <p>The separation of the “good” from the “evil”
                        woman (in Lerner’s terms, the veiled is opposed to the unveiled
                        woman; in Blake’s terms, Vala—her name, of course, punning on
                        “veil”—is separated from Jerusalem) has led to a moral
                        code of good and evil that becomes increasingly abstract, and which
                        characterizes everything regarding the body as sinful. Vala and Jerusalem,
                        body and spirit, are properly dynamic contraries; the Sons have separated
                        them into negating opposites. These historical developments find their
                        culmination in a god who is male and totally abstract/transcendent. The
                        transformation of the patriarch into an abstract father-god means that
                        patriarchy can live on even though the patriarch himself (or an overtly
                        patriarchal religion) may appear to be dead, like the paralyzed Albion.
                        Patriarchy continues to operate, reproducing itself with mechanical
                        persistence: this is one significance of the turning of the “Starry
                        Wheels,” the activity of Albion’s Sons. The Twelve Sons form
                        themselves into “Three Immense Wheels” (18:8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163), because they are “Jealous of Jerusalems
                        children” (18:6, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163), and covetous of their
                        heritage as Albion’s lawful sons by Vala.</p>
          <p>The Sons want Jerusalem to be cast out because, in the words of Harold Bloom,
                        “if she is reunited to man, their reign ends” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 934): <q> Cast! Cast ye Jerusalem forth! The Shadow of
                            delusions!<lb/> The Harlot daughter! Mother of pity and dishonourable
                            forgiveness<lb/> Our Father Albions sin and shame!<lb/> (18:11-13, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163) </q> The Sons complain that their father has
                        destroyed the patriarchal family by his indiscretions with Jerusalem. With
                        their cry for punishment, they think they are redressing their
                        father’s crimes; in fact, they are repeating them, because it was
                        Albion who first declared Jerusalem sinful. In this ironic way, the sins of
                        the fathers are visited on the children, and patriarchy replicates itself
                        though the cycle of guilt and repression. The Sons pledge allegiance to: <q>
                            Babylon the City of Vala, the Goddess Virgin-Mother.<lb/> She is our
                            Mother! Nature! Jerusalem is our Harlot-Sister<lb/> Return’d with
                            Children of pollution, to defile our House,<lb/> With Sin and
                            Shame.<lb/> (18:29-32, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163) </q> Vala and Jerusalem
                        were originally one, in the form of Brittannia. In casting Jerusalem out,
                        the Sons are only furthering the initial act of Albion, who separated the
                        two and covered Vala with the veil of patriarchal property.</p>
          <p>This issue of property underlies Albion’s plight: <q> His Children
                            exil’d from his breast pass to and fro before him<lb/> His birds
                            are silent on his hills, flocks die beneath his branches<lb/> His tents
                            are fall’n! his trumpets, and the sweet sound of his harp<lb/>
                            Are silent on his clouded hills, that belch forth storms &amp;
                            fire.<lb/> His milk of Cows, &amp; honey of Bees, &amp; fruit of
                            golden harvest,<lb/> Is gather’d in the scorching heat, &amp; in
                            the driving rain:<lb/> (19:1-6, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 163-64) </q></p>
          <p>Albion’s loss is here, as in Blake’s Job illustrations, both
                        internal and external. Albion’s wealth is at once the true riches of
                        the realized spirit and senses, and the material, projected forms in which
                        the patriarch tries unsuccessfully to capture and hold those riches. The act
                        of projection is in itself a loss: in creating wealth, Albion in fact loses
                        it. His loss becomes a loss of riches as well as family (Albion’s
                        children are similarly both the disowned parts of himself and the real
                        children whom he alienates by that act of disowning). Blake here anticipates
                        Lerner’s view that all wealth comes not from labor, as in Marx, but
                        from male control of woman’s sexuality, the act which for Lerner is
                        the very origin of private property. The same imagery of loss of wealth
                        pervades Albion’s own description of his situation: <q> Shame divides
                            Families. Shame hath divided Albion in sunder!<lb/> First fled my Sons,
                            &amp; then my Daughters, then my Wild Animations<lb/> My Cattle next,
                            last ev’n the Dog of my Gate. the Forests fled<lb/> The
                            Corn-fields, &amp; the breathing Gardens outside separated<lb/>
                            (21:6-9, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 166) </q></p>
          <pb id="p30-73" n="73"/>
          <p>Albion’s complaint, earlier in the same lament, that “The
                        disease of Shame covers me from head to feet: I have no hope / Every boil on
                        my body is a separate &amp; deadly Sin” (21:3-4, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                        166), again links him to Job, who was likewise afflicted with boils. The
                        boils of Blake’s Albion/Job are really an inner “disease of
                        Shame”; the loss of his children is not their physical death but the
                        loss of their love and respect, and the loss of wealth and property is not
                        only a material loss but, as noted above, the loss of the full realization
                        of the spirit and of the senses in all their abundance. These losses come to
                        pass as a result of Albion’s desire to control the sexuality and
                        fertility of woman. Albion now has control over woman, but has lost the
                        capacity for sexual joy because sin and guilt are the vehicle of that
                        control. He mourns “Vala! O that thou wert pure! / That the deep
                        wound of Sin might be clos’d up with the Needle” (21:12-13,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 166), but it was he himself who made the vagina
                        sinful when he made it the source of wealth. Albion eventually comes to look
                        back nostalgically on a time when “Albion coverd the whole
                        Earth” (24:44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 170) because woman’s
                        sexuality had not been divided and apportioned.</p>
          <p>As Paley points out, Albion in Jerusalem “takes on many of the
                        characteristics assigned to Urizen-figures in Blake’s earlier
                            works.”<ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> A plea by Jerusalem
                        makes it clear that Albion has both Urizen’s sense of sin and his
                        capacity for reductive over-analysis: <q> Then spoke Jerusalem O Albion! my
                            Father Albion<lb/> Why wilt thou number every little fibre of my
                            Soul<lb/> Spreading them out before the Sun like stalks of flax to
                            dry?<lb/> The Infant Joy is beautiful, but its anatomy<lb/> Horrible
                            ghast &amp; deadly!<lb/> (22:19-23, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 167) </q> Blake
                        has actually made two significant switches here: not only has Albion been
                        described in Urizenic terms, but Jerusalem speaks the same words with which
                        Tharmas accuses Enion in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> 4:29-33 (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 302). There, the (male) Tharmas complained of
                        Enion’s (female) jealousy. Blake’s transfer of the speech to
                        the female Jerusalem makes clear the paranoia behind Tharmas’s
                        declaration in the earlier poem: his need to dominate, rather than
                        woman’s jealousy, is the ultimate source of sexual guilt. <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Paley 198.</note></p>
          <p>As with Urizen in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, the masculine triumph of
                        Albion is actually a triumph of Vala. Albion pleads: <q> But come O Vala
                            with knife &amp; cup: drain my blood<lb/> To the last drop! then hide
                            me in thy Scarlet Tabernacle<lb/> For I see Luvah whom I slew. I behold
                            him in my Spectre<lb/> (22:29-31, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 167-68) </q> He
                        has accepted the veil of Vala, which he himself imposed, as a final reality,
                        and he is afflicted with an unbearable sense of guilt because his
                        institution of sin has “slain” humankind’s passional
                        life. Albion can think of no remedy but to elevate Vala into a
                        virgin-goddess and to offer himself as a human sacrifice. In terms of
                        Lerner’s historical model, Albion here is at the stage where
                        patriarchy institutionalizes and encourages the worship of the
                        mother-goddess; Babylon was such a civilization. Whereas Lerner sees the
                        religion of the goddess as having both positive and negative aspects (the
                        goddess is a powerful female, but her power is restricted to sexuality and
                        fertility), Blake can see any goddess-worship only as a form of Natural
                        Religion, demanding human sacrifice.</p>
          <p>In order to replace this constant blood-sacrifice, Albion takes Vala’s
                        veil and uses it as a “Veil of Moral Virtue, woven for Cruel
                        Laws” (23:22, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 168). This corresponds to a stage
                        in Lerner’s model where the religion of the goddess is suppressed and
                        supplanted by the moral religion of the abstract and invisible father-god.
                        This has the advantage for Albion of changing his position from that of
                        accused to that of accuser: “every Act a Crime, and Albion the
                        punisher &amp; judge” (28:4, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 174). He can now
                        condemn his offspring instead of vice versa: the patriarch has resumed his
                        position of authority. The Cities of England make a last effort to redeem
                        him, asking <q> What is a Wife &amp; what is a Harlot? What is a Church?
                            &amp; What<lb/> Is a Theatre? Are they Two &amp; not One? can they
                            Exist Separate?<lb/> Are not Religion &amp; Politics the Same Thing?
                            Brotherhood is Religion<lb/> O Demonstrations of Reason Dividing
                            Families in Cruelty &amp; Pride!<lb/> (57:8-11, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                            207) </q></p>
          <p>The separation of “Wife” from “Harlot,” in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and in Lerner’s model, is the source, the
                        first separation from which other divisions spring. The patriarchal family
                        is broken by this same chain of separations, but however broken, divided,
                        “dysfunctional” in the current parlance, the patriarchal
                        family still perpetuates itself through the mechanistic power of guilt.
                        Albion, his fall complete, sinks down to the Rock of Ages, where he remains
                        until the apocalypse.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>II</title>
          </head>
          <p>Jerusalem and Vala represent Blake’s most sophisticated development of
                        positive and negative female figures, yet a problem inherent in this
                        dichotomy from its first appearance in the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
                            and of Experience</hi> remains: to use Paley’s words,
                        “Blake’s ranging of female figures along the lines of the
                        Jerusalem-principle and the Vala-principle <pb id="p30-74" n="74"/>
                        threatens to become congruent with the old cultural bifurcation” that
                        Blake ostensibly wants to protest.<ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
                        Almost all the women in the poem are subsumed as “surrogates”
                        (Paley’s term) of Jerusalem or Vala. As surrogates of Jerusalem,
                        Paley lists Erin, Dinah, Rosamund, Oothoon and Mary, each of whom represents
                        “an aspect of redemption through female love.”<ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Vala’s camp includes Rahab and
                        Tirzah, familiar from the earlier poetry, and the malevolent Daughters of
                        Albion, chief among them Cambel and Gwendolen (the one important female
                        figure not connected to either Jerusalem or Vala is Enitharmon, about whom
                        more later). In <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Blake was
                        intent upon questioning the validity of oppositional thinking altogether
                        (“Excess of sorrow laughs. Excess of joy weeps” [8:26, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 36]). The opposition of the two groups of women is a
                        similarly false dualism, created by the deluded Albion. However,
                        Blake’s presentation of the inversion of the dualism as an
                        apocalyptic revelation—Jerusalem, the bad woman is really good; the
                        chaste Vala is really evil—has the effect of making the opposition
                        seem authoritative, with only the specific terms of the dichotomy brought
                        into question. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Paley 194.</note><note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Paley 185.</note></p>
          <p>In dividing Jerusalem from Vala, Albion invents sin and accuses Jerusalem of
                        its commission: <q> Jerusalem! dissembler Jerusalem! I look into thy
                            bossom:<lb/> I discover thy secret places: Cordella! I behold<lb/> Thee
                            whom I thought pure as the heavens in innocence &amp; fear:<lb/>
                            (21:18-20, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 166) </q> The echoes of Lear and Cordelia
                        are appropriate (one of the Daughters of Albion is named Ragan as well):
                        Lear was another mistaken patriarch involved in the division of property and
                        the desire to possess <hi rend="i">all</hi> of his daughters’ love.
                        Vala is the real dissembler and hider of secrets; her secret is that the
                        patriarchal division of women into virgins and whores is a deception. Albion
                        accedes to the demands of Vala and his sons and daughters and casts
                        Jerusalem out. Los later encounters her as he wanders the night streets of
                        London, the domain of the impoverished (45:39-43, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 195).
                        This is Jerusalem’s appropriate place, because in casting out
                        Jerusalem, Albion created private property and social classes (as in
                        Lerner’s theory), dividing rich and poor.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> here links the division of women into two camps
                        with the division of humanity into impoverished and wealthy classes. Vala
                        wears the veil which is an ancient signifier of both the married woman and
                        the priestess or nun (often spoken of as being married to the deity).<ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> The veil denotes that the woman is
                        property, an item of wealth, but as such she is also under the protection of
                        patriarchal power in either its secular or ecclesiastical form, and
                        therefore enjoys certain privileges. The unveiled woman has no protector, no
                        connection with wealth and consequently no status. Jerusalem therefore
                        dwells among the wretched, where the Daughters of Los are building
                        Golgonooza in the midst of the squalor of the fallen city of London: <q>
                            Terrible their distress &amp; their sorrow cannot be utterd<lb/> And
                            another Daughter of Los sat at the Spinning Wheel<lb/> Endless their
                            labour, with bitter food. void of sleep,<lb/> Tho hungry they labour:
                            they rouze themselves anxious<lb/> Hour after hour labouring at the
                            whirling Wheel<lb/> Many Wheels &amp; as many lovely Daughters sit
                            weeping<lb/> (59:28-33, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 209) </q><note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> David G. Riede, “The Symbolism of
                            the Loins in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” (see n5)
                            links the veil to the physical hymen “and . . . its simultaneous
                            meaning as the cover of mystery” (553). The veil of the wife or
                            the nun is a kind of permanent hymen, which signifies the control and
                            protection of the woman’s sexuality by patriarchal institutions.
                            “Once the veil is torn, the loins lose their all-obsessing
                            importance,” Riede goes on to say (557), describing
                            Blake’s apocalypse as a deliverance from the tyranny of
                            genitality. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake establishes the
                            connection between this fallen genitality and the obsession with
                            material wealth.</note></p>
          <p>The Daughters weave to re-form the ancient work of Vala, who wove the veil of
                        fallen nature. The spinning wheels they turn indicate the source of their
                        suffering in the Starry Wheels of patriarchal Deism turned by
                        Albion’s Sons. Never before, except perhaps in
                        “London,” has Blake so clearly based his portrayal on real
                        scenes of the exploitation of women in the London of his day. The Divine
                        Voice searches for Jerusalem and finds her <q> closd in the Dungeons of
                            Babylon<lb/> Her Form was held by Beulahs Daughters. but all within
                            unseen<lb/> She sat at the Mills, her hair unbound her feet naked<lb/>
                            Cut with the flints: her tears run down, her reason grows like<lb/> The
                            Wheel of Hand. incessant turning day &amp; night without rest<lb/>
                            (60:39-43, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 210) </q></p>
          <p>This is the fate of women without a “veil,” without the
                        protection of a male.</p>
          <p>Jerusalem dwells here because the oppressed necessarily know the reality of
                        the spirit, the spirit being all they have because their physical life is
                        bondage. Yet the suffering can become so intense that even the consolations
                        of the spirit are lost: “Insane she raves upon the winds hoarse,
                        inarticulate” (60:44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 210). In despair, Jerusalem
                        questions the existence of God, the “Human Imagination”
                        (60:57, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 211). To comfort her, the Divine Voice tells her
                        Blake’s revisionist version of the story of Joseph and Mary, in which
                        Mary <pb id="p30-75" n="75"/> has been impregnated not by God but simply by
                        a man other than her husband. Joseph at first throws her out as a harlot,
                        but he hears the Divine Voice in a dream and realizes he must forgive Mary
                        and take her back. Jerusalem realizes her essential humanity is still
                        unsullied within her and takes heart: “Every Harlot was once a
                        Virgin: every Criminal an Infant Love!” (61:52, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                        212).</p>
          <p>Blake has affirmed woman’s right to a sexual freedom commensurate with
                        that of man; but more importantly, Joseph has not only forgiven Mary, but
                        renounced as well the fundamental privilege of all patriarchy: he has
                        accepted as his own offspring the impending child of his wife by another
                        man. Mary’s song of freedom is a chant of female sexuality unleashed:
                            <q> Then Mary burst forth into a Song! she flowed like a River of<lb/>
                            Many Streams in the arms of Joseph &amp; gave forth her tears of
                            joy<lb/> Like many waters, and Emanating into gardens &amp; palaces
                            upon<lb/> Euphrates &amp; to forests &amp; floods &amp; animals wild
                            &amp; tame from<lb/> Gihon to Hiddekel, &amp; to corn fields &amp;
                            villages &amp; inhabitants<lb/> (61:28-32, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 212)
                        </q> Blake’s symbolism corroborates Lerner’s view that
                        patriarchal society is founded upon the control of female sexuality: the
                        rushing torrent of Mary’s freed libido in effect reclaims all the
                        institutions and products of the society built upon the repression of that
                        sexual force.</p>
          <p>However, Blake, as much as any patriarch, <hi rend="i">identifies</hi> woman
                        with sexuality, and treats the liberation of that sexuality as
                        woman’s total liberation. Blake envisions a good woman as either an
                        ardent lover or nurturing mother. It is in the form of maternity that Mary
                        offers consolation to Jerusalem: “Jerusalem recieved / The Infant
                        into her hands in the Visions of Jehovah” (61:47-48, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 212). The long lament which is Jerusalem’s last major
                        speech in the poem makes clear her longing for the unfallen state which she
                        experienced as a kind of universal maternity: <q> The Fifty-two Counties of
                            England are hardend against me<lb/> As if I was not their Mother, they
                            despise me &amp; cast me out<lb/> London coverd the whole Earth.
                            England encompassd the Nations:<lb/> And all the Nations of the Earth
                            were seen in the Cities of Albion:<lb/> My pillars reachd from sea to
                            sea: London beheld me come<lb/> From my east &amp; from my west; he
                            blessed me and gave<lb/> His children to my breasts, his sons &amp;
                            daughters to my knees<lb/> (79:20-26, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 234-35) </q></p>
          <p>In this state, the roles of lover and mother were apparently conjoined: <q>
                            the Lamb of God met me there.<lb/> There we walked as in our secret
                            chamber among our little ones<lb/> They looked upon our loves with joy:
                            they beheld our secret joys:<lb/> With holy raptures of adoration<lb/>
                            (79:41-44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 235) </q> Jerusalem in the illustration
                        on plate 46 is depicted as just such an ideal conjunction of lover and
                        mother. There Vala covers herself with the veil of mystery, and would cover
                        the naked beauty of Jerusalem, who stands apart surrounded by three
                        children.</p>
          <p>Unlike Jerusalem, Vala is interested in power. Just as Blake does not imagine
                        a good woman as other than a mother or lover, he likewise seems unable to
                        see a willful female as other than evil. There are no women in Jerusalem who
                        are strong-willed yet positive with which to balance the negativity of Vala
                        and her surrogates. Blake does, however, integrate the malevolence of Vala
                        with his analysis of the evils of patriarchy. Immediately after he separates
                        Vala from Jerusalem, Vala is described as “spreading her scarlet Veil
                        over Albion” (21:50, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 167). She is smart enough to
                        see that the veil that disempowers also empowers; she can turn the
                        patriarchal creation of sin against its author. Vala condemns Albion with
                        his own invention, using the same words Enion spoke to Tharmas in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: “I have looked into the secret Soul
                        of him I loved / And in the dark recesses found Sin &amp; can never
                        return” (22:14-15, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 167).</p>
          <p>Vala celebrates her power in the aggregate form of the Daughters of Albion:
                            <q> She cries: The Human is but a Worm, &amp; thou O Male: Thou
                            art<lb/> Thyself Female, a Male: a breeder of Seed: a Son &amp;
                            Husband: &amp;<lb/> Lo.<lb/> The Human Divine is Womans Shadow, a Vapor
                            in the summers heat<lb/> Go assume Papal dignity thou Spectre, thou Male
                            Harlot!<lb/> Arthur<lb/> Divide into the Kings of Europe in times remote
                            O Woman-born<lb/> And Woman-nourishd &amp; Woman-educated &amp;
                            Woman-scorn’d!<lb/> (64:12-17, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 215) </q> On
                        one level, this speech is an apt and even feminist mockery of the
                        pretensions of patriarchy (“Papal dignity;”
                        “Arthur;” “the Kings of Europe”) to some sort of
                        divinely ordained masculine authority. Vala reminds Los that the edifice of
                        his civilization is built upon the control of female sexuality. However, in
                        the context of the entire poem, <pb id="p30-76" n="76"/> we can see that the
                        poet shares the patriarch’s terror of being “feminized”
                        by passive (i.e. “womanly”) dependence on a woman for nurture
                        and sexual gratification (“a Son &amp; a Husband”).</p>
          <p>For instance, anxiety about the sexual power of woman predominates in
                        Blake’s depiction of the sacrificial altar of Natural Religion: <q>
                            they sit naked upon the Stone of trial.<lb/> the Knife of flint passes
                            over his howling Victim: his blood<lb/> Gushes &amp; stains the fair
                            side of the fair Daug[h]ters of Albion.<lb/> . . . . .<lb/> They pour
                            cold water on his brain in front, to cause.<lb/> Lids to grow over his
                            eyes in veils of tears: and caverns<lb/> To freeze over his nostrils,
                            while they feed his tongue from cups<lb/> And dishes of painted clay.
                            Glowing with beauty &amp; cruelty:<lb/> They obscure the sun &amp; the
                            moon; no eye can look upon them.<lb/> (66:19-21, 30-34, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 218) </q></p>
          <p>This is the agony of Albion tormented by woman as depicted in plate 26, where
                        Vala, Rahab and Tirzah wind his umbilical cord (or his bowels) into a ball.
                        Woman is indicted as the agent of Natural Religion; her rejection of man
                        causes the fall of the senses. In scenes like this, the indictment of the
                        patriarchy recedes and woman seems to act as an independent agent of the
                        fall.</p>
          <p>Blake further condemns the female as the cause of war; the Daughters of
                        Albion are <q> Ashamed to give Love openly to the piteous &amp; merciful
                            Man<lb/> Counting him an imbecile mockery: but the Warrior<lb/> They
                            adore: &amp; his revenge cherish with the blood of the Innocent<lb/>
                            (67:19-21, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 220) </q></p>
          <p>The Warriors then sing a song of homage: <q> I am drunk with unsatiated
                            love<lb/> I must rush again to War: for the Virgin has frownd &amp;
                            refusd<lb/> Sometimes I curse &amp; sometimes bless thy fascinating
                            beauty<lb/> (68:62-64, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 222) </q> Certainly woman
                        throughout history has been dangled before men as a prize of war, but Blake
                        makes her the willful initiator of the conflict. Gwendolen, the Emanation of
                        Hyle, confesses to as much a bit later: “I have mockd those who
                        refused cruelty &amp; I have admired / The cruel Warrior” (81:1-2,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 238).</p>
          <p>The entire drama of the Daughters of Albion triumphant takes place after
                        Albion has collapsed onto the Rock of Ages. Blake seems to imply that with
                        the patriarch unconscious, Vala, or the Female Will, runs amok. Still, the
                        poet does juxtapose this nightmarish portrayal of female power against the
                        sufferings of Jerusalem in the Dungeons of Babylon, and holding the two in
                        balance, one could argue that Blake has in sum presented a myth that
                        symbolizes the contention of Mary Wollstonecraft and other female writers of
                        the era: while real women are exploited, men engage in the violent and
                        tormented pursuit of ideal female beauty and the glittering wealth produced
                        by woman’s enslavement.<ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
                        Blake’s remedy for this situation, however, is a problematic one: <q>
                            they refuse liberty to the male; &amp; not like Beulah<lb/> Where every
                            Female delights to give her maiden to her husband<lb/> The Female
                            searches sea &amp; land for gratification to the Male Genius:<lb/>
                            (69:14-17, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 223) </q> This passage is the culmination
                        in Blake’s poetry of a long series of declarations, beginning with
                        Oothoon’s famous speech in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion</hi> (7:23-29, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 50) in which the female
                        tolerance of male promiscuity is posited as a condition of the paradisal
                        state. Oothoon at least claims a corresponding sexual freedom for herself,
                        but in subsequent poems (see, for example, Milton 33:1-9 [<hi rend="i">E</hi> 132]), where the Divine Voice reproaches the Daughters of
                        Beaulah for cutting off his sexual pleasures with jealousy) promiscuity is
                        depicted as an exclusively masculine prerogative. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Mary Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">A Vindication of
                                the Rights of Woman</hi> (New York: Norton, 1988). Wollstonecraft
                            succinctly refutes the canard that the beauty of women gives them a
                            power over individual men that compensates for their powerlessness in
                            society, commenting: “I do not wish women to have power over men,
                            but over themselves” (62). Nelson Hilton in “An Original
                            Story,” 69-78 (see n3), provides a thorough summary of the
                            circumstantial case that indicates Blake and Wollstonecraft might have
                            known each other personally. Other female writers of the period who
                            shared Wollstonecraft’s condemnation of the cult of beauty were
                            Mary Anne Radcliffe, <hi rend="i">The Female Advocate</hi> (New York: G.
                            Olms, 1980): Mary Hays, <hi rend="i">An Appeal to the Men of Great
                                Britain on Behalf of Women</hi> (New York: Garland, 1974), and even
                            the later and much more conservative Priscilla Wakefield in <hi rend="i">Reflections on the Present Condition of the Female Sex</hi>
                            (London: Darton, 1817). Blake shares these writers’ disdain for
                            the cult of female beauty, but not their parallel exaltation of
                            woman’s rational powers.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s sexual paradise, Beulah, is a lower state than Eden, but still
                        an ostensible improvement over our fallen world of Generation. In the latter
                        world, Blake expresses an alternative to fallen reality through the actions
                        of the character Los.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>III</title>
          </head>
          <p>Los is for Blake the anti-patriarch, the character whose actions are meant to
                        undo the negative heritage of patriarchy. In order to redeem Albion, Los
                        must persuade him to put aside his patriarchal pride; to become a member of
                        a brotherhood of (male) equals, as in the message of the Divine Vision:
                        “I am not a God afar off, I am a brother and a friend” (4:18,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 146). Because “Los was the friend of Albion
                        who most lov’d him” (35:12, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 181), Los
                        calls the cities of <pb id="p30-77" n="77"/> England to help him restore
                        Albion: “Brotherhood is Religion,” (57:10, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                        207), the Cities declare. In the poem’s apocalyptic climax, Albion
                        sees Los and Jesus become the same person, saying to Jesus, “I see
                        thee in the likeness &amp; similitude of Los my Friend” (96:22, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 256), and Jesus declares, “nor can Man exist but
                        by Brotherhood” (96:28, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 256).<ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref><note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> The most extensive recent discussion of
                            Blake’s notion of brotherhood is in Michael Ferber’s <hi rend="i">The Social Vision of William Blake</hi> (Princeton:
                            Princeton University Press, 1985) 69-88. Ferber notes that “The
                            prime source of Blake’s ideas about brotherhood, as about so much
                            else, is the New Testament” (69) so that “Spiritual
                            brotherhood is a state where none are inferior or superior and all
                            equally share in the benevolence and joy, a state of unity founded on,
                            and symbolized by, the Eternal Man who walks among us, Jesus the
                            Imagination or Albion the collective man himself” (84). However,
                            Ferber notes that Blake was deeply interested in liberty and fraternity
                            but “had almost nothing to say . . . about equality” (68),
                            an idea whose implications for the female become clear when Ferber
                            remarks that the Christian fraternity upon which Blake modeled his own
                            idea of brotherhood “is a fraternity in the literal sense: the
                            only full participants are male” (86), and that, though
                            “Blake’s fraternity seems not to exclude women,”
                            still “Blake was content to deploy the traditional symbols and
                            analogies, which bore indelibly the stamp of the patriarchal society
                            where they were established” (87).</note></p>
          <p>In Gerda Lerner’s model of history, however, brotherhood did not
                        overthrow patriarchy; it refined and sustained it.<ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> In the Western tradition, this historical
                        development is represented by the covenant made by God with Israel in
                        Genesis and Exodus. Lerner argues that “The decisive change in the
                        relationship of man to God occurs in the story of the covenant, and it is
                        defined in such a way as to marginalize women.”<ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> Women are definitively excluded from the access to
                        God shared by members of this brotherhood. <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Lerner 180-99.</note><note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Lerner 188.</note></p>
          <p>Blake never uses the word “covenant” before <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, yet there it appears six times, including four
                        occasions on plate 98, the poem’s apocalyptic conclusion. The poet
                        declares: <q> And I heard Jehovah speak<lb/> Terrific from his Holy Place
                            &amp; saw the Words of the Mutual Covenant Divine<lb/> . . . . . .<lb/>
                            In the Forgiveness of Sins according to the Covenant of Jehovah. They
                            Cry<lb/> Where is the Covenant of Priam, the Moral Virtues of the
                            Heathen<lb/> (98:40-41, 45-46, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 258). </q> For Blake
                        this new covenant fulfills the true covenant of the Bible, but cancels the
                        covenant of morality, which he regards as heathen. The emphasis of the new
                        covenant on the forgiveness of sins is consonant with traditional
                        Christianity. Nowhere does Blake imply that this new covenant includes
                        women.</p>
          <p>Lerner notes that the key ritual by which the Judaic covenant was reaffirmed,
                        circumcision, by its very nature excludes women. She maintains that it marks
                        the male as the older of procreative power, countering the goddess-religions
                        in which priests were either castrated or else forced to give the fruit of
                        their sexual couplings to the goddess.<ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
                        “Circumcision” is another word that never appears in
                        Blake’s earlier poetry; in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, as Edward J.
                        Rose points out, it appears nine times, always as a positive symbol.<ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> As Rose also notes, Blake goes to
                        great lengths in the poem “to contrast circumcision with
                        Virginity” (16), portraying the latter negatively: the Eternals cry
                        out, “Establishment of Truth depends on destruction of Falshood
                        continually / On Circumsion: not on Viginity, O Reasoners of Albion”
                        (55:65-66, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 205). Virginity for Blake relates to the
                        religion of the goddess in its castrating mode; its modern incarnation is
                        the cult of female modesty and chastity. The same “female”
                        religion is condemned when Los’s Spectre and Emanation, observing
                        Albion’s fall, see “the Sexual Religion in its embryon
                        Uncircumcision” (44:11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 193). In the apocalypse,
                        the Divine Vision is seen “Circumscribing &amp; Circumcising the
                        excrementitious / Husk &amp; Covering into Vaccuum evaporating revealing
                        the lineaments of Man” (98:18-19, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 257). <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Lerner 191-92.</note><note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Edward J. Rose, “Circumcision
                            Symbolism in Blake’s Jerusalem,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Romanticism</hi> 8 (1968) 16-25.</note></p>
          <p>It is not surprising that the female in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is
                        frequently portrayed as the barrier to this new brotherhood that Los would
                        create: Vala attempts to delude Albion that she is the true Jerusalem,
                        declaring that “the Divine appearance is Brotherhood, but I am Love /
                        Elevate into the Region of Brotherhood with my red fires” (29:52 -
                        30:1, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 176). Albion shrinks from the revelation Los would
                        show him, “Rending the fibres of Brotherhood &amp; in Feminine
                        Allegories / Inclosing Los” (44:18-19, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 193). In
                        the poem’s ultimate crisis, Los posits the impossibility of male
                        brotherhood without the submission of woman: “How then can I ever
                        again be united as Man with Man / While thou my Emanation refusest my Fibres
                        of dominion” (88:12-13, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246). Implicit here and
                        elsewhere is the notion that the ideal brotherhood would involve the sharing
                        of women, a development that might at first appear to abolish woman’s
                        status as property but actually compounds it. Jerusalem, Blake’s
                        ideal female, yearns for the ancient times when she was shared in this
                        manner: <q> Italy saw me, in sublime astonishment: France was wholly
                            mine:<lb/> As my garden &amp; as my secret bath; Spain was my heavenly
                                <pb id="p30-78" n="78"/> couch:<lb/> I slept in his golden hills:
                            the Lamb of God met me there.<lb/> (79:39-41, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 235)
                        </q></p>
          <p>Jerusalem maintains that <hi rend="i">she</hi> was the owner of these places,
                        but in fact her act of ownership was to yield herself up to one and all as a
                        lover. Blake here means this woman-sharing to be pure metaphor, but it is a
                        metaphor founded on the derogation of the feminine in relation to the
                        masculine, in contrast to the democratic, egalitarian metaphor of sharing
                        brothers that characterizes the ideal relations of males to other males in
                        the poem.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>IV</title>
          </head>
          <p>On plate 86 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Los struggles with Enitharmon in
                        what Harold Bloom calls “Los’s own crisis with his
                        Emanation” (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 944). The crisis is in fact the
                        crisis of Blake’s entire mythic structure; a crisis provoked by the
                        contradictions inherent in the concept of gender on which the poet has based
                        his visionary universe.</p>
          <p>There are hints throughout the first three chapters of the epic that Blake is
                        directing the poem toward a revelation about the sexes. There are in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> more usages of the word “sex” and
                        its derivatives than in all of Blake’s earlier writings combined. The
                        word is sometimes employed in a sense subtly different than contemporary
                        usage: in these instances, sex and the sexual are pejorative terms, as when
                        Los’s Spectre and Emanation perceive “the Sexual Religion in
                        its embryon Uncircumcision” (44:11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 193), or when
                        the “Spectrous Uncircumcised Vegetation” of the Ulro forms
                        “a Sexual Machine: an Virgin Form” (39:24-25, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 186-87) or when Los denounces Vala as “The Sexual Death
                        living on accusation of Sin &amp; Judgment” (64:22, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 215). When Blake speaks of the sexual here, he in fact means the
                            <hi rend="i">anti</hi>-sexual (Milton O. Percival points out that the
                        fall into sex is for Blake a fall into chastity<ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>. The Sexual Religion is the patriarchal religion of chastity
                        and the repression of sex; that is why it appears in the form of an aged
                        virgin. Blake calls the anti-sexual “Sexual” because he
                        believes that the sexual personality as we know it is the product of
                        repression. The sexual “Garment,” or persona, is for Blake put
                        off in the act of sex, in which the two participants momentarily become one.
                        Hence, by engaging in unrepressed sex, we become less
                        “Sexual”; this is why Los can say of Beulah, the realm of
                        sexual consummation, “Humanity knows not of Sex: wherefore are Sexes
                        in Beulah?” (44:33, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 193). <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Milton O. Percival, <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake’s Circle of Destiny</hi>, 117.</note></p>
          <p>This unrepressed sex is for Blake necessarily polymorphous, not centered upon
                        genitality. Los therefore denounces “Sexual Organization,”
                        which is a false organization of the body around genitality: “O worm
                        of sixty winters said Los / Consider Sexual Organization &amp; hide thee in
                        the dust” (30:57-58, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 177). Sexual organization is
                        overcome in embraces which are properly “Cominglings: from the Head
                        even to the Feet; / And not a pompous High Priest entering by a Secret
                        Place” (69:43-44, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 223). Blake’s oftquoted
                        denunciation of the phallic here links the phallic to the patriarchal
                        “Sexual” Religion in which the male hierophant presides over a
                        mystery which is really the hidden and subjugated sexuality of woman.</p>
          <p>At first, the Blakean “Sex” may sound like the contemporary
                        “gender”: a culturally-defined set of differences, often
                        arbitrary and unjust. However, Blake also seems to believe that beneath this
                        false, culturally-constituted set of differences there is a real and
                        essential system of difference. Blake, as much as the patriarchy he
                        condemns, fears the collapse of sexual difference, an event that he believes
                        will throw humanity into the chaos of Ulro—the hell-realm that Blake
                        associates with hermaphroditism. The separation of male and female becomes
                        part of the eternal artistic labor of Los, with whom Blake is more closely
                        identified in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> than ever before. In order that
                        “Rational Philosophy” and “Mathematic
                        Demonstration” might be removed from the realm of abstraction where
                        they possess the power of religious mystery, Los splits them into gendered
                        forms: <q> And Los fixes them on his Anvil, incessant his blows:<lb/> He
                            fixes them with strong blows. placing the stones &amp; timbers.<lb/> To
                            Create a World of Generation from the World of Death:<lb/> Dividing the
                            Masculine &amp; Feminine: for the comingling<lb/> Of Albions &amp;
                            Luvahs Spectres was Hermaphroditic.<lb/> (58: 16-20, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                            207) </q> It is highly significant that Los here is depicted as a
                        “divider.” Almost everywhere else in the poem, it is Albion
                        who divides and Los who seeks to unify.<ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> The maintenance of male and female identities is essential to
                        the world of Generation; sexual ambiguity hints not of a higher world but of
                        a fall into the “hermaphroditic” hell of Ulro. <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> There is only one other instance where
                            division is used in a positive sense associated with Los: on 91:52, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 252, where Los alters his Spectre “Till he
                            had completely divided him into a separate space.” This
                            separation of the Spectre is analogous to the necessary separation of
                            the two genders in Blake’s myth, each to its own “separate
                            space.”</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> uses the hermaphroditism trope extensively, and
                        Blake links hermaphroditism directly to the anti-sexual
                        “Sexual” of the Sexual Religion (I will presently deal with
                        the difference between Blakean “hermaphroditism” and
                        “androgyny”): <q> Albions Emanation which he had hidden in
                            Jealousy<lb/> Appeard now in the frowning Chaos prolific upon <pb id="p30-79" n="79"/> the Chaos<lb/> Reflecting back to Albion in
                            Sexual Reasoning Hermaphroditic<lb/> (29:26-28, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 175)
                        </q> Albion, like Satan in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, has become
                        “feminized” by his jealous failure to project his Emanation,
                        which he then internalizes. Without the crucial difference produced by
                        gender, Blake’s system collapses into “frowning Chaos prolific
                        upon the Chaos.” It is therefore appropriate to see anxiety about
                        gender underlying Los’s tirades against the Female Will: <q> What may
                            Man be? who can tell! but what may Woman be?<lb/> To have power over Man
                            from Cradle to corruptible Grave.<lb/> There is a Throne in every Man,
                            it is the Throne of God<lb/> This woman has claimd as her own &amp; Man
                            is no more!<lb/> Albion is the Tabernacle of Vala &amp; her Temple<lb/>
                            And not the Tabernacle &amp; Temple of the Most High<lb/> O Albion why
                            wilt thou Create a Female Will?<lb/> (30:25-31, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 176)
                        </q> The female survives, hidden beneath the orthodox surface of modern
                        patriarchal religion, which through repression makes female sexuality seem
                        even more mysterious and secret than the ancient religions of the goddess. A
                        bit later, the same Female Will is indicted for the latest development of
                        Natural Religion, an anti-sexual, mechanistic Deism: “Is this the
                        Female Will O ye lovely Daughters of Albion. To / Converse concerning Weight
                        &amp; Distance in the Wilds of Newton &amp; Locke” (30:39-40, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 177).</p>
          <p>Blake can only see any degree of female willfulness as a negative,
                        “hermaphroditic” mingling of genders. However, he does seem to
                        see the apparent contradiction between his ostensibly egalitarian beliefs
                        and a visionary universe that derives its structure from a dualistic
                        hierarchy of gender, in which one gender is central and primary and the
                        other “emanated” and secondary. He briefly makes an attempt at
                        a resolution of this contradiction near the end of chapter 3, in his
                        exploration of the “Eternal States” of the Blakean universe,
                        Ulro, Generation, Beulah and Eden/Eternity, previously charted in detail
                        (and in terms of gender) in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> The poet mentions that
                        Albion’s Sons and Daughters “intermarry in Beulah / For all
                        are Men in Eternity” (71:14-15, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 225). In this
                        otherwise insignificant passage, Blake states outright something that his
                        imagery has long implied: Eden/Eternity, the ultimate fulfillment of the
                        human, is an entirely masculine realm. For the first time, Blake tells us
                        the fate of women in paradise: they may enter, but only as males, leaving
                        all female traits behind in the lower realms. This declaration does seem to
                        indicate that Blake sees the need for some form of female equality in a
                        redeemed, fully human universe. The problems, however, are fairly obvious:
                        anything feminine or female is implicitly an indicator of the fallen state.
                        Blake possibly has in mind a strategy that Alan Richardson has identified as
                        characteristic of male romantic writers: the attempt to
                        “colonize” the feminine by appropriating traditionally female
                        characteristics as a part of a new “higher” masculine
                            self.<ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref><note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Alan Richardson, “Romanticism and
                            the Colonization of The Feminine” in Anne K. Mellor, ed., <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Feminism</hi> (Bloomington: Indiana
                            University Press, 1988) 13-26. It can be demonstrated that Blake has
                            indeed employed Richardson’s “colonization”
                            strategy in earlier poems: in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, for instance,
                            Blake maps a metaphysics that in a traditional fashion defines time as
                            masculine (Los) and space as female (Enitharmon). However, Los declares
                            in 22:17 (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 117) that “both Time &amp; Space
                            obey my will” indicating that in Blake’s apocalypse, male
                            time <hi rend="i">subsumes</hi> female space. Again in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, masculine Time is the redeemer; he is “the
                            mercy of Eternity,” (24:72, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 121), while the
                            female’s place is vital but subordinate: “And between
                            every two Moments stands a Daughter of Beulah / To feed the Sleepers on
                            their Couches with maternal care.” (28:48-49, <hi rend="i">E</hi>
                            126). The redeeming quality of female space comes into being only as a
                            consequence of the creation of Moments of Time by Los.</note></p>
          <p>One can understand, then, the reluctance of Enitharmon to accept Los’s
                        “proposition” at the climax of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
                        The most human of Blake’s females, and the one most identified with
                        Catherine Blake, Enitharmon has been strangely absent from the poem since
                        her separation from the body of Los in 17:49-55 (<hi rend="i">E</hi> 162).
                        For the second time in the poem, Enitharmon divides away from Los, implying
                        an even deeper rift between male and female: “Two Wills they had; Two
                        Intellects: &amp; not as in times of old” (86:61, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 245). A state which in fact sounds like a condition of equality
                        is lamented by the poet.</p>
          <p>Los and Enitharmon begin a game of sexual hide and seek that recalls
                        “The Mental Traveller.” Finally, Los speaks his love: <q> O
                            lovely Enitharmon: I behold thy graceful forms<lb/> Moving beside me
                            till intoxicated with the woven labyrinth<lb/> Of beauty &amp;
                            perfection my wild fibres shoot in veins<lb/> Of blood thro all my
                            nervous limbs. soon overgrown in roots<lb/> I shall be closed from thy
                            sight. sieze therefore in thy hand<lb/> The small fibres as they shoot
                            around me draw out in pity<lb/> And let them run on the winds of thy
                            bosom: I will fix them<lb/> With pulsations. we will divide them into
                            Sons &amp; Daughters<lb/> To live in thy Bosoms translucence as in an
                            eternal morning<lb/> (87:3-11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246) </q></p>
          <p>Los is asking Enitharmon to help him control the “fibres” of
                        sexual desire, to convert sexual energy into the “Sons &amp;
                        Daughters” of creative work. This is the offer that Enitharmon
                        accepted at the climax of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>; to <pb id="p30-80" n="80"/> assist Los in the creation of redemptive
                        “counterparts” to the minute particulars of the fallen world.
                        This time Enitharmon has a different answer: <q> No! I will sieze thy Fibres
                            &amp; weave<lb/> Them: not as thou wilt but as I will, for I will
                            Create<lb/> A round Womb beneath my bosom lest I also be overwoven<lb/>
                            With Love; be thou assured I never will be thy slave<lb/> Let Mans
                            delight be love; but Womans delight be Pride<lb/> In Eden our loves were
                            the same here they are opposite<lb/> I have Loves of my own<lb/>
                            (87:12-18, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246) </q></p>
          <p>Blake allows Enitharmon’s voice considerable autonomy, and she speaks
                        well, perhaps even better than the poet realizes. For the first time, one of
                        Blake’s women speaks not merely willfully but in a manner akin to a
                        modern feminist polemic; indeed, in a manner akin to Mary Wollstonecraft:
                        “be thou assured I never will be thy slave.” When Enitharmon
                        vows to “Create a round Womb” from the fibres of Los, she
                        means that she would “naturalize” the sexual energies to deal
                        with the needs of this world, not Los’s ideal world of art. She
                        subsequently gives a rationale for this: “In Eden our loves were the
                        same here they are opposite.” She concisely informs Los that the
                        needs of men and women in an unjust world may be quite different. The prior
                        statement of Enitharmon, “Let Mans delight be love; but Womans
                        delight be Pride,” echoes Gwendolen’s earlier statement of
                        81:6. Blake begins to sound like the Restoration authors (whom he disliked
                        intensely) who never tired of accusing woman of pride; he never suggests
                        that pride might be woman’s understandable response to a situation in
                        which the female’s only path to power is through beauty.</p>
          <p>Enitharmon is meant to seem perverse in rejecting Los, but she sounds
                        altogether reasonable. Her best arguments are saved for last: <q> thou
                            hidest Vala<lb/> From her these fibres shoot to shut me in a Grave.<lb/>
                            You are Albions Victim, he has set his Daughter in your path<lb/>
                            (87:22-24, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246) </q> Enitharmon’s analysis is
                        superior to that of Los, who thinks he opposes Vala, but in fact practices a
                        covert Natural Religion in the form of sexism. Los is not the foe of
                        patriarchy, but rather, as “Albions victim,” he has fallen
                        into its trap: he thinks he will overturn patriarchy by replacing
                        traditional legalistic authority with an authority linked to a principle of
                        masculinity; in fact, this will only perpetuate the abuses of patriarchy in
                        a new guise.</p>
          <p>Los attempts to plead his case: <q> Man cannot unite with Man but by their
                            Emanations<lb/> Which stand both Male &amp; Female at the Gates of each
                            Humanity<lb/> How then can I ever again be united as Man with Man<lb/>
                            While thou my Emanation refusest my Fibres of domininion.<lb/> When
                            Souls mingle &amp; join thro all the Fibres of Brotherhood<lb/> Can
                            there be any secret joy on Earth greater than this?<lb/> (88:10-15, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246) </q> Line 11 is key to the argument of those
                        who maintain that Blake in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is advocating
                        androgyny; I will have more to say about it when I discuss Blake’s
                        concept of androgyny. That one very ambiguous line aside, Los is offering
                        Enitharmon a bad bargain. She must receive his “Fibres of
                        dominion,” acknowledge his dominance, so that he can join with other
                        men in “Fibres of Brotherhood”—in other words,
                        Lerner’s all-male society of the covenant, with women shared out
                        among the brothers.</p>
          <p>Enitharmon’s response is redolent of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>: as in that earlier work, the world is portrayed as a
                        female hell, with woman as a demiurge, “This is Womans World”
                        (88:16, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 247). The triumph of the Female Will brings
                        about the final manifestation of Vala as “A terrible indefinite
                        Hermaphroditic form” (89:3, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 248), the ultimate
                        consolidation of the monstrous hermaphrodites of Blake’s myth: the
                        Covering Cherub. The Cherub amalgamates Rahab-Tirzah, the Whore of Babylon,
                        and all of the “female-males” and “male-females”
                        who block entry into paradise.</p>
          <p>On the heels of this revelation, Blake makes a direct attempt to resolve the
                        contradictions in his sexual myth. This he would do putting forth a concept
                        of gender as a fallen state, ultimately to be replaced by an androgyny that
                        is to be distinguished from this fallen hermaphroditism. The fall is first
                        described: “The Feminine separates from the Masculine &amp; both
                        from Man, / Ceasing to be His Emanations, Life to Themselves
                        assuming!” (90:1-2, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 249). If “Man”
                        is read as humanity, the statement might be read as a very contemporary
                        formulation of the problem of gender as a reductive division of all that is
                        human into a binary set of characteristics. Blake finds the source of this
                        problem in the appropriation of what he calls “Universal
                        Characteristics” by individuals: <q> For Los said: When the
                            Individual appropriates Universality<lb/> He divides into Male &amp;
                            Female: &amp; when the Male &amp; Female,<lb/> Appropriate
                            Individuality, they become an Eternal Death.<lb/> Hermaphroditic
                            worshippers of a God of curelty &amp; law!<lb/> (90:52-55, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 250) </q> This doctrine of Universal Characteristics is an
                        extension of the of States as presented in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>:
                        individuals pass through States, but must avoid identification with any <pb id="p30-81" n="81"/> single State. To identify with a State is to freeze
                        ourselves into a fixed, immutable Selfhood and to lose touch with our total
                        humanity. Gender is one of these States; to over-identify with a single
                        gender ironically makes us “hermaphroditic”: we end up
                        internalizing the sexual Other rather than finding it outside our selves.
                        However, I believe that the “androgyny” that Blake would set
                        against this negative hermaphroditism can be demonstrated to be nothing more
                        than the personification of the familiar androcentric voice of Western
                        literature, that voice which feminist critics have repeatedly accused of
                        representing a masculinist agenda in the guise of an ungendered
                        universalism.</p>
          <p>Earlier, Los declared “Man cannot unite with Man but by their
                        Emanations / Which stand both Male &amp; Female at the Gates of each
                        Humanity” (88:10-11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 246). Thomas D. Frosch, a
                        champion of Blake as a proponent of androgyny, interprets the lines: <q>
                            This is a difficult passage and line 11 is capable of supporting
                            contradictory interpretations. Each man might have four gates, for
                            instance, as paradise does, and his emanations might be both
                            “both Male &amp; Female,” or themselves androgynous. As I
                            understand the lines, however, the suggestion seems to be that each
                            Edenic Humanity emanates what we might consider to be two sexual
                            persons, a male and a female, at its points of communication with other
                            human forms, as if each Edenic being, then, appeared to others a
                            radically unified couple.<ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref><note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Thomas D. Frosch, <hi rend="i">The
                                    Awakening of Albion</hi>, 174.</note></q></p>
          <p>The difficulty that Frosch has in describing Blake’s concept of
                        androgyny is typical of critical attempts to define this elusive
                            proposition.<ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> Frosch is probably
                        close to the truth in describing the individual in the awakened Edenic
                        Humanity as a “radically unified couple,” but it is a couple
                        in which the male has (in Los’s words) “dominion” over
                        and in fact <hi rend="i">subsumes</hi> the female. At the climax of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Ololon is in fact incorporated into
                        Blake-Los-Milton. The subsumption of the female by the male in
                        Blake’s poetry has been remarked upon by Alicia Ostriker, while the
                        same motif in Blake’s visual art has been noted by Anne K.
                            Mellor.<ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> The closing plates of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> show this same strategy at work, and Alan
                        Richardson’s principle of the “colonization” of the
                        feminine by male romantic writers again seems to be an entirely appropriate
                        characterization of Blake’s narrative. <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Camille Paglia in <hi rend="i">Sexual Personae</hi> (New
                            York: Viking Press, 1991) 291-92, comments that in <hi rend="i">A Blake
                                Dictionary</hi>, S. Foster Damon “makes a distinction between
                            hermaphrodite and androgyne that makes no sense whatever to me. Damon
                            and Percival believe that the sexes are equal in the androgyne but that
                            the female dominates in the hermaphrodite,” and she adds a bit
                            later, “The words hermaphrodite and androgyne should be
                            synonymous.” In point of fact, any figure in the poetry that
                            seems at all androgynous is labelled hermaphroditic and condemned. The
                            beings described as androgynous, in the positive sense invoked by Damon
                            and Percival, are figured as masculine.</note><note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Ostriker (see n3) 163; Mellor,
                            “Blake’s Portrayal of Women,” 151. The two
                            articles, taking similar critical stances toward Blake’s sexual
                            politics, appeared in the same issue of <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Los at the climax of the poem never directly resolves his crisis with
                        Enitharmon; instead he turns to confront the Spectre. Spectre and Emanation
                        have been linked since the beginning of the poem; they were the two
                        survivors who escaped Albion’s fall in chapter 2, and plate 44 shows
                        them flying side by side into the arms of Los. The effect of this connection
                        is to link the female with that which is most negative in the (male) psyche:
                        fear, anger, vanity, phallocentrism. Los subdues his Spectre in the famous
                        “It is easier to forgive an Enemy than to forgive a Friend”
                        (91:1, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 251) speech that occupies the whole of plate 91.
                        Los’s victory comes from the renunciation of personal vanity,
                        “In unpitying ruin driving down the pyramids of pride” (91:43,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 252). Through the abdication of pride, “Los
                        alterd his Spectre” (91:50, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 252), and he triumphs
                        over Spectre and Emanation simultaneously.</p>
          <p>There is no corresponding scene in which Los deals with the challenge of
                        Enitharmon. After his contest with the Spectre, she reappears, already
                        defeated and lamenting: “The Poets Song draws to its period &amp;
                        Enitharmon is no more” (92:8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 252). The female
                        will be subsumed in the masculine identity of the awakened Albion. Los
                        informs her that “Sexes must vanish &amp; cease / To be, when Albion
                        arises from his dread repose O lovely Enitharmon” (92:13-14, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 252), but what he really means is that <hi rend="i">woman</hi> (traditionally designated as “the sex”) will
                        vanish; there is no indication that Los’s masculine characteristics
                        will disappear or in any way be transformed. In Blake’s myth, woman
                        resists the end of sexual division because it means a loss of power for her.
                        Since in Blake’s redeemed universe the mending of sexual division
                        means the subsumption and containment of the female by the male, it is easy
                        to see why woman would resist.</p>
          <p>The last element of woman to vanish is her maternity. Enitharmon wails to her
                        sons Rintrah and Palamabron, “The Mothers love of obedience is
                        forgotten &amp; you seek a Love / Of the pride of dominion” (93:4-5,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 253). Enitharmon’s comments again seem a
                        disturbingly accurate critique of Blake’s own project. The poet will
                        overturn the traditional patriarchal control of woman’s sexuality by
                        subsuming that sexuality into a masculine creativity that is
                        “higher” than mere “natural” procreativity. Los,
                        the new patriarch, reassures his Sons: “Fear not my Sons this Waking
                        Death. he is become One with me / Behold him here! We shall not Die! we
                        shall be united in Jesus” (93:18-19, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 253).</p>
          <p>The rest of the poem deals with the awakening of Albion. Brittannia, the
                        reunified form of Jerusalem and Vala, lies across his prone body and
                        attempts to rouse him. She moans in contrition, “In dreams of
                        Chastity &amp; Moral Law I have Murdered Albion! Ah! / . . . behold ye the
                        Jealous Wife” (94:23-26, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 254). It is this wail of
                        female self-abnegation <pb id="p30-82" n="82"/> that wakes Albion, at which
                        point <q> England who is Brittannia enterd Albions bosom rejoicing,<lb/>
                            Rejoicing in his indignation! adoring his wrathful rebuke.<lb/> She who
                            adores not your frowns will only loathe your smiles<lb/> (95:22-24, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 255) </q> This, alas, is the apotheosis of Blakean
                        woman. Brittannia is subsumed by the male: her entry into
                        “Albion’s bosom rejoicing,” as depicted on plates 96
                        and 99,<ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> implies an incorporation into
                        the male body. Brittannia does not reappear in the poem. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Mellor, “Blake’s Portrayal of
                            Women,” 151-52, sees subsumption at work in Plate 99 in the
                            masculine characteristics of the body of Jerusalem. I see the
                            Jerusalem-figure as female, and attribute its masculine musculature to
                            Blake’s problematic draftsmanship and his too-assiduous copying
                            of Michelangelo, but I see a clearer suggestion of subsumption in the
                            way that Albion/Jehovah/Urizen gathers Jerusalem in, coupled with her
                            disappearance from the poetry.</note></p>
          <p>The depiction of a postapocalyptic world in the remainder of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> bears out the earlier pronouncement that in
                        Eden/Eternity “all are Men.” The poet hears the “Vision
                        of Albion” speak; the Vision of Albion is, as Blake’s faculty
                        of “Vision” has always been since the <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi>, an irreducibly masculine ability to organize perception.
                        The Vision of Albion is identified with “The Universal Father”
                        (97:6, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 256): patriarchy is not wiped out; rather,
                        authority has been apportioned “universally” among the male
                        members of a brotherhood; it is the final stage in Lerner’s
                        developmental model of patriarchal history.</p>
          <p>There is, however, a hint of the persistence of the female at the
                        poem’s conclusion: <q> All Human Forms identified even Tree Metal
                            Earth &amp; Stone. all<lb/> Human Forms identified, living going forth
                            &amp; returning wearied<lb/> Into the Planetary lives of Years Months
                            Days &amp; Hours reposing<lb/> And then Awaking into his Bosom in the
                            Life of Immortality.<lb/><lb/> And I Heard the Name of their Emanations
                            they are named Jerusalem<lb/> (99:1-5, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 258-59) </q>
                        It seems fitting that, in the very last line of the epic that the poet
                        intended to be his greatest statement, Blake’s proliferating myth
                        should come to rest upon its central contradiction, a contradiction that
                        remains unresolved: a system that wishes to unify and equalize all persons
                        is founded upon the principle of the dominance of a masculine subject over
                        an emanated and secondary female object.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">REVIEW</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Veils, Infinity, a Roof, and “One thought” in Contemporary Art<lb/> A
              Note on Four Exhibitions</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>D. W. <name>Dörrbecker</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>At the brink of the new millennium, Blake still hasn’t found that large readership in
            the German-speaking countries which Henry Crabb Robinson had expected to grow so rapidly
            when drafting the essay he contributed to the <hi rend="i">Vaterländisches Museum</hi>
            in 1811. Therefore, it comes as a surprise to find that over the past few years Blake’s
            works have inspired a series of exhibitions by contemporary artists in Austria, Germany,
            and Switzerland which may warrant a brief report.</p>
          <p>Supposedly, only few of the visitors who came to see Verena Immenhauser’s installation
            “Beneath the Veil of Vala” at the Berner Galerie in 1988 were fully aware of the Swiss
            artist’s understanding of the symbol of Vala’s veil/vale and its complex meaning in the
            poetry and art of William Blake. And yet, anybody ready to engage with the aesthetic
            experience offered by that installation must have felt the urge to question the
            relationship between the veil and the veiled, center and circumference, form and
            formlessness, the cycle of natural growth and decay (reigning in Vala’s vale) and the
            ideas of stability and of eternity (governing a realm that lies beyond it). Employing
            soft transparent wrapping foils, Immenhauser created an environment inside the small
            gallery space which at first sight seemed devoid both of calculated form and all
            specific content. However, the movements of the visitors quite literally breathed life
            into the room which was filled with draped “veils” (illus. 1) hanging from the ceiling
            and hiding the measured dimensions of the walls. The softly whispering and everchanging
            folds of the thin and shining plastic veils remained entirely abstract in shape, but
            functioned as an appropriate representation of Vala’s veil of nature. Their
            rippling-rustling texture lured the sense of touch and the ear, while their utter
            refusal of all representational concreteness, the complete lack of linear (and optical)
            solidity, and their shimmering, silvery reflections, irritated and fascinated the
            eye.</p>
          <p>In a sense, this finely tuned metaphor of Vala’s art of seduction seemed related to
            Marcel Duchamp’s famous “spider-web” installation for the Surrealist exhibition at 451
            Madison Avenue in 1942. But it also anticipated such “physical sculptures” as the
            “Bodycheck” contributed by Flatz to the documenta IX in 1992, or the labyrinth of
            measured time made from hundreds of clocks, hanging folding rules, <pb id="p30-83" n="83"/><figure n="ImmenhauserUntitled.30.3.bqscan" rend="file">
              <head>1 Verena Immenhauser, “Untitled,” a figural veil/a veiled figure, executed in
                preparation of the installation shown at Berne, Switz., dimensions vary,
                1988.</head>
              <figDesc>Collection of the artist.</figDesc>
            </figure> and “lost” digits that was shown by Cildo Meireles on the same occasion in
            Kassel. The magic and attractiveness which Blake and most of his (male?) readers fear in
            Vala was reflected by the artistic sorcery with which Immenhauser handled the
            insubstantiality of the translucent yet blinding and suffocating quality of her simple
            materials.</p>
          <p>For his “1992 Infinite Painting on A Vision of the Last Judgment by William Blake
            1808,” shown in Berlin at the Zwinger Galerie, Nikolaus Utermöhlen mounted enlarged
            photocopies of Blake’s “Vision” on thirteen aluminum panels (200 × 80 cm. each). The
            reproductions had been produced on a color photocopying machine which was manipulated by
            the artist so that a sequence of color variations resulted. Each panel (or, as
            Utermöhlen prefers to call them, each “spectre”) displayed a different layering of the
            primary colors, blurring and distorting the clarity of Blake’s original watercolor. Its
            design was thus supplanted with the cool glow of industrial colors which had been
            heightened by additional hand-tinted patterns and which produced the effect of a giant
            kaleidoscope. Utermöhlen’s interest in the openness and mechanical “infinity” of
            possible color variations and in the configurations which can be assembled by grouping
            the aluminum panels on the gallery walls, produced <figure n="LochleStonyRoof.30.3.bqscan" rend="file">
              <head>2 Dieter Löchle, “Stony Roof,” pencil and encaustic painting, 50 × 35 cm.,
                1994.</head>
              <figDesc>Collection of the artist.</figDesc>
            </figure> a decorative color rhythm quite appropriate for a postmodern ice cream parlor.
            Sure enough, Utermöhlen’s project may pass as yet another artistic experiment with the
            representational implications of technical reproduction and repetition. Moreover, the
            artist may well have hoped for a meaningful contrast between “classical form” and
            “modern technique” similar to the one achieved by, say, Jim Dine’s appropriation of the
            Venus of Melos. However, I failed to trace any deeply felt conceptual relation between
            Utermöhlen’s “Infinite Painting” and Blake’s understanding of infinity or his idea of a
            Last Judgment. Rather, Blake’s watercolor painting apparently had been chosen more or
            less at random, and the artist’s references to a Blakean model served, in the end, as no
            more than a fairly banal attempt to dignify with iconographical content what was merely
            another more or less interesting experiment in replacing the old-fashioned brush with a
            xerox machine.</p>
          <p>If Utermöhlen’s central concern was that of a formalist, one will have to locate the
            works of Dieter Löchle at the other end of the spectrum. Under the title “Roof’d in from
            Eternity,” his Blakean drawings, prints, and paintings were on show at the Tübingen
            university library in 1995. Almost devoid of color, Löchle’s paintings relied on the
            simple opposition of darkness and light, created by black, white, <pb id="p30-84" n="84"/><figure n="LochleMilton.30.3.bqscan" rend="file">
              <head>3 Dieter Löchle, “Milton,” pencil on encaustic ground, 64.0 × 47.5 cm.,
                1995.</head>
              <figDesc>Collection of the artist.</figDesc>
            </figure> and thinly saturated yellowish washes. These almost unstructured encaustic
            color fields provide the backdrop for the artist’s similarly simplified linear
            adaptation of Blake’s figural language. Drawing with the brush, with pen and ink, or
            with black and white chalks in what seems a consciously retrospective manner, Löchle
            reinvents the imagery of the illuminated books. Visitors to the exhibition were allowed
            to gauge this reference to Blake’s relief-etched designs in the modernized versions by
            means of a generous selection from the Trianon Press facsimiles of the illuminated books
            which was on show in the library’s vestibule. Löchle handles his lines with great
            clarity and achieves solid, almost “architectural” compositions that are all based on
            only one or two figures (as in many of Blake’s own illuminated pages). For example, the
            German painter has translated figural motifs from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 41, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 21, the frontispiece for <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>, and plates 10
            and 17 from <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> into his own pictorial idiom (illus. 2-3).</p>
          <p>Occasionally, when confronted with the symbolic portrait heads and some of the
            eroticized designs which were included in the show, I felt struck by what seems a
            curiously straightforward approach to the problems and functions of contemporary visual
            representation, an approach bordering on the naive. However, Löchle’s linear
            abbreviations of the “human form divine” generally work well enough as a modern
            interpretative response to Blake. Because the expressive use of bodily movements in
            Blake’s designs is perpetuated in Löchle’s pictorial homage, his images seem highly
            charged with symbolic energy and meaning. And it is here that they provide an antithesis
            to Utermöhlen’s dominantly formalist concerns. At the same time, the austerity and
            abstract quality of Löchle’s <pb id="p30-85" n="85"/> draughtsmanship steer clear of the
            preoccupation with those “sublime,” “fantastic,” “weird,” and more narrative aspects of
            the art of Blake and Fuseli which have previously attracted the attention of other
            Austrian and German artists such as Günter Brus, Alfred Hrdlicka, or Horst Janssen in
            some of their exhibitions of the 1970s and 1980s.</p>
          <p>Löchle’s stylistic choices lead towards a relative independence of his images from
            their Blakean blueprints. But they draw the viewer’s attention to such characteristics
            as the white-line technique—first in Löchle’s own prints, drawings, and paintings, but
            then, on the way out and through the show-cases lined up in the entrance hall, also in
            Blake’s illuminated prints. In this sense, “Roof’d in from Eternity” was a group
            exhibition, ideally suited for an academic library. Löchle not only paid homage to
            Blake, he also invited the visitors to find out for themselves what he had seen in
            Blake’s colored relief-etchings, and how he had seen it.</p>
          <p>An entirely different and certainly non-didactic approach was chosen for a fourth
            exhibition which presented a far more radical, avantgardist, and in its own way very
            exciting use of the raw materials provided by Blake for the making of contemporary art.
            The first major one-man show in Germany for the Spanish sculptor and installation artist
            Jaume Plensa was organized by the Städtische Galerie Göppingen in the summer of 1995.
            Plensa’s art often combines the visual and the verbal in a surprising, some may say an
            absurd manner. While this relationship of image and text cannot be described as
            “narrative” in any common sense of the word, it succeeds in making familiar objects seem
            strange, and it creates “new” and challenging combinations which provoke the senses and
            the imagination. His recent work exposes the spectator to environments assembled from
            prosaic objects of the artist’s own everyday life and from inscribed panels, boxes, or
            cages which are cast in synthetic resin. Together with two other installations, the
            Göppingen exhibition introduced Plensa’s (as yet unfinished) project on Blake’s
            “Proverbs of Hell” from <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (illus. 4-5).
            Similar to Immenhauser’s veils, but adding Blake’s own words in blind-stamped letters on
            his polyester panels, Plensa’s “Proverbs” provide a highly personal interpretation of
            Blake, the rich associations of which remain valid (or at least intellectually
            fascinating) even for an onlooker who is entirely unacquainted with the British
            poet-artist’s works.</p>
          <p>Most of the 1995 “Proverbs” consist of three elements, which are usually mounted at a
            right angle on the gallery’s walls. The first of these elements is an object from the
            “hell” of the artist’s studio work, such as a red plastic bucket which had been used in
            the preparation of the plaster Plensa employs in an early stage of his casting
            technique, or a cheap metal wastepaper basket which, one imagines, had once been filled
            with discarded sketches and studies for the artist’s projects. The second element is a
            pillar, protruding <figure n="PlensaProverbs.30.3.bqscan" rend="file">
              <head>4 Jaume Plensa, “Proverbs of Hell 73: ‘Enough or too much’,” wall piece made
                from synthetic resin and a plastic bucket, 65 × 130 × 144 cm., 1995.</head>
              <figDesc>Private collection, Barcelona, Spain; photo: Lluis Bover.</figDesc>
            </figure> about three feet from the wall into the exhibition space. Attached to the top
            of this pillar, sometimes standing, sometimes dangling headlong, is a small statue of a
            naked child. Both the pillar and the statuette are cast from semi-transparent polyester
            resin. The naked child is placed in a position which seems to defy the law of gravity
            and often suggests that it is contemplating the object from everyday life and the third
            element, a cast polyester panel with Blake’s proverb inscribed in relief. By
            reading/viewing, for example, “The busy bee has no time for sorrow” in the panel mounted
            on top of one of the waste-baskets, the small figures on their pillars supply the
            visitors with directions for the use of the entire installation.</p>
          <p>At the same time the transparent three-dimensional figures prompt us to muse about the
            relationship between the various elements that have been combined for each of the
            “Proverbs” and outward reality—to ponder on the practical usefulness of a red plastic
            bucket, a usefulness which is lost once it is made part of a work of art—to realize that
            thereby it may, however, achieve a different function, and may as such become useful in
            a different sense—to contemplate the representation of the human figure in its relation
            to the abstract stereometry of the pillar-cube it is attached to—and, of course, to
            think about the continuing relevance of what Blake’s devils have to say concerning the
              <pb id="p30-86" n="86"/> nature, the social conditions and conditioning, and the role
            of the imagination in this world. One thing I didn’t like about the exhibition at
            Göppingen: its title, “One thought fills immensity.” In Plensa’s work, just as in many
            other instances of contemporary installation and concept art (and even in Blake), formal
            repetitions, the reduplication of a specific motif or shape are of essential importance.
            I doubt, however, that an irony was intended, and that the title was meant to draw the
            spectator’s attention to the filling of the “immensity” of the gallery space with just
            “One thought.” Even if it was, “The road of excess leads to the palace of wisdom,” and
            “Enough! or Too much” would have described Plensa’s secular modernization of Blake more
            appropriately.</p>
          <p>Each of these four exhibitions tells us about specific modes and possibilities of the
            creative appropriation of Blake’s words and images. What Michelangelo was to Blake,
            Blake is to Löchle who—in the group of works discussed in the present
            note—literally/visually cites the elder artist’s figural language and/or entire
            compositional arrangements. Not only is the artist consciously transforming Blakean
            models, he also wants the viewer to recognize his citations as such. Just as an editor
            or a critic of Blake’s works might do, Löchle asks for the meaning which Blake’s art may
            have for an audience separated from its initial production by two centuries. The tension
            between the historicity of the pictorial inventions and the actuality of their rendering
            in Löchle’s “cover version,” between the identity of the motifs and the discrepancy of
            the formal qualities of their representation is exactly where the “meaning” of these
            paintings and prints from 1994-95 appears to be situated. Löchle’s insistence on
            visually confronting Blake’s images (by means of the facsimiles included in the
            exhibition) with his own works demonstrates a historical awareness which in turn allows
            for linking his art with certain techniques of scholarly interpretation.</p>
          <p>If Löchle’s art is inspired by the “historical approach,” Immenhauser’s seems to
            provide a parallel with gender criticism. Those of the visitors to her installation who
            were alert to the Blakean connotations of Vala’s veil, will have glimpsed at a critical
            and revisionist view of the role assigned to Vala in the poem which was named after her,
            in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and in almost any learned commentary on these works.
            Immenhauser, it seems, “reads” Blake against the masculine grain, and by doing so she
            opens up an alternative understanding of Vala and her veil which attempts to visually
            “explain” some of the fascination which Blake himself apparently felt when creating the
            mythic character. To take this just one step further, one might classify Plensa’s
            sculptural montage of the “Proverbs” as an example of a “deconstructive” or a
            “hypermedia” art, the creation of an unstable artistic reality from seemingly unrelated
            textual elements, which in a continual flux combine and dissociate to form a variety of
            meaningful, yet “open” constellations.</p>
          <figure n="PlensaProverbs3.30.3.bqscan" rend="file">
            <head>5 Jaume Plensa, “Proverbs of Hell 3: ‘The road of excess leads to the palace of
              wisdom’,” wall piece made from synthetic resin and a brass object, 98 × 71 × 50 cm.,
              1995.</head>
            <figDesc>Städtische Galerie, Göppingen, Germany; photo: Lluis Bover.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Now, does this mean that these contemporary artists work with scholarly methodologies
            in mind? Or that scholars unconsciously are creating their texts along the same lines
            that artists create their works? Though Immenhauser and Löchle have indeed written
            academic theses on Blake, such a conclusion would seem rather ludicrous to me. The
            construction of abstract analogies between art and scholarship as two “fruits” of the
            human mind still seems synonymous with comparing apples to peaches. However, to look at
            contemporary artists’ reactions to Blake’s words and images, and to draw such parallels,
            may still be a heuristically useful exercise, one that will remind the critic of the
            plurality of legitimate and potentially meaningful engagements with Blake’s works.</p>
          <pb id="p30-87" n="87"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Artists, Exhibitions, and Catalogues</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Verena Immenhauser (b. 1939), <hi rend="i">Vala: Arbeiten zu Blake</hi>, Berner
              Galerie, Berne, Switz., 1-24 Nov. 1988. On show were the installation “Beneath the
              Veil of Vala” (as reviewed above), as well as a selection of the artist’s “Vala”
              photographs and oil paintings (the latter somehow reminiscent of Cy Twombly’s “Wilder
              Shores of Love”). There was no catalogue, but the exhibition was previously reviewed
              in <hi rend="i">Der Bund</hi> and by Ester Adeyemi, <hi rend="i">Berner Zeitung</hi>,
              12 Nov. 1988.</p>
            <p>Dieter Löchle (b. 1952), <hi rend="i">William Blake—Roof’d in from Eternity</hi>,
              Universitätsbibliothek, Tübingen, Ger., 3 Apr.-25 May 1995. The catalogue, with a note
              on the artist by Susanne Padberg, translations from Blake’s poetry, and a commentary
              on Blake’s prophecies by the artist, is being distributed by the Galerie Druck &amp;
              Buch (Nauklerstrasse 7, D-72074 Tübingen, Ger.). The show was previously reviewed by
              Kurt Oesterle, <hi rend="i">Schwäbisches Tagblatt</hi>, 6 Apr. 1995: 27. On the
              occasion of the exhibition, and under the same title, two portfolios with
              reproductions of Löchle’s designs and his prints in offset lithography were issued in
              a limited edition of 50 copies each (Tübingen, Ger.: Galerie Druck &amp; Buch,
              1995).</p>
            <p>Jaume Plensa (b. 1955), “<hi rend="i">One thought fills immensity</hi>,” Städtische
              Galerie, Göppingen, Ger., 2 July-6 Aug. 1995. The exhibition catalogue contains
              Blake’s “Proverbs of Hell” and contributions by the artist, Werner Meyer, and Alain
              Charre (parallel texts in German and English).</p>
            <p>Nikolaus Utermöhlen (b. 1958), <hi rend="i">1992 Nikolaus Utermöhlen “An Infinite
                Painting” on A Vision of the Last Judgment by William Blake 1808</hi>, Zwinger
              Galerie, Berlin, Ger., 5 Sept.-10 Oct. 1992. In lieu of a catalogue, the gallery
              issued an “artist’s book” in an exceedingly small (and expensive) edition. The
              exhibition has been briefly reviewed in <hi rend="i">Die Tageszeitung</hi>, 15 Sept.
              1992.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Seeing Thel as Serpent</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Hilda <name>Hollis</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Thel’s motto remains one of the most enigmatic aspects of William
                        Blake’s short <hi rend="i">Book of Thel.</hi> It is composed of a
                        series of questions, the intent of which is unclear, and which only seem to
                        provoke more questions: <q> Does the Eagle know what is in the pit?<lb/> Or
                            wilt thou go ask the Mole:<lb/> Can Wisdom be put in a silver rod?<lb/>
                            O Love in a golden bowl?<lb/> (i.1-4, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) </q> Most
                        discussion focuses on the second pair of questions, and my argument begins
                        with this set. Two major sources are widely suggested for these lines:
                        Ecclesiastes and Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> The former refers
                        to the issue of mortality which is of paramount concern to Thel, and the
                        latter bears a relation to Thel’s virginal and frightened chastity. I
                        suggest that, while contributing to our understanding of these lines,
                        neither Ecclesiastes nor <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> comprehends the full or
                        multiple meaning of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and its motto. Blake first
                        composed these lines in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> in a section which he
                        subsequently deleted, and this original context suggests another metaphor
                        which has implications for the whole of the later book.</p>
          <p>When Tiriel first utters the questions about the rod and bowl, there is no
                        clear reference to sexuality and certainly no allusion to <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> Tiriel’s concern with his old age and mortality
                        echoes Ecclesiastes: “before the silver cord is snapped, or the
                        golden bowl is broken” (12:6). But there are significant differences.
                        Cord is replaced by rod, and neither wisdom nor love is associated with
                        these objects in Ecclesiastes. Originally a single line, “Can wisdom
                        be put in a silver rod or love in a golden bowl” (deleted from <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> 8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 815), these questions occur
                        in Tiriel’s final venting of rage against his father. The anger
                        expressed by Tiriel against power supported by a hypocritical religion is a
                        familiar theme in Blake’s work. Here Tiriel questions the
                        universalizing myth of “Thy God of love thy heaven of joy”
                        (del., <hi rend="i">E</hi> 815) invoked by a natural religion which turns
                        Tiriel into a serpent. As a child, Tiriel claims that he was not given
                        nourishment and milk by his mother, and that his father scourged him into
                        weak infant sorrow. This treatment bred hypocrisy—“the idiots
                        wisdom &amp; the wise mans folly” (del., <hi rend="i">E</hi> 815).
                        Elizabeth Stieg identifies Tiriel as a false prophet, “one who speaks
                        in God’s name to tyrannize over others” (296). Tiriel is
                        brought to that hypocritical and limiting religion which Blake elsewhere
                        identifies as feminine: “Compelld to pray repugnant &amp; to humble
                        the immortal spirit / Till I am subtil as a serpent in paradise”
                        (8.23-24, <hi rend="i">E</hi><pb id="p30-88" n="88"/> 285). I suggest the transformation into a serpent
                        that Tiriel undergoes is identical to Blake’s intention in the
                        drawing of a serpent at the end of Thel.</p>
          <p>When Tiriel asks “Can wisdom be put in a silver rod or love in a
                        golden bowl,” he appears to allude to his father’s scourging
                        “off all youthful fantasies” (8.18, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 285)
                        and to the replacement of his mother’s milk and nourishment
                        presumably by food served in a dish. As a metaphor extending Tiriel’s
                        personal experience, the silver rod and golden cup have wider reference to
                        abusive political and religious authorities which can be identified with the
                        sceptre and the chalice. Blake’s condemnation and linking of King and
                        Priest occur throughout his work. For instance, in “The Chimney
                        Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, Blake connects
                        “God &amp; his Priest &amp; King / Who make up a heaven of our
                        misery” (11-12, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 23). This identification is also
                        seen clearly in the alliance between the Archbishop and the sceptre-wielding
                        King in <hi rend="i">The French Revolution.</hi> Tiriel thus inquires
                        whether wisdom can come from a silver sceptre and if love can be found in a
                        golden chalice. The gold and silver symbolize the hypocrisy with which these
                        symbols are overlaid. In particular, the image of the golden bowl is
                        striking since it recalls the Eucharistic cup representing Christ’s
                        sacrificial offering. But the golden chalice of a wealthy and selfish church
                        in the face of poverty creates an image of contradiction. While wisdom and
                        love are declared, their opposite is evinced. Gold and precious jewels are
                        used in the same way in “I saw a chapel all of gold.” Just as
                        Tiriel is transformed into a serpent, this chapel breeds a serpent who
                        vomits “his poison out / On the bread &amp; on the wine”
                        (13-14, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 467).</p>
          <p>I suggest that we read Thel as a type of the Female Will, and, as such, as a
                        metaphor for the limiting natural religion enforced by priest and king.
                        Thel’s name is itself a Greek pun on <hi rend="i">female</hi>
                        (thel)and <hi rend="i">will</hi> (thel).<ref target="n28" type="note">1</ref> Susan Fox argues that in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> Blake depicts a
                        feminine failure which <q> foreshadows the genderless failure of active
                            desire Blake will develop in later poems: in the context of his other
                            works Thel suggests not just the frailty of women, but the
                            “feminine” frailty of all human beings. In <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794), engraved five years after the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> songs and <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, female characters
                            represent not only the darker propensities Blake feared in women, but
                            the technically genderless tyrannies of nature and religion as well.
                            (511) </q> In later works, Blake consolidates his idea of Female Will
                        and develops it in an explicit opposition to an active Will. While there is
                        no male Will in this early poem, Blake depicts in Thel the attributes that
                        he will later give to the separated female emanation. <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">1</hi> E. B. Murray draws attention to the popular
                            contemporary recognition of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> as Greek for <hi rend="i">woman</hi> after the publication in 1780-81 of Martin
                            Madan’s notorious polemic, <hi rend="i">Thelyphthora</hi> (see
                            esp. 276 and n4).</note></p>
          <p>Foster Damon draws our attention to two traditional ways of understanding
                        Thel. While Damon argues that Thel’s fear of maturation and
                        motherhood is an “obvious” interpretation of the poem, he also
                        suggests that Thel represents a soul fearful of entering the world and
                        hypothesizes that the <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> is an elegy for a
                        possible stillborn child of the Blakes.<ref target="n29" type="note">2</ref>
                        In either case, Damon contends that Thel never reappears in any of
                        Blake’s later poetry, either because she is “far too nice a
                        girl” (<hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> 401) or because the poem lacks a
                        universal application since “most souls do not refuse to be
                        born” (“Blake and Milton” 94). In contrast to Damon, I
                        argue that we do see a reincarnation of Thel in Blake’s development
                        of a fearful Female Will. The “Thel” who reappears is the one
                        who corresponds to the first interpretation of Thel acknowledged by Damon to
                        be obvious, but I place a more sinister interpretation on this girl who is
                        “too nice.” In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Los’s
                        thunderous query, “O Albion why didst thou a Female Will
                        Create?” (56.43, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 206), is uttered in response to
                        the Albion women’s declaration of timidity: “We Women tremble
                        at the light therefore: hiding fearful/The Divine Vision with Curtain &amp;
                        Veil &amp; fleshly Tabernacle” (56.39-40, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 206).
                        The women’s statement of prohibitive fear recalls the near final
                        lines of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>: “Why a tender curb upon the youthful
                        burning boy! / Why a little curtain of flesh on the bed of our
                        desire?” (6.19-20, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 6). Limited by her mortality,
                        Thel separates herself from her fellow creatures and, by refusing to give,
                        she becomes symbolic of self-oriented religion. <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Damon finds support for this hypothesis in what he contends
                            is yet another allusion to a miscarriage in Los’s words to the
                            Albion women in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: <q> To the golden Loom of
                                Love! to the moth-labourd Woof<lb/> A Garment and Cradle weaving for
                                the infantine Terror:<lb/> For fear; at entering the gate into our
                                World of cruel<lb/> Lamentation: it flee back &amp; hide in
                                Non-Entitys dark wild.<lb/> (56.13-16, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 206) </q>
                            Damon makes this argument in <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (401)
                            and “Blake and Milton” (94).</note></p>
          <p>Rather than seeing an infinite world, Thel is bound by death, wanting to
                        “hear the voice / Of him that walketh in the garden in the evening
                        time” (1.14, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). In Genesis, when God is heard
                        walking in the garden in the evening time, Adam and Eve hide themselves
                        because they have disobeyed, and then God curses them with their own
                        mortality: “for dust thou art, and unto dust shalt thou
                        return” (Genesis 3:19). The voice which speaks in the garden is
                        punitive and utters death; Thel desires to be bound by this voice which
                        insists on mortality.</p>
          <p>Some recent critics read Thel in a positive light and see in her a rebellious
                        female—a type of proto-feminist, years beyond Mary
                            Wollstonecraft.<ref target="n30" type="note">3</ref> Applauding
                        Thel’s refusal to <pb id="p30-89" n="89"/> submit to masculine
                        demands, sexual or otherwise, they suggest that Blake approved of Thel. It
                        is important, however, to distinguish a feminist sympathy with Thel from
                        Blake’s attitude, and I would avoid the danger of falsely attributing
                        a feminist agenda to Blake. Blake’s work is not written in support of
                        the 1990s hard won recognition of a woman’s right to say <hi rend="i">no</hi>, but rather identifies the nay-saying virgin with natural
                        religion. Alicia Ostriker’s comment that “Thel is selfish, and
                        a coward” (151), while not representative of most current feminist
                        readings of Thel’s actions, is probably closer to Blake’s own
                        reading of his creation. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">3</hi> For example,
                                Gerda Norvig argues,
                            <p>For despite the evidence that Blake later on adopted a revisionary
                                form of these same Christian ideals, my contention is that in <hi rend="i">this</hi> text he represented and endorsed a liminal
                                view of the desiring self for the purpose of critiquing a philosophy
                                detrimental to the energies of real women even as it served the
                                so-called feminine values of an empirical, deistical patriarchal
                                order. (271)</p></note></p>
          <p>Throughout the book, images identify Thel as a parody or false Christ. In the
                        frontispiece, Thel is depicted as a shepherdess without sheep. Originally
                        she is not without a caring role, but like the leaders of the church or
                        false prophets, she is a false shepherd and abandons her sheep. In each of
                        the illustrations, Thel does not act, but merely presents a formal imitation
                        of her interlocutors’ activities. In the second plate, the lily bows
                        deeply because she is weighed down by her fruit—representing her
                        generative powers and her gifts. Thel, in contrast, engages in a shallow
                        ritual bow. While the cloud in plate 4 spreads his arms to drop his
                        moisture, Thel spreads her arms over the baby worm at a safe distance from
                        which she can give nothing to him. David Erdman comments that in plate 5
                        Thel “almost makes a cradle of her arms” (39). This empty
                        cradle parodies the clod of clay lying on the ground and perhaps playing
                        with the baby. Thel is like a golden bowl, for like it, she is a
                        hypocritical imitation of loving kindness. While Thel does eventually enter
                        the earth, she does not engage experience; she only observes, listens and
                        then flees.</p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, the verses concerning the silver rod and golden
                        bowl are preceded by two other questions: “Does the Eagle know what
                        is in the pit? / Or wilt thou go ask the Mole” (i.1-2, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). The reference to the Mole, in connection with gold and
                        silver symbols of religion and authority, recalls the only mole who appears
                        in the Bible. Because of Blake’s immersion in the Bible’s
                        prophetic books, this passage in Isaiah should be viewed as an important,
                        though previously neglected, intertext: <q> And they shall go into the holes
                            of the rocks, and into the caves of the earth, for fear of the Lord, and
                            for the glory of his majesty, when he ariseth to shake terribly the
                            earth. In that day a man shall cast his <hi rend="i">idols of
                                silver</hi>, and his <hi rend="i">idols of gold</hi>, which they
                            made each one for himself to worship, to the moles and to the bats.
                            (Isaiah 2:19-20; my emphasis) </q> This passage speaks of powerful
                        leaders taking refuge in the ground when “the day of the Lord”
                        comes and of their realization that their limiting natural religion is not
                        large enough. In particular, “The Lord will enter into judgement with
                        the ancients of his people, and the princes thereof: for ye have eaten up
                        the vineyard; the spoil of the poor is in your houses” (Isaiah 3:14).
                        Thel’s visit to the caves of the earth is prompted by a personal fear
                        of death or her own “day of the Lord” rather than a universal
                        and apocalyptic one, but in these caves she also encounters terror in the
                        face of insistent and unrelenting questioning. The silver and gold
                        idols—the silver sceptre which pretends to wisdom, but really is a
                        sign of self serving power, and the gold chalice which symbolizes not love,
                        but self-love—are undermined by the questions which are asked.</p>
          <p>The series of questions emphasizes Thel’s dependence on her eyes and
                        ears—her mortal senses. They query the bounds placed on love. In
                        contrast to the motto’s silver rod, Isaiah introduces a rod which is
                        not limited and bound, and which will contain wisdom: “there shall
                        come forth a rod out of the stem of Jesse . . . And the Spirit of the Lord
                        shall rest upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding” (Isaiah
                        11:1-2). In contrast to Thel whose “Ear cannot be closed to its own
                        destruction/ Or the glistning Eye to the poison of a smile” (6.11-12,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 6), he “shall not judge after the sight of
                        his eyes, neither reprove after the hearing of his ears” (Isaiah
                        11:3). Thel, however, is concerned with self, and she will not face the
                        challenge posed by the questions which she encounters under the earth.
                        Rather than entering into an active love which will confront natural
                        religion, she flees. Thel attempts to escape her own mortality by entering
                        the holes of the earth, but eventually she opts to return to her own
                        enclosing, safe and dissembling world.</p>
          <p>Donald Pearce argues that Thel’s mistake was to have inquired of moles
                        rather than eagles. He comments that the lily, the cloud, and the clod only
                        encourage Thel towards a limiting natural religion since they do not have
                        prophetic and spiritual vision. Similarly, Gerda Norvig asserts that
                        Thel’s “represented desire for a real female subjectivity is
                        meant to undermine the powerful calls from her interlocutors to embrace a
                        philosophy of repetitive and uncreative self sacrifice” (271). But
                        the poem actually suggests that none of the characters of whom Thel inquires
                        feels limited by their activities. All see their work within a wider and
                        infinite spiritual framework: the lily looks towards eternal vales; the
                        cloud lives on though vanishing to mortal sight; and the clod has an eternal
                        crown. While these creatures are not bound by their physicality, Thel, in
                        contrast, by engaging in imitative gestures, places herself under mortal
                        bounds and within the “same dull round” (<hi rend="i">There is
                            No Natural Religion</hi>, b, IV, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 2) so loathed by
                        Blake.</p>
          <pb id="p30-90" n="90"/>
          <p>Each of the creatures encountered by Thel—the lily, the cloud and the
                        clod—is initiated into love. As Michael Ferber points out, the lily
                        and the clod become brides of Christ while the cloud is united with the dew.
                        The lily is visited from heaven, and the clod is bound with “his
                        nuptial bands” (5, 2, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 5). Ferber argues that the
                        cloud’s marriage, although more oblique, also suggests a transcendent
                        marriage to God (45-48). Thel, however, remains a virgin and refuses to
                        enter into this bridal role. The <hi rend="i">Bride of Christ</hi> is a
                        title which the church claims for itself,<ref target="n31" type="note">4</ref> but Blake’s assessment of official religion suggests
                        that the church has not actually fulfilled this role. Likewise, Thel
                        imitates love, but does not love. This false pretense reminds us of
                        Tiriel’s self-description: “subtil as a serpent” (8.37,
                            <hi rend="i">E</hi> 285). In order to achieve his ends he must
                        dissimulate. Is this also the meaning of the enigmatic serpent at the end of
                        Thel? As commentators have noted, Thel is not the child riding the serpent.
                        Her disappearance from the illustration suggests the possibility that she,
                        like Tiriel, has been transformed into a serpent. Eugenie Freed argues that
                        the children riding the serpent may represent the lady and her two brothers
                        from <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> If Thel is understood to represent the moral
                        law, then this identification is apt. Thel, as the moral law, carries the
                        three children on her serpent-back. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See
                            Ephesians 5:31-32.</note></p>
          <p>By employing in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> the pair of enigmatic questions from
                        the deleted section in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, Blake is able to take
                        advantage of their wide allusive potential in the new setting. Rod and cup
                        are clearly sexual images, and the magician of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> is
                        recalled. The silver cord and golden bowl, symbols of mortality from
                        Ecclesiastes, become important in the context of Thel’s preoccupation
                        with death. But Blake also uses the image of rod and bowl, as sceptre and
                        chalice, in order to introduce Thel as a metaphor for a hypocritical and
                        limiting religion. Thel’s refusal to engage in an active giving role
                        becomes clear as the depictions of her imitative and inactive stance
                        progress throughout the poem. Her transformation into the serpent finally
                        confirms her identity as Thel—<hi rend="i">Female Will.</hi></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Damon, Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of
                                William Blake.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves. Rev. ed. Hanover: University
                            Press of New England, 1988.</p>
            <p>—. “Blake and Milton.” <hi rend="i">The Divine
                                Vision: Studies in the Poetry and Art of William Blake born November
                                28th, 1757.</hi> Ed. Vivian de Sola Pinto. London: Victor Gollancz,
                            1957. 89-96.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
                                William Blake.</hi> Newly rev. ed. Garden City, NY: Anchor
                            Press/Doubleday, 1982.</p>
            <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake: William Blake’s
                                Complete Works with a Plate-by-Plate Commentary.</hi> Garden City,
                            NY: Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1974.</p>
            <p>Ferber, Michael. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and the
                            Bride of Christ.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 9 (1980):
                            45-56.</p>
            <p>Fox, Susan. “The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s
                            Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 3 (1977): 507-19.</p>
            <p>Freed, Eugenie. “‘Sun-Clad Chastity’ and
                            Blake’s ‘Maiden Queens’” <hi rend="i">Comus,
                                Thel</hi>, and ‘The Angel.’” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 25 (1991-92): 104-16</p>
            <p>Murray, E.B. “Thel, <hi rend="i">Thelyphthora</hi>, and the
                            Daughters of Albion.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 20
                            (1981): 275-97.</p>
            <p>Norvig, Gerda. “Female Subjectivity and the Desire of Reading
                            In(to) Blake’s Book of Thel.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Romanticism</hi> 34 (1995): 255-71.</p>
            <p>Ostriker, Alicia. <hi rend="i">Vision and Verse in William Blake.</hi>
                            Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1965.</p>
            <p>Pearce, Donald. “Natural Religion and the Plight of Thel.”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 8 (1978): 23-35.</p>
            <p>Stieg, Elizabeth. “Reinterpreting the Old Testament:
                            Blake’s Tiriel as Prophet.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Romanticism</hi> 29 (1990): 273-96.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Seduction of Self-Abnegation in <hi rend="i">The Book of
                                Thel</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Deborah <name>McCollister</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In his 1961 analysis of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Thel</hi> and Tiriel, critic Peter F. Fisher comments: <q> Thel is
                            represented as a woman because she succumbs to mortality in a feminine
                            way—that is to say, passively—by a retreat into
                            wish-fulfilling fantasy. Tiriel is represented as a man because he
                            succumbs in a masculine way, and actively pursues the lure of tyrannical
                            power. . . . Both lose themselves—Tiriel by the path of tyranny,
                            and Thel by the way of suicide. She gives way to the indolence which
                            refuses to desire a human life, and he gives way to that aggression
                            which fails to understand and realize it. (206) </q></p>
          <p>In these characterizations, Fisher’s assignment of gender traits is
                        intriguing: “the feminine way” is “passive,” and
                        Thel’s refusal to enter human life is attributed to
                            “indolence.”<ref target="n32" type="note">1</ref>
                        Similarly, despite his revolutionary spirit, William Blake reflected his
                        culture—one that believed woman’s essential worth lay in her
                        ability to procreate and nourish others.<ref target="n33" type="note">2</ref> As Thel searches to discover meaning in the vapor <pb id="p30-91" n="91"/>
						<supplied type="emend">of mortal life, personified natural elements demonstrate</supplied> 
						to her their own worth in the life cycle, a worth
                        achieved through self-abnegation. My purpose here is not simply to translate
                        the myth of Thel, but rather to discuss arguments for a mortal life of
                        self-abnegation as presented in <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi><note id="n32"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Interestingly, in a 1989 assessment of
                                <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, Paul Youngquist says that
                                “<hi rend="i">an adolescent fear</hi> of sexual experience. .
                            .precipitates the denial of life” [emphasis mine] in <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi> On the other hand, Urizen withdraws from eternity due to
                            “something in the organization of the mind itself, some <hi rend="i">principle of self-preservation</hi> that paradoxically
                            wills death rather than submit to the contingencies of existence”
                            [emphasis mine] (90).</note><note id="n33"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Contemporary handbooks exhorted young
                            ladies to sweetly accept their roles “of servitude to masculine
                            desires and expectations” (Eaves et al. 80).</note></p>
          <p>Since the name “Thel” is derived from the Greek word for
                        “will” or “desire,” the implications for
                        Thel’s characterization are manifold. Some readers might see her as
                        willful, while others might attribute her name to the desire for knowledge
                        about life that motivates her.<ref target="n34" type="note">3</ref> At any
                        rate, early in the poem, Blake presents her as ripe for seduction from the
                        safe Vales of Har, which Foster Damon defines as “the state of
                        Self-love” (401). Her motto (i.1-4, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) reveals
                        her desire to know—but only from secondhand sources at first. A. G.
                        Den Otter, who classifies the forms of questions in <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Thel</hi>, observes that on the title page, the plate contains a bud
                        that “slithers up to her knee,” suggesting the temptation of
                        Eve (646). The motto “hooks Thel’s interest, managing
                        successfully to guide her to the altar of sacrifice” (647).
                        Blake’s pictures of Thel present her as an adolescent; her incessant
                        questions in the motto and throughout the work likewise convey a childish
                        and innocent nature.<ref target="n35" type="note">4</ref> In her innocence,
                        she seeks to know what is in the pit, just as the Eagle and the Mole know,
                        but she trusts a predator and a blind, limited creature for her answers. Her
                        questions about Wisdom and Love, with their respective containers, a rod and
                        a bowl, suggest her naive eagerness to explore a contained, mortal life. But
                        in her innocence, she does not realize that both containers represent the
                        necessity of procreation in the cycle of mortal existence. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Michael Ferber identifies many of the names in
                            the poem by showing connections with other Blakean works and myths
                            outside Blake; at the same time, he postulates that Blake may have
                            alluded to traditional myths only to make fresh suggestions from those
                            associations.</note><note id="n35"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
                            Joseph Viscomi point to Blake’s “subtle uses of the
                            interrogative [in his illuminated books] as a way to confound common
                            assumptions, suggest alternatives, and engage the reader’s
                            imagination” (14).</note></p>
          <p>Thel is also ripe for seduction because of her willingness to separate from
                        her sisters, while not knowing who she is. The other Daughters of Mne
                        Seraphim know their place—tending the flocks (1.5, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). Their dwelling, The Vales of Har, receives more attention in
                        Blake’s complementary work, <hi rend="i">Tiriel.</hi> It is a
                        peaceful valley, ruled by the senile Har and his sister/wife, Heva, who
                        “dwell in an extreme and childish old age, tended by Mnetha”
                        (their mother/nurse). Har is “the God of Moral Law” who holds
                        to “uninspired wisdom to enforce restrictive morality upon
                        man.” In fact, the dotard himself has authored the code (Sloss and
                        Wallis 275-76). Although this pastoral setting offers relative safety, Thel
                        is restless.</p>
          <p>Thel’s description of herself reveals another problem that contributes
                        to her vulnerability to seduction: although she is essentially selfish, she
                        does not possess identity. Refering to lines 10-18, Nelson Hilton observes:
                        “Thel displays an essential aspect of lamentation: not going
                        anywhere, not standing firm, but assimilating everything to its vision.
                        Narcissus-like, lamentation centers on itself and so defeats its
                        fulfillment” (30). Her description of herself in comparison to
                        objects—typical of Blake’s intentional
                        ambiguity—further reveals a female who does not realize her essence.
                        While she bemoans her destiny—should she be born—she first
                        compares herself with “a wat’ry bow” (1.8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). Such an object is beautiful, but exists only because of the
                        light. “A parting cloud” (1.8, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) collects
                        life-giving moisture, as Blake mentions later, but paradoxically, its
                        absence is usually heralded by humans since it obscures the favored
                        sunshine. “A reflection in a glass” is only a representation
                        of the real object, just as “shadows in the water” (1.9, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) are not solid entities and can change with the
                        ripples of the waves. The “dreams of infants” are not actual
                        events; even their smiles (1.10, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3) are pointless,
                        since, as she has lamented earlier, they are “born but to smile
                        &amp; fall” (1.7, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). As she continues to
                        catalog transient forms, the ambiguities continue. A “dove’s
                        voice” is sweet, but mournful; “transient day”
                        enlightens, but grows dark; “music in the air” may be either
                        joyful or funereal (1.11, <hi rend="i">E</hi> 3). In brief, even after Thel
                        has described herself, we know that she will fade, but we do not know how or
                        if the world will change when she does.</p>
          <p>Finally, Thel may be easily seduced into the mortal world because she is
                        ignorant of the harshness outside the Vales of Har. She uses
                        “gentle” (ll. 16-17) to describe the act of dying/rebirth and
                        the euphemism “sleep of death”; however, the vision she later
                        experiences in the land of the dead (plate 8) shatters these expectations.
                        Similarly, her expectations of “him that walketh in the garden in the
                        evening time” (l. 18) reveal her naivete. Genesis 3:8 uses this
                        phrase immediately after the fall of Adam and Eve and immediately before God
                        reprimands the pair and casts them out of the Garden of Eden. Ironically,
                        the voice she later hears in the land unknown is her own “voice of
                        sorrow” (l. 117).</p>
          <p>Blake has thus created a naive woman who asks questions restlessly, refuses
                        to accept her place in the Vales of Har passively, sees herself only in
                        vague terms, and expects to be treated consistently with gentleness.
                        Moreover, the Lilly, the Cloud, the Worm, and the Clay each attempts to
                        seduce Thel into mortal existence by appealing to her most outstanding
                        characteristic—her need to have a unique and lasting place in the
                        universe. In addition to the lines with which she has described her
                        transience (II. 12-15), an echoing refrain is formed by such lines as the
                        following: “I vanish from my pearly throne, and who shall find my
                        place?” (l. 41). “I complain, and no one hears my
                        voice” (l. 51). “And all shall say, ‘Without a use this
                        shining woman liv’d’” (l. 69). Morris Eaves, Robert
                        Essick, and Joseph Viscomi aptly note that “<hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Thel</hi> is Blake’s version of Ecclesiastes, with an innocent
                        woman substituted for the melancholy patriarch for whom ‘all is
                        vanity’” (78).</p>
          <pb id="p30-92" n="92"/>
          <p>Thel’s primal need, then, to feel significant in the universe, is
                        itself universal and thus common to both genders. Mindful of the culture of
                        Blake’s day, one can easily speculate as to the solutions the four
                        natural beings would have offered a young male in Thel’s state of
                        mind: perhaps that he win a battle, or make his voice eternal through poetic
                        expression, or accomplish some other substantial feat. However, the male
                        Cloud, the male Worm, the female Lilly, and the female Clay offer her
                        eternal life in exchange for what she can give to the earth in spite of, and
                        because of, her feminine gender. As Den Otter comments: “Rather than
                        satisfying Thel’s concern for the meaning of things, these small
                        educators [he mentions all but the Worm] redirect her focus to the <hi rend="i">use</hi> of things” (640).</p>
          <p>An examination of the designs highlights the consequential tensions: In some,
                        Thel “responds to her companions with imitative or sympathetic
                        gestures [see pls. 4 and 6], much as she speaks about her similarity to
                        them” (Eaves et al. 81). This very tendency to imitate and identify
                        with her potential seducers is thus in conflict with her reluctance to
                        acquiesce to their definition of her role, as is evident in plate 2, where
                        “she stands apart as a spatial expression of her separateness and
                        role as an observer more than an actor” (Eaves et al. 81).</p>
          <p>The Lilly of the valley is the first entity to address Thel’s problem.
                        Quite simply, she suggests that Thel imitate her by sacrificing herself and
                        accepting the cycle of life passively and even thankfully. Not only does the
                        Lilly accept her lowly position, but she loves it (ll. 19-21). The Lilly,
                        “So weak, the gilded butterfly scarce perches on [her] head”
                        (l. 22), is like Thel in that she is a virgin (l. 31). But she gives herself
                        to everything around her and rejoices to do so because “he that
                        smiles on all” has told her to do so (ll. 23-25). She is
                        “clothed in light” (l. 27) only to be melted later in the heat
                        produced by the light (l. 28). She will dwell in “eternal
                        vales” (l. 29) that are fertile, but remain in the place of
                        death.</p>
          <p>Thel sees irony in the Lilly’s gift of self. The bloom that makes her
                        beautiful and sweet-smelling attracts the innocent lamb, who devours her
                        while she “sittest smiling in his face, / Wiping his . . .
                        mouth” (ll. 36). But Thel admires the power that the Lilly’s
                        gift includes—the power to purify, revive, and tame, while being
                        consumed (ll. 37-39). The last line about the Lilly reinforces her role as
                        nurturer/giver: “[She] went to mind her numerous charge among the
                        verdant grass” (l. 47).</p>
          <p>Swinburne said that the Lilly, Cloud, and Worm teach that “the secret
                        of creation is sacrifice; the very act of growth is a sacrament . . . each
                        thing is redeemed from perpetual death by perpetual change” (quoted
                        in Sloss and Wallis 2:267). Thel is impressed by the flower, but is not
                        comforted and is not seduced quite yet into sacrificing herself. She has
                        seen the example, but still laments her own uselessness (Bloom 56).</p>
          <p>Compared with the obsequious female Lilly, the Cloud—a male
                        figure—is quite bold and impressive. His “golden head”
                        and “bright form” hover and “glitter” over Thel
                        as he addresses her, and the import of the Cloud’s exhortation to
                        Thel lies in its sexual meaning. The Cloud supplies the moisture for the
                        rivers where Luvah’s horses drink. In other Blakean mythology, Luvah
                        is the “mythical embodiment of the passional and sexual aspect of man
                        [who] repairs to the Vales of Har simply in order to rest and water his
                        horses” (Abrams 64). The Cloud seems to feel important largely
                        because he serves a god of eros.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, seeing Thel’s need to be significant in eternity, the
                        Cloud describes his union with the dew and what it produces. He makes Thel
                        identify with the female dew, whom he calls a “weeping virgin”
                        (l. 61). After all, Thel’s “gentle lamentation falls like
                        morning dew” (l. 9). The Cloud’s lofty language describes the
                        union explicitly: “And [I] court the fair-eyed dew to take me to her
                        shining tent: / The weeping virgin, trembling, kneels before the risen sun,
                        / Till we arise link’d in a golden band and never part, / But walk
                        united, bearing food to all our tender flowers” (ll. 60-63). In other
                        words, the dew is seduced into an ecstatic experience, she is never alone
                        again, and—most importantly—her ability to nurture tender
                        flowers is validation for her being. The Cloud thus suggests that if Thel
                        would yield herself to her proper function, she too could have the joy of
                        fruitful existence.</p>
          <p>Thel, however, recognizing that she has never nurtured, remains depressed
                        (ll. 64-68). She asks the Cloud what she intends as a rhetorical question:
                        “Or did [Thel] only live to be at death the food of worms?”
                        (l. 70). Echoing the heavenly being who has earlier told the Lilly to
                        rejoice in her ephemeral state (l. 25), the Cloud instructs Thel relative to
                        the “blessing” of the Worm (l. 73). Just before the Cloud goes
                        to find “his partner in the vale” (l. 78), he reminds her:
                        “Everything that lives / Lives not alone nor for itself” (ll.
                        73-74). But before she can be useful, Thel must abandon her fear of the
                        Worm. Brenda S. Webster acknowledges that critics often overlook “the
                        implicit degradation and forced submission of the woman. . . . In the
                        speeches of both Thel and the Cloud, the theme of degradation is condensed
                        in the opposition of high and low, shining virgin and earth worm”
                        (52).</p>
          <p>The thought of the Worm—associated symbolically with both death and
                        procreation—frightens the virgin Thel. So the Cloud shows her a worm
                        that will woo her without frightening her. Appearing as a naked, helpless
                        infant, the Worm immediately appeals to her repressed maternalism (Bloom
                        57). She speaks to it, but it can only weep in return (ll. 80-84). Of
                        course, these cries touch her more than any of the speeches she has heard
                        previously. The worm’s seductive powers are so strong that,
                        ironically, she sympathizes with the very entity that will devour her.</p>
          <pb id="p30-93" n="93"/>
          <p>The Clod of Clay that appears and nourishes the infant worm further arouses
                        Thel’s maternal drive and her search for significance. Modeling
                        self-sacrifice, the Clay exhales “her life. . ./In milky
                        fondness” (ll. 86-87). Her first words to Thel exhort the ideals of
                        sacrificial motherhood: “we live not for ourselves” (l. 88).
                        Moreover, the Clay describes a relationship derived from the account in
                        Genesis of the creation of man in which God began the human race by forming
                        Adam from clay and breathing into him the breath of life. Though a humble
                        entity, the Clay has gained eternity by joining God and bearing His
                        children: “My bosom of itself is cold, and of itself is dark; / But
                        he, that loves the lowly, pours his oil upon my head, / And kisses me, and
                        binds his nuptial bands around my breast, / And says: ‘Thou mother of
                        my children, I have loved thee, / And I have given thee a crown that none
                        can take away’” (ll. 90-94). The Clay does not understand this
                        relationship; she simply lives and loves (l. 96). Thus, the Clay models the
                        following message for Thel: Accept your role on earth, and do not
                        question.</p>
          <p>In plate 7, Thel’s hidden face suggests the loss of identity implicit
                        in maternal sacrifice, and as she cries again, she wipes her tears on her
                        white veil (l. 97). Blake is apparently playing upon the phrase “vale
                        of tears,” for the virgin draws closer here to a vision of the end of
                        life. Ironically, she cries to learn that God cares for the worm (l. 100),
                        but the glimpse she soon receives of her ultimate destiny as a mortal
                        reveals no benevolent God. The Worm and the Clay present danger for Thel,
                        although they appear as innocent entities coming to the aid of a wandering
                        innocent. Note, however, how the Clay’s appeal to Thel gradually
                        evolves from an invitation, to a suggestion, to a command: “Wilt
                        thou, O Queen, enter my house? ’Tis given thee to enter / And to
                        return: fear nothing, enter with thy virgin feet” (ll. 106-07). The
                        last line is deceitful: Thel has much to fear because she is indeed a
                        vulnerable virgin.</p>
          <p>The Clod of Clay, who has modeled benevolent motherhood and told Thel about a
                        benevolent God, is able to bring her to the brink of mortal
                        experience—but only with the condition that the virgin can return to
                        the vales of Har (l. 107). Here at last Thel sees her destiny: After
                        entering earthly existence, she will indeed be eternal, but eternally dying,
                        mournful, and—despite her usefulness as mate and mother—alone.
                        Simply put, her sacrifice (in following the example of the female Lilly,
                        dew, and Clay) will not bring her eternal peace. The intention of the Clay
                        (and Blake) is ambiguous here. Although the Clay has seduced her into a
                        terrible place, the revelation of that place allows Thel to know the truth
                        and to reject her destiny on earth.</p>
          <p>In the “land unknown” (l. 109), Thel witnesses the corrupted
                        forms of two of her advisors. Before, the Cloud was “golden,”
                        “bright,” and “glittering” (ll. 52-53), but the
                        “land of clouds” is dark and foreboding (l. 113). The dew had
                        once united with the Cloud, to “never part” and to bear food
                        (ll. 62-63). Here the dew rests on graves (l. 114). These ironies have been
                        foreshadowed, however, as early as on plate 2, where a vine “forms a
                        traditional emblem of marriage or education” but in outline also
                        suggests a tombstone, and the figure of Thel observes two other figures,
                        either in a moment of happy union or of rape, thus symbolizing Thel’s
                        own uncertainties about sexuality (Eaves et al. 81-82).</p>
          <p>For the first time in the poem, Thel dares to listen to her own voice, now
                        coming from her grave (ll. 116-17). It laments the sorrowful fact that her
                        senses have “whirled her to destruction” (Bloom 61). The
                        sensory images gradually grow darker and more sexual. The first sensory
                        organ mentioned is the Ear (l. 118). After all, she has listened to
                        others’ voices. Brenda Webster observes: “A further image of
                        the ear as a whirlpool that fiercely ‘draws creation in’ is
                        linked to the Clod’s womb-grave and foreshadows Blake’s view
                        of the ravenous earth . . . who tries to draw all existence into her
                        voice” (56). Next is the Eye, and Thel asks why it cannot be closed
                        “to the poison of a smile” (ll. 118-19). This question
                        reflects the foolishness of the “pitying tears” (l. 97) that
                        once trusted the benevolence of God (ll. 98-101). Other temptations to the
                        Eye are then listed (ll. 120-22), along with the honeyed Tongue and
                        responsive Nose (ll. 123-25). Finally, the mention of touch boldly reveals a
                        daunting picture of sexual union: “a little curtain of flesh on the
                        bed of our desire”—one that can place “a tender curb
                        upon the youthful burning boy” (ll. 126-27)—is not the
                        pleasant image that the united Cloud and dew earlier suggested to Thel. She
                        learns that even in experience, she will find no fulfillment (Bloom, in
                        Erdman 809).</p>
          <p>The truth about her mortal initiation into the sexual experience has this
                        result: “The Virgin started from her seat, &amp; with a shriek /
                        Fled back unhinder’d till she came into the vales of Har” (ll.
                        129-30). Alicia Ostriker says “She discovers that her fate is far
                        worse than she imagined. Instead of merely fading away and dying gracefully,
                        she will have to undergo a storm of passions and restraints”
                        (154).</p>
          <p>Blake’s decision concerning Thel’s fate was made after at least
                        two years of incubation. Although the title page reads “1789,”
                        the same date as <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, textual critics
                        believe that plate 6 was actually completed two years later, along with <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> During this time, Blake decided that
                        Thel would wander into the “land unknown” at the Clay’s
                        invitation, but that she would lose her courage upon hearing her own voice
                        from the grave. Unlike Oothoon of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion</hi>, she does not fly to her lover (Ferber 52-53).</p>
          <p>A decade ago, G. E. Bentley, Jr. remarked upon a recently discovered sketch
                        for <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi> The sketch indicates Blake’s plan for two
                        designs facing each other, with lines indicating text. On the left is a
                        sketch of the brooding Thel that later became plate 7. On the right is a
                        figure with outstretched arms, resembling the figure of Thel later printed
                        as plate 6. Obviously, the designs were reversed for printing, and a
                        structure <pb id="p30-94" n="94"/> resembling a Greek temple was discarded
                        from above the Thel with outstretched arms, probably because this manmade
                        object distracts from the context of the pastoral setting. Bentley
                        postulates that in the early sketch, “Thel appears to be on the
                        threshold of the Temple of the Earth, about to enter without fear”
                        (139). But in the course of crafting this illustrated poem, Blake chose to
                        have Thel enter reluctantly, only to flee in fear.<ref target="n36" type="note">5</ref><note id="n36"><hi rend="s">5</hi> For a detailed discussion of the
                            controversial dating of the plates in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, see Joseph
                            Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi> 234-37 and
                            252-58.</note></p>
          <p>Critics have noted the different ages of children riding upon the serpent in
                        plate 8, suggestive of the process of maturation “in accordance with
                        the use of snakes as emblems of natural life and mortality . . . [and] in
                        the context of phallic symbolism, the design would seem to indicate a
                        control over sexual experience by playful innocence.” The reins also
                        suggest “prudence controlling desire” (Eaves et al. 85). If
                        the female driving the snake is Thel, she looks not so much frightened as
                        determined, with a steady, forward gaze. Whereas Michael Ferber posits that
                        the pictured serpent and children allude to Blake’s early play <hi rend="i">King Edward the Third</hi>, where the prince says that his
                        recklessness is like “the innocent child” who
                        “unthinking, plays upon the viper’s den” (62-63), I
                        suggest that the serpent recalls the one in Eden that tempts Eve. Unlike
                        Eve, however, Thel has harnessed and controlled the serpent and uses it to
                        take her “unhinder’d . . . [to] the vales of Har” (l.
                        129).</p>
          <p>Because she has been allowed to see the truth, the attempted seduction of
                        Thel into the cycle of a mortal woman’s life fails at last. She will
                        not surrender her haven of virginity in order to live eternally in such a
                        dark world. The sacrifice of her present self for a utilitarian, earthly
                        self would be a mistake. Disappointed by her adventurous quest away from the
                        valley, Thel chooses to live in a world governed by the dotard Har and his
                        restrictive codes, rather than enter into a mortal body, encumbered by
                        sensory temptations and death. In the vale, she faces the future of becoming
                        like the eternally aging Har and Heva in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (Ostriker
                        151).</p>
          <p>Or is her life in the Vales of Har necessarily full of dread? One critic has
                        speculated that “Thel” is an anagram of “Lethe,”
                        the river of forgetfulness. Perhaps Thel will forget her cares and become
                        more like her sisters. W. J. T. Mitchell suggests still another possibility:
                        When Thel returns to the Vales of Har and to the “Daughters of Mne
                        Seraphim,” is she returning to “a land of infantile regression
                        [with] . . . daughters of ineffectual memories (Mnemosyne) rather than
                        inspiration?” Or could the prophetic Blake be predicting an age where
                        “Daughters of Memory shall become the Daughters of
                        Inspiration?” (83). Just as Thel has raised incessant questions, the
                        conclusion of the poem and the enigmatic emblems in the illustrative plates
                        raise questions and offer few resolutions.<ref target="n37" type="note">6</ref><note id="n37"><hi rend="s">6</hi> In their edition of <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake: The Early Illuminated Books</hi>, Eaves, Essick and Viscomi
                            contextualize the ending of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, noting the outcome
                            of other female figures in Blakean works, and comparing what Thel
                            learns—or fails to learn—with the doctrines expressed in
                            Blake’s annotations to Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                                Heaven and Hell, There is No Natural Religion</hi>, the botanical
                            poems of Langhorn and Darwin, and cultural ideologies of the day
                            (80-81).</note></p>
          <p>One matter is resolved, however. Although Blake shows that Thel’s only
                        alternative to relative obscurity in the Vales of Har is for her to listen
                        to the voices of Earth that tell her to yield herself to the cycle of life,
                        he does give her a choice. With a loud shriek, his heroine, in effect, cries
                        “No!” to the experience of the earthly woman.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Works Cited</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Abrams, M. H., ed. <hi rend="i">The Norton Anthology of English
                                Literature.</hi> 3rd ed. 2 vols. New York: Norton, 1968.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “From Sketch to Text in Blake: The Case of The
                            Book of Thel.” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19 (1986): 128-41.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic
                                Argument.</hi> Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1963.</p>
            <p>Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols
                                of William Blake.</hi> Providence: Brown UP, 1965.</p>
            <p>Den Otter, A. G. “The Question and The Book of Thel.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 30 (1991):633-55.</p>
            <p>Eaves, Morris, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Early Illuminated Books.</hi> Princeton:
                            Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake.</hi> Commentary by Harold Bloom. Garden City, N.Y.:
                            Doubleday, 1965, cited hereafter as <hi rend="i">E.</hi></p>
            <p>Ferber, Michael. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Blake.</hi> London:
                            Penguin, 1991.</p>
            <p>Fisher, Peter F. <hi rend="i">The Valley of Vision: Blake as Prophet and
                                Revolutionary.</hi> Ed. Northrop Frye. Toronto: U of Toronto,
                            1961.</p>
            <p>Hilton, Nelson. <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision
                                of Words.</hi> Berkeley: U of California, 1983.</p>
            <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of
                                the Illuminated Poetry.</hi> Princeton: Princeton, 1978.</p>
            <p>Ostriker, Alicia. <hi rend="i">Vision and Verse in William Blake.</hi>
                            Madison: U of Wisconsin, 1965.</p>
            <p>Sloss, D. J. and Wallis, J. P. R. <hi rend="i">The Prophetic Writings of
                                William Blake.</hi> 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon, 1926.</p>
            <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book.</hi>
                            Princeton: Princeton UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>Webster, Brenda S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology.</hi>
                            Athens: U of Georgia, 1983.</p>
            <p>Youngquist, Paul. <hi rend="i">Madness and Blake’s Myth.</hi>
                            University Park: Pennsylvania UP, 1989.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <pb id="p30-95" n="95"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Jah Wobble Inspired by Blake</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>According to Robert Sandall in the Sunday <hi rend="i">Times</hi> for 22
                        September 1966 (<hi rend="i">The Culture</hi>, sec. 10, p. 28), rock singer
                        John Wardle, aka Jah Wobble, is a “genuine eccentric who makes up in
                        inspiration and audacity what he lacks in musical talent.” His latest
                        offering is <hi rend="i">The Inspiration of William Blake</hi> (All Saints
                        ASCD 29), which delivers up Blake’s poetry in a voice
                        “somewhere between that of a panto villain and a loquacious London
                        cabbie.” In Sandall’s opinion, Wobble’s otherwise
                        dubious performance is considerably aided by a persuasive band such that
                        “the atmospheric charm of the music consistently draws you in, even
                        while the poetry reading threatens to crack you up.” [Eds.]</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <pb id="p30-95" n="95"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Armand Hammer Museum Exhibition of the Boydell Shakespeare
                                Gallery</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The Armand Hammer Museum Exhibition of the Boydell Shakespeare Gallery will
                        open Tuesday, 14 January and run thrrough Sunday, 9 March 1997. Prints from
                        the collection of Robert N. Essick, which contains “an astonishing
                        set of the first and second state proofs,” will be displayed, and the
                        exhibition, “in contrast to the one that was sponsored by the German
                        Shakespeare Society in Bochum, Germany, last spring, will provide a stunning
                        display of the engraver’s art.”</p>
          <p>In conjunction with this exhibition, David Rodes (Director of the Grunewald
                        Center at the Armand Hammer) and Fred Burwick will offer a six-session
                        non-credit lecture series for the general public on “Boydell’s
                        Shakespeare Gallery: Shakespeare Then and Now.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0008">
      	<pb id="30-95" n="95"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">New Issue of <hi rend="i">Romanticism On the Net</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Romanticism On the Net</hi> is a peer-review electronic journal
                        entirely devoted to romantic studies. In addition to new articles and
                        reviews in each issue, the journal includes calls for papers, descriptions
                        of other academic journals, and links to other Web sites. One of the unique
                        features of the Internet is that articles and reviews from previous issues
                        are still easily accessible for consultation.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Romanticism On the Net</hi> can be accessed at the following
                        Internet address:</p>
          <p>http://users.ox.ac.uk/-scat0385</p>
          <p>US mirror site: http://www-sul.stanford.edu/mirrors/romnet/</p>
          <p>Editor: Michael Laplace-Sinatra; Assistant Editor: Michael Gamer</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0008">
      	<pb id="30-95" n="95"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Blake’s Notebook Facsimile Available</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Edward Hamilton Bookseller in Falls Village CT 06031-5000 (whole address) is
                        selling remaindered copies of the hardback edition of Blake’s
                        Notebook (ed. David V. Erdman and Donald K. Moore) for $13.95 plus $3.00
                        shipping (no matter how many you order the total shipping charge is $3.00)
                        (no tax except in CT). The stock number required is 062839. Checks only; no
                        orders by phone/credit card.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0008">
      	<pb id="30-95" n="95"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Romantic Circles Web Site</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>This is to announce a new web site for research, Romantic Circles: Byron,
                        Keats, the Shelleys and Their Contemporaries. Its prototype can be found at
                        the following URL:</p>
          <p>http://www.inform.umd.edu/RC/rc.html</p>
          <p>According to the editors, Romantic Circles is organized as a meta-resource
                        that will be openended, collaborative, and porous—maintaining and
                        encouraging many potential links to other sites on the Web. As currently
                        conceived, the site will be divided into three main entities: Electronic
                        Editions, Scholarly Resources, and Critical Exchange. The last of these will
                        include a real-time, interactive MOO, the Villa Diodati.</p>
          <p>Two general principles will guide the development of the site: “We
                        will value quality over quantity, mounting only resources produced and
                        maintained according to high scholarly standards; and we will give priority
                        to innovative, creatively-conceived resources that take advantage of the
                        electronic medium in ways that could not be duplicated easily in print. We
                        invite you to visit the site, read the prospectus, and see what we and our
                        co-editors have planned for the coming months. Romantic Circles will be
                        formally launched in November, to coincide with the NASSR conference in
                        Boston. Until then, users are welcome to watch the site develop as we
                        construct it and to try out features as they become available, including our
                        NASSR ’96 Conference pages.” [Neil Fraistat, Steve E. Jones,
                        and Donald H. Reiman, General Editors; and Carl Stahmer, Design and
                        Technical Editor.]</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0008">
      	<pb id="30-95" n="95"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">NEWSLETTER</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Call For Papers: Carolinas Symposium on British
                                Studies</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The 24th annual conference of the Carolinas Symposium on British Studies will
                        be held at Augusta State University in Augusta, Georgia on 4 and 5 October
                        1997. The Symposium provides an annual forum for the delivery of scholarly
                        presentations and the exchange of ideas relating to all aspects of British
                        Studies, including history, literature, art and architecture, government,
                        dance and music.</p>
          <p>While the Symposium is regionally based in the Southeast, participants from
                        all parts of the country are encouraged to submit proposals for individual
                        papers, full sessions, and panel discussions.</p>
          <p>We also invite submissions for the student paper session from both graduate
                        and undergraduate students, with a prize in each category.</p>
          <p>Proposals or papers should be sent to Dr. William S. Brockington, Department
                        of History, University of South Carolina at Aiken, Aiken, SC 29801 by 15
                        March 1997. Student papers, which must be complete, should be sent to Dr.
                        Jacqueline L. Gmuca, Department of English, Coastal Carolina University,
                        Conway SC 29526 by 1April 1997.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_30">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-30-3-0008">
      	<pb id="30-95" n="95"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Correction: Blake Archive</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The URL for the Blake Archive given in the last issue was incorrect.</p>
          <p>The correct address is:</p>
          <p>http://jefferson.village.virginia.edu/blake</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
