<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <idno>Emend</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Emendations</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <respStmt>
              <principal/>
              <resp>Emendations by:</resp>
              <name>Adam McCune</name>
              <name>Ashley Reed</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
      <editionstmt/>
      <publicationStmt/>
      <seriesstmt/>
      <notesstmt/>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingdesc/>
    <profiledesc/>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <head>
      <title>The following emendations have been made to all issues in this digital edition:</title>
    </head>
    <p>Whenever possible, the halftone images that appeared in the print edition of <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> have been replaced with full-color JPEG images color-corrected by the editors and staff of the William Blake Archive. Where color images are not available, halftone images from the print journal have been scanned and incorporated into this digital edition.</p>
    <p>When an image that appears in this digital edition of <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> also appears in the William Blake Archive, the image caption includes a link to the relevant digital edition at www.blakearchive.org.</p>
    <p>Most images in the print edition include location designations: "above," "below," "facing page," etc. In this digital edition all images appear inline and centered, with captions immediately beneath the images. Location designations have thus been removed.</p>
    <p>The print edition often included cover images of books reviewed. In most cases these images have not been retained in this digital edition.</p>
    <p>Advertisements that appeared in the print edition have not been reproduced in this digital edition.</p>
    <p>Notes which appeared as footnotes in the print edition have been converted to endnotes in this digital edition.</p>
    <p>The editors of this digital edition have made no effort to confirm the accuracy of URL's, email addresses, or mailing addresses, which have been reproduced just as they appeared in the print edition and may be incorrect or out of date.</p>
  </text>
  <head>
    <title>The following emendations have been made to particular issues in this digital edition:</title>
  </head>
  <text type="special">
    <div1 id="042-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 42, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="042-04" target="p116">page 116</ref>: The print edition of this issue asserts that color images of all illustrations in the article "Blake in the Marketplace, 2008" are available at the <ref type="ext" target="http://blake.lib.rochester.edu/blakeojs/index.php/blake"><hi rend="i">BIQ</hi> subscription site</ref>. These images are no longer available, so this note has been removed.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="042-03">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 42, Issue 3</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="042-03" target="p84">page 84</ref>: The print edition of this issue asserts that additional illustrations for the article "'This Extraordinary Performance': William Blake’s Use of Gold and Silver in the Creation of His Paintings and Illuminated Books" are available at the <ref type="ext" target="http://blake.lib.rochester.edu/blakeojs/index.php/blake"><hi rend="i">BIQ</hi> subscription site</ref>. These additional illustrations have been moved to the <ref type="html-issue" issue="toc-bonus">Bonus Content</ref> page in the online edition, so the note has been revised to reflect the new location. For the subset of these images which appeared in the print edition in halftone, we have included the color versions of the images in the online edition in place of the halftone print images.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="041-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 41, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="041-04" target="p140">page 140</ref> and following: The print edition of this issue asserts that color images of prints from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy Y are available at the <ref type="ext" target="http://blake.lib.rochester.edu/blakeojs/index.php/blake"><hi rend="i">BIQ</hi> subscription site</ref>. These images have been moved to the <ref type="html-issue" issue="toc-bonus">Bonus Content</ref> page in the online edition, so this note has been revised to reflect the new location. For the subset of these images which appeared in the print edition in halftone, we have included the color versions of the images in the online edition in place of the halftone print images, with the exception of "A Cradle Song," because the halftone image shows the entire sheet.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="039-02">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 39, Issue 2</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="039-02" target="p101">page 101</ref>: In the print edition of this issue, the caption for images 1-2 in the article "Blake's Only Surviving Palette" asserts that color images of the palette are available at the <ref type="ext" target="http://blake.lib.rochester.edu/blakeojs/index.php/blake"><hi rend="i">BIQ</hi> subscription site</ref>. We have included the color versions of the images in the online edition in place of the halftone print images, so this note has been removed from the caption.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="039-01">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 39, Issue 1</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="039-01" target="p11">page 11</ref>: In the print edition of this issue, the recto image of this letter (25 November 1825) appeared inside the journal while the verso appeared on the front cover. For easier viewing, both images (recto and verso) have been placed within this article, and the image caption altered to reflect this new placement. 
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="038-03">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 38, Issue 3</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="038-03" target="p119">page 119</ref>: In the print edition of this issue, the "Newsletter" section asserts that more materials are available at the <ref type="ext" target="http://blake.lib.rochester.edu/blakeojs/index.php/blake"><hi rend="i">BIQ</hi> subscription site</ref>. These materials have been moved to the <ref type="html-issue" issue="toc-bonus">Bonus Content</ref> page in the online edition, so the newsletter section has been revised to reflect the new location. Additionally, the print version listed one additional item available online, an online version of &#x201C;Introducing The Blake Model.&#x201D; Because the print version of the article is now rendered online, we have simply omitted this item from the list.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="038-02">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 38, Issue 2</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="038-02" target="p55">page 55</ref>: In the print edition, images 2 and 3 ("DITTO" and "A HAND WITH A TORCH") were provided by the author. In the online edition they have been replaced with high-resolution images from the collection of Robert N. Essick, and the image captions have been altered to reflect this change.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="037-02">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 37, Issue 2</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="037-02" target="p68">page 68</ref>: The print edition incorrectly attributed this image to the Library of Congress. This is in fact the water color owned by the Morgan Library and Museum; the caption has been altered accordingly.
		</p>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="037-02" target="p74">page 74</ref>: The print edition incorrectly attributed this image from Blake's <i>Illustrations to the Book of Job</i> to the Library of Congress. We have substituted an image from the copy owned by Robert N. Essick, and have altered the caption accordingly.</p> 
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="037-02" target="p77">page 77</ref>: The print edition incorrectly attributed this Laocoön image to the Library of Congress. This is in fact the separate print owned by the Fitzwilliam Museum; the caption has been altered accordingly.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="035-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 35, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="035-04" target="p108">page 108</ref>: The print edition of this issue asserts that color images of all illustrations in the article "Blake in the Marketplace, 2001" are available at the <ref type="ext" target="http://blake.lib.rochester.edu/blakeojs/index.php/blake"><hi rend="i">BIQ</hi> subscription site</ref>. These images are no longer available, so this note has been removed, but all images in the online edition of the article are in full color.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="034-02">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 34, Issue 2</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="034-02" target="p42">page 42</ref>: Corrected <q rend="qm">Entharmonian</q> to <q rend="qm">Enitharmonian</q>.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="032-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 32, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="032-04" target="p105">page 105</ref>: Corrected <q rend="qm">Butlin #11</q> to <q rend="qm">Butlin #113</q>.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="031-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 31, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="031-04" target="p116">page 116</ref>: Omitted <q rend="qm">Photo courtesy of Christie’s London</q> because we substituted an image from the <ref type="ext" target="http://www.blakearchive.org">William Blake Archive</ref>.
			</p>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="031-04" target="p139">page 139</ref>: Omitted <q rend="qm">expertly photographed by John Sullivan of the Huntington</q> because we substituted an image from the <ref type="ext" target="http://www.blakearchive.org">William Blake Archive</ref>.
			</p>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="031-04" target="p145">page 145</ref>: Omitted <q rend="qm">photographed by John Sullivan at the Huntington</q> because we substituted an image from the <ref type="ext" target="http://www.blakearchive.org">William Blake Archive</ref>. Also corrected <q rend="qm">splater</q> to <q rend="qm">splatter</q> in the same caption.
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="021-03">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 21, Issue 3</title>
		</head>
		<p>Leslie Brisman, <ref type="issue" issue="021-03" target="n13">footnote 1</ref>: Corrected <q rend="qm"><rtl>שקראוני</rtl></q> (to read; to call out to, to summon; to call, to name; to shout) to <q rend="qm"><rtl>שהראוני</rtl></q> (to show; to indicate; to explain, to demonstrate). The quotation with the reading we have substituted appears in a dozen different books, whereas the quotation with the original reading appears in none (see <ref type="ext" target="http://books.google.com/">Google Books</ref>). It is unclear to us whether the English translation provided (<q rend="qm">dictated</q>) is meant to render the Hebrew word printed or the one we have substituted. (The English definitions of the Hebrew words given here are taken from the <ref type="ext" target="http://www.morfix.co.il/en/">Morfix Hebrew-English Dictionary</ref>.)
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="021-02">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 21, Issue 2</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="021-02" target="p61">page 61</ref>, <ref type="issue" issue="021-02" target="p73">page 73</ref>: Corrected <q rend="qm">Poprzȩcka</q> to <q rend="qm">Poprzęcka</q>.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="018-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 18, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="018-04" target="p231">page 231</ref>, <ref type="issue" issue="018-04" target="p233">page 233</ref>: Replaced <q rend="qm">^.</q> and <q rend="qm">^</q> with <q rend="qm"><hi rend="sub">^</hi></q> as a representation of <q rend="qm">a caret below the line which indicates an insertion</q>. (To avoid numerous intrusive marks, we have labeled only the first such emendation on page 233.)
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="018-02">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 18, Issue 2</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="018-02" target="p106">page 106</ref>, <ref type="issue" issue="018-02" target="p114">page 114</ref>: Corrected <q rend="qm">Poprzȩcka</q> to <q rend="qm">Poprzęcka</q>.
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="017-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 17, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p>Joan K. Stemmler, <ref type="issue" issue="017-04" target="n48">footnote 2</ref>, and Judith Ott, <ref type="issue" issue="017-04" target="n92">footnote 9</ref>: Corrected <q rend="qm">Abo̊</q> to <q rend="qm">Åbo</q>.
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="016-02">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 16, Issue 2</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="016-02" target="p82">page 82</ref>: In a quotation from Euripedes' <hi rend="i">Medea</hi>, corrected <q rend="qm">῏ειτ᾽</q> (beginning with an epsilon with smooth breathing and circumflex, even though a circumflex cannot be applied to epsilon) to <q rend="qm">εἶτ᾽</q>, the reading given in the David Kovacs edition (line 1176) in the <ref type="ext" target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu">Perseus Digital Library</ref>. (For other differences between Kovacs's edition and the text provided in this article, we have left the article's text as it stands.)
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="015-03">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 15, Issue 3</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="015-03" target="p144">page 144</ref>: Corrected <q rend="qm">Movos o Iεsous</q> to <q rend="qm">Μονος ο Ιεςους</q>.
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="015-02">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 15, Issue 2</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="015-02" target="p84">page 84</ref>: Corrected <q rend="qm">En O̊ På Månen</q> to <q rend="qm">En Ö På Månen</q>.
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="013-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 13, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="013-04" target="p178">page 178</ref>: Removed extra character <q rend="qm"> ̑</q> from after the word <q rend="qm">armor</q>. 
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="013-01">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 13, Issue 1</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="013-01" target="p44">page 44</ref>: Removed extra character <q rend="qm">`</q> from before the word <q rend="qm">ύψος</q>.
			</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="009-02b">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 9, Issue 2b</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="009-02b" target="pi">page i</ref>: Added a table of contents.
			</p>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="009-02b" target="p1">page 1</ref>: Added the heading <q rend="qm">Blake’s Visions of the Last Judgment: Plates and Editorial Note</q>. Altered the heading <q rend="qm">List of Plates</q> to <q rend="qm">Plates</q> and distributed plate descriptions into captions below the plates. Also duplicated the cover image (the first plate) below the heading for ease of use.
			</p>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="009-02b" target="p8">page 8</ref>: Corrected the typographical error <q rend="qm">iconotraphy</q> to <q rend="qm">iconography</q>.
			</p>
    </div1>
	<div1 id="006-03">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 6, Issue 3</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="006-03" target="p68">page 68</ref>, <ref type="issue" issue="006-03" target="p70">page 70</ref>: In the original printed issue, several quotations were rendered using all capital letters, with some initial letters triple-underlined. It appears that the journal was following a print convention wherein a triple underline represents a full capital letter among small capitals (since, when one lacks a typeface for small capitals, they must be rendered as full capitals). Because triple underline cannot be rendered in HTML, we have instead rendered these quotations as small capitals with the emphasized characters as full capitals.
			</p>
    </div1>
	<div1 id="002-04b">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 2, Issue 4b</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="002-04b">throughout</ref>: Due to numerous bibliographic entries being cut off at the end of a line in the print edition, we supplied missing bibliographic information, such as publication dates.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="001-04">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 1, Issue 4</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="001-04" target="p10">page 10</ref>: Due to several words being cut off at the end of a line in the print edition, we supplied missing characters to complete the words.
		</p>
	</div1>
	<div1 id="001-01">
		<head>
		  <title rend="h4">Volume 1, Issue 1</title>
		</head>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="001-01" target="p1">page 1</ref>: Added a table of contents.
			</p>
		<p><ref type="issue" issue="001-01" target="p7">page 7</ref>: Corrected typographical error <q rend="qm">firt</q> to <q rend="qm">first</q>.
		</p>
	</div1>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
