<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
 <idno>20.3.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1986-87</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986-87</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">20.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stewart Crehan</name>
              <name>D. W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <front>
      <pb id="p20-73-74" n="73-74"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.020.03.bqscan" rend="file">
          <figTranscr>Blake<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            VOLUME 20<lb/>
            NUMBER 3<lb/>
            WINTER 1986-87</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="9" cols="2">
          <row>
          	<cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>
            	  <hi rend="b">
              		<hi rend="i">CONTENTS</hi>
            	  </hi>
          		</title>
        	  </head>
          	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="20.3.dorrbecker">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</ref> by Detlef W. Dörrbecker</cell>
            <cell>76</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="20.3.tolley">The <hi rend="i">Allegorical Female Figure</hi>: She Cometh With Clouds</ref> by Michael J. Tolley</cell>
            <cell>101</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="20.3.heppner">The New Jerusalem Defended</ref> by Christopher Heppner</cell>
            <cell>102</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="20.3.crehan">Blake, Context and Ideology</ref> by Stewart Crehan</cell>
            <cell>104</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="20.3.peterfreund">Reply to Stewart Crehan</ref> by Stuart Peterfreund</cell>
            <cell>108</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <ref type="article" issue="20.3.defaced"><hi rend="i">De-Faced Blake</hi></ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="20.3.errata"><hi rend="i">Errata’s Errata</hi></ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="20.3.play"><hi rend="i">Call for Plays</hi></ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="20.3.energy"><hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi></ref>
            </cell>
            <cell>110</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <figure/>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">CONTRIBUTORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">STEWART CREHAN</hi> teaches in the Department of Literature and Languages, University of Zambia. He is the author of <hi rend="i">Blake, Context and Ideology.</hi></p>
        <p><hi rend="b">D. W. DÖRRBECKER</hi>, an art historian at the University of Trier, is presently preparing a notice of four hitherto unrecorded copies of Blake’s illuminated books, which he located among the holdings of what used to be the royal collections of the Austrian and Bavarian courts.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">CHRISTOPHER HEPPNER</hi>, Associate Professor of English at McGill University, Montreal, has published articles on several aspects of Blake’s work.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">STUART PETERFREUND</hi> is the editor of <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> (which will become <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Contexts</hi> with its next volume), <hi rend="i">PSLS: The Newsletter of the Society for Literature and Science</hi> (of which he is a founding member), and the <hi rend="i">Proceedings</hi> of the Northeastern University Center for Literary Studies. He is working on a book that studies the emergence of energy as a cultural concept in English during the period 1775-1825.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">MICHAEL J. TOLLEY</hi>, Reader in English at the University of Adelaide, is currently at work on the page-by-page <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> commentary. He postpones to another year or ten his massive study of Blake’s use of the Bible.</p>
        <figure/>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p20-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">EDITORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editors:</hi> Morris Eaves, University of Rochester, and Morton D. Paley, University of California, Berkeley.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Bibliographer:</hi> Detlef W. Dörrbecker, Universität Trier, West Germany.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Review Editor:</hi> Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia, Athens.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Associate Editor for Great Britain:</hi> Frances A. Carey, Assistant Curator, Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Production Office:</hi> Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627, <hi rend="b">Telephone</hi> 716/275-3820.<lb/>
Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720.<lb/>
Detlef W. Dörrbecker, Universität Trier, FB III Kunstgeschichte, Postfach 3825, 5500 Trier, West Germany. Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602.<lb/>
Frances A. Carey, Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum, Great Russell Street, London WC1B 3DG, United Kingdom.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">INFORMATION</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Managing Editor:</hi> Patricia Neill.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the Department of English, University of Rochester.</p>
        <figure/>
        <p><hi rend="b">Subscriptions</hi> are $18 for institutions, $15 for individuals. All subscriptions are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments received after the summer issue will be applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and Mexico) require a $3 per volume postal surcharge for surface mail, a $10 per volume surcharge for air mail delivery. U.S. currency or international money order necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to Patricia Neill, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627, USA.</p>
        <p>Many <hi rend="b">back issues</hi> are available at a reduced price. Address Patricia Neill for a list of issues and prices.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Manuscripts</hi> are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to the forms suggested in the MLA Style Sheet, 2nd ed., to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY 14627; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">International Standard Serial Number:</hi> 0006-453x. <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is <hi rend="b">indexed</hi> in the Modern Language Associations International Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, <hi rend="i">English Language Notes’</hi> annual Romantic Bibliography, ART bibliographies MODERN, American Humanities Index, and the Arts and Humanities Citation Index.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <pb id="p20-76" n="76"/>
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">D.W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Because of various technical and organizational difficulties, no annual checklist of recent scholarship was published in the 1985 volume of <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> The present compilation therefore tries to catch up with what has happened since Thomas L. Minnick and I handed in the 1984 list (see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 18 [1984]: 100-15); it covers the period from summer 1984 to—roughly—early summer 1986, with some additional pre-1984 items interspersed which previously had escaped our attention. If, therefore, the 1986 edition of the checklist is much bulkier than earlier ones, this is the most important and obvious reason. But there are some others, too.</p>
        <p>It needs no stressing, I suppose, that a periodical checklist like this may well reach for but never will attain completeness, and this is especially so if such a list is concerned with English art and literature, but compiled at various museum and university libraries in Germany. However, there are at least two distinct features of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>’s checklists which, I believe, guarantee their usefulness to its readers. One is the actuality of this report on recent developments in Blake studies and its neighboring fields (particularly when we resume publication on an annual basis). The other is the reviews section. This part of the checklist—despite its being very likely the least complete—gives access to a field of publication where one can often meet with observations as pertinent and innovative as those of the scholarly books and articles listed in the other sections. Since no other bibliography attempts to give a full account of the review literature in Blake studies, I have devoted more time and care to this than to any other class of publications—well knowing that all too many lacunae will remain.</p>
        <p>A few more words concerning the organization, entry format, and coverage of the present checklist may prove useful. In general, I have retained the format of four main sections with a number of subdivisions which has been known to the readers of this journal since 1980. Coverage in parts II and III, however, has always been—and probably to a certain extent will remain—problematic. Are Mary Wollstonecraft and Angelica Kauffmann or Thomas Paine and William Godwin to be considered members of Blake’s circle?—and has not the Related Interest section always looked a little haphazard in scope, either too inclusive or exclusive in its coverage?</p>
        <p>Let me recite a few of the criteria for selection, annotation, and bibliographical style that I have followed while compiling the present list.</p>
        <p>(1) Blake’s circle has been drawn slightly smaller than in previous years, thus excluding, for example, Edward Young and Robert Blair (whose works were illustrated by the artist, just as those of Dante and Milton or the Bible, but whom he did not know personally), while retaining entries for such figures as Cowper or Erasmus Darwin (contemporaries at least, whose inclusion is nevertheless open to discussion, I think).</p>
        <p>(2) Part III is the only section of the checklist which—by necessity—is selective rather than extensive in its coverage. Its contents have been assembled (and subdivided) according to the following few guidelines. First there are entries for some general studies of British Romantic poetry and art which either mention Blake’s works in a larger context and/or are thought to have some bearing on the interpretation of these works, and/or have been reviewed in the pages of this journal. Then, I have included here a selection of books and articles on what might be termed Blake’s “outer circle,” i.e., some contemporary authors and artists who may have been influential for his productions here or there, and who are not covered in any other subject bibliography that is known to me. Since the history of Blake scholarship—during the next decade or so—is bound to become a major field of study in itself, part III also includes entries for biographical and critical assessments of some influential Blake scholars and collectors (and even lists the printing of two of Foster Damon’s poems). Reports on poetical, theatrical, or film adaptations of Blake’s works, as well as statements concerning their influence on modern contemporary art and literature, make up the final section of part III. I have decided, however, to omit adaptations of Blake’s poems by recording artists such as Marianne Faithfull, who quotes from “The Tyger” in her “Eye Communication,” or Sting, who refers
<pb id="p20-77" n="77"/>
to the “dark satanic mills” in his “We Work the Black Seam.”</p>
        <p>(3) Brief annotations have been provided for at least those book-length studies which to my knowledge have not hitherto been the subject of extensive reviews, and to a number of articles the titles of which I thought were not fully self-explanatory. These annotations follow the bibliographical information in square brackets. Prices have been quoted where available.</p>
        <p>(4) I have agreed with the editors to adopt (with very few exceptions) for the formal presentation of the bibliographical data the rules and regulations laid down by Walter S. Achtert and Joseph Gibaldi in <hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi> (New York, NY: Modern Language Association of America, 1985). This explains the punctuation of the entries, which differs slightly from our earlier lists, and explains the use of certain standard abbreviations such as “U” for “University,” or “P” for “Press.” The items in each section are arranged in strict alphabetical order by name of author and title. At least in the reviews section of earlier editions of this checklist I often attempted a chronological sequence where the same book had been reviewed more than once; now, these entries have been alphabetized by the reviewers’ names and, for easy reference, have also been numbered review by review.</p>
        <p>From the foregoing it should be fairly evident that something can be done (and maybe even has to be done) about the organization and the scope of parts II and III in the future. I shall be grateful for any suggestions made by those who work with these checklists.</p>
        <p>Finally, it gives me great pleasure to record my indebtness to those friends and colleagues who have shared some bibliographical information with me or have kindly sent offprints from their articles (which is always very helpful): Rodney M. Baine, Stephen C. Behrendt, G. E. Bentley, Jr., Martin Butlin, Claudia Corti, Morris Eaves, Helen B. Ellis, Robert N. Essick, Michael Fischer, David S. Fuller, Marilyn Gaull and Maurizio Giammarco, Mark L. Greenberg, Jean H. Hagstrum, Nelson Hilton, Terence A. Hoagwood, Traude Kannengiesser, Donald Masterson, Horst Meller, Edward O’Shea, Morton D. Paley, François Piquet, Kathleen Raine, Aquilino Sánchez Pérez, Wilhelm Schlink, and Joseph S. Viscomi. The Darwin section would not be half so well informed without the expert knowledge of Desmond King-Hele. Also, I wish to thank all those publishing houses, museums, and journal editors in Britain, Italy, Japan, and the United States who have kindly supplied me with inspection copies and have thus contributed largely to the accuracy and completeness of the present list. Any omissions that remain, will, of course, if brought to my attention, duly be recorded in next year’s compilation.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="i">Note: An asterisk beside an entry on the list identifies an item that I have not examined.</hi>
        </p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part I William Blake</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Editions, Translations, Facsimiles, Reproductions</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1. Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Works in Conventional Typography: Facsimile Reproductions.</hi> Scholars’ Facsimiles and Reprints 388. Delmar, NY: Scholars’ Facsimiles and Reprints, 1984. $55.</p>
            <p>2. *Blair, Robert. <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> 1858. West Orange, NJ: Saifer, 1984. $25. [Probably a facsimile reproduction of the Stanford and Delisser reissue of A. L. Dick’s steel engravings after Blake’s 1808 Blair illustrations.]</p>
            <p>3. Blondel, Jacques, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">Vala, ou Les Quatre vivants.</hi> Vol. 4 of <hi rend="i">Oeuvres de William Blake.</hi> Paris: Aubier, 1983. Fr.150. [This is the fourth volume of the bilingual edition which was initiated by Pierre Leyris. Besides the translation of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, it also contains the French versions of Blake’s annotations to Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology</hi>, to Bacon’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>, and to Boyd’s commentary on Dante’s <hi rend="i">Inferno.</hi> Blondel’s introduction takes up pp. 7-55, and there is a short bibliography on pp. 597-98.]</p>
            <p>4. Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">To the Nightingale.</hi> By William Blake. Isle of Ely: Waterside P, 1981. [This edition, printed privately and limited to 100 copies which are signed by the editor, consists of only two printed crown quarto pages of text, the first of which contains the poem itself, and the second a “Statement” concerning its attribution to the author of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi> This attribution has also been made in an article for the <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> and a <hi rend="i">Nightingale</hi> anthology, compiled by the late Sir Geoffrey in collaboration with Peter Davidson; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 16 (1982): 114, #80; 18 (1984): 100, #6.]</p>
            <p>5. *Milton, John. <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity.</hi> With a Note on the Illustrations by Martin Butlin. Andoversford: Whittington P, 1981. [Reproduces the Whitworth series of Blake’s watercolors in color.]</p>
            <p>6. Schmiele, Walter, ed. <hi rend="i">Poesie der Welt: England.</hi> Edition Stichnote: Ex Libris Ausgabe. Frankfort on Main, W. Ger.: Propyläen-Ullstein, 1985. 50-71. [These pages contain a selection of translations from Blake’s shorter poems; no translator is credited.]</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">See also #110 for a complete printing of Blake’s</hi> Song of Los, <hi rend="i">and #119 for a newly attributed poem.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p20-78" n="78"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Bibliographies, Bibliographical Essays, Catalogues</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>7. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Keynes and Blake at Cambridge.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 69-71.</p>
            <p>8. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography</hi> ns 6 for 1980. New York, NY: AMS P, 1984. [For Blake entries see pp. 320, 396 to 402. The more extensive reviews in this annotated bibliography are listed separately in part IV, where this volume is referred to in abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980).”]</p>
            <p>9. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography</hi> ns 7 for 1981. New York, NY: AMS P, 1985. [For Blake entries see pp. 392-401 and passim. The more extensive reviews in this annotated bibliography are cited separately in part IV, where this volume is referred to in abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981).”]</p>
            <p>10. Brown, David Blayney. “The Romantic Tradition: William Blake to Robin Tanner.” <hi rend="i">The Print in England, 1790-1930: A Private Collection.</hi> Ed. Craig Hartley and Susan Ridyard. Cambridge, Cambs.: Fitzwilliam Museum, 1985. 40-69. [Works by Blake, Flaxman, and Palmer were included in this section (#53-108) of an exhibition which drew on the holdings of the Robert Loder collection. See also #19, below.]</p>
            <p>11. Burns, Bryan, Philip Dodd, and Vincent Newey. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic Period.” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 62 (1981). Ed. Laurel Brake. London: Murray; Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P; for the English Association, 1984. 277-305. [See pp. 280-84 for a summary review of 1981 Blake scholarship by Newey; additional references are listed in the index of authors treated.]</p>
            <p>12. Burns, Bryan, Philip Dodd, and Vincent Newey. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic Period.” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 63 (1982). Ed. Laurel Brake. London: Murray; Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P; for the English Association, 1985. 277-307. [See pp. 278-81 for Vincent Newey’s summary review of 1982 Blake scholarship; again, more references to Blake will be found in the index.]</p>
            <p>13. Cox, Stephen D. “Recent Work on Blake.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405. [A review article; its contents are listed separately in part IV, below.]</p>
            <p>14. Erdman, David V., with the assistance of Brian J. Dendle, et al., eds. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography for 1982.</hi> Garland Reference Library of the Humanities 217. New York, NY: Garland, 1983. [For Blake entries see pp. 77-94. The more extensive reviews in this annotated bibliography are also cited separately in part IV, where this volume is referred to in abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">RMB for 1982.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>15. Erdman, David V., with the assistance of Brian J. Dendle, et al., eds. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography for 1983.</hi> Garland Reference Library of the Humanities 218. New York, NY: Garland, 1984. [For Blake entries see pp. 74-89. The more extensive reviews in this annotated bibliography are also listed separately in part IV, where this volume is referred to in abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">RMB for 1983.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>16. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake in the Huntington Collections: A Complete Catalogue.</hi> San Marino, CA: Henry E. Huntington Library, 1985. [Very fully annotated entries, a model of what a catalogue of a museum’s special collections can be, and often supplying information which is important for the understanding of Blake’s works in other collections, too.]</p>
            <p>17. [Haddad, Rosemary, Christopher Heppner, and Elizabeth Lewis]. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of the Lawrence Lande William Blake Collection in the Department of Rare Books and Special Collections of the McGill University Libraries.</hi> Montreal, PQ: McLennan Library/McGill U, 1983. $60. [A limited edition of 500 numbered copies, only 400 of which are for sale. A fine collection, and a catalogue printed on fine paper; the compilation of the entries, however, does follow standard librarian practice, which is not particularly illuminating for a figure like Blake, whose works have already—and more than once—been the subject of competent bibliographical description. The contents of the Lande collection can best be compared with those of the Preston Blake Library; the catalogue of the latter, published by Westminster City Libraries in 1969 and 1976, is similar in scope, but was sold at a much more reasonable price.]</p>
            <p>18. Hawcroft, Francis W. <hi rend="i">“The most beautiful art of England:” Fifty Watercolours, 1750-1850.</hi> Manchester, Lancs.: Whitworth Art Gallery, 1983. [Blake was represented by no less than four out of the fifty works in this exhibition; they are here catalogued as #17-20.]</p>
            <p>19. Loder, R[obert] B. <hi rend="i">William Blake to David Hockney: A Private Collection of British Prints.</hi> Oxford, Oxon.: Ashmolean Museum, 1982. £0.75. [This leaflet was published to accompany an exhibition of some of the finest works in the Loder collection, staged at the Ashmolean from 5 Feb. to 28 Mar. 1982. Besides a brief foreword by Kenneth Garlick, it contains an introduction and a list of the exhibits by the collector, including eleven Blakes, one Linnell, four Calverts, and thirteen Palmer prints. See also #10, above, for another exhibition catalogue with materials from the same private collection.]</p>
            <p>20. Minnick, Thomas L., and Detlef W. Dörrbecker. “Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 100-15.</p>
            <pb id="p20-79" n="79"/>
            <p>21. Modern Language Association of America. “Blake, William (1757-1827).” <hi rend="i">1983 MLA International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and Literatures.</hi> Vol. 1: “Classified Listings.” New York, NY: MLA, 1984. 59-60. [See also s. v. “Blake” in vol. 1 of the subject index for further references.]</p>
            <p>22. Modern Language Association of America. “Blake, William (1757-1827).” <hi rend="i">1984 MLA International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and Literatures.</hi> Vol. 1: “Classified Listings.” New York, NY: MLA, 1985. 62-63. [See also s. v. “Blake” in vol. 1 of the subject index for further references.]</p>
            <p>23. Smith, Michael, with the assistance of Mary Jean DeMarr, eds. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature</hi> 56 for 1981. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1984. [Blake entries appear on pp. 330-33 as #5955-6033.]</p>
            <p>24. Smith, Michael, with the assistance of Mary Jean DeMarr, eds. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature</hi> 57 for 1982. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1985. [Blake entries appear on pp. 325-30 as #5921-6016.]</p>
            <p>25. [William Weston Gallery]. <hi rend="i">The English Vision: An Exhibition of Original Prints by William Blake 1757-1827, Samuel Palmer 1805-1881, Edward Calvert 1799-1883.</hi> Catalogue 11 (1985) [whole no. 195]. London: William Weston Gallery, 1985. [There are some sixty unnumbered pages in this small, but illustrated catalogue of a sale exhibition. The forty-seven items offered included sets of Blake’s Virgil wood-engravings, his <hi rend="i">Job</hi> prints, as well as some of the rarer Calvert engravings.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #198 below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Critical Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>26. Adkins, Camille. “In Adam’s Room: Incarnation of the Divine Image in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1984): 1404A. Texas Christian U. [“. . . Blake . . . shared Milton’s interest in the concept of incarnation. Both poets uphold the Protestant assertion which entitles each individual to private judgment in matters of conscience. This individualism leads Milton and Blake to unique perceptions of the myths which underlie <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>—the myth of Genesis, the fall and redemption of the Sophia, several mystic marriages, including that of Eros and Psyche. . . . Milton perceives a God who is all light, whereas Blake recognizes light and darkness in divinity.”]</p>
            <p>27. Adlard, John. “Blake and Wimbledon.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984): 468.</p>
            <p>28. Adlard, John, and B. J. M. Folliot. “A Blake Poem.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 21 Sept. 1984: 1055. [Two letters to the editor, commenting on Geoffrey Keynes’s attribution of “The Phoenix to Mrs Butts” to William Blake; see #119, below.]</p>
            <p>29. Anderson, Mark. “Oothoon, Failed Prophet.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 8.2 (1984): 1-21.</p>
            <p>30. Anderson, Mark. “Why Is That Fairy in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>?” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 21 (1985): 122-33.</p>
            <p>31. Baine, Rodney M. “Blake’s Sons of Los.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 63 (1984): 239-54.</p>
            <p>32. Beer, John. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Writers and Their Work 277. Windsor, Berks.: Profile Books, 1982. £1.50. [A brief introduction to Blake’s work (46 pp. of text), obviously designed to replace Miss Raine’s text of 1951 in the same series (3rd ed., 1969). The select bibliography has been augmented and brought up to date (pp. 47-52), but retains most of the misprints of publication dates of the earlier editions and adds a few new ones.]</p>
            <p>33. Behrendt, Stephen C. “<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and Blake’s View of the Fall.” <hi rend="i">Trivium</hi> 18 (1983): 39-48.</p>
            <p>34. Behrendt, Stephen C. “‘This Accursed Family:’ Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and the American Revolution.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 26-51.</p>
            <p>35. Bennett, Shelley M. “A New Blake at the Huntington.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 132-39.</p>
            <p>36. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Daughters of Albion and the Butts Household.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 116.</p>
            <p>37. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Felpham Rummer: A New Angel and ‘Immoral Drink’ Attributed to William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 94-99.</p>
            <p>38. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “From ‘London’ to ‘Jerusalem:’ The City in William Blake’s Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 10 (1985): 35-48.</p>
            <p>39. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “From Sketch to Text in Blake: The Case of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 128-41.</p>
            <p>40. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Thomas Sivright and the Lost Designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 103-06.</p>
            <p>41. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “‘The Triumph of Owen:’ William Owen Pughe and Blake’s ‘Ancient Britons.’ ” <hi rend="i">National Library of Wales Journal</hi> 24 (1985): 248-61.</p>
            <p>42. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “[‘Tyger’ and ‘Lamb:’ A Question Easy to Pose, Yet Hard to Answer.]” <hi rend="i">Guo-wai Wenxue</hi> 15 (1984): 86-113. [An essay on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, printed in no. 3 of the 1984 volume of this Chinese journal on the foreign languages—not only the first of Bentley’s articles I have seen in Chinese characters, but also the first time I have come across Chinese versions of Blake’s poems; I couldn’t read either.]</p>
            <pb id="p20-80" n="80"/>
            <p>43. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Way of a Papermaker with a Poet: Joshua Gilpin, William Blake, and the Arts in 1796.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 33 (1986): 80-84. [In a “Postscript,” which has not yet been published, the author presents additional evidence that—alas!—leaves no doubts as to the identity of Gilpin’s Blake: he was the writing engraver William Staden Blake of Exchange Alley, not the painter-poet as Bentley had assumed when submitting his article in 1985.]</p>
            <p>44. Berninghausen, Thomas F. “The Marriage of Contraries in ‘To Tirzah.’ ” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 191-98.</p>
            <p>45. Bidney, Martin. “Faulkner’s Variations on Romantic Themes: Blake, Wordsworth, Byron, and Shelly in <hi rend="i">Light in August.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Mississippi Quarterly</hi> 38 (1985): 277-86.</p>
            <p>46. Billigheimer, Rachel V. “The Eighth Eye: Prophetic Vision in Blake’s Poetry and Design.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 22 (1986): 93-110.</p>
            <p>47. Blaydes, Sophia B., and Philip Bordinat. “Blake’s ‘Jerusalem’ and Popular Culture: <hi rend="i">The Loneliness of the Long-Distance Runner</hi> and <hi rend="i">Chariots of Fire.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Literature / Film Quarterly</hi> 11 (1983): 211-14.</p>
            <p>48. *Blondel, Jacques. “L’Eros blakien.” <hi rend="i">Romantisme anglais et Eros.</hi> Ed. Christian La Cassagnère. Publications de la Faculté des Letters et Sciences Humaines de l’Université de Clermont-Ferrand II 14. Clermont-Ferrand: U de Clermont-Ferrand II, 1982. 7-16.</p>
            <p>49. *Blondel, Jacques. “William Blake: De l’enfance au progrès de contraries.” <hi rend="i">L’Enfance et les ouvrages d’éducation.</hi> Vol. 1: “Avant 1800.” Ed. Paule M. Pénigault-Duhet. Nantes: U de Nantes, 1983. 119-42.</p>
            <p>50. Bloom, Harold, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Modern Critical Views. New York, NY: Chelsea House, 1985. $17.95. [“This volume gathers together a representative selection of the best criticism devoted to William Blake from 1950 until the present.” To this purpose Bloom has selected essays by David V. Erdman, Robert F. Gleckner, Northrop Frye, W. J. T. Mitchell, Thomas R. Frosch, Thomas Weiskel, Susan Fox, Leslie Brisman, Leopold Damrosch, Jr., David Wagenknecht, Diana Hume George, and by himself. There are about 200 pages of text, plus a select bibliography.]</p>
            <p>51. Bracher, Mark. <hi rend="i">“Being Form’d:” Thinking Through Blake’s</hi> Milton. Barrytown, NY: Clinamen Studies—Station Hill P, 1985. $9.95 paper.</p>
            <p>52. Bracher, Mark. “The Metaphysical Grounds of Oppression in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 164-76.</p>
            <p>53. Brown, James Boyd. “The History of an Illusion: The Meaning of the Four Zoas in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984): 3385-86A. York U, Canada. [Intended “to demonstrate two hypotheses. The first is that each of the Zoas has an essential core of meaning which can be understood by ‘translating’ it into regular English words. . . . My second hypothesis is that the poem has a referential structure: its plot presents Blake’s view of the history of man.”]</p>
            <p>54. Butlin, Martin. “Two Blakes Reappear and Make Three.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 118-19.</p>
            <p>55. *Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Rev. ed. Salem, NH: Salem House-Merrimack, 1985. $6.95. [According to the author, this is a revised version in a larger format of his guide to the Tate Gallery’s Blake collection; first published in The Tate Gallery Little Book Series in 1966, reprinted in 1968, 1972, 1975, 1978, and—revised—in 1983.]</p>
            <p>56. Butter, P. H. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 4 Feb. 1983: 108. [A letter to the editor in reply to Enright’s review of the author’s <hi rend="i">Blake: Selected Poems</hi>; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 72, #214.]</p>
            <p>57. Chayes, Irene H. “Blake’s Ways with Art Sources: Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 60-89.</p>
            <p>58. Connolly, Thomas E. “Point of View in Interpreting ‘The Fly.’ ” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 22.1 (1984): 32-37.</p>
            <p>59. Cooper, Robert M. “Felpham.” <hi rend="i">The Literary Guide and Companion to Southern England.</hi> Athens, OH: Ohio UP, 1985. 115-17. [No news in this account of Blake’s Felpham years.]</p>
            <p>60. Cramer, Patricia. “The Role of Ahania’s Lament in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of Ahania</hi>: A Psychoanalytic Study.” <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 83 (1984): 522-33.</p>
            <p>61. Crossan, Greg. “‘Infant Sorrow’ and Robert Greene’s <hi rend="i">Menaphon.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 142-43.</p>
            <p>62. Cushing, James Byers. “The Figure of the Poet: Self-Representation in Young, Blake, and Wordsworth.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984): 3387A. U of California, Irvine. [Treats Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs as a critical comment on Young, and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as responding “to <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> in its (the poem’s) focus on the figure of the poet, Los, and his struggle to represent himself.”]</p>
            <p>63. Deen, Leonard W. <hi rend="i">Conversing in Paradise: Poetic Genius and Identity-as-Community in Blake’s Los.</hi> Columbia, MO: U of Missouri P, 1983. $23.</p>
            <p>64. Dörrbecker, Detlef W. “Fläche, Linie, Figur und Raum: Grundzüge der Bildform bei William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Unijournal: Zeitschrift der Universität Trier</hi> 12.2 (1986): 6. [A dissertation abstract; U of Trier, West Germany.]</p>
            <p>65. Dörrbecker, D. W. “Grant’s ‘Problems in Understanding:’ Some Marginalia.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 185-90. [Part of the public debate between one of the editors of the Clarendon edition
<pb id="p20-81" n="81"/>
of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs and some of its reviewers; see also #89, 140, and 148, below.]</p>
            <p>66. Ellis, Helen. “Blake’s ‘Bible of Hell:’ <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> and the Song of Solomon.” <hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi> 12 (1986): 23-36.</p>
            <p>67. *Engelborghs, Maurits. “Het grafisch werk van William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dietsche Warande en Belfort</hi> 128 (1982): 297-300. [Possibly not more than a review of the Dutch edition of Bindman’s <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake.</hi>]</p>
            <p>68. Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1982-1983.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 68-93.</p>
            <p>69. Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1984.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 24-38.</p>
            <p>70. Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1985.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 12-31.</p>
            <p>71. Essick, Robert N. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>: Some Unrecorded Proofs and Their Inscriptions.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 96-102.</p>
            <p>72. Essick, Robert N. “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Intention and Production.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 216-220.</p>
            <p>73. Essick, Robert N. “A ‘New’ Blake Engraving?” <hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi> 2 (1985): 42-47. [Discusses an engraving showing the “Carfax Conduit, Oxford,” signed “Blake sc.,” and probably to be attributed to the poet-engraver William Blake. “The graphic style and subject of <hi rend="i">Carfax Conduit</hi> support the attribution made possible by the signature in the plate. Although this assemblage of evidence is far from conclusive, it is at least as convincing as the reasons for attributing to Blake a number of book illustrations of the 1770s generally included in his canon without hesitation.” (p. 47)]</p>
            <p>74. Essick, Robert N. “Variation, Accident, and Intention in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.” Studies in Bibliography</hi> 39 (1986): 230-35. [Demonstrates that a loose impression of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 4 originally had been intended for inclusion in Copy G, and thereby defines the extent to which accidents in the printing process may have affected the texts of Blake’s illuminated books—brief, but important.]</p>
            <p>75. Essick, Robert N. “William Blake, William Hamilton, and the Materials of Graphic Meaning.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 52 (1985): 833-72.</p>
            <p>76. Fenske, Siglinde, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Maler: Leben, Werk und ihre Zeit 15. Hamburg, W. Ger.: Marshall Cavendish International, 1986. DM4.90. [An illustrated pamphlet in a popular series; an English version has probably been published in the United Kingdom and the United States.]</p>
            <p>77. *Ferber, Michael. <hi rend="i">The Social Vision of William Blake.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1985. $29.50.</p>
            <p>78. *Filipova, Evgenija. “Revducionnite idei v poezijata na Uiljam Bleik [Revolutionary Ideas in the Poetry of William Blake].” <hi rend="i">Rodna reč</hi> 26.4 (1982): 40-42.</p>
            <p>79. Finch, G. J. “Romantic Poetry and the Limits of Explication.” <hi rend="i">Ariel</hi> 16.1 (1985): 27-42. [For a discussion of these limits in the interpretation of the works of Blake see pp. 37-41.]</p>
            <p>80. Fischer, Michael. “Blake’s Quarrel with Indeterminacy.” <hi rend="i">New Orleans Review</hi> 10 (1983): 43-49. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 68, #133.]</p>
            <p>81. *Forbes, Gregory. <hi rend="i">A Companion to the New Musical Settings</hi> [for <hi rend="i">Selections from William Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience] <hi rend="i">by Gregory Forbes.</hi> Kingston, ON: Quarry P, 1983.</p>
            <p>82. Fuller, David. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and the Development of Blake’s Thought.” <hi rend="i">An Infinite Complexity: Essays in Romanticism.</hi> Ed. J. R. Watson. University of Durham Commemoration Series 1. Edinburgh: Edinburgh UP, 1983. 46-94.</p>
            <p>83. Gaddy, Holly C. “The Poet as Monk.” <hi rend="i">Massachusetts Studies in English</hi> 9.4 (1984): 1-12. [The monk is Thomas Merton, and the article is devoted to Blake’s influence on him.]</p>
            <p>84. Genet, Jacqueline. “Blake et Yeats: Deux modes d’approche d’une mě;me tradition.” <hi rend="i">Études Irlandaises</hi> ns 8 (1983): 21-39.</p>
            <p>85. Glausser, Wayne. “The Gates of Memory in Night VIIa of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.” Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 196-203.</p>
            <p>86. *Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake and Spenser.</hi> Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins UP, 1985. $29.50.</p>
            <p>87. Godard, Jerry Caris. <hi rend="i">Mental Forms Creating: William Blake Anticipates Freud, Jung, and Rank.</hi> Lanham, MD: UP of America, 1985. $25.25 cloth / $11.25 paper.</p>
            <p>88. Grams, Paul Mueller. “Blake’s Antinomianism.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985): 2110A. U of Michigan. [“This study focuses on the theological expressions in Blake’s pre-1800 writings to demonstrate that Blake held antinomian beliefs from the start of his artistic career.”]</p>
            <p>89. Grant, John E. “A Re-View of Some Problems in Understanding Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.” Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 155-81. [See also #65, 140, and 148.]</p>
            <p>90. Greenberg, Mark L. “William Michael Rossetti’s Transcription and William Bell Scott’s Tracings from Blake’s Notebook.” <hi rend="i">Library</hi> 6th ser. 6 (1984): 254-70.</p>
            <p>91. Gross, David. “Infinite Indignation: Teaching, Dialectical Vision, and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell.” College English</hi> 48 (1986): 175-86.</p>
            <p>92. Gross, David. “ ‘Mind Forg’d Manacles:’ Hegemony and Counter-Hegemony in Blake.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 3-25.</p>
            <pb id="p20-82" n="82"/>
            <p>93. Groves, David. “Blake, Thomas Boston, and the Fourfold Vision.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 142.</p>
            <p>94. Gugelberger, Georg M. “Blake, Neruda, Ngugi wa Thiong’o: Issues in Third World Literature.” <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature Studies</hi> 21 (1984): 463-82.</p>
            <p>95. Gully, Anthony Lacy. “Mr. B. and the Cherubim: A Critical Examination of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809.” <hi rend="i">Phoebus: A Journal of Art History</hi> 1 [1978]: 23-45.</p>
            <p>96. Hagstrum, Jean H. “Richardson and Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 236-37.</p>
            <p>97. Hagstrum, Jean H. “‘What Seems to Be: Is:’ Blake’s Idea of God.” <hi rend="i">Johnson and His Age.</hi> Ed. James Engell. Harvard English Studies 12. Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP, 1984. 425-58. [Jean Hagstrum’s contribution to a <hi rend="i">festschrift</hi> for Walter Jackson Bate.]</p>
            <p>98. Haigwood, Laura Ellen. “Eve’s Daughters: The Subversive Feminine in Blake and Wordsworth.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1985): 157A. U of California, Santa Cruz. [“ . . . beginning with a comparison of Blake’s and Milton’s images of Eve and of woman, using Blake’s illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> as the central text (sic). . . . (followed by) a reading of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, arguing that Oothoon’s apparently subversive arguments for free love are embedded in sexist assumptions about the nature of woman which compromise her revolutionary potential and that her speeches may be an example of Blake’s skill at dramatic irony rather than a simple enunciation of his own views on free love.”]</p>
            <p>99. Hall, Carol Louise. <hi rend="i">Blake and Fuseli: A Study in the Transmission of Ideas.</hi> Garland Publications in Comparative Literature. New York, NY: Garland, 1985. $30.</p>
            <p>100. *Hearn, Michael Patrick. “William Blake’s Illustrations for Children’s Books.” <hi rend="i">American Book Collector</hi> ns 2.2 (1981): 33-43.</p>
            <p>101. *Heinzelman, Kurt. <hi rend="i">The Economics of the Imagination.</hi> Amherst, MA: U of Massachusetts P, 1980, 110-33.[This chapter on Blake is a revision of the author’s 1978 essay on “William Blake and the Economics of the Imagination;” see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 14 (1980): 88.]</p>
            <p>102. Heppner, Christopher. “Blake’s ‘The New Jerusalem Descending:’ A Drawing (Butlin #92) Identified.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 4-11.</p>
            <p>103. Hilton, Nelson. “Blakean Zen.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 183-200.</p>
            <p>104. Hilton, Nelson. “Pudendaddendum.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 235-36.</p>
            <p>105. *Hilton, Nelson, and Thomas A. Vogler, eds. <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality.</hi> Berkeley CA: U of California P, 1986. $34. [A collection of studies by David Simpson, Gavin Edwards, Paul Mann, Donald D. Ault, Stephen Leo Carr, Robert N. Essick, V. A. De Luca, Geoffrey H. Hartman, and the editors. Most of these essays are based on papers read at the 1982 Santa Cruz Conference on “Blake and Criticism;” see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 68, #133.]</p>
            <p>106. *Himy, Armand. “Un Symbole de Blake: Le <hi rend="i">Sparagmos.” Bulletin de la Société d’Études Anglo-Americaines des XVII<hi rend="s">e</hi> et XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> Siècles</hi> 16 (1983): 89-105.</p>
            <p>107. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. “‘God Blessing the Seventh Day:’ William Blake’s Visions of God and His Biblical Watercolors.” <hi rend="i">Studia Mystica</hi> 7.2 (1984): 65-77.</p>
            <p>108. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. “Pictorial Apocalypse: Blake’s ‘Great Red Dragon and the Woman Clothed with the Sun.’ ” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 21 (1985): 11-21.</p>
            <p>109. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. <hi rend="i">Prophecy and the Philosophy of Mind: Traditions of Blake and Shelley.</hi> University, AL: U of Alabama P, 1985. $23.50. [The author specifies the philosophic sources which helped to shape <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi> and attempts to establish the philosophical impact that he believes these poetic creations can justly claim: “Prior relations subsisted between Christian biblical commentaries and secular philosophies of mind, but the poets’ splendid unification of these traditions is revolutionary.” (p. ix)]</p>
            <p>110. Holloway, John. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> The Open University Arts (A Third Level Course, ser. A362: “Romantic Poetry,” units 2-3). Milton Keynes, Bucks.: Open UP, 1984. [Holloway’s coursebook on Blake’s “Romantic Poetry” is concerned with his writings up to <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, which is reprinted in its entirety from Stevenson’s 1971 edition as “Appendix 2.” The three epics, however, remain unstudied. The booklet is structured by a succession of introductory and interpretative chapters on Blake’s “lyrics and <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>,” on the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> and the “Prophetic Books” of the 1790s; these chapters are interspersed with “Questions and Problems” addressed to the reader. There are 57, pages, complete with text extracts and a list for further reading. A television program which was connected with the Open University course concentrated on Blake’s art and was presented by David Bindman.]</p>
            <p>111. *Howard, John. <hi rend="i">Infernal Poetics: Poetic Structure in Blake’s Lambeth Prophecies.</hi> East Brunswick, NJ: Fairleigh Dickinson UP-Associated UP, 1984. $34.50.</p>
            <p>112. Howard, Seymour. “Blake: Classicism, Gothicism, and Nationalism.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 21 (1985): 165-87. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 103, #64.]</p>
            <p>113. *Johnston, Arthur. “William Blake and the ‘Ancient Britons.’ ” <hi rend="i">National Library of Wales Journal</hi> 22 (1982): 304-20.</p>
            <p>114. Johnston, John H. “Thomson, Jago, Cowper, Blake, and Seward.” <hi rend="i">The Poet and the City: A Study in</hi><pb id="p20-83" n="83"/><hi rend="i">Urban Perspectives.</hi> Athens, GA: U of Georgia P, 1984. 56-82.</p>
            <p>115. Kauvar, Elaine M. “Blake’s Interpretation of Dreams: ‘Mental Forms Creating.’ ” <hi rend="i">American Imago</hi> 41 (1984): 19-45.</p>
            <p>116. *Kauvar, Elaine M. “The Sorrows of Thel: A Freudian Interpretation of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Journal of Evolutionary Psychology</hi> 5 (1984): 210-22.</p>
            <p>117. Keane, Patrick J. “Time’s Ruins and the Mansions of Eternity: or, Golgonooza and Jerusalem, Yes; Bloomusalem and Beulah, No; Ithaca, Yes and No: Another Joyce-Blake Parallel at the End of Bloomsday.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983): 33-66.</p>
            <p>118. Kemeny, Tomaso, ed. <hi rend="i">Seminario sull’opera di William Blake.</hi> Pubblicazioni della facoltà di lettere e filosofia dell’Università di Pavia 30. Proc. of a Conference at the Istituto di lingua e letteratura inglese. Jan. 1982. Florence, It.: Nuova Italia, 1983. Lit. 10’000. [This volume of conference papers from Pavia presents Claudia Corti on Blake’s “poetical iconism,” Marcella Quadri on word and image in Blake’s oeuvre, Carla Locatelli on “tautology” in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Roberto Sanesi on Blake and Newton, Rossana Bossaglia on Blake and the “problem of the predecessors of symbolism,” and the editor on Blake and Joyce. The publication of the booklet attests to how firmly Italian Blake scholarship has been established at English Departments on the peninsula during the past four or five years.]</p>
            <p>119. Keynes, Geoffrey. “An Unpublished Poem by William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 14 Sept. 1984: 1021-22. [“The Phoenix to Mrs Butts” published, attributed to Blake, and interpreted to illuminate the poet’s personal relation with Elizabeth Butts; see also #28, above.]</p>
            <p>120. Kittel, Harald Alfred. “Perception and Reflection: The Text and Title-Page Design of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Poetic Knowledge: Circumference and Centre—Papers from the Wuppertal Symposium 1978.</hi> Ed. Roland Hagenbüchle and Joseph T. Swann. Schriftenreihe Literaturwissenschaft 18. Bonn: Bouvier, 1980. 30-41. [Should, of course, have been listed years ago, but wasn’t.]</p>
            <p>121. LaBelle, Jenijoy. “A Pencil Sketch for Blake’s Dante Illustrations.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 73-74.</p>
            <p>122. Latané, David E., Jr. “The Door into <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 7.2 (1983): 17-26.</p>
            <p>123. Latané, David Eaton, Jr. “ ‘Energetic Exertion’ —Reading and the Romantic Long Poem: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and Browning’s <hi rend="i">Sordello.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985): 192A. Duke U. [“Blake’s annotations, illustrations and poems show that he practiced an active reading that engages in dialogue with the text. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> his difficult rhetoric makes language itself sublime and compels the reader’s energetic exertion in response. Blake plays on the incomprehensibility of the sublime and the morphology of prophecy . . . to draw the reader into the poem.”]</p>
            <p>124. Lesser, Harry. “Blake and Plato.” <hi rend="i">Philosophy</hi> 56 (1981): 223-30.</p>
            <p>125. Lincoln, Andrew. “Blake and the Natural History of Creation.” <hi rend="i">Essays and Studies</hi> 39 (1986): 94-103.</p>
            <p>126. Linkin, Harriet Kramer. “The Search for a Transcendent Language: Linguistic Strategies in Herbert and Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1985): 989A. U of Michigan. [“George Herbert and William Blake are two poets who devise poetic systems or metaphors that attempt transcendence by mimetically representing the infinitude hidden within the mundane, secular, or experientially bound universe. Though Herbert and Blake disagree on the specific nature of immanence, both believe language provides a means of approaching their visions of sublimity.”]</p>
            <p>127. Mann, Paul. “Apocalypse and Recuperation: Blake and the Maw of Commerce.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 52 (1985): 1-32.</p>
            <p>128. Mann, Paul. “The Final State of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 204-15.</p>
            <p>129. Marvel, Laura. “Blake and Yeats: Visions of Apocalypse.” <hi rend="i">College Literature</hi> 13 (1986): 95-105.</p>
            <p>130. Masterson, Donald, and Edward O’Shea. “Code Breaking and Myth Making: the Ellis-Yeats Edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Works.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Yeats Annual</hi> 3 (1985): 53-80.</p>
            <p>131. Matsushima, Shōichi. <hi rend="i">Koko no Geijutsuka William Blake.</hi> Tokyo: Hokuseido, 1984. ¥5000.</p>
            <p>132. McCord, James. “Historical Dissonance and William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Song of Los.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 22-35.</p>
            <p>133. McCord, James. “John Butler Yeats, ‘The Brotherhood,’ and William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983): 10-32.</p>
            <p>134. McCord, James. “An Unrecorded Colored Copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 116-18.</p>
            <p>135. McHenry, Henry Davis, Jr. “I. Prolegomenon for a Complete Angler: The Social Conditioning of Learning—II. Reference and Exuberance: Blake’s Idea of Language.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1984): 821A. U of Virginia. [“To Blake the most insidious danger is the use of the referential language prescribed by Locke and the scientists. . . . Blake uses his own exuberant poetic language as an ‘adverse wheel’ to reveal the limitations of the empiricist paradigm. . . .”]</p>
            <p>136. Meller, Horst. “Audens ‘As I Walked Out One Evening’ und Blakes ‘London:’ Zwei Epiphanien großstädtischer Unheimlichkeit.” <hi rend="i">Anglistik und Englischunterricht</hi> 26 (1985): 107-25.</p>
            <p>137. Meller, Horst. “Gedichtstruktur und die ungelösten Antagonismen der Realität: Blakes ‘London’-Gedicht.”
<pb id="p20-84" n="84"/><hi rend="i">Zum Verstehen englischer Gedichte.</hi> Literaturstudium 2 / Uni-Taschenbücher 1070. München: UTB-Fink, 1985. 169-84.</p>
            <p>138. Miller, Dan. “Contrary Revelation: <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 491-509.</p>
            <p>139. Mitchell, Orm. “Blake’s Subversive Illustrations to Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Stories.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi> 17.4 (1984): 17-34.</p>
            <p>140. Mitchell, W. J. T. “Reply to John Grant.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 181-83. [See also #65, 89, and 148.]</p>
            <p>141. Mitchell, W. J. T. “Visible Language: Blake’s Wond’rous Art of Writing.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer. Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP, 1986. 46-86. [This essay was first read to a group of students participating in a course on “The Romantic Self,” 1982-83, at the Department of English, University of New Mexico. It is here printed together with a series of questions and the author’s answers on pp. 86-95.]</p>
            <p>142. Moskal, Jeanne. “Every Word and Every Character Was Human: Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and Literary History.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1985): 431A. U of Washington. [“This study outlines a theory of literary history based on the work of William Blake, and in particular on his poem <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> The cornerstone of this theory is Blake’s idea that poets construct their personal identities in the process of writing their poems.”]</p>
            <p>143. Mulhallen, Karen. “The Crying of Lot 318; or, Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> Colored Once More.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 71-72.</p>
            <p>144. *Nanavutty, Piloo. “Blake and Gnostic Imagery: A Note.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 9 (1984): 43-55.</p>
            <p>145. *Okuma, Akinoku. “Blake no Shiteki Gengo.” <hi rend="i">Eigo Seinen</hi> 129 (1984): 574-78.</p>
            <p>146. Ostriker, Alicia. “Reply to Hagstrum.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 238. [See also #96, above.]</p>
            <p>147. Ott, Judith Lynn. “The Illuminations of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem, The Emanation of the Giant Albion</hi>: What Are Those Golden Builders Doing?” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985): 1897-98A. Ohio State U. [“. . . an explication of the illuminations of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> with an emphasis on establishing the perimeters of his multiple sources, an understanding of his working methods as an artist and an informed appreciation of the visual themes in his symbolic system.”]</p>
            <p>148. Paley, Morton D. “Further Thoughts on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 183-84. [See also #65, 89, and 140.]</p>
            <p>149. Paley, Morton D. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and the Form of History.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 10 (1985): 66-80.</p>
            <p>150. *Pasquier, Pierre. “L’Infini qui naît au creux de la paume ou Edward Gordon Craig et William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Revue d’Histoire du Théatre</hi> 36 (1984): 227-46.</p>
            <p>151. Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake, Freemasonry and the Builder’s Task.” <hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi> 17.3 (1984): 35-57.</p>
            <p>152. Peterfreund, Stuart. “The Problem of Originality and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi>” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 52 (1985): 673-705.</p>
            <p>153. Phipps, Frances. <hi rend="i">Let Me Be Los: Codebook for</hi> Finnegans Wake. Lubbock, TX: Toth-Maatian P, 1985. $50. [This richly illustrated study was published as “Supplement A” to the <hi rend="i">Toth-Maatian Review</hi> 3.5 (1985). “Convinced of Blake’s importance to Joyce, the compiler of this codebook has put together isolated suggestions in an order which it is hoped can prove useful.” Besides this “Stolen-Telling” (p. 9), the commentary consists of hundreds of illustrations—many of ancient Egyptian artifacts, others taken from Blake’s prints and paintings—and diagrams. Orders and inquiries should be sent to the publisher’s new address at 503 West Indiana Avenue, Urbana, IL 61801.]</p>
            <p>154. Piquet, François. “Blake, l’intertexte de <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> et les tribulations d’Albion.” <hi rend="i">Romantisme</hi> 15.49 (1985): 35-45.</p>
            <p>155. *Piquet, François. “Quelques aspects de l’Eros chez Blake.” <hi rend="i">Romantisme anglais et Eros.</hi> Ed. Christian La Cassagnère. Publications de la Faculté des Lettres et Sciences Humaines de l’Université de Clermont-Ferrand II 14. Clermont-Ferrand: U de Clermont-Ferrand II, 1982. 17-28.</p>
            <p>156. Punter, David. “Blake/Hegel/Derrida: A Response to Nelson Hilton’s Review of <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel and Dialectic.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 58-63. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 113, #273.]</p>
            <p>157. Punter, David. “Blake, Trauma and the Female.” <hi rend="i">New Literary History</hi> 15 (1984): 475-90.</p>
            <p>158. Punter, David. “The Sign of Blake.” <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 26 (1984): 313-34.</p>
            <p>159. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and the City.</hi> Academic Inn Discussion Papers 7. London: privately printed for the Academic Inn, Institute of Directors, 1984. [The text of a lecture given on 20 Nov. 1984. According to the bookdealer Julian Nangle of Words etcetera, only 100 copies of this leaflet have been printed.]</p>
            <p>160. Raine, Kathleen. “Blake and Maya.” <hi rend="i">Indian Horizons</hi> 32.3 (1983): 5-24.</p>
            <p>161. Reisner, Thomas A. “Blake and Chatterton.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 328-29.</p>
            <pb id="p20-85" n="85"/>
            <p>162. *Rix, Donna S. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Blake’s Reading of Second Isaiah.” <hi rend="i">Poetic Prophecy in Western Literature.</hi> Ed. Jan Wojcik and Raymond-Jean Frontain. Rutherford, NJ: Fairleigh Dickinson UP; London: Associated UP, 1984. 106-18.</p>
            <p>163. Robertson, P. J. M. “Criticism and Creativity IV: Blake and Keats.” <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 91 (1984): 941-53.</p>
            <p>164. Rose, Edward J. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, St. Paul, and Biblical Prophecy.” <hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi> 11 (1985): 396-412.</p>
            <p>165. Rothenberg, Molly Anne. “Blake’s Higher Criticism: Rhetoric and Re-Vision in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1985): 973A. U of California, Irvine. [“I argue that Blake wrote <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in order to teach his readers to recognize the rhetorical strategies by which sacred texts are constructed so that he could liberate his readers from the institutionalized, oppressive effects of the interpretative conventions of traditional exegesis.”]</p>
            <p>166. Ryskamp, Charles. “Paul Mellon and William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Essays in Honor of Paul Mellon: Collector and Benefactor.</hi> Ed. John Wilmerding. Washington, DC: National Gallery of Art, 1986. 329-37. [A concise history of the growth of Mellon’s splendid Blake collection.]</p>
            <p>167. Sánchez Pérez, Aquilino. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Graphic Work and the Emblematic Tradition.</hi> Murcia, Spain: Secretariado de Publicaciones, U de Murcia, 1982.</p>
            <p>168. Sánchez [Pérez], Aquilino. “William Blake, pintor y poeta: hacia una nueva perspectiva en la lectura de su obra.” <hi rend="i">Departomento de Inglés: Anuario</hi> 1981: 5-23. [Published for the Facultad de Letras at the Universidad Autònoma de Barcelona.]</p>
            <p>169. Schiff, Gert. “William Blake: Anarchist, Haeretiker und Moralist.” <hi rend="i">Forma et subtilitas: Festschrift für Wolfgang Schöne zum 75. Geburtstag.</hi> Ed. Wilhelm Schlink and Martin Sperlich. Berlin: de Gruyter, 1986. 229-48.</p>
            <p>170. Shabetai, Karen. “Blake’s Perception of Evil.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1984): 1762A. U of California, San Diego. [“ . . . examines the connection between Blake’s idea about evil and his theory of perception. I locate contradictions in Blake’s ideas about theodicy, which have to do with the problems he encounters when he posits the internal world as the exclusive source of creativity, and with a system of meaning that depends on the psychological state of the perceiving subject. . . . I concentrate on Blake’s illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, early versions of the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> poems, and his Job illustrations.”]</p>
            <p>171. Shaviro, Steven. “‘Striving With Systems:’ Blake and the Politics of Difference.” <hi rend="i">Boundary 2</hi> 10.3 (1982): 229-50.</p>
            <p>172. Singh, Charu Sheel. <hi rend="i">The Chariot of Fire: A Study of William Blake in the Light of Hindu Thought.</hi> Salzburg Studies in English Literature III: Romantic Reassessment 104. Salzburg, Austria: Institut für Anglistik und Amerikanistik, U of Salzburg, 1981. $25. [Distributed in the United States by Humanities P.]</p>
            <p>173. Singh, Gurbhagat. <hi rend="i">Poetry as Metaconsciousness: Readings in William Blake.</hi> Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P, 1983. $16.</p>
            <p>174. Sosnowski, T. Ford. “Meter and Form in Blake’s ‘The Lamb’ and ‘The Tyger.’ ” <hi rend="i">Kwartalnik Neofilologiczny</hi> 31 (1984): 407-16.</p>
            <p>175. Spector, Sheila A. “Death in Blake’s Major Prophecies.” <hi rend="i">Studia Mystica</hi> 7.3 (1984): 3-28.</p>
            <p>176. *Staudt, Kathleen Henderson. “The Text as Material and as Sign: Poetry and Incarnation in William Blake, Arthur Rimbaud, and David Jones.” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Studies</hi> 14 (1984): 13-30.</p>
            <p>177. Storch, Margaret. “The ‘Spectrous Fiend’ Cast Out: Blake’s Crisis at Felpham.” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 44 (1983): 115-35. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 68, #133.]</p>
            <p>178. Suzuki, Masashi. “[Confined Force and Motion: <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> and Newtonian Dynamics.]” <hi rend="i">Studies in English</hi> [Tokyo] 59 (1982): 29-42. [For a summary in English see <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi> 59 (1983): 251-52.]</p>
            <p>179. Taft, Richard Tomlinson. “The Relationship between Art and Philosophy: An Examination of Hegel, Blake, Nietzsche and Heidegger.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985): 3367A. Duquesne U. [“In Chapter 4 the works of William Blake and Friedrich Nietzsche are discussed because each attempts to transgress the traditionally established boundary between art and philosophy.”]</p>
            <p>180. Taylor, Dena Bain. “Emanations of the Divine: Kabbalistic Elements in the Poetry and Designs of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985): 2889A. U of Toronto. [The author “establishes the significance of the influence of the Kabbalah in Blake’s work and a biographical context for the influence.”]</p>
            <p>181. Tidwell, Paul Alexander. “Joyce’s Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984): 3075A. State U of New York, Buffalo. [“Joyce refused to adhere to his contemporaries’ classification of Blake as a mystic . . . (he) learned contrariety, simultaneity, tenacity, and charity from Blake.”]</p>
            <p>182. Twitchell, James B. “Blake: The Anti-Sublime.” <hi rend="i">Romantic Horizons: Aspects of the Sublime in English Poetry and Painting 1770-1850.</hi> Columbia, MO: U of Missouri P, 1983. 40-59.</p>
            <p>183. Van Schaik, Pamela. “Blake’s Vision of the Fall and Redemption of Man: A Reading Based on the Contrary Images of Innocence and Experience.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1984): 1411A. U of South Africa. [“This thesis explores Blake’s vision of the Fall of Man, and his restoration to Eden, in terms of the poet’s
<pb id="p20-86" n="86"/>
consistent use of contrary pairs of images to denote the ‘States’ of Innocence and Experience. It attempts to provide a matrix for Blake’s images, and to demonstrate the unity and coherence of his symbolic vision by relating the symbols of his poetry to those of his visual art.”]</p>
            <p>184. Viscomi, Joseph. “Recreating Blake’s Illuminated Prints: The Facsimiles of the Manchester Etching Workshop.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 4-23.</p>
            <p>185. Vogler, Thomas A. “Intertextual Signifiers and the Blake of That Already.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 9.1 (1985): 1-33.</p>
            <p>186. Warner, Janet A. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art.</hi> Kingston, ON: McGill-Queen’s UP; Gloucester, Glos.: Sutton, 1984. $29.95. [This study is concerned with “a kind of visual vocabulary,” “with a set of visual forms, gestures and attitudes of the human body,” which were repeatedly used in Blake’s designs. As in her earlier articles, the author’s “approach to Blake is from design to poetry” and attempts “to demonstrate the variety and importance” of the artist’s “visual shorthand.” Thus, Warner’s “central concern” is to show “to what extent Blake’s formula-figures stand alone as symbols and to what extent their meanings are defined by the context in which they appear.” (pp. xvii-xviii)]</p>
            <p>187. Warner, Nicholas O. “Visual Analogues to Blake’s ‘The Dog.’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 140-43.</p>
            <p>188. Weathers, Winston. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>: A Transaction.” <hi rend="i">The Nature of Identity: Essays Presented to Donald E. Hayden by the Graduate Faculty of Modern Letters, The University of Tulsa.</hi> Tulsa, OK: U of Tulsa, 1981. 71-91.</p>
            <p>189. Wetenhall, John. “Blake’s Sketches for ‘Hamlet.’ ” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 127 (1985): 229. [A letter to the editor, discussing the subject and date (c. 1805-06) of Butlin’s #74 recto and verso, #75, 140, and 547(5).]</p>
            <p>190. Whitmarsh-Knight, David Edward. “Structure as a Key to Meaning in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1984): 1764A. U of New Brunswick. [“This dissertation provides virtually a line by line textual analysis and critical commentary of . . . <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> which traces the poem’s mythology and plot, helps reveal Blake’s conscious craftsmanship, and relates the poem’s parts to the work as a whole.”]</p>
            <p>191. Wilkinson, D. R. M. “Blake’s ‘Songs:’ Taking Stock, 1984.” <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi> 66 (1985): 227-40.</p>
            <p>192. “William Blake: Prints and Drawings.” <hi rend="i">National Galleries of Scotland News</hi> May / June 1986: n. pag. [An anonymous announcement of a small studio exhibition of the Blake holdings at the Department of Prints and Drawings of the National Gallery of Scotland which was to be seen at The Mound from 3 May to 13 July 1986.]</p>
            <p>193. Wintersgill, Donald. “Museum Is Given Blakes.” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> 16 May 1985: 5. [Reports the acquisition of the late Sir Geoffrey Keynes’s Blake collection by the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, Cambs.]</p>
            <p>194. *Witke, Joanne. <hi rend="i">William Blake and Human Imagination.</hi> London: Croom Helm, 1986. £19.95.</p>
            <p>195. Yoshimura, Masakazu. “[Blake and the Cycle Symbolism.]” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi> [Tokyo] 60 (1983): 47-59. [For a summary in English see <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi> 61 (1984): 116-17.]</p>
            <p>196. Zimmerman, Daniel John. “‘What Are Those Golden Builders Doing?:’ A Study of Blake’s Poetics of Reception.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984): 3075A. State U of New York, Buffalo. [“William Blake’s poetics establishes his authority to divine and revise the received word in two dimensions, contention and combat, each of them twofold. . . . Examined in this framework, the dynamics of Blake’s poetic ‘moves’ suggest the need to enlarge reception theory with imaginal ‘fit auditors’ of inspiration in poet and reader alike. . . .”]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part II Blake’s Circle</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">General Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>197. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">The Thames and Hudson Encyclopaedia of British Art.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, 1985. £10.50. [Contains entries on most of the artist members of Blake’s circle (Barry, Bartolozzi, Blake himself, Calvert, Flaxman, Fuseli, Gillray, the two classicist Hamiltons, Jeffreys, Kauffmann, Payne Knight, Linnell, Loutherbourg, the Master of the Giants, Mortimer, Opie, Palmer, Richmond, Romney, the Runcimans, Stothard, Varley, and West), and with short articles on history painting, Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, the industrial revolution, neoclassicism, the Royal Academy, Shoreham, and the sublime will make a most useful work of reference for anybody interested in British art of Blake’s—or, in fact, any other—period.]</p>
            <p>198. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Great Images of British Printmaking: A Descriptive Catalogue 1789-1939.</hi> London: Garton, 1978. [Published in conjunction with an exhibition at Garton’s gallery; prints by Blake, Richmond, Calvert, Palmer, and the British neoromantics who were influenced by them, figured largely in the show (see #2-6, 9, 10, 18 and 19 of this catalogue).]</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">James Barry</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>199. *Allan, D. G. C. “Barry and Johnson.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 133 (1985): 628-32.</p>
              <p>200. Barrell, John. “The Functions of Art in a Commercial Society: The Writings of James Barry.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 25 (1984): 117-40.</p>
              <pb id="p20-87" n="87"/>
              <p>201. Brown, David Blayney. “Testaments of Friendship; Two New Portraits by James Barry of Francis Douce and Joseph Nollekens.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 27-31.</p>
              <p>202. *Hamlyn, Robin. “James Barry: The Ideals of High Art and the Problems of Patronage.” <hi rend="i">Antique Collector</hi> 54 (1983): 66-70. [Possibly no more than a review of Pressly’s monograph and / or the Tate Gallery’s Barry exhibition of 1983.]</p>
              <p>203. McNamara, RuthAnn. “The Theme of the Learned Painter in Eighteenth-Century British Self-Portraiture.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984): 3526A. Bryn Mawr College. [Examines “the interpretation of the ideal of the learned painter in eighteenth-century England as revealed in the self-portraits of Hogarth, Reynolds, West, Barry, and Fuseli. . . . In the fourth chapter, the self-portraits of Barry and Fuseli are examined as examples of the ambivalence created by the clash between the ideal of the learned painter and the growing strength of the concept of original genius. Finally, Blake’s total rejection of the premises upon which the ideal of the learned painter rested is seen as heralding the decline of the influence of the notion of the learned painter in eighteenth-century England.”]</p>
              <p>204. *Pressly, William L. “A Chapel of Natural and Revealed Religion: James Barry’s Series for the Society’s Great Room Reinterpreted.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 132 (1984): 543-46, 634-37, and 693-95.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Staden Blake</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>205. Warner, Janet [A.] “Trade Cards of W. S. Blake.” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 32 (1983): 105-07.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">See also</hi> #43, <hi rend="i">above.</hi></p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Edward Calvert</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See #19, 25, and 198 above, as well as #250, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Cowper</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>206. Anderson, David R. “Landscape and Theodicy in Pope, Thomson, and Cowper.” <hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi> 13 (1986): 13-27.</p>
              <p>207. Davie, Donald. “Homage to Cowper.” <hi rend="i">PN Review</hi> 6.6 (1980): 21-24.</p>
              <p>208. Digby, Joan Owen. “Survival of the ‘Stricken Deer.’ ” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 85 (1982): 341-43.</p>
              <p>209. *Hartley, Lodwick. “Harlequin Intrudes: William Cowper’s Venture into the Satiric Mode.” <hi rend="i">The Dress of Words: Essays on Restoration and Eighteenth-Century Literature in Honor of Richmond P. Bond.</hi> Ed. Robert B. White, Jr. Lawrence, KS: U of Kansas Libraries, 1978. 127-37.</p>
              <p>210. King, James. “Some Additions and Corrections to ‘New and Corrected Cowper Correspondence.’ ” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 30 (1983): 63. [See also #223, below.]</p>
              <p>211. *King, James. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: A Biography.</hi> Durham, NC: Duke UP, 1986. $35.</p>
              <p>212. *Moreux, Françoise. “Identité et folie chez Cowper.” <hi rend="i">Folie, folies, folly dans le monde anglo-américain aux XVII<hi rend="s">e</hi> et XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> siècles.</hi> Aix-en-Provence: PU de Provence, for the Société d’Ètudes Anglo-Américaines des XVII<hi rend="s">e</hi> et XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> Siècles, 1984. 165-75.</p>
              <p>213. *Rawson, Claude. <hi rend="i">Order from Confusion Sprung: Studies in Eighteenth-Century Literature from Swift to Cowper.</hi> London: Allen, 1985. $31.</p>
              <p>214. Schmidt, A. V. C. “T. S. Eliot and William Cowper: A New <hi rend="i">Waste Land</hi> Source.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 29 (1982): 347.</p>
              <p>215. Sherbo, Arthur. “Cowper’s ‘Stricken Deer’ and Literary Tradition.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 85 (1982): 336-40.</p>
              <p>216. Sherbo, Arthur. “Three Letters of Samuel Boyse and a Poem by Cowper(?).” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 33 (1986): 78-80.</p>
              <p>217. Sherbo, Arthur. “William Cowper and the <hi rend="i">European Magazine.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 34 (1981): 238-41.</p>
              <p>218. Sherbo, Arthur. “William Cowper’s Bullfinch Poem: a Minor Sub-Genre?” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 243-45.</p>
              <p>219. Smith, Margaret M. “A Missing Cowper Letter Found.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 245-46.</p>
              <p>220. Ty, Eleanor. “Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Connoisseur</hi> #138 and Samuel Johnson.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 33 (1986): 63-64.</p>
              <p>221. Vogler, Thomas A. “The Tropology of Silence in Eighteenth-Century English Blank Verse.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 26 (1985): 211-37. [Besides Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Task</hi>, Vogler discusses works such as Thomson’s <hi rend="i">Seasons</hi> or Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>]</p>
              <p>222. Watson, J. R. “Cowper’s Olney Hymns.” <hi rend="i">Essays and Studies</hi> 38 (1985): 45-65.</p>
              <p>223. Weinglass, D[avid] H. “New and Corrected Cowper Correspondence.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 27 (1980): 416-18. [Includes the publication of a letter by Hayley to Mrs. Rose of 7 March 1794.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #114, above, and #240 and 319, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">George Cumberland</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>224. *Cumberland, George. <hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar.</hi> Ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr. Newcastle-upon-Tyne: Avero, 1983. £14. [This entry was lifted from the current edition of <hi rend="i">British Books in Print</hi>; G. E. Bentley, Jr., however, now informs me that his edition of Cumberland’s narrative so far has <hi rend="i">not</hi> been printed at all, but may be available from a different publisher in 1987-88.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #260, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p20-88" n="88"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>225. Becquemont, Daniel. “Erasmus Darwin, médecin et poète: 1731-1802.” <hi rend="i">Revue des Sciences Humaines</hi> 69.198 (1985): 9-29.</p>
              <p>226. Cohen, B. “Erasmus Darwin’s Observations on Rotation and Vertigo.” <hi rend="i">Human Neurobiology</hi> 3 (1984): 121-28.</p>
              <p>227. Colp, Ralph, Jr. “The Relationship of Charles Darwin to the Ideas of His Grandfather, Dr. Erasmus Darwin.” <hi rend="i">Biography</hi> 9 (1986): 1-24.</p>
              <p>228. Hart, Clive. “Erasmus Darwin’s Model Goose.” <hi rend="i">Aeronautical Journal of the Royal Aeronautical Society</hi> 89 (1985): 17-20.</p>
              <p>229. Hassler, Donald M. “New Diggings in Old Mines: Erasmus Darwin and Romantic Views on Evolution.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 26-28.</p>
              <p>230. *King-Hele, Desmond. <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin and the Romantic Poets.</hi> London: Macmillan, 1985. [Darwin’s influence on Blake’s writings of the Lambeth period is dealt with in detail.]</p>
              <p>231. King-Hele, Desmond. “Erasmus Darwin: Master of Interdisciplinary Science.” <hi rend="i">Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</hi> 10 (1985): 170-91. [An extremely useful introduction to Darwin’s career and many-faceted scientific achievements.]</p>
              <p>232. King-Hele, Desmond. “Erasmus Darwin’s Contributions to Geophysics and Astronomy.” <hi rend="i">Vistas in Astronomy</hi> 27 (1984): 63-75.</p>
              <p>233. Sheffield, Charles. <hi rend="i">Erasmus Magister.</hi> New York, NY: Ace Books, 1982. [Described by Desmond King-Hele as a kind of “historical fiction.”]</p>
              <p>234. *Ullrich, David W. “Distinctions in Poetic and Intellectual Influence: Coleridge’s Use of Erasmus Darwin.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 74-80[?81].</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>235. Hendriks, Ella. “The First Patron of Flaxman.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 618-25.</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #10, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>236. Andrews, Keith. “Scottish Artists in the Roman Circle of Winckelmann and Fuseli.” <hi rend="i">“Sind Briten hier?:” Relations between British and Continental Art 1680-1880.</hi> Ed. Zentralinstitut für Kunstgeschichte in München. Proc. of a Conference at the Zentralinstitut, organized on the occasion of the exhibition “Zwei Jahrhunderte englische Malerei.” 14-15 Jan. 1980. Munich: Fink, 1981. 83-95. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 14 (1980): 86.]</p>
              <p>237. *Gizzi, Corrado, ed. <hi rend="i">Füssli e Dante.</hi> Milano, It.: Torre de’Passeri-Pinacoteca di Brera, 1985. [An exhibition catalogue, reported to contain a series of essays on Fuseli’s early and important “discovery” of Dante’s poetry as a subject for the visual arts.]</p>
              <p>238. Hahn, Karl-Friedrich. “‘Raffael und die Fornarina:’ eine Bilderfindung Johann Heinrich Füsslis.” <hi rend="i">Labyrinthos</hi> 3.5-6 (1984): 37-53.</p>
              <p>239. Hammerschmidt-Hummel, Hildegard. “Johann Heinrich Füsslis Illustrationen zu Shakespeares <hi rend="i">Macheth</hi> unter besonderer Berücksichtigung seiner Kunsttheorie.” <hi rend="i">Arcadia</hi> 20 (1985): 225-38.</p>
              <p>240. King, James. “An Unlikely Alliance: Fuseli as Revisor of Cowper’s Homer.” <hi rend="i">Neophilologus</hi> 67 (1983): 468-79.</p>
              <p>241. Klemm, Christian. <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli: Zeichnungen.</hi> Kunsthaus Zürich: Sammlungsheft 12. Zurich: Kunsthaus Zürich, 1986. [Almost a catalogue raisonné of the Kunsthaus’ holdings of Fuseli drawings, published in conjunction with an exhibition of fifty of these drawings held at the Kunsthaus from 23 May to 17 Aug. 1986.]</p>
              <p>242. Ottani Cavina, Anna. “Giani e la cerchia di Füssli a Roma.” <hi rend="i">Paragone</hi> 36.419/421/423 (1985): 279-85.</p>
              <p>243. *Schiff, Gert, and Paola Viotto. <hi rend="i">Tout l’oeuvre peint de Füssli.</hi> Classiques de l’Art. Paris: Flammarion, 1980. [The French edition of vol. 91 in the Classici dell’Arte series which was first published at Milan in 1977; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12 (1978): 147.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #99 and 203, above, as well as #280, #290, and #320, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Hayley</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>244. *Bishop, Morchard [i.e., Oliver Stoner]. “William Haley [sic] and His Last Printer.” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 31 (1982): 187-200. [Includes the publication of almost seventy letters exchanged between Hayley and the family of William Mason, who became Seagrave’s successor as Hayley’s favorite printer.]</p>
              <p>245. *Whiteley, Paul. “Beattie, More, and Hayley.” <hi rend="i">The Late Augustans and the Origins of English Romanticism.</hi> London: Croom Helm, 1985. £15.95.</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #223, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Linnell</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See #19, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>246. Bindman, David. “Samuel Palmer’s <hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors of West Kent, 1832</hi> Rediscovered.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 56-59. [See also #251, below.]</p>
              <p>247. Butlin, Martin. “Connoisseurship and the Palmer Fakes.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19
<pb id="p20-89" n="89"/>
(1986): 155. [A reply to Lister’s review of <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers</hi> that is listed as #471.2, below.]</p>
              <p>248. *Irwin, Helen. “Samuel Palmer, Poet of Light and Shade: His Last Years at Reigate, Surrey.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 114 (1981): 109-13.</p>
              <p>249. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, in association with the Pevensey P, 1985. £17.50. [This is not a catalogue raisonné; the volume offers some 75 color plates which reproduce, besides Palmer’s oil paintings, some of his watercolors, his gouaches, his drawings, and even his prints; all are briefly described by the author. A companion volume on <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake</hi> in the same format is to be published in fall 1986.]</p>
              <p>250. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer and ‘The Ancients.’</hi> Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, for the Fitzwilliam Museum, 1984. £24 cloth/£8.95 paper. [The catalogue of an exhibition which was shown at the Fitzwilliam from 9 Oct. to 16 Dec. 1984. Represented in the exhibition were 149 items, all of which are illustrated and discussed in this catalogue; besides the Palmers they include works by Calvert, Finch, Richmond, Sherman, Tatham, as well as a few Blakes.]</p>
              <p>251. Palmer, Samuel. “An Address to the Electors of West Kent [ . . . ] 1832.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 60-68. [A reprint of Palmer’s <hi rend="i">Address</hi>, edited by David Bindman. See also #246, above.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #10 and 19, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">George Romney</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>252. Burkett, Mary E., ed. <hi rend="i">George Romney 1734-1802.</hi> Kendal, Cumbria: Abbot Hall Gallery, 1984. [The catalogue of a small exhibition, shown from 5 July to 2 Sept. 1984 in Romney’s home county to celebrate the 250th anniversary of the artist’s birth. Besides ten oil paintings, a selection of thirty-nine pencil, pen and ink, and wash drawings were on show. The small catalogue also contains a four-page essay on “George Romney and His Drawings” by Gerhard Charles Rump.]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Varley</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>253. Kauffmann, C. M. <hi rend="i">John Varley 1778-1842.</hi> British Watercolours. London: Batsford, in association with the Victoria and Albert Museum, 1984. £7.95 paper.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part III Works of Related Interest</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some General Studies, Mostly of Romantic Art, Poetry, and Their Historical Context</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>254. *Albright, Daniel. <hi rend="i">Lyricality in English Literature.</hi> Lincoln, NE: U of Nebraska P, 1985. $24.50.</p>
            <p>255. *Alford, Steven E. <hi rend="i">Irony and the Logic of the Romantic Imagination.</hi> American University Studies, 3rd ser.: Comparative Literature 13. New York, NY: Lang, 1984. $19.45.</p>
            <p>256. *Altizer, Thomas J. J. “The Apocalyptic Identity of the Modern Imagination.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the American Academy of Religion: Thematic Studies</hi> 48 (1981): 19-29.</p>
            <p>257. *Baker, Carlos. <hi rend="i">The Echoing Green: Romanticism, Modernism, and the Phenomena of Transference in Poetry.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1984. $32.50.</p>
            <p>258. Behrendt, Stephen C. “The Best Criticism: Imitation as Criticism in the Eighteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 24 (1983): 3-22. [Blake’s works are cited as an <hi rend="i">exemplum.</hi>]</p>
            <p>259. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Freaks of Learning: Learned Pigs, Musical Hares, and the Romantics.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 18 (1982): 87-104. [Includes a discussion of Blake’s learned pigs and his “Hare playing on a Tabor;” see pp. 101-03.]</p>
            <p>260. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “<hi rend="i">Rasselas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Gaudentio di Lucca</hi> in the Mountains of the Moon.” <hi rend="i">Revista Canaria de Estudios Ingleses</hi> 9 (1984): 1-11. [In a “Postscript” (pp. 9-10) Bentley compares Johnson’s and Berington’s novels with George Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Captive of the Castle of Sennaar</hi> and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi>]</p>
            <p>261. *Bridson, Gavin, and Geoffrey Wakeman. <hi rend="i">Printmaking and Picture Printing: A Bibliographical Guide to Artistic and Industrial Techniques in Britain 1750-1900.</hi> Kidlington, Oxon.: Plough P, 1984. £30.</p>
            <p>262. Bruntjen, Sven H. A. <hi rend="i">John Boydell (1719-1804): A Study of Art Patronage and Publishing in Georgian London.</hi> Outstanding Dissertations in the Fine Arts. New York, NY: Garland, 1985. $50. [The reprint of a 1974 Stanford U Ph.D. thesis.]</p>
            <p>263. Cantor, Paul A. <hi rend="i">Creature and Creator: Myth-Making and English Romanticism.</hi> Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1984. $34.50. [Includes a discussion of the creation myth in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>]</p>
            <p>264. Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi> Vols. 13-16 (Jan. 1814 to Dec. 1821). Studies in British Art. New Haven, CT: Yale UP, for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1984. £90. [The entire text of the diary has now been printed; despite the annoying number of typographical as well as editorial errors that have already been detected, the sixteen volumes certainly mark a major achievement for all future “Studies in British Art” of the times of William Blake. A detailed editorial commentary and the much needed index are said to be forthcoming.]</p>
            <p>265. *Cook, Albert. <hi rend="i">Thresholds: Studies in the Romantic Experience.</hi> Madison, WI: U of Wisconsin P, 1985. $37.50. [Said to treat Blake in the ‘context’ of such writers as Dickinson, Dostoevsky, and Mallarmé.]</p>
            <pb id="p20-90" n="90"/>
            <p>266. Cooke, Michael G. “Romanticism and the Paradox of Wholeness.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 23 (1984): 435-53. [There are numerous references to the “paradox of wholeness” in the writings of Blake.]</p>
            <p>267. Cooksey, Thomas L. “Dante’s England, 1818: The Contribution of Cary, Coleridge, and Foscolo to the British Reception of Dante.” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 20 (1984): 355-81.</p>
            <p>268. Dobai, Johannes. <hi rend="i">Die Kunstliteratur des Klassizismus und der Romantik in England.</hi> Vol. 4: “Registerband.” Comp. Katharina Dobai. Berne: Benteli, n.d. [1984]. DM140. [On more than 300 pages these indexes supply an indispensable guide to the astonishing riches of the previous three volumes of Dobai’s monumental “Prolegomena.” It is to be regretted, however, that illness prevented the author from contributing a list of <hi rend="i">errata et corrigenda</hi> for vols. 1-3 to the present publication, the compilation of which he entrusted to his daughter.]</p>
            <p>269. Epstein, Julia L., and Mark L. Greenberg. “Decomposing Newton’s Rainbow.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi> 45 (1984): 115-40. [On “the history of the rainbow as natural object, as object of scientific study, and as poetic image” (p. 140); Blake’s reaction towards Newton is briefly sketched on pp. 136-37.]</p>
            <p>270. Frye, Northrop. “The Survival of Eros in Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer. Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP, 1986. 15-29. [Frye’s essay is not directly concerned with the poetry of Blake; it was originally read to a class of students participating in a course on “The Romantic Self,” offered by Eaves and Fischer in 1982-1983 at the Department of English of the University of New Mexico; it is here printed together with the students’ questions and Frye’s answers, however, and there the author tells his audience how he has learned his “views of Christianity more or less from Blake.” (p. 29)]</p>
            <p>271. Garlick, Kenneth. “Illustrations to ‘A Midsummer Night’s Dream’ Before 1920.” <hi rend="i">Shakespeare Survey</hi> 37 (1984): 41-53.</p>
            <p>272. Gourlay, Alexander S. “Iphigenia in England: A Postscript to ‘The Melancholy Shepherdess.’ ” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983): 223-26. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 103, #56.]</p>
            <p>273. McGann, Jerome J. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical Investigation.</hi> Chicago, IL: U of Chicago P, 1983. $15. [Blake’s writings are referred to throughout. In 1985, a paperback edition of this book was issued at $6.50.]</p>
            <p>274. Meller, Horst. “Prometheus im romantischen Heiligen-Kalender.” <hi rend="i">Antike Tradition und Neuere Philologien: Symposium zu Ehren des 75. Geburtstages von Rudolf Sühnel.</hi> Ed. Hans-Joachim Zimmermann. Heidelberg, W. Ger.: Winter, 1984. 151-75.</p>
            <p>275. Melot, Michel. <hi rend="i">The Art of Illustration.</hi> New York, NY: Rizzoli, 1984. $60.</p>
            <p>276. Mitchell, W. J. T., ed. <hi rend="i">The Language of Images.</hi> Chicago, IL: U of Chicago P, 1980. $7.95. [Most of the fourteen essays in this collection had previously appeared in print in <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry.</hi>]</p>
            <p>277. Rosenblum, Robert, and H. W. Janson. <hi rend="i">Art of the Nineteenth Century: Painting and Sculpture.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, 1984. £25. [The US edition was published under the slightly different title of <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Art</hi> (New York, NY: Abrams, 1984). For some general accounts of artists such as Banks, Barry, Blake, Flaxman, Fuseli, Loutherbourg, Palmer, or West, refer to the index.]</p>
            <p>278. *Schwartz, Richard B. <hi rend="i">Daily Life in Johnson’s London.</hi> Madison, WI: U of Wisconsin P, 1984. $25 cloth / $9.95 paper.</p>
            <p>279. Stafford, Barbara Maria. “From ‘Brilliant Ideas’ to ‘Fitful Thoughts:’ Conjecturing the Unseen in Late Eighteenth-Century Art.” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Kunstgeschichte</hi> 48 (1985): 329-63.</p>
            <p>280. *Starobinski, Jean. <hi rend="i">1789: The Emblems of Reason.</hi> Trans. Barbara Bray. Charlottesville, VA: UP of Virginia, 1982. $24.95. [The American edition of Starobinski’s book of 1973 with a chapter on Fuseli. For the original French edition and a German translation see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 15 (1981): 88, #131; 16 (1982): 117, #147.]</p>
            <p>281. Wilson, Peter Lamborn. <hi rend="i">Angels.</hi> New York, NY: Pantheon; London: Thames and Hudson, 1980. [A general survey of the iconography and formal history of the winged figure, with reproductions and brief discussions of five Blakean examples.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Contemporary Artists, Collectors, and Connoisseurs</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>282. Abrams, Ann Uhry. “Benjamin West’s Documentation of Colonial History: ‘William Penn’s Treaty with the Indians.’ ” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 64 (1983): 59-75.</p>
            <p>283. *Abrams, Ann Uhry. <hi rend="i">The Valiant Hero: Benjamin West and Grand-Style History Painting.</hi> New Directions in American Art 1. Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution P, 1985. $48 cloth / $24.95 paper.</p>
            <p>284. Dekker, H. T. Douwes. “Angelica Kaufmann [sic] imitatrice de Madame Vigée-LeBrun?” <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 104 (1984): 195.</p>
            <p>285. *Erffa, Helmut von, and Allen Staley. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Benjamin West.</hi> New Haven, CT: Yale UP, in association with the Barra Foundation, 1986. £50. [A catalogue raisonné.]</p>
            <p>286. *Flexner, James Thomas. <hi rend="i">America’s Old Masters.</hi> New York, NY: McGraw-Hill, 1982. [A revised edition of Flexner’s pioneering study of 1939; contains chapters on West and Copley.]</p>
            <pb id="p20-91" n="91"/>
            <p>287. Honour, Hugh. “Benjamin West’s ‘Indian Family.’ ” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 125 (1983): 726-33.</p>
            <p>288. *Maue, Claudia. “Angelica Kauffmann invenit—Bildvorlagen für Wiener Porzellane.” <hi rend="i">Keramos</hi> 90 (1980): 9-38. [On Vienna porcelain decorated with pictures following Angelica’s compositions.]</p>
            <p>289. Nobs-Greter, Ruth. “Zur Rezeptionsgeschichte von Angelika Kauffmann (1741-1807): ‘Weiblichkeit’ im Urteil der deutschsprachigen Kunstgeschichtsschreibung.” <hi rend="i">Die Künstlerin und ihr Werk in der deutschsprachigen Kunstgeschichtsschreibung.</hi> Zurich: Juris, 1984. 121-63. [Feminist in approach, this chapter from a Zurich Ph.D. thesis traces the prejudices involved in the critical literature on ‘Miss Angel’ from Herder to the present.]</p>
            <p>290. O’Brien, Elvy Setterqvist. “Johan Tobias Sergell (1740-1814) and Neoclassicism: Sculpture of Sergell’s Years Abroad, 1767-1779.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1983): 5A. U of Iowa. [Treats Sergel’s artistic relationship with Fuseli and analyzes Ozias Humphrey’s comments on Sergel’s Roman works.]</p>
            <p>291. *Ottley, William Young. <hi rend="i">The Italian School of Design.</hi> 1823. New York, NY: Garland, 1980. $50.</p>
            <p>292. Petschauer, Peter. “Christina Dorothea Leporin (Erxleben), Sophia (Gutermann) von La Roche, and Angelika Kauffmann: Background and Dilemmas of Independence.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi> 15 (1986): 127-43.</p>
            <p>293. Roworth, Wendy Wassyng. “Angelica Kauffman’s [sic] ‘Memorandum of Paintings.’ ” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 629-30.</p>
            <p>294. Roworth, Wendy Wassyng. “The Gentle Art of Persuasion: Angelica Kaufman’s [sic] ‘Praxiteles and Phryne.’ ” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 65 (1983): 488-92.</p>
            <p>295. Sund, Judy. “Benjamin West: A Scene from <hi rend="i">King Lear.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Detroit Institute of Arts</hi> 58 (1980): 127-36. [Discusses the sketch for West’s painting in the Boydell Shakespeare Gallery.]</p>
            <p>296. Sutton, Denys. “Aspects of British Collecting, Part IV, 14: From Ottley to Eastlake.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 122 (1985): 84-95.</p>
            <p>297. Walker, John. “Maria Cosway: An Undervalued Artist.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 123 (1986): 318-24.</p>
            <p>298. Waterhouse, Ellis K. “Reynolds, Angelica Kauffmann and Lord Boringdon.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 122 (1985): 270-74.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Contemporary Authors</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>299. *Butler, Marilyn, ed. <hi rend="i">Burke, Paine, Godwin, and the Revolutionary Controversy.</hi> Cambridge: Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1984. $39.50 cloth / $13.95 paper.</p>
            <p>300. Butler, Marilyn. “Godwin, Burke, and <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 32 (1982): 237-57.</p>
            <p>301. Canovan, Margaret. “The Un-Benthamite Utilitarianism of Joseph Priestley.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi> 45 (1984): 435-50.</p>
            <p>302. DePorte, Michael. “The Consolations of Fiction: Mystery in <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 20 (1984): 154-64.</p>
            <p>303. Elder, Thomas Balfour. “Godwin and ‘The Great Springs of Human Passion.’ ” <hi rend="i">Ariel</hi> 14.1 (1983): 15-31.</p>
            <p>304. Ferguson, Moira, and Janet Todd. <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft.</hi> Twayne English Authors Series 381. Boston, Mass.: Twayne-G. K. Hall, 1984. $17.95.</p>
            <p>305. *Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Politics of Richard Price and Joseph Priestley: A Study in Late Eighteenth-Century English Republican Millennialism.</hi> Transactions of the American Philosophical Society 73.4. Philadelphia, PA: American Philosophical Society, 1983. £10.</p>
            <p>306. Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. “Joseph Priestley on Rhetoric and the Power of Political Discourse.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi> ns 7.3 (1982): 37-47.</p>
            <p>307. Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. “The Revolutionary Millennialism of Thomas Paine.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi> 13 (1984): 65-77.</p>
            <p>308. Garrett, Clarke. “Swedenborg and the Mystical Enlightenment in Late Eighteenth-Century England.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi> 45 (1984): 67-81.</p>
            <p>309. Graham, Kenneth W. “The Gothic Unity of Godwin’s <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 20 (1984): 47-59.</p>
            <p>310. *Hardt, Ulrich H., ed. <hi rend="i">A Critical Edition of Mary Wollstonecraft’s</hi> A Vindication of the Rights of Woman: With Strictures on Politics and Moral Subjects. Troy, NY: Whitston, 1982. $45.</p>
            <p>311. Kelly, Gary. “Convention and Criticism in William Godwin’s Early Novels.” <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 33 (1984): 52-69.</p>
            <p>312. *Marshall, Peter H. <hi rend="i">William Godwin: Philosopher, Novelist, Revolutionary.</hi> New Haven, CT: Yale UP, 1984. $30.</p>
            <p>313. *Palacio, Jean de. <hi rend="i">William Godwin et son monde intérieur.</hi> Lille: PU de Lille, 1980.</p>
            <p>314. *Payne, Michael. “Priestley, Paine, and the Tradition of English Dissent.” <hi rend="i">Pennsylvania English</hi> 10 (1983): 5-13.</p>
            <p>315. Poovey, Mary. “Mary Wollstonecraft: The Gender of Genres in Late Eighteenth-Century England.” <hi rend="i">Novel: A Forum on Fiction</hi> 15 (1982): 111-26.</p>
            <p>316. Poovey, Mary. <hi rend="i">The Proper Lady and the Woman Writer: Ideology as Style in the Works of Mary Wollstonecraft, Mary Shelley, and Jane Austen.</hi> Women in Culture and Society. Chicago, IL: U of Chicago P, 1984. [“Man’s Discourse, Woman’s Heart: Mary Wollstonecraft’s Two Vindications” is on pp. 48-81; Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> and <hi rend="i">Maria, or the Wrongs of Woman</hi> are
<pb id="p20-92" n="92"/>
discussed in the following chapter on pp. 82-113.]</p>
            <p>317. Scheuermann, Mona. “The Study of Mind: the Later Novels of William Godwin.” <hi rend="i">Forum for Modern Language Studies</hi> 19 (1983): 16-30.</p>
            <p>318. Stewart, Sally N. “Mary Wollstonecraft’s Contributions to the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi> 11 (1984): 187-99.</p>
            <p>319. Tysdahl, B. J. <hi rend="i">William Godwin as Novelist.</hi> London: Athlone P, 1981. £15 cloth / £5.95 paper. [Discusses “links between social forces and mental disease” as interpreted by Godwin, Cowper, and Blake; see pp. 143-45.]</p>
            <p>320. Willey, Edward P. “The Works of Alexander Chalmers, Journalist, Editor, Biographer.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983): 94-104. [In 1805, Chalmers edited <hi rend="i">The Plays of William Shakspeare</hi>, illustrated with engravings by Blake, Cromek, et al. after a series of designs by Henry Fuseli.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Blake Scholars and Collectors</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>321. Bentinck-Smith, William. “Prince of the Eye: Philip Hofer and the Harvard Library.” <hi rend="i">Harvard Library Bulletin</hi> 32 (1984): 317-47. [A second part of this article is forthcoming.]</p>
            <p>322. Damon, S. Foster. “<hi rend="i">Thy</hi> Hand, Great Anarch.” <hi rend="i">Michigan Quarterly Review</hi> 24 (1985): 371. [A reprint of one of Foster Damon’s poems, first published in <hi rend="i">Nightmare Cemetry</hi> (1964).]</p>
            <p>323. Greenberg, Mark L. “Relentless Quest for Association Copy.” <hi rend="i">AB: Bookman’s Weekly / Antiquarian Bookman</hi> 68.11 (1981): 1587-96. [Relates the story of the author’s (successful) search for William Bell Scott’s transcript and tracings from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook.</hi> See also #90, above.]</p>
            <p>324. *Grigson, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">Recollections: Chiefly of Writers and Artists.</hi> London: Hogarth P-Chatto and Windus, 1984. £12.50. [Recalling, amongst many others, his friendship with Ruthven Todd.]</p>
            <p>325. Grob, Alan. “The Uses of Northrop Frye: ‘Sunday Morning’ and the Romantic Topocosm.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 22 (1983): 587-615.</p>
            <p>326. Keynes, Stephen J. “Blake Trust Chairman’s Report.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 126-27. [A complete reprint of a mimeographed text which had been circulated by the Trust “to Members and Patrons” in Oct. 1984.]</p>
            <p>327. *Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">Life Rarely Tells: Life Rarely Tells, The Roaring Twenties, and Fanfrolico and After.</hi> Harmondsworth, Mddx.: Penguin, 1982. £5. [A new edition of the first three volumes of Lindsay’s autobiography; the author wrote his first Blake book in the roaring twenties.]</p>
            <p>328. Luria, Maxwell, and Richard E. Brewer. “The Caliph and the Professor: A. Edward Newton’s Correspondence with Chauncey Brewster Tinker.” <hi rend="i">Harvard Library Bulletin</hi> 33 (1985): 114-73.</p>
            <p>329. *Luria, Maxwell, and Richard E. Brewer. “‘Dear Charley:’ A. Edward Newton’s Letters to Charles Grosvenor Osgood.” <hi rend="i">Princeton Library Chronicle</hi> 45 (1984): 230-54.</p>
            <p>330. McConnell, Frank. “Northrop Frye and <hi rend="i">Anatomy of Criticism.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi> 92 (1984): 622-29.</p>
            <p>331. McQuail, Josephine. “An Unpublished Poem by S. Foster Damon.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 72.</p>
            <p>332. “The Mellon Centre.” Editorial. <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 603.</p>
            <p>333. *Murry, Katherine Middleton. <hi rend="i">Beloved Quixote: The Unknown Life of John Middleton Murry.</hi> London: Souvenir P, 1985. £14.95.</p>
            <p>334. Reading, Peter. “Geoffrey Grigson, 1905-1985.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 17 Jan. 1986: 59.</p>
            <p>335. Robertson, P. J. M. “Criticism and Creativity VI: George Orwell and Northrop Frye.” <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 92 (1985): 374-84.</p>
            <p>336. <hi rend="i">Rosenwald and Rosenbach: Two Philadelphia Bookmen.</hi> Philadelphia, PA: Rosenbach Museum and Library, 1983. [The catalogue of an exhibition (30 April to 31 July 1983) in honor of the two Blake collectors. Contains introductory essays by Seymour Adelman and Kathleen T. Hunt, and includes catalogue entries for the Rosenwald copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> (pp. 33-35), plus a color reproduction of “The Tyger” from Copy Z.]</p>
            <p>337. Smith, Bernard. “Jack Lindsay.” <hi rend="i">Australian Literary Studies</hi> 11 (1983): 216-26.</p>
            <p>338. Sullivan, Rosemary. “Northrop Frye: Canadian Mythographer.” <hi rend="i">Journal of Commonwealth Literature</hi> 18.1 (1983): 1-13.</p>
            <p>339. Wilmerding, John, ed. <hi rend="i">Essays in Honor of Paul Mellon: Collector and Benefactor.</hi> Washington, DC: National Gallery of Art, 1986. [Ryskamp’s contribution to this <hi rend="i">festschrift</hi>, an article on Mellon and Blake, is listed separately as #166, above.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Blakean Echoes in the Twentieth Century</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>340. *Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Joyce Cary’s Trilogies: Pursuit of the Particular.</hi> Tallahassee, FL: Florida State UP, 1983. $20. [In the words of one reviewer, “in the theoretical discussions (of this book) Blake overwhelms Cary” and the “Blake-allusiveness in Cary’s work” is said to be “carefully documented;” see #346.5, below.]</p>
            <p>341. Bell, Dan. “The [First] Book of Blake: Katmandu. Typed by Gypsy 1983.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 122-23. [A parody, closely modeled on <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi>]</p>
            <p>342. *Cassill, R. V. “The Folly &amp; Imagination of Wm. Blake.” <hi rend="i">R. V. Cassill.</hi> Ed. Kay Cassill, Orin E. Cassill, and Curt Johnson. December 23. Chicago, IL: December, 1981. 49-54.</p>
            <pb id="p20-93" n="93"/>
            <p>343. *Gorsen, Peter. <hi rend="i">Alfred Hrdlicka: Blake und Füssli—47 Zeichnungen.</hi> Frankfort on Main, W. Ger.: Galerie Timm Gierig, 1983. [An exhibition catalogue.]</p>
            <p>344. Stevenson, Warren. “On Blake’s Painting of Jesus and the Woman Taken in Adultery.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 150. [A poem by a Blake scholar which “supplements” Christopher Heppner’s recent essay on this painting; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 44-60; 18 (1984): 103, #61.]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part IV Reviews of Works Cited Above and in Previous Checklists</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>345. Abrams, Ann Uhry. <hi rend="i">The Valiant Hero: Benjamin West and Grand-Style History Painting.</hi> Reviewed by L[ynn] R. Matteson, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1046-48.</p>
          <p>346. Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Joyce Cary’s Trilogies: Pursuit of the Particular.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Robert Bloom, <hi rend="i">Èire-Ireland</hi> 20.4 (1985): 149-52; by (2) David Bradshaw, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 2 Nov. 1984: 1240; in (3) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1462; by (4) Edwin Ernest Christian, <hi rend="i">Studies in the Novel</hi> 17 (1985): 311-12; by (5) Elizabeth D. Ermarth, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 576-78; by (6) Michael Feehan, <hi rend="i">Genre</hi> 17 (1984): 429-34; by (7) David E. Latané, Jr., <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 19 (1985): 382-84; by (8) Brian Murray, <hi rend="i">Modern Fiction Studies</hi> 30 (1984): 770-72; by (9) Yvon Tosser, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 345-46.</p>
          <p>347. Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Philosophy of the Literary Symbolic.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Michel Cusin, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 296-97; by (2) Denis Donoghue, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 6 Apr. 1984: 370; by (3) Michael Feehan, <hi rend="i">Genre</hi> 17 (1984): 429-34; by (4) Hans Kellner, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 99 (1984): 1220-25; by (5) David E. Latané, Jr., <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 19 (1985): 382-84; by (6) Daniel T. O’Hara, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 45 (1984): 311-14.</p>
          <p>348. Albright, Daniel. <hi rend="i">Lyricality in English Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *Dale K. Boyer, <hi rend="i">Rocky Mountain Review of Language and Literature</hi> 39 (1985): 277-78; by (2) Anne Williams, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 144-46.</p>
          <p>349. Alexander, David, and Richard T. Godfrey. <hi rend="i">Painters and Engraving: The Reproductive Print from Hogarth to Wilkie.</hi> Reviewed by Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 251-52.</p>
          <p>350. Alford, Steven E. <hi rend="i">Irony and the Logic of the Romantic Imagination.</hi> Reviewed by David Simpson, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 106.</p>
          <p>351. Allen, Brian. <hi rend="i">George Romney as a Painter of Children.</hi> Reviewed by E. K. W. [Sir Ellis K. Waterhouse], <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 515-16.</p>
          <p>352. Allen, Robert R., ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography.</hi> Vols. 3 and 4 for 1977 and 1978 reviewed by (1) Paula R. Backscheider, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 80 (1985): 681-84; by (2) P.-G. B. [Paul-Gabriel Boucé?], <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 235. Vol. 5 for 1979 reviewed by (3) P.-G. B. [Paul-Gabriel Boucé?], <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 490-91; by (4) A. J. Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 81 (1986): 424-26.</p>
          <p>353. Ault, Donald D. <hi rend="i">Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton.</hi> Reviewed by *A. A. Ansari, <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 7 (1982): 92-100.</p>
          <p>354. Baird, John D., and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Cowper.</hi> Vol. 1 reviewed by (1) *James Fenton, <hi rend="i">Listener</hi> 106 (1981): 277-78; by (2) Frank Kermode, <hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi> 21 Oct. 1982: 39-41.</p>
          <p>355. Baker, Carlos. <hi rend="i">The Echoing Green: Romanticism, Modernism, and the Phenomena of Transference in Poetry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) P. Brazeau, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 677; by (2) Sean French, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 17 Aug. 1984: 925; by (3) Robert [F.] Gleckner, <hi rend="i">American Literature</hi> 57 (1985): 158-59; by (4) Warwick Gould, <hi rend="i">Yeats Annual</hi> 4 (1986): 269-76 [for a brief commentary on Baker’s book see p. 273]; by (5) Stuart M. Sperry, <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 23.1 (1985): 79-81.</p>
          <p>356. Beer, John. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Reviewed by (1) James Bogan, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 151-52; by (2) *Grevel Lindop, <hi rend="i">Charles Lamb Bulletin</hi> 44 (1983): 89-90.</p>
          <p>357. Behrendt, Stephen C. <hi rend="i">The Moment of Explosion: Blake and the Illustration of Milton.</hi> Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1130; by (2) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (3) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 74-75; by (4) Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 106-12; by (5) Karl Kroeber, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 75; by (6) Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 110; by (7) Dennis M. Welch, <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 64 (1984): 424-26; by (8) Joseph Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 92-94.</p>
          <p>358. Bertholf, Robert J., and Annette S. Levitt, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Moderns.</hi> Reviewed by (1) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1982</hi>: 77-80; by (2) John Williams, <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 11 (1985): 142-43.</p>
          <p>359. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman, R. A.</hi> Reviewed by *Alison Kelly, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 128 (1980): 532-33.</p>
          <p>360. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">The Thames and Hudson Encyclopaedia of British Art.</hi> Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 49-50; by (2) Richard Kingzett, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 123 (1986): 292; by (3) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 7 Feb. 1986: 144.</p>
          <p>361. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and Times.</hi> Reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 54 (1985): 297-99.</p>
          <pb id="p20-94" n="94"/>
          <p>362. Blake, William. America: A Prophecy <hi rend="i">and</hi> Europe: A Prophecy—<hi rend="i">Facsimile Reproductions of Two Illuminated Books.</hi> Reviewed by (1) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 76-77; by (2) Jenijoy La Belle, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 83-84.</p>
          <p>363. Blake, William. Songs of Experience—<hi rend="i">Facsimile Reproduction.</hi> Reviewed by Jenijoy La Belle, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 83-84.</p>
          <p>364. Blake, William. Songs of Innocence <hi rend="i">and</hi> Songs of Experience. The Manchester Etching Workshop prints reviewed by Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 39-51. [See also #184, above.]</p>
          <p>365. Blondel, Jacques, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">Vala, ou Les Quatre vivants.</hi> Vol. 4 of <hi rend="i">Oeuvres de William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1) David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 46 (1984): 118-19; by (2) Peter [H.] Marshall, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 235-36.</p>
          <p>366. Bogan, James, and Fred Goss, eds. <hi rend="i">Sparks of Fire: Blake in a New Age.</hi> Reviewed by Jenijoy La Belle, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 48-49.</p>
          <p>367. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography.</hi> Vol. 6 for 1980 reviewed by A. J. Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 81 (1986): 424-26.</p>
          <p>368. Boulger, James D. <hi rend="i">The Calvinist Temper in English Poetry.</hi> Reviewed by *A. G. Newell, <hi rend="i">Evangelical Quarterly</hi> 56 (1984): 110-11.</p>
          <p>369. Bridson, Gavin, and Geoffrey Wakeman. <hi rend="i">Printmaking and Picture Printing: A Bibliographical Guide to Artistic and Industrial Techniques in Britain 1750-1900.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Richard W. Clement, <hi rend="i">Library Quarterly</hi> 55 (1985): 357-58; by (2) Antony Griffiths, <hi rend="i">Library</hi> 6th ser. 7 (1985): 285-87.</p>
          <p>370. Brisman, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Romantic Origins.</hi> Reviewed by Heide N. Rohloff, <hi rend="i">Anglia</hi> 103 (1985): 220-24.</p>
          <p>371. Brogan, T. V. F. <hi rend="i">English Versification, 1570-1980: A Reference Guide with a Global Appendix.</hi> Reviewed by Anne Elliott, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 419-20.</p>
          <p>372. Burke, Joseph. <hi rend="i">English Art 1714-1800.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Luke Herrman, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 120 (1978): 36; by (2) Lynn R. Matteson, <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi> 39 (1979): 78-80.</p>
          <p>373. Burkett, Mary E., ed. <hi rend="i">George Romney 1734-1802.</hi> Reviewed by *Nicholas Usherwood, <hi rend="i">Country Life</hi> 9 Aug. 1984: 378-79.</p>
          <p>374. Butler, Marilyn, ed. <hi rend="i">Burke, Paine, Godwin, and the Revolution Controversy.</hi> Reviewed by (1) D. A. N. Jones, <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 6-19 Sept. 1984: 18-19; by (2) Don Locke, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 21 Sept. 1984: 1061.</p>
          <p>375. Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Peter Parker, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 29 Jan. 1982: 18-19.</p>
          <p>376. Butter, P. H., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected Poems.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Bernard Beatty, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 7 (1984): 130; by (2) F. P. [François Piquet], <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 363-64.</p>
          <p>377. [Cannon-Brookes, Peter, et al.] <hi rend="i">The British Neo-Romantics, 1935-1950.</hi> Reviewed by John Spurling, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 5 Aug. 1983: 30-31.</p>
          <p>378. Cantor, Paul A. <hi rend="i">Creature and Creator: Myth-Making and English Romanticism.</hi> Reviewed by (1) T[erence Allan] Hoagwood, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 421-22; by (2) Iain McGilchrist, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 3 Aug. 1984: 862; by (3) Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 23.1 (1985): 77-79; by (4) Mark Roberts, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 103-05; by (5) Nicholas Roe, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 562-63.</p>
          <p>379. Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi> Vols. 7 and 8 reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 24 (1983): 80. Vols. 7-10 reviewed by (2) Anne Tennant, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 7 (1984): 375-78. Vols. 13-16 reviewed by (3) L. H. [Luke Herrmann], <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 796; by (4) Luke Herrmann, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 127 (1985): 814; by (5) Marcia Pointon, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 17 May 1985: 539.</p>
          <p>380. Chan, Victor. <hi rend="i">“Leader of My Angels:” William Hayley and His Circle.</hi> Reviewed by [Anne-Marie S. Logan], <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi> 22 (1984): 330-31.</p>
          <p>381. Clarke, Michael, and Nicholas Penny, eds. <hi rend="i">The Arrogant Connoisseur: Richard Payne Knight 1751-1824.</hi> Reviewed by George B. Tatum, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians</hi> 44 (1985): 398-99.</p>
          <p>382. Cook, Eleanor, et al., eds. <hi rend="i">Centre and Labyrinth: Essays in Honour of Northrop Frye.</hi> Reviewed by (1) David Scott Kastan, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 17 Feb. 1984: 163; by (2) Dan[iel T.] O’Hara, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 26 (1984): 91-95.</p>
          <p>383. Cooper, Robert M. <hi rend="i">The Literary Guide and Companion to Southern England.</hi> Reviewed by Phillip Ward-Green, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 25 Oct. 1985: 1217.</p>
          <p>384. Corti, Claudia. <hi rend="i">Il primo Blake: Testo e sistema.</hi> Reviewed by Serena Cenni, <hi rend="i">Rivista di letterature moderne e comparate</hi> 33 (1980): 313-15.</p>
          <p>385. Cox, Stephen D. <hi rend="i">“The Stranger Within Thee:” Concepts of the Self in Late Eighteenth-Century Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *James S. Grotstein, <hi rend="i">Review of Psychoanalytic Books</hi> 2 (1983-1984): 367-73; by (2) John Sitter, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 17 (1983-1984): 189-93; by (3) David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 31-32.</p>
          <p>386. Crehan, Stewart. <hi rend="i">Blake in Context.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (2) T[erence Allan] Hoagwood, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 266; by (3) Stuart Peterfreund, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 113-16.</p>
          <pb id="p20-95" n="95"/>
          <p>387. Crouan, Katherine. <hi rend="i">John Linnell: A Centennial Exhibition.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Frances Spalding, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 29 Oct. 1982: 1190; by (2) William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 7 (1984): 368-74.</p>
          <p>388. Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *Stuart Curran, <hi rend="i">Review</hi> 4 (1982): 135-57; by (2) *Kevin Lewis, <hi rend="i">Religious Studies Review</hi> 9 (1983): 370; by (3) Leland E. Warren, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981): 393-94.</p>
          <p>389. Deen, Leonard W. <hi rend="i">Conversing in Paradise: Poetic Genius and Identity-as-Community in Blake’s Los.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (2) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 77; by (3) Mary Lynn Johnson, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 107-10; by (4) Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 576-77; by (5) Victoria Myers, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 141-43; by (6) Edward J. Rose, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 111-12; by (7) [Bette] Charlene Werner, <hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 35-36.</p>
          <p>390. DiSalvo, Jackie. <hi rend="i">War of Titans: Blake’s Critique of Milton and the Poetics of Religion.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 97; by (2) Anne Ferry, <hi rend="i">Renaissance Quarterly</hi> 37 (1984): 671-72; by (3) Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 146-50; by (4) Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 105-07; by (5) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 78-79.</p>
          <p>391. Doskow, Minna. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem: <hi rend="i">Structure and Meaning in Poetry and Picture.</hi> Reviewed by (1) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 79-80; by (2) V. A. DeLuca, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 56-58; by (3) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (4) Donald John, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 434-36.</p>
          <p>392. Dowdey, Landon, ed. The Four Zoas: The Torments of Love and Jealousy in the Death and Judgment of Albion the Ancient Man, <hi rend="i">by William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by W. J. T. Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Library Quarterly</hi> 55 (1985): 115-17.</p>
          <p>393. Dunbar, Pamela. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of Milton.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981): 395-96; by (2) Bette Charlene Werner, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 33-34.</p>
          <p>394. Eaves, Morris. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art.</hi> Reviewed by (1) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1982</hi>: 83-84; by (2) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (3) *Richard Harter Fogle, <hi rend="i">Clio</hi> 13 (1984): 293-95; by (4) *Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 132 (1983): 86-87; by (5) Peter A. Taylor, <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 91 (1984): 719-22; by (6) Thomas A. Vogler, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 289-300; by (7) Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 138-40.</p>
          <p>395. Einem, Herbert von. <hi rend="i">Deutsche Malerei des Klassizismus und der Romantik, 1760 bis 1840.</hi> Reviewed by Jens Christian Jensen, <hi rend="i">Kunstchronik</hi> 33 (1980): 68-72.</p>
          <p>396. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1) the Santa Cruz Blake Study Group, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 4-31; by (2) Peter A. Taylor, <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 91 (1984): 719-22.</p>
          <p>397. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi> Reviewed by (1) M. Baridon, <hi rend="i">Dix-huitième Siècle</hi> 16 (1984): 513 [very briefly!]; by (2) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 80-81; by (3) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405.</p>
          <p>398. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Jim Springer Borck, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 398-99; by (2) David E. McKenty, <hi rend="i">College Literature</hi> 8 (1981): 196-97; by (3) *Mark Trevor Smith, <hi rend="i">American Book Collector</hi> ns 2.2 (1981): 75-77.</p>
          <p>399. Essick, Robert N., and Morton D. Paley, eds. <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave, <hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1982</hi>: 85; by (2) Claudia Corti, <hi rend="i">Rivista di letterature moderne e comparate</hi> 38 (1985): 97-100; by (3) David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 46 (1984): 119-23; by (4) Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 54-56; by (5) Jonathan Wordsworth, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 547-48.</p>
          <p>400. Fairchild, B. H. <hi rend="i">Such Holy Song: Music as Idea, Form, and Image in the Poetry of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Stephen Leo Carr, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 399-400.</p>
          <p>401. Ferber, Michael. <hi rend="i">The Social Vision of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by G. A. Cevasco, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 867.</p>
          <p>402. Ferguson, Moira, and Janet Todd. <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1605.</p>
          <p>403. Forbes, Gregory. <hi rend="i">Selections from William Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience: <hi rend="i">Musical Settings / A Companion to the New Musical Settings by Gregory Forbes.</hi> Reviewed by Joseph Viscomi, with Margaret LaFrance, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 84-89.</p>
          <p>404. Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Politics of Richard Price and Joseph Priestley: A Study in Late Eighteenth-Century English Republican Millennialism.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Martin Fitzpatrick, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 8 (1985): 236-38; by (2) A. Thomson, <hi rend="i">Dix-huitième Siècle</hi> 17 (1985): 474.</p>
          <p>405. Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">The Great Code: The Bible and Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Paul-Gabriel Boucé, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 449-50; by (2) J. M. Cameron, <hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi> 15 Apr. 1982: 28-31; by (3) *Robert P. Carroll, <hi rend="i">Scottish Journal of Theology</hi> 37
<pb id="p20-96" n="96"/>
(1984): 246-50; by (4) Peter Conradi, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 18 June 1982: 20-21; by (5) S. G. K. [S. G. Kossick], <hi rend="i">UNISA English Studies</hi> 22.2 (1984): 63; by (6) Herbert J. Levine, <hi rend="i">Georgia Review</hi> 36 (1982): 900-04; by (7) Gottfried Mehnert, <hi rend="i">Literatur in Wissenschaft und Unterricht</hi> 18 (1985): 80-82; by (8) *A. G. Newell, <hi rend="i">Evangelical Quarterly</hi> 57 (1985): 188; by (9) *Carl Ridd, <hi rend="i">Studies in Religion / Sciences Religieuses</hi> 11 (1982): 446-48; by (10) Nicholas Smith, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 302-03; by (11) Karina Williamson, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984): 288; see also (12) “A Little Symposium on <hi rend="i">The Great Code.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dalhousie Review</hi> 63 (1983): 400-21.</p>
          <p>406. Gallant, Christine. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos.</hi> Reviewed in (1) *<hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 6 (1981): 107-13; by (2) *Thomas J. J. Altizer, <hi rend="i">Journal of the American Academy of Religion</hi> Sept. 1979: 485-86; by (3) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 15 (1981-1982): 205-09.</p>
          <p>407. Garlick, Kenneth, and Angus Macintyre, eds. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi> Vols. 1-6 reviewed by Anne Tennant, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 7 (1984): 375-78.</p>
          <p>408. George, Diana Hume. <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *Stuart Curran, <hi rend="i">Review</hi> 4 (1982): 135-57; by (2) William H. Galperin, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 17 (1983): 79-82; by (3) L. F. M. [Leonard F. Manheim], <hi rend="i">University of Hartford Studies in Literature</hi> 13 (1981): 201-02; by (4) *Charles E. May, <hi rend="i">Christianity and Literature</hi> 31.1 (1981): 55-57.</p>
          <p>409. Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prelude:</hi> Poetical Sketches. Reviewed by (1) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 81-83; by (2) Thomas J. Corr, <hi rend="i">College Literature</hi> 11 (1984): 286-89; by (3) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (4) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (5) Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 23 (1984): 409-13; by (6) Donald John, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 434-36; by (7) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 237-38; by (8) Dennis M. Welch, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 45 (1984): 301-02; by (9) Joseph Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 113-14.</p>
          <p>410. Glen, Heather. <hi rend="i">Vision and Disenchantment: Blake’s</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">and Wordsworth’s</hi> Lyrical Ballads. Reviewed by (1) James R. Bennett, <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 54 (1985): 299-303; by (2) Avril Horner, <hi rend="i">PN Review</hi> 11.3 (1984): 54-56; by (3) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 465-66; by (4) David Simpson, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 227-31; by (5) John Williams, <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 10 (1984): 272; by (6) M. A. Williams, <hi rend="i">UNISA English Studies</hi> 23.1 (1985): 41-42.</p>
          <p>411. Grant, John E., Edward J. Rose, and Michael J. Tolley, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s</hi> Night Thoughts: <hi rend="i">A Complete Edition.</hi> Reviewed by Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Fine Print</hi> 8.2 (1982): 49-50.</p>
          <p>412. Grate, Pontus, et al. <hi rend="i">PÅ klassisk mark: Malere i Rom pÅ 1780-talet.</hi> Reviewed by (1) G. L. M. [Gian Lorenzo Mellini], <hi rend="i">Labyrinthos</hi> 2.3/4 (1983): 253; by (2) Anna Ottani Cavina, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 125 (1983): 54-57.</p>
          <p>413. Grigson, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">Recollections: Chiefly of Writers and Artists.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Valentine Cunningham, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 14 Dec. 1984: 1439; by (2) Dick Davis, <hi rend="i">PN Review</hi> 11.6 (1985): 43-46; by (3) Bernard Gutteridge, <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> 24.7 (1984): 97-100.</p>
          <p>414. Hagstrum, Jean H. <hi rend="i">Sex and Sensibility: Ideal and Erotic Love from Milton to Mozart.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *Maurice Charney, <hi rend="i">Review of Psychoanalytic Books</hi> 2 (1983-1984): 500-01; by (2) Dimiter Daphinoff, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi> 64 (1983): 279-81; by (3) Joan F. Gilliland, <hi rend="i">College Literature</hi> 9 (1982): 71-72; by (4) Alicia Ostriker, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 52-53; by (5) Peter Wagner, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi> 8.3 (1983): 108-14.</p>
          <p>415. Halsband, Robert. The Rape of the Lock <hi rend="i">and Its Illustrations 1714-1896.</hi> Reviewed by William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 4 (1981): 485.</p>
          <p>416. Hanke, Amala M. <hi rend="i">Spatiotemporal Consciousness in English and German Romanticism: A Comparative Study of Novalis, Blake, Wordsworth, and Eichendorff.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Dennis F. Mahoney, <hi rend="i">Aurora: Jahrbuch der Eichendorff-Gesellschaft</hi> 42 (1982): 254-55; by (2) John D. Simons, <hi rend="i">German Quarterly</hi> 57 (1984): 156.</p>
          <p>417. Hardt, Ulrich H., ed. <hi rend="i">A Critical Edition of Mary Wollstonecraft’s</hi> A Vindication of the Rights of Woman: With Strictures on Political and Moral Subjects. Reviewed by (1) J. D. F., <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984): 137-38; by (2) Sara Hudson, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 18 (1984): 185-88; by (3) Mitzi Myers, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 33 (1984): 231-34.</p>
          <p>418. Haskell, Francis, and Nicholas Penny. <hi rend="i">Taste and the Antique.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Clifford W. Currie, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi> 7.1 (1981): 114-30; by (2) Leopold D. Ettlinger, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 66 (1984): 527-28; by (3) Frank Felsenstein, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 5 (1982): 287-89; by (4) Seymour Howard, <hi rend="i">Journal of Modern History</hi> 55 (1983): 300-03; by (5) Christopher Lloyd, <hi rend="i">English Historical Review</hi> 100 (1985): 415; by (6) Hugh Plommer, <hi rend="i">Classical Review</hi> ns 32 (1982): 264-65; by (7) *Francis Russell, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 129 (1981): 803-04.</p>
          <p>419. Hilton, Nelson. <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of Words.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (2) Michael Ferber, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 26 (1984): 397-99; by (3) David Wagenknecht, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 117-20; by (4) Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 83 (1984): 566-68.</p>
          <pb id="p20-97" n="97"/>
          <p>420. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. <hi rend="i">Prophecy and the Philosophy of Mind: Traditions of Blake and Shelley.</hi> Reviewed by M. Minor, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1634.</p>
          <p>421. Hodnett, Edward. <hi rend="i">Image and Text: Studies in the Illustration of English Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Karl Kroeber, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 75; by (2) Joachim Möller, <hi rend="i">Germanisch-Romanische Monatsschrift</hi> ns 35 (1985): 119-21; by (3) *Tobin A. Sparling, <hi rend="i">American Book Collector</hi> ns 5.5 (1984): 41.</p>
          <p>422. Hutchings, Bill. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Cowper.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Richard Bradford, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 398; by (2) Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi> 66 (1985): 69-72; by (3) Vincent Newey, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 7 (1984): 247-48.</p>
          <p>423. Irwin, David. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman 1755-1826: Sculptor, Illustrator, Designer.</hi> Reviewed by *Alison Kelly, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 128 (1980): 532-33.</p>
          <p>424. James, G. Ingli, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Annotations to Richard Watson</hi>, An Apology for the Bible in a Series of Letters Addressed to Thomas Paine, <hi rend="i">8th ed. 1797.</hi> Reviewed by Nicholas O. Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 116-17.</p>
          <p>425. Johnston, John H. <hi rend="i">The Poet and the City: A Study in Urban Perspectives.</hi> Reviewed by D. D. Kummings, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1333.</p>
          <p>426. Kauffmann, C. M. <hi rend="i">John Varley 1778-1842.</hi> Reviewed by (1) William Joll, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 121 (1985): 359; by (2) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 26 Apr. 1985: 465.</p>
          <p>427. Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Ralph Colp, Jr., <hi rend="i">Biography</hi> 9 (1986): 89-91; by (2) Sonya Rudikoff, <hi rend="i">Hudson Review</hi> 36 (1983): 199-204.</p>
          <p>428. Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake.</hi> 3rd, rev. ed. Reviewed by *Sheila M. Smith, <hi rend="i">British Journal of Aesthetics</hi> 22 (1982): 90-91.</p>
          <p>429. King, James. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: A Biography.</hi> Reviewed by W. B. Carnochan, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 11 July 1986: 765.</p>
          <p>430. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of William Cowper.</hi> Vols. 1 and 2 reviewed by (1) Frank Kermode, <hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi> 21 Oct. 1982: 39-41. Vol. 2 reviewed by (2) Norma Dalrymple-Champneys, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 29 (1982): 557-58; by (3) *James Fenton, <hi rend="i">Listener</hi> 106 (1981): 277-78. Vol. 3 reviewed by (4) Norma Dalrymple-Champneys, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 134-35; by (5) W. H. [W. Bill Hutchings?], <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 25.3 (1983): 90; by (6) Donald H. Reiman, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 146-51; by (7) Serge Soupel, <hi rend="i">Etudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 332. Vols. 3 and 4 reviewed by (8) Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi> 66 (1985): 561-64; by (9) Peter J. de Voogd, <hi rend="i">Dutch Quarterly Review of Anglo-American Letters</hi> 14 (1984): 308-19 [see p. 315]. Vol. 4 reviewed by (10) M. Baridon, <hi rend="i">Dixhuitième Siècle</hi> 17 (1985): 432 [briefly!]; by (11) Norma Dalrymple-Champneys, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 268-69; by (12) Vincent Newey, <hi rend="i">Prose Studies</hi> 8.3 (1985): 95-96; by (13) Pat Rogers, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 11 May 1984: 519; by (14) C. H. Sisson, <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 2 Aug.-5 Sept. 1984: 26-27.</p>
          <p>431. King-Hele, Desmond, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Erasmus Darwin.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Clive Bush, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 15 (1985): 306-07; by (2) Roy Porter, <hi rend="i">English Historical Review</hi> 99 (1984): 444-45.</p>
          <p>432. Kroeber, Karl, and William Walling, eds. <hi rend="i">Images of Romanticism: Verbal and Visual Affinities.</hi> Reviewed by Jeffry B. Spencer, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 331-33.</p>
          <p>433. Leader, Zachary. <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s</hi> Songs. Reviewed by (1) Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981): 397-98; by (2) Thomas A. Vogler, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 39-47.</p>
          <p>434. LeBris, Michel. <hi rend="i">Die Romantik in Wort und Bild.</hi> Reviewed by Volkmar Stein, <hi rend="i">Aurora: Jahrbuch der Eichendorff-Gesellschaft</hi> 44 (1984): 252-54.</p>
          <p>435. Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">Life Rarely Tells: Life Rarely Tells, The Roaring Twenties, and Fanfrolico and After.</hi> Reviewed by Andy Croft, <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> 24.11 (1985): 90-93.</p>
          <p>436. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 123 (1986): 288; by (2) J. Riely, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1203.</p>
          <p>437. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer and ‘The Ancients.’</hi> Reviewed by R. E. McVaugh, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1625.</p>
          <p>438. Loder, R[obert] B. <hi rend="i">William Blake to David Hockney: A Private Collection of British Prints.</hi> Reviewed by Celina Fox, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 26 Feb. 1982: 215.</p>
          <p>439. Marshall, Peter H. <hi rend="i">William Godwin: Philosopher, Novelist, Revolutionary.</hi> Reviewed by (1) M. B. Friedman, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 558; by (2) D. A. N. Jones, <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 6-19 Sept. 1984: 18-19; by (3) Don Locke, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 21 Sept. 1984: 1061; by (4) B. J. Tysdahl, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 19 (1986): 435-37.</p>
          <p>440. McGann, Jerome J. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical Investigation.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Michael Fischer, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 152-55; by (2) Paul H. Fry, <hi rend="i">Yale Review</hi> ns 73 (1984): 603-16; by (3) William H. Galperin, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 135-38; by (4) J. H. Haeger, <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 9.2 (1985): 75-83; by (5) Beatrice Marie, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 99 (1984): 1188-92; by (6) Marlon B. Ross, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 83 (1985): 204-09; by (7) Frederick W. Shilstone, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 19 (1985): 176-78; by (8) Peter L. Thorslev, Jr., <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 33 (1984): 205-08;
<pb id="p20-98" n="98"/>
see also (9) James M. Kee, “Narrative Time and Participating Consciousness: A Heideggerian Supplement to McGann’s <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 9.2 (1985): 51-63 (with a reply by McGann on pp. 65-73).</p>
          <p>441. Melot, Michel. <hi rend="i">The Art of Illustration.</hi> Reviewed by S. Skaggs, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1151.</p>
          <p>442. Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of the Illuminated Poetry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) J. M. Q. Davies, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 42 (1980): 116-17; by (2) P. M. S. D. [P. M. S. Dawson], <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 26.4 (1984): 93.</p>
          <p>443. Mitchell, W. J. T., ed. <hi rend="i">The Language of Images.</hi> Reviewed by Stephen Leo Carr, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 35-38.</p>
          <p>444. Murry, Katherine Middleton. <hi rend="i">Beloved Quixote: The Unknown Life of John Middleton Murry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) David Sexton, <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> 26.1 / 2 (1986): 172-76; by (2) Hilary Spurling, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 4 Apr. 1986: 352.</p>
          <p>445. Newey, Vincent. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s Poetry: A Critical Study and Reassessment.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi> 66 (1985): 369-72; by (2) Morris Golden, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 114-16; by (3) W. [Bill] Hutchings, <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 25.2 (1983): 84-85; by (4) Verlyn Klinkenborg, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1984): 89-92; by (5) A. J. Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 16 (1986): 279-80; by (6) Serge Soupel, <hi rend="i">Etudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 331; by (7) Peter J. de Voogd, <hi rend="i">Dutch Quarterly Review of Anglo-American Letters</hi> 14 (1984): 308-19 [see pp. 315-16]; by (8) J. R. Watson, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 6 (1983): 213-15; by (9) Karina Williamson, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 553-54.</p>
          <p>446. Nobs-Greter, Ruth. <hi rend="i">Die Künstlerin und ihr Werk in der deutschsprachigen Kunstgeschichtsschreibung.</hi> Reviewed by Hanna M. Gagel, <hi rend="i">Kritische Berichte</hi> 13.3 (1985): 81-85.</p>
          <p>447. Palacio, Jean de. <hi rend="i">William Godwin et son monde intérieur.</hi> Reviewed by (1) M. Baridon, <hi rend="i">Dixhuitième Siècle</hi> 15 (1983): 532 [briefly]; by (2) Alice Green Fredman, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 33 (1984): 229-31; by (3) Peter [H.] Marshall, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 35 (1982): 335-36.</p>
          <p>448. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem. Reviewed by (1) Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 22.4 (1985): 72-74; by (2) James Bogan, <hi rend="i">Western Humanities Review</hi> 39 (1985): 90-92; in (3) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1608; by (4) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (5) V. A. De Luca, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 76-79; by (6) David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 577-78; by (7) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (8) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 236-37; by (9) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 85-86; by (10) Frank Stack, <hi rend="i">Times Higher Education Supplement</hi> 6 Jan. 1984: 19.</p>
          <p>449. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Book and Painting—Shakespeare, Milton, and the Bible: Literary Texts and the Emergence of English Painting.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Geoffrey Ashton, <hi rend="i">Shakespeare Quarterly</hi> 35 (1984): 373-74; by (2) David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 6 Jan. 1984: 10; by (3) Roland Mushat Frye, <hi rend="i">Renaissance Quarterly</hi> 37 (1984): 488-90; by (4) Kenneth Garlick, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 424-26; by (5) Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 223-26.</p>
          <p>450. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Literary Landscape: Turner and Constable.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Alan Bird, <hi rend="i">Journal of European Studies</hi> 13 (1983): 223-24; by (2) Douglas Brooks-Davies, <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 25.4 (1983): 89-91; by (3) Nathan Cervo, <hi rend="i">Journal of Pre-Raphaelite Studies</hi> 4.2 (1984): 118-23; by (4) Patricia Crown, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 26 (1985): 94-101; by (5) Roland Mushat Frye, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 82 (1985): 431-34; by (6) Laurence Lerner, <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi> 37 (1985): 169-73; by (7) Paul D. McGlynn, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 18 (1984): 174-75; by (8) Martin Meisel, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 267-71; by (9) Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 223-26; by (10) *Marcia Pointon, <hi rend="i">British Journal of Aesthetics</hi> 24 (1984): 177-79; by (11) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 118 (1983): 111-12.</p>
          <p>451. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Representations of Revolution (1789-1820).</hi> Reviewed by (1) Alan Bird, <hi rend="i">Journal of European Studies</hi> 14 (1984): 63; by (2) Norman Bryson, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 127 (1985): 102-03; by (3) W. B. Carnochan, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 83 (1985): 80-82; by (4) David Carrier, <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi> 42 (1983): 223-25; by (5) Laurence Goldstein, <hi rend="i">Michigan Quarterly Review</hi> 23 (1984): 455-58; by (6) Norman Hampson, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 4 Nov. 1983: 1225; by (7) A. W. Heffernan, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 103-05; by (8) Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 221-23; by (9) Michel Jouve, <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 104 (1984): “La Chronique des Arts.” Nov. 1984: 20; by (10) Fred V. Randel, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 268-71; by (11) William Ruddick, <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 11 (1985): 143-44; by (12) William Walling, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 34 (1985): 201-03; by (13) Hugh Witemeyer, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 45 (1984): 204-07; by (14) Jonathan Wordsworth, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 581-82; by (15) Richard Wrigley, <hi rend="i">Art Forum International</hi> Sept.-Nov. 1984: 73-75.</p>
          <p>452. Poovey, Mary. <hi rend="i">The Proper Lady and the Woman Writer: Ideology as Style in the Works of Mary Wollstonecraft, Mary Shelley, and Jane Austen.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Nancy Armstrong, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 99
<pb id="p20-99" n="99"/>
(1984): 1251-57; by (2) Robert A. Colby, <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Fiction</hi> 39 (1984): 339-44; by (3) Laurie A. Finke, <hi rend="i">Genre</hi> 17 (1984): 337-40; by (4) Alice Green Fredman, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 34 (1985): 190-94; by (5) Deborah Kaplan, <hi rend="i">Novel: A Forum on Fiction</hi> 17 (1983): 81-84; by (6) April London, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 270-71; by (7) Susan Morgan, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 27 (1985): 100-03; by (8) M. Rooney, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 100; by (9) M. E. S., <hi rend="i">Prose Studies</hi> 8.3 (1985): 100-01; by (10) James Thompson, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 101-06.</p>
          <p>453. Pressly, Nancy L. <hi rend="i">Revealed Religion: Benjamin West’s Commissions for Windsor Castle and Fonthill Abbey.</hi> Reviewed by Allen Staley, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 120-21.</p>
          <p>454. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">James Barry: The Artist as Hero.</hi> Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi> 22 (1984): 220 [briefly!]; by (2) John Spurling, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 4 Mar. 1983: 30-31. [See also #202, above.]</p>
          <p>455. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *D. G. C. Allan, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 130 (1981): 60-62; in (2) <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi> 22 (1984): 220 [briefly!]; by (3) Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981): 281-82; by (4) *Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">Turner Studies</hi> 2 (1982): 49-50. [See also #202, above.]</p>
          <p>456. Priestman, Martin. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s</hi> Task<hi rend="i">: Structure and Influence.</hi> Reviewed by (1) P. M. S. Dawson, <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 27.3 (1985): 84-85; by (2) W. B[ill] Hutchings, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 7 (1984): 248-49; by (3) Vincent Newey, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 575-76.</p>
          <p>457. Punter, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel, and Dialectic.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Pierre Dubois, <hi rend="i">Revue Philosophique de la France et de l’Ètranger</hi> 173 (1983): 139-40; by (2) *Kevin Lewis, <hi rend="i">Religious Studies Review</hi> 10 (1984): 384; by (3) Stephen Prickett, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 81 (1986): 159-60; by (4) John Williams, <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 11 (1985): 142-43.</p>
          <p>458. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and the New Age.</hi> Reviewed by Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 401-02.</p>
          <p>459. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">The Human Face of God: William Blake and The Book of Job.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Glyn Hughes, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 2 Apr. 1982: 23; by (2) Bo Ossian Lindberg, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 151-55.</p>
          <p>460. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">The Inner Journey of the Poet.</hi> Reviewed by (1) P. M. S. D. [P. M. S. Dawson], <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 25.1 (1983): 93; by (2) Edna Longley, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984): 562.</p>
          <p>461. Rawson, Claude. <hi rend="i">Order from Confusion Sprung: Studies in Eighteenth-Century Literature from Swift to Cowper.</hi> Reviewed by David Nokes, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 8 Nov. 1985: 1261.</p>
          <p>462. Rosenblum, Robert, and H. W. Janson. <hi rend="i">Art of the Nineteenth Century: Painting and Sculpture.</hi> Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1457; by (2) Nicholas Penny, <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 21 Mar. 1985: 12-14; by (3) Richard Thomson, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 9 (1986): 108-15; by (4) William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 23 Mar. 1984: 316.</p>
          <p>463. Sánchez Pérez, Aquilino. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Graphic Work and the Emblematic Tradition.</hi> Reviewed by Joseph S. Salemi, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 50-52.</p>
          <p>464. Schiff, Gert, and Paola Viotto, <hi rend="i">Tout l’oeuvre peint de Füssli.</hi> Reviewed in *<hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 96 (1980): “La Chronique des Arts.” Dec. 1980: 16.</p>
          <p>465. Schwartz, Richard B. <hi rend="i">Daily Life in Johnson’s London.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Max Byrd, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 110-11; in (2) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1609; by (3) Derek Jarrett, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 8 (1985): 239-40.</p>
          <p>466. Singh, Charu Sheel. <hi rend="i">The Chariot of Fire: A Study of William Blake in the Light of Hindu Thought.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Pamela Dunbar, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 80 (1985): 129; by (2) Mary V. Jackson, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 121-25.</p>
          <p>467. Stock, R. D. <hi rend="i">The Holy and the Daemonic from Sir Thomas Browne to William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 327; in (2) <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 24 (1983): 85; by (3) Christopher Fox, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 144-46; by (4) Robin Robbins, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 24 Sept. 1982: 1046; by (5) Pat Rogers, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 377-78; by (6) Patricia Meyer Spacks, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 82 (1984): 206-09; by (7) L. J. Swingle, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 44 (1983): 80-91; by (8) D. R. M. Wilkinson, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 16 (1986): 286-88.</p>
          <p>468. Tannenbaum, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies: The Great Code of Art.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Stephen C. Behrendt, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 106-08; by (2) Jerome J. McGann, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 120-21; by (3) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1982</hi>: 90-91; by (4) Michael J. Tolley, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 300-07; by (5) D. R. M. Wilkinson, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 16 (1986): 286-88.</p>
          <p>469. Twitchell, James B. <hi rend="i">Romantic Horizons: Aspects of the Sublime in English Poetry and Painting, 1770-1850.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Matthew C. Brennan, <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 8.2 (1984): 45-49; by (2) Theresa M. Kelley, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 34 (1985): 203-05; by (3) William Walling, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 108-09.</p>
          <p>470. Tysdahl, B.J. <hi rend="i">William Godwin as Novelist.</hi> Reviewed by N. H. Rose, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 242-43.</p>
          <pb id="p20-100" n="100"/>
          <p>471. Wark, Robert R., ed. <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers.</hi> Reviewed by (1) T. L. A. [Thomas L. Ashton], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 83-84; by (2) Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 80-83.</p>
          <p>472. Warner, Janet A. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art.</hi> Reviewed by (1) John Dixon Hunt, <hi rend="i">Word and Image</hi> 1 (1985): 409-20; by (2) L[ynn] R. Matteson, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1486; by (3) Peter A. Taylor, <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 92 (1985): 859-60.</p>
          <p>473. Webster, Brenda S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (2) Kelvin Everest, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 8 (1985): 106-07; by (3) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (4) T[erence Allan] Hoagwood, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 104; in (5) “Notes on Current Books.” <hi rend="i">Virginia Quarterly Review</hi> 60.3 (1984): 84-86; by (6) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 466-67.</p>
          <p>474. Weinglass, David H., ed. <hi rend="i">The Collected English Letters of Henry Fuseli.</hi> Reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 231-34.</p>
          <p>475. Wendorf, Richard, ed. <hi rend="i">Articulate Images: The Sister Arts from Hogarth to Tennyson.</hi> Reviewed by (1) C. L. Brooks, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 128-30; by (2) Stephen Leo Carr, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 26 (1985): 203-08; by (3) John Dixon Hunt, <hi rend="i">Word and Image</hi> 1 (1985): 409-20; by (4) Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 112-13; by (5) Bruce Redford, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 83 (1986): 316-18; by (6) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 25 May 1984: 578.</p>
          <p>476. Wilmerding, John, ed. <hi rend="i">Essays in Honor of Paul Mellon: Collector and Benefactor.</hi> Reviewed by Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 123 (1986): 438-39.</p>
          <p>477. Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. <hi rend="i">Visionary Poetics: Milton’s Tradition and His Legacy.</hi> Reviewed by Walter Weihermann, <hi rend="i">Anglia</hi> 103 (1985): 484-88.</p>
          <p>478. Young, Howard T. <hi rend="i">The Line in the Margin: Juan Ramòn Jiménez and His Readings in Blake, Shelley, and Yeats.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Michael André Bernstein, <hi rend="i">Yeats Annual</hi> 2 (1983): 136-37; by (2) Paul R. Olson, <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi> 37 (1985): 378-79.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <pb id="p20-101" n="101"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi></hi>
          </title>
          <title type="section-subtitle">
            <hi rend="b">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of thought</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The <hi rend="i">Allegorical Female Figure</hi>: She Cometh With Clouds</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Michael J. <name>Tolley</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Christopher Heppner’s article on an obscure drawing, in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 20 (summer 1986), is given an over-confident title: “Blake’s ‘The New Jerusalem Descending’: A Drawing (Butlin #92) Identified.” After reading it, I find myself unpersuaded about almost every submission of importance that he makes, even the new reading “GOG” for what was formerly read as “525.” I am, however, prepared to go along with the identification of the male figure at the lower left of the design as Gog, because there is nothing inherently implausible about it. Whether Blake wrote the inscription seems still doubtful; the proposed analogy, capital letters in <hi rend="i">The Making of Magna Charta</hi>, is suggestive but unpersuasive, both because of their relative thinness of line and because there the lettering is deliberately archaic. What I cannot accept is Heppner’s strange methodology. He explains the obvious (Gog in Ezekiel is to be related to Gog in Revelation and might have contemporary political implications for an artist in the late eighteenth century) by the obscure (eighteenth-century biblical commentary), ignores obvious difficulties, blinds us with irrelevant light (Dürer’s and Duvet’s treatments of the New Jerusalem), and fails to present or consider adequately the necessary evidence.</p>
          <p>What is first required in an exercise of this kind is a clear description of the design. Heppner’s description is perfunctory and cannot be checked thoroughly against the reproduction, which is itself obscure and has even been trimmed. This unfortunate fact is crucial, because one simply has to be able to see all the lettering on the book in the bottom left corner of the page before one may propose a new reading. What one can see does not tally very happily with what Heppner claims to have seen after a “close look at the original drawing.” Until I can take such a close look myself, or see reliable photographs, I am not about to propose a new reading. Unfortunately, the reproduction in Butlin (plate 102 of <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, Yale UP, 1981) is far too small to be of help; all one can say about this photograph and the one which accompanies the article is that they make one wonder why so early a date is given for the drawing. However, apart from this inscription, one would like to know exactly what objects are in the lower part of the design, and whether there is an inscription, perhaps a monogram, just below the corner of the woman’s hem, at right.</p>
          <p>A thesis should be tested against objections. Heppner grants that the New Jerusalem does not descend in Revelation 20, when Gog is described, but can claim only that this narrative “leads directly to the Last Judgment and the descent in chapter 21 of ‘the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of heaven, prepared as a bride adorned for her husband.’ ” This is to jump a wide stretch of narrative. Scripturally, there is no authority for having Jerusalem descending into a confused rabble and so Heppner argues that “Blake is not illustrating Revelation and Ezekiel directly, but is rather illustrating—or creating—a prophetic text of his own, based on, but not limited by, the language of those earlier prophets.” This proposition may not be as daft as it sounds, but one needs a much stronger reason for advancing it than any of those adduced by Heppner; it has an air of desperation. Is Blake really, to quote Heppner again, “creating a new but implicit text, founded on the prophets but constituting a new virtual text of his own invention?” The question is begged but not answered.</p>
          <p>“New Jerusalem” seems too narrow an identification: Blake may be alluding to her, but his real subject may well be Truth or Wisdom; the spiked crown suits such a figure better than it might Jerusalem as a bride. The design seems very close in spirit to “The Voice of the Ancient Bard.” I am surprised that Heppner did not relate it to two Resurrection designs in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series, 1 (31E, The 1797 Night IV Title Page) and 264; supposing that we can find better information about this drawing, it should be possible to read it (not necessarily as a resurrection subject, of course) in a thoroughly Blakean manner; it has some affinities, also, with the account of the descent of Jesus in the Clouds of Ololon at the end of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> This is an interesting question, because one is bound to wonder whether the woman is “coming in the clouds” (in which case, why is she a woman?) or simply dispelling them (in which case, why is she to be seen as “descending,” rather than, say, “manifesting herself”?).</p>
          <p>In note 7, Heppner’s remarks on the Matthew Henry commentary may be misleading to <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> readers. He implies that the “completed commentary” was not available until 1811. My own complete edition is dated 1721. What happened, as Darlow and Moule explain, is that “Before his death he had reached the end of Acts, and the New Testament was afterwards finished by a number of Nonconformist divines. . . . The edition of 1811 contains additional matter from Henry’s manuscripts.” Darlow and Moule, incidentally, is usually the place to go for this kind of information, not <hi rend="i">DNB.</hi> See <hi rend="i">Historical Catalogue of Printed Editions of the English</hi><pb id="p20-102" n="102"/><hi rend="i">Bible 1525-1961</hi>, revised and expanded from the edition of T. H. Darlow and H. F. Moule by A. S. Herbert, London and New York, 1968, p. 241. The preface to volume 6 gives credit to Henry for much of the substance of that volume (Epistles and Revelation). But why drag in Henry, when all one needs is a Bible with marginal references or a Cruden or “what every Sunday school girl knows”?</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The New Jerusalem Defended</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Christopher <name>Heppner</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>It is clear that Michael Tolley finds my essay irritating. It is not so clear that he finds it as unpersuasive as he originally claims, since he is “prepared to go along with the identification of the male figure . . . as Gog,” and accepts the claim that “Blake may be alluding to” the new Jerusalem in the female figure. That grants my argument a fair amount of what it claims, and I could simply thank Tolley for his grudging and discourteous support and leave it at that. But he raises enough interesting questions that I welcome the opportunity to both answer him and develop further aspects of my own argument.</p>
          <p>Tolley’s complaints about the reproduction have some justification. The original photograph is of good quality, and the reproduction is in most respects up to <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>’s usual high standard, but there has been a little trimming along the edges. All I can do is confirm that the reading given in the essay of the letters on the scroll at bottom left, hypothetical though it be in some cases, is the best I can do, with one exception. Inadequate proofing on my part allowed the omission of an apostrophe between the capital “L” and “G” of the third line.</p>
          <p>It is not clear whether Tolley doubts my reading of the word “GOG,” or simply doubts whether it was Blake who wrote it. On the first question, I can only reiterate that it looks like “GOG” to me, and that hypothesis helps explain the hardware at the bottom of the design. On the second question, I was careful in the essay not to make a categorical assertion that Blake himself wrote the word. I believe that he did, but there remains the remote possibility that we are dealing with a case analogous to the informed interpretations of plates in copy D of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> In any case, the name seems genuinely explanatory, and I can think of no reason why anyone should write on the design a number that so carefully follows the outline of a figure. A glance ahead to the <hi rend="i">Epitome of James Hervey’s “Meditations among the Tombs”</hi> will show that there too names have a strong tendency to follow the outlines of the bodies to which they refer. The evidence available suggests that the inscription reads “GOG,” and that Blake wrote it, though whether at the time of executing the drawing or at some later date I shall not attempt to decide.</p>
          <p>Having rejected, in whichever mode, my reading of the brief inscription that is clearly visible, Tolley wishes to find one that is hidden in the slight lines below the right corner of the woman’s hem. I cannot see such a text in the photograph, nor did I see one while looking at the original drawing. Perhaps another pair of eyes will have better luck.</p>
          <p>Another point on which Tolley expresses doubts is the date of the design. Butlin writes simply “A typical wash drawing of the 1780s.” On stylistic grounds that dating seems appropriate, and I see no reason to question it. Tolley refers to the possibility of finding “better information” about this drawing; that would be pleasant, but for the moment we must work with what we have.</p>
          <p>Having objected to my use of obscure biblical commentary, Tolley finds fault with note 7 for potentially misleading readers, and for an inappropriate reference. He has part of a point here. The essential part of my note, that the commentary on Ezekiel quoted in the essay was published by 1710, is correct. But the note does imply that the completed commentary was first published in 1811 and that, as Tolley points out, is incorrect. My error originated in the ambiguity of the account of Henry in the <hi rend="i">DNB.</hi>, which does not give the date of the first complete edition, and so permitted my misapprehension. However, Darlow and Moule also fail to give the date of the first complete edition, and do not list the edition of 1721 which Tolley owns. In fact, their account, which was very likely part of the original edition of 1903, reads like a brief synopsis of the <hi rend="i">DNB</hi> account, which was published not long before that. In addition, the “Preface to First Edition” of Darlow and Moule makes it clear that “Commentaries are omitted, unless they contain a continuous text,” so that their work is not a reliable guide to the world of biblical commentary. So I apologize for the potential of my note to mislead, albeit in a direction irrelevant to the essay, and I probably should have consulted Darlow and Moule, though in this case they would not have helped very much. On another issue they were helpful; as if to counter the charge that I used overly obscure material (Mede? Pareus? Newton? Lowth?) Darlow and Moule call Henry’s work the “most popular of English commentaries.”</p>
          <p>The question of the spiked crown is a real and interesting one which I neglected in the essay. As so often in art the meaning of a particular motif is largely determined by the context. Crowns in Blake’s work frequently bear negative connotations; they are signs of kingship, or of a variety of often negative allegorical functions based on the notion of power. In the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> drawings,
<pb id="p20-103" n="103"/>
for instance, Young’s Oppression, Life, Earth, Fortune, and Eternity are all figured as crowned women (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 22, 105, 106, 185, 210, 435, 436), as is the Great Whore (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 345). But a very different tradition is recorded in “To Spring” (E 408), where Spring is invited to put his “golden crown” upon the head of the “love-sick land” in token of celestial marriage. This tradition appears again in <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, where “he that loves the lowly,” and has bound his “nuptial bands” around her breast, has also given the Clod of Clay “a crown that none can take away” (E 5). I believe that the new Jerusalem’s crown is a sign of her adornment as a bride, in accord with this Blakean symbolism of the 1780s.</p>
          <p>It is time to turn to Tolley’s central objection to my essay, which is to the “strange methodology” he intuits behind my daftness. That methodology, though that is much too grand a term, simply accepts and articulates further Blake’s own understanding of his procedure. This is not to claim that he consciously thought things through in exactly this way on each occasion.</p>
          <p>Blake’s several comments on the work of inventing a design (e.g., “All but Names of Persons &amp; Places is Invention” [E 650], the note on <hi rend="i">The Ancient Britons</hi> [E 542-45], <hi rend="i">A Vision of The Last Judgment</hi> passim) point to the model of a two-stage process, which begins usually from a text, and then organizes and / or transforms that to produce a virtual or second-order text. Such a virtual text enables Blake both to distance himself in whatever direction he chooses from the values, implicit or explicit, embodied in the initial text, and to produce a structure which can articulate and control the interrelationships between figures in the completed design.</p>
          <p>Perhaps the most significant text on this matter is Blake’s statement that “what Critics call The Fable is Vision itself” (E 554). I believe that “Fable” is here Blake’s term for what I have defined as the virtual or second-order text, and that “Vision” is his term for the total meaning of that Fable, which I would define as the product of both the pictorial realization of the second-order text and the relationships between that and the initiating text.</p>
          <p>In the case of the present drawing, I reconstructed a typologically based second-order text which combined elements from Ezekiel with elements from Revelation to produce a narrative or Fable which brought Gog and the new Jerusalem into immediate relationship with each other. Tolley accuses me of jumping a “wide stretch of narrative” in going from Gog as described in Revelation 20 to the descent of the new Jerusalem in Revelation 21. A central purpose of the essay was to sketch in a back-ground of typologically based exegesis which bridged that apparent gap by seeing an analogy with the sequence in Ezekiel which moves from Gog to the description of the temple of the Lord. Tolley seems to believe that “all one needs is a Bible with marginal references,” and so protests that “Scripturally, there is no authority for having Jerusalem descending into a confused rabble . . . .” But a typological reading of scripture can produce such a scene, and in fact did so in the sixteenth-century tapestry which I described briefly in the essay. Perhaps if Tolley had paid more attention to typology, which was the point of my use of the “obscure,” he might not have been so scandalized by my exposition of the “obvious.”</p>
          <p>The kind of typologically based structure that I reconstruct has its roots in the Protestant tradition of commentary on the prophets of the Old and New Testaments, and I sketched in something of that commentary. I did not claim that Blake had read any specific portion of it, but he certainly might have, and I would claim that that way of thinking formed part of his intellectual weaponry.</p>
          <p>Blake saw the Bible as “the Great Code of Art” (E 274) because it provided “every pathetic story possible to happen. . . / All that can happen to Man in his pilgrimage of seventy years” (E 161), and the defeat of Gog and the revelatory descent of the new Jerusalem are two such basic events. Such stories have a tendency to move into and shape Blake’s imagery, just as they form the foundation for many of his designs. Among the texts that Tolley suggests might have been related to the drawing under discussion is “The Voice of the Ancient Bard” (E 31-32). There is indeed an analogy between the drawing and the poem, and it exists because Blake probably had the descent of the new Jerusalem in mind as the archetype behind the “opening morn” of the poem, and the defeat of Gog and his armies as the archetype behind the fallen and the “bones of the dead” (cf. Ezekiel 39:4-16). I do not think that the poem sheds much direct light on the drawing, but both seem structured out of the same basic images.</p>
          <p>Tolley’s suggestion that Blake “may be alluding to” the new Jerusalem, but “his real subject may well be Truth or Wisdom,” raises several issues and problems. To bring Gog, a historically oriented figure from prophecy, into relation with figures from moral allegory is in itself fraught with difficulty, and is to substitute Allegory for “The Fable [that] is Vision itself.” The notion of the “real subject” of a design is difficult in a way that can be illustrated by looking at Blake’s description of Number IV of <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>: “A Spirit vaulting from a cloud to turn and wind a fiery Pegasus—Shakspeare. The Horse of Intellect is leaping from the cliffs of Memory and Reasoning; it is a barren Rock: it is also called the Barren Waste of Locke and Newton” (E 546). Specific meanings are here fitted into a structure of imaginative action derived from contemplation of a poetic text. But is the “real subject” to be described as “A Spirit vaulting from a cloud to turn and wind a fiery Pegasus,” or as “The Horse of Intellect is leaping from the cliffs of Memory and Reasoning”?</p>
          <pb id="p20-104" n="104"/>
          <p>I would argue that the confounding of Gog by the descent of the new Jerusalem is the visionary Fable that gives center to the meaning of the design. Having recognized that Fable, we can if we wish proceed to allegorize it into a variety of contexts, as Blake himself did when he wrote that “Jerusalem is called Liberty among the Children of Albion” (E 203). In the essay I explored briefly the contemporary political context as one possible meaning that could be fitted into the structure; certainly others are possible, and if Tolley wishes, in effect, to call Jerusalem Truth or Wisdom, I am content, though I hope he would allow Liberty as another name. As Blake wrote in a different but related context, “Tell me the Acts, O historian, and leave me to reason upon them as I please” (E 544).</p>
          <p>Tolley suggests several designs with which I might have compared the design I discussed. At some level such comparisons can be very helpful, but too often easy analogies between surface elements leave the underlying structure of a design in darkness, as I have argued elsewhere happened with the color print known as <hi rend="i">Hecate.</hi> I therefore resist what seem premature attempts to get at the Vision by seeing every motif in a design in terms of Blakean motifs from other works. Specifically, the suggestion that I should have related this design to the Resurrection designs (nos. 1, 264) in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series I find unhelpful. Both show a male, Jesus; the first shows him ascending, the position of the legs making the upward, gravity-defying surge quite clear (see Janet Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art</hi>, 122-49). In contrast, the new Jerusalem, though the position of her arms is similar to that of the arms of Jesus in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1, has her left leg bent underneath her at the knee; the figure has no upward moving energy at all. The position of Gog in the design, moving and leaning towards the left, strongly implies that the female figure is descending and displacing him from the center. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 264, the second of Tolley’s suggested comparisons, shows how Blake handles a figure in process of “manifesting;” it represents Jesus’ head, arms, and upper torso emerging out of darkness towards the viewer. It bears no similarity at all to the drawing I discuss. Comparison with the account of the descent of Jesus in the Clouds of Ololon would seem equally unhelpful.</p>
          <p>I thank Tolley for his commentary, but for the time being I stand by both my method and my reading of this particular work. I look forward with interest to whatever interpretation Tolley may in the future offer of this “obscure drawing”—though it is a moot point whether that adjective remains appropriate.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake, Context and Ideology</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Stewart <name>Crehan</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Stuart Peterfreund’s review of my <hi rend="i">Blake in Context, Blake</hi>, 19 (winter 1985-86), shows, once again, that while the liberal text can be encompassed and “deconstructed” by the Marxist text, the Marxist text can only be ignored or misread by the liberal text. Peterfreund begins by stating that writers such as Bronowski, Schorer, “and above all, Erdman,” have already dealt with the social and historical context of Blake’s poetry and art, “but not, apparently, to Crehan’s satisfaction.” Although I do not say so in the book, I did not find Bronowski’s pioneering study satisfactory, though it was one of my starting points. Erdman’s work was an inspiration, as will be evident from the references, and the fact that I followed Erdman in foregrounding the phrase “Republican Art,” used as the title for chapter 8. The tone of Peterfreund’s comment implies, however, that Bronowski, Schorer and Erdman have closed the case on the context issue, a fear I myself began to harbor until I realized that some areas (especially that of ideology) still needed to be explored, and that new approaches were possible. But Peterfreund oversteps the bounds of academic propriety when he attributes to me the view that “the discussion of Blake’s artistic form and practice has been dominated by ‘formalists’ such as Erdman and Anne K. Mellor (see pp. 240-45), who hold power in the academy and insist that the ideology in Blake’s art be de-emphasized or ignored outright.” In the pages cited, Anne K. Mellor is not even mentioned, and nowhere do I attach the label “formalist” to Erdman, or to Mellor. Indeed, my criticism of Mellor’s approach (pp. 260-62) is that it is not formalist enough: “Such a loose, generalising approach, which interprets ‘the bounding line <hi rend="i">or enclosed form</hi> as the work of an oppressive reason,’ fails to appreciate the fact that meaning, execution and design in Blake are subtly and <hi rend="i">necessarily</hi> interwoven” (p. 261). As for David Erdman, in a personal letter to me dated 21 January 1985, he graciously said of my book that it would help others writing on Blake “to get a better sense of Blake’s context,” and that “All of us who study and teach Blake will benefit—and our students especially—from your book. Thank you for writing it!” Had I regarded Erdman as some kind of establishment enemy, as Peterfreund tries to insinuate, it is highly unlikely that he would have responded so favorably.</p>
          <pb id="p20-105" n="105"/>
          <p>A quotation from my discussion of metrics leads to a more serious misreading. Blake, I say, “pushed the freedom principle further than any other English Romantic poet, even to the extent of writing a free verse poem—the first of its kind in English” (p. 31). Peterfreund says: “The poem Crehan has in mind is <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which supposedly makes good Blake’s intention to move away from the decasyllabic line and thus avoid ‘any “Augustan” relapse into some easy, confident expectation or passive observation’ (p. 31).” First, the poem Crehan has in mind is <hi rend="i">not Jerusalem</hi>, as is clear from the context. The poem he has in mind is the short free-verse Argument at the beginning of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, which opens: “Rintrah roars,” and is introduced on page 33: “The next stage, then, is free verse itself. . . .” Nowhere do I refer to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as a “free verse poem.” But Peterfreund evidently wants to put in my mind that which will serve his own project. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (which I am supposed to champion as the apotheosis of formal freedom, against everything I say elsewhere) is used to advance Peterfreund’s own undialectical approach to literary history. Concerning “To the Public,” Peterfreund says: “What Crehan does not seem to realize is that most of what Blake has to say in the paragraph under discussion refers, in a highly self-conscious manner, to the statement entitled ‘The Verse’ which prefaces <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi>” Why I should be thought unaware of such an obvious quotation is quite beyond me. Let me simply refer Peterfreund to my note on the same passage on page 249 of my <hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected Poetry and Letters</hi> (Pergamon, 1976), to clear him of any misapprehensions. Blake’s self-conscious repudiation of blank verse involves both a repudiation of Milton and, at the same time, through the use of the phrase “modern bondage,” a recognition of Milton’s contribution towards such a metrical revolution. But the dialectics of transcendence are lost on Peterfreund, who sees both Blake’s and Milton’s metrical innovations simply as a return to the past. The key word here is “modern” (rather than “bondage”).</p>
          <p>“If Blake really intends to repudiate the poetic past, including the Miltonic source of his very words of repudiation, Blake does so more in the service of convention than in the service of freedom, authenticating his vision in relation to his poetic precursors just as Milton had authenticated his vision in relation to his precursors.” From details of metrics we have wandered into “vision.” But this vision, according to Peterfreund, depends for its authenticity, within its own terms, not on Poetic Genius, or Imagination, or Inspiration, but on the Letter—on written tradition, and memory of that written tradition. According to Blake, “As a man is, So he Sees. As the Eye is formed, such are its Powers. You certainly Mistake, when you say that the Visions of Fancy are not to be found in This World. To Me This World is all One continued Vision of Fancy or Imagination. . . .” Peterfreund would presumably add that none of this was authentic for Blake until it had been stamped by the authority of certain “poetic precursors.” While we are on this topic, do poets have given precursors, like people have ancestors? Or do poets select their own precursors? And if they select their own, in what sense are they a validating authority? Why, in particular, was Milton a precursor for Blake, rather than Pope or Shakespeare? What makes a poet anyhow? Peterfreund’s glibness suddenly betrays an appalling superficiality.</p>
          <p>Let us return to the text in question. What Milton says (and Peterfreund quotes) is that his rhyme-less poem should be “esteem’d an example set, the first in <hi rend="i">English</hi>, of ancient liberty recover’d to Heroic Poem from the troublesome and modern bondage of Riming.” The invocation of ancient rights and liberties was, of course, the accepted rhetoric of the seventeenth-century parliamentary cause. Milton is proclaiming his verse as “the first” of its kind in English. In other words, as something <hi rend="i">new.</hi> In quoting “the Miltonic source of his very words of repudiation,” Blake is not serving “convention,” or tying himself to the past, but self-consciously placing his own work as the next stage in the metrical revolution after Milton, rejecting <hi rend="i">blank verse itself</hi> as “derived from the modern bondage of Rhyming.” I had, I confess, thought all this too obvious to go into, not realizing that for some, nothing is obvious. (The comparisons I make between Miltonic and Blakean epic on pages 292-98 are a critical analysis of Blake’s attempt to transcend Milton.)</p>
          <p>Peterfreund’s way of thinking is further illustrated when, referring to Enlightenment rationalism, he says: “As a notebook poem like ‘Mock On Mock On Voltaire Rousseau’ makes clear, the cure for such rationalism is hebraic vision, not bourgeois or popular revolution.” Peterfreund does not explain his handy catchphrase. However, if it has anything to do with Mosaic law and the God of the Old Testament, we should bear in mind Blake’s annotations to Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology for the Bible</hi>, where he defends a notable Enlightenment rationalist and revolutionary, Thomas Paine. (I ought to point out that I do not share Peterfreund’s simplistic view of Blake’s relationship to Enlightenment rationalism.) Paine, according to Blake, “only denies that God conversed with Murderers &amp; Revengers such as the Jews were, &amp; of course he holds that the Jews conversed with their own State Religion which they call’d God &amp; so were liars as Christ says,” adding: “That the Jews assumed a right Exclusively to the benefits of God will be a lasting witness against them &amp; the same will it be against Christians.” Not much “hebraic vision” there. But then it all depends what is meant by the phrase. In a late letter to
<pb id="p20-106" n="106"/>
George Cumberland (12 April 1827) Blake speaks of “Newton’s Doctrine of the Fluxions of an Atom, A Thing that does not Exist.” However, the last stanza of the notebook poem cited by Peterfreund reads:
<q>
The Atoms of Democritus<lb/>
And Newton’s Particles of light<lb/><hi rend="i">Are</hi> sands upon the Red sea shore,<lb/>
Where Israel’s tents do shine so bright.<lb/>
(my emphasis)
</q>
Instead of simply denying the existence of atoms and particles, the poem imagines how, perceived from a synthesizing viewpoint, they are <hi rend="i">transformed.</hi> In the synthesizing vision, they “Are” Red Sea sands and shining tents, viewed prophetically, “every sand <hi rend="i">becomes</hi> a Gem” (stanza two). For Blake, the atomizing mentality justifies a social order in which “minute particulars” (human beings) are reduced and hardened into “grains of sand”—a profound critique, as I show on pages 78-84, of <hi rend="i">both</hi> analytical philosophy <hi rend="i">and</hi> the alienating isolation of the individual under the new capitalism. For the catchphrase “hebraic vision” to mean anything at all, it would have to include such a critique, one that relates, as I point out on page 41, to a major Blakean insight: the <hi rend="i">ideological</hi> nature of perception. For some reason, Peterfreund associates “the situation Blake describes as the ‘sands along the Red sea shore / Where Israel’s tents do shine so bright’ ” with the “final stage of the socialist revolution,” i.e., the millennium. Why? Even if we accept that the lines allude to the Israelites’ encampment <hi rend="i">after</hi> the crossing (Exodus in fact only mentions the Israelites encamping <hi rend="i">before</hi> the crossing), there is nothing necessarily millennial here. The Israelites still had a long way to go, and many difficulties to overcome, before they would see the Promised Land. On one level, then, the phrase “shine so bright” connotes faith in the certainty of final victory, rather than celebration of an achieved “final stage.”</p>
          <p>Peterfreund objects to the way I connect the lines: “You accumulate Particulars, &amp; murder by analyzing, that you / May take the aggregate; &amp; you call the aggregate Moral Law” with passages from <hi rend="i">Capital</hi>, informing us that what Blake “is actually talking about is the effect of pharasaical codification on one’s perception of divinity in the world.” Like Thomas A. Vogler, reviewing Morris Eaves’ <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art</hi> (<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 24 [summer 1985]), I am always suspicious of those who, with an air of magisterial authority, tell us what Blake is “<hi rend="i">actually</hi> talking about.” If the Blakean text were so transparent, Blakean criticism and interpretation would have dried up long ago. Blake’s “actual” words are, in fact, merely given another pseudo-Blakean gloss by Peterfreund. Every “explanation” of the Peterfreund type thus leads to another: every decoding becomes another encoding. In this way, the tedious business of interpreting, paraphrasing and explaining to the uninitiated what poets are “actually talking about” helps to keep the mill-wheels of the academy turning. While I do not claim that my own gloss mirrors more faithfully what Blake is “actually talking about”—I leave that to Peterfreund—I <hi rend="i">would</hi> claim that by placing the passage in which the quoted lines occur in the context of contemporary philosophical, scientific and economic discourse, I am at least able to suggest the historical and ideological resonances of the precise words used, namely: “accumulate,” “Particulars,” “analyzing,” “aggregate,” and “Moral Law.” Instead of rewriting Blake, which invariably means concocting a prosaic pseudo-Blake (“the effect of pharasaical codification on one’s perception of divinity in the world”), I tried, through the contextual approach, to show how the Blakean text <hi rend="i">refracts</hi> contemporary ideological discourses, grapples and battles with them, and seeks, through its various literary strategies, to absorb, criticize, and finally transcend them.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> is, as Peterfreund obsessively reiterates, a Marxist analysis. Its faults I would now be the first to acknowledge, especially the tendency towards reductionism and “economistic” Marxism. Nevertheless, its discussion of visual art (praised by other critics as the most original part of the book) best demonstrates its thesis, and it may be for this reason that Peterfreund has chosen to completely ignore these crucial chapters. Instead, he pillories me for being “completely oblivious (or willfully impervious)” to earlier statements by Morris Eaves, notably an article in <hi rend="i">Publishing History</hi>, 2 (1977), which addresses one of the central concerns of my book: the artist as independent producer. Here I plead guilty. I did not know the article. What Eaves, quoted by Peterfreund, says, is that “Blake’s artistic decision to become an independent publisher” was “a landmark in the history of publishing” because “he was far more aware than most others of why he was doing it.” Nothing to argue with there. My own view, carefully elaborated throughout the book, is that Blake’s independent stand was a radical yet logical extension of the Romantic project (the emergence of “a freely creating individual” whose source of creativity lies within his “own” personality and way of perceiving—what Caudwell calls the quintessential bourgeois illusion); a break with Tory patronage and Royalist norms; an attempt to “absorb the role of that spectre, the commercial middleman” (p. 16); a utopian reaction against the middle-class art market and the reduction of art to a commodity, a reaction that is also part of a new historical phenomenon—“the Radical, plebeian intellectual and self-educated artist or craftsman who is now emerging as a potent force for change” (pp. 143-44); a revival of the medieval illuminated manuscript tradition, combined with a conscious enhancement of the print, unparalleled in the history of art; a triumph of anti-illusionism, “visionary art” and the linearist
<pb id="p20-107" n="107"/>
tradition, impossible without an independent stand; a craftist reaction, anticipating William Morris; an aesthetic revolution (unity and interdependence of text and illustration, word and image); a series of technical innovations (etching technique, color printing, etc.) foreshadowing Walter Benjamin’s argument that any artistic challenge to the dominant production relations must also revolutionize “the techniques and forces of artistic production” (p. 242); an insistence on the unity of conception and execution, separated in the patronprotégé relationship, as with Hayley; an assertion of the central importance of creative labor, and so on. In sum: “Blake was always his own printer and bookseller—not out of some Crusoe-like, do-it-yourself crankiness, but for important artistic and ideological reasons” (p. 148).</p>
          <p>Ignoring this analysis, Peterfreund says: “Eaves succeeds in his book, while Crehan fails in his.” By way of reply, I would refer Peterfreund to Vogler’s review of <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art</hi>, which “undoes” Eaves’ text by revealing, and thus deconstructing, its recurrent metaphors of private property. Far from equipping us with a historically objective account of Romantic ideology, which <hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> explicitly attempts, these metaphors remain imprisoned in that ideology. As Jerome McGann says: “the scholarship and criticism of Romanticism and its works are dominated by a Romantic Ideology, by an uncritical absorption in Romanticism’s own self-representations.”<ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> To quote Vogler: “Eaves’ argument is thus informed by a paradigm of class structure which privileges the isolation and monadic autonomy of the bourgeois subject, and ‘behind’ his theory of art there would seem to be a theory of the subject in consumer or late monopoly capitalism.”<ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> One could go further: Eaves’ ‘monadic’ paradigm is even given determinate form by the subject of Eaves’ own discourse: William Blake. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Jerome McGann, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical Investigation</hi> (Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press, 1983), p. 1.</note><note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Thomas A. Vogler, review of Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art</hi>, in <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 24 (summer 1985), 294.</note></p>
          <p>We come, finally, to the most astonishing remark in Peterfreund’s review: that in chapter 10 I seek to show “that the aptness of [my] social and artistic analysis rests on a hitherto undiscussed tradition of working-class English radical protestantism,” and that if this tradition had not existed, “Blake, Marx (perhaps), and Crehan (certainly) would have found it necessary to invent” it! I am hardly the first to view Blake’s work in the light of this radical, millenarian tradition. Denis Saurat began to do so as long ago as 1929. The many references in my book to Edward Thompson’s classic study, <hi rend="i">The Making of the English Working Class</hi>, and to related work by A. L. Morton, Christopher Hill, Jack Lindsay, J. F. C. Harrison, and others, including David Erdman, are proof enough. One is left with the astonishing conclusion that Peterfreund himself thinks that such a tradition has been “hitherto undiscussed.” His remarks about having to invent it even indicate a certain careless indifference as to whether it existed or not. I would not insist that an intimate knowledge of this tradition is essential for readers of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, or that writers of pseudo-Blake need to brush up on their working-class history to be clear on what Blake “is actually talking about.” However, if I were ignorant of such a tradition, I would not feel particularly proud of the fact, especially if I claimed to know something about the Blakean millennium. Peterfreund evidently <hi rend="i">is</hi> proud, and for this he surely deserves an award of some kind. His attitude shows star quality.</p>
          <p>Peterfreund’s last little dart is that my book was written in Zambia (in fact, it was written in England) and needs buttressing with “more evidence of careful and reputable research.” Dutiful, graduate-style buttressing was a preliminary stage, admittedly; after four or five years I was able to get rid of the scaffolding, and to resist the temptation to fill the book with counterarguments and refutations. The task was not easy, but in Blake studies, one has to be selective. I decided, in other words, to let the argument speak for itself, to present my ideas in a distilled form, rather than playing the academic game, in the possibly naive belief that no amount of buttressing compensates for a poverty of ideas. The principle was this: that when a building is complete, the scaffolding is removed, and that when a wine is bottled, no sediment remains. If Peterfreund likes sediment in his wine, that is up to him. Likewise, should he wish, at some future date, to rifle my book for his own scholarly purposes without acknowledging his source (I particularly recommend the comparison between Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and Richard Brothers’ <hi rend="i">Description of Jerusalem</hi> on pages 348-49), then that is also up to him. What he should not do is pretend, with First World arrogance, that he has something spiritually in common with Blake because he can trot out a phrase such as “hebraic vision.” The school of Blake is a hard school, especially for reactionary academicians (whom Blake, we know, detested). For the likes of Peterfreund, who have made it their profession to twist revolutionary thought into its opposite, I doubt if it is possible to gain access to what Blake “was actually saying” at all, despite pretensions to the contrary.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0006">
        <pb id="p20-108" n="108"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Reply to Stewart Crehan</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Stuart <name>Peterfreund</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>When a book review of some 3000 words occasions an angry author’s response of approximately equal length—a response that accuses the reviewer of, among other things, “First World arrogance” and “twist[ing] revolutionary thought into its opposite,” and strongly implies that the reviewer should be numbered among the “reactionary academicians (whom Blake, we know, detested)”—it is tempting to spend another 3000 words to engage the author on each point raised and to defend or amend one’s original assessment of the book. In a sense, Stewart Crehan makes such a project unnecessary. The tone of his response, in which he once again does all he can to alienate those who would hope to engage him in productive dialogue regarding Blake’s historical, social, and intellectual contexts, suggests that his repeated imputations of misreading and misunderstanding may have a basis. But that basis is not a liberal ideology and a “liberal text” by which “the Marxist text can only be ignored or misread,” but “the Marxist text” itself, at least if his text be taken to be what he intends by the appellation “Marxist.”</p>
          <p>The result of undertaking a dialectical analysis that divides the world into opposing camps of “liberal” and “Marxist,” “reactionary” and “revolutionary,” and valorizing the latter at the expense of the former is that one tends to lose sight of the possibility that the very heuristic by which he identifies other ideologies may, itself, be an ideology. Just as it is not possible simultaneously to use language and to be “outside” of it, it is not possible to discuss ideologies and be outside of them, especially since language is predisposed because prestructured to create ideologies in the very act of discussing them.</p>
          <p>Even Marxist critics as astute as Fredric Jameson, who have done much to gain a secure and respected place for Marxist approaches to literary studies, have been held to account on precisely this point. In an important discussion of <hi rend="i">The Political Unconscious</hi> (1981), James H. Kavanaugh, writing in “The Jameson-Effect” (<hi rend="i">New Orleans Review</hi>, 11 [spring 1984]), identifies Jameson’s notion of “untranscendable horizons” as his means of deemphasizing the ideological status of his own discourse and suggests that a proper Marxist critical praxis engages the problem of ideology by the sort of critical intertextuality adumbrated by the visionary conversation that occurs at the end of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> In Kavanaugh’s closing words, “Jameson’s properly ideological discourse must be completed by ‘other’ Marxist theory that recognizes the very limited validity of looking for ‘untranscendable horizons’ on the battlefield of theory.”</p>
          <p>Yet Crehan seems unaware of the problem. His Marxism, which is calculated to suppress conversation rather than to encourage it, is a monolithic science the sole purpose of which is to identify and establish “the primacy of social laws over artistic ones,” and in doing so to correct the “too many books on Blake that analyse the art, poetry, and ideas (especially the ideas) and forget the social process” (p. 13). In Crehan’s universe of intellect and labor, analysis of the sort he decries is as parasitic as capital itself, living off the labor of its artist-subject while fetishizing the commoditized result of that labor. “In epitomising the <hi rend="i">meaning</hi> of a work, however, bourgeois criticism frequently resorts to subjective impressions and perennial, supra-historical thoughts and feelings” (p. 4).</p>
          <p>Even if one concedes the justice of this analysis, it does not follow that epitomizing the social and historical <hi rend="i">context</hi> of a work offers an antidote to the sort of “subjective impressions” of which Crehan is leery. Indeed, in characterizing his study as “one contribution to <hi rend="i">the</hi> Marxist approach to literature and art” and specifying as his salient concern “<hi rend="i">the</hi> social and historical context within which an artist such as Blake emerges” (pp. 12, 13; emphasis added), Crehan evokes a consensus which does not in fact exist. There is no unitary “Marxist approach,” any more than there is a unitary “social and historical context.” Yet Crehan takes as axiomatic the existence of both, and he does so for the purpose of establishing that interim bureaucracy of the critical proletariat that will lead to the ascendancy of Marxist literary studies rather than creating an examplary study of the kind. Under the terms of this interim bureaucracy, analysis is a form of private property that is absolutely forbidden. Crehan himself “doubt[s] if it is possible to gain access to what Blake ‘was actually saying’ at all, despite pretensions to the contrary.”</p>
          <p>Crehan may well be right. It is true, as he argues, that “[T]he idea that a unique style can be developed rests on the bourgeois-Romantic belief in the individual as creative centre of his own work” (p. 183). And it is true that this belief is central to the Romantic ideology that Jerome J. McGann has set about interrogating so well. But arguing that “even the most individualistic artist is produced by the manifold social and historical contradictions of which he is a part” (p. 184) rests on an equally dubious belief underwritten by an equally subtle and powerful ideology. Self-determination and other-determination are limits or boundaries, not modes. Thus Crehan’s discussion of Blake’s “visual ideology” is at once overdetermined and underdetermined. His context provided him with certain technological and socioeconomic options for producing art, but it produced
<pb id="p20-109" n="109"/>
neither Blake nor his art wholesale. If the context had done so, there would be little to choose between the engravings of William Sharp, whom Crehan discusses, and those of Blake. And there is something to choose between them.</p>
          <p>In the final analysis, I neither credit the position of Anne K. Mellor that Crehan attacks, namely, “that Blake ‘formed a distinctly personal style,’ ” nor do I credit his position that it was a style entirely determined by an external context. In arguing over whether “things happen” in the life-world because of innate, personal or external, social causes, Crehan falls prey to what is perhaps humanity’s oldest and least productive hermeneutical conundrum. “Things happen” in the life-world as the result of both sorts of cause. Blake’s visual art is in part of his time, but it is also heavily influenced by a religious commitment closely tied to his readings in gnosticism, especially those pertaining to the supplantation of the true story of the first creation by a false one. This supplantation is picked up by Warburton in <hi rend="i">The Divine Legation of Moses Demonstrated</hi> (1738-41), in his discussion of the manner in which the place of the original, “hieroglyphic” account of the creation (Genesis 2:4b-2:25) was usurped by that of a later Mosaic hymn (Genesis 1:1-2:4a). Thus while Blake may have used certain collectively recognizable artistic conventions and techniques of his time, he did so to the end of recovering the authentic hebraic vision that he identified with a usurped and betrayed gnosticism, epitomized by a “hieroglyphic” style successively debased by the civilizations of Egypt, Greece, and Rome. Speaking of context, this is a position that Blake probably assumed no later than the period in which he, as an apprentice to Basire, executed several of the engravings for Jacob Bryant’s <hi rend="i">A New System of Ancient Mythology</hi> (1774-76), which argues that mythologies such as the Egyptian and the Greek are corrupted accounts of originals found in the Old Testament.</p>
          <p>There simply is no place in Crehan’s analysis of contexts for innate, personal causes such as religious commitment. He has occasion, for example, to refer to “Blake’s ideological revolt” being “not merely a response to contemporary realities; it can also be seen as the continuation of hitherto submerged traditions” such as those of “the antinomians, Ranters, and other radicals of the seventeenth century” (pp. 7-8). But by assuming that these traditions offered Blake the option of discarding one preexistent ideology and taking up another, Crehan completely fails to understand that Blake may have actually harbored strong, <hi rend="i">personal</hi> religious beliefs, and that these beliefs may have been the result not of passive acceptance, but of the sort of vigorous conversation that begins in the Memorable Fancies of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and ends in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> While I myself harbor no strong religious commitment (raised in Reformed Judaism, I remain a secular Jew), I would think twice before dismissing as ideological the religious agenda that informs both Blake’s verbal art and his visual.</p>
          <p>It strikes me that this rejoinder has grown oblique, and I apologize for that. Moreover, I apologize to Stewart Crehan for having, in a few instances, misread the intent or the substance of his comments. Whether it is the fault of the author or the reviewer, it was not always clear to me that Crehan’s intent was “equipping us with a historically objective account of Romantic ideology,” especially since the ideology was alternately discovered underwriting the Romantics themselves and their later critics, nor was the ideology underwriting the critics the same as the one underwriting the Romantics, as it is for McGann. It is finally difficult to know precisely what Crehan defines as ideology, except that anything so defined lies on the other side of the dialectical divide from that on which Crehan situates himself. This is not to say that good ideological analysis is impossible. McGann’s is exemplary on a theoretical plane, while that of Maureen McNeil on the Lunar Society of Birmingham is exemplary on the practical.</p>
          <p>One reason for the increasing obliqueness of this rejoinder and the occasional obtuseness of the review is that <hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> does not invite engagement. It is at once grandiose in its debunking of a good part of Blake studies and evasive in failing to provide well-buttressed alternatives, at once sweeping in its sociohistorical generalizations and question-begging in its attempt to situate Blake meaningfully in the contexts those generalizations evoke. In its taunting of bourgeois critics and spineless intellectuals for the benefit of an assumed intellectual proletariat, the book alienates precisely those with whom Crehan must close. But he wishes to keep his distance, apparently, and his tactic of dialectical analysis, replete with the bandying about of ideologies and ideological labels of all sorts is finally nothing other than a form of what in psychology is known as projection and denial. If there is a classic case of the syndrome in Blake, it is not Los, who becomes what he beholds, but Urizen, who compels others to worship a horizoned view of reality that he at once creates and denies responsibility for creating. If Crehan’s is exemplary of “the Marxist approach to literature and art,” there is little to choose between its “untranscendable horizons” and the bounding ones of the Urizenic landscape.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <pb id="p20-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">DE-FACED BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Readers may have noticed a certain patchiness in the type of our fall issue, the unfortunate but unavoidable result of having some articles set in Albuquerque and some in Rochester. The patchiness will continue until all articles set in New Mexico have been published, perhaps as late as the summer and fall issues next year.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <pb id="p20-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">ERRATA’S ERRATA</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Our readers might like to note these corrections to “Improving the Text of <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Prose of William Blake</hi>” (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, fall 1986):
<q><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> p. 50:<lb/>
p. xvii canterbury <hi rend="i">should read</hi> Canterbury<lb/>
*p. 148 Line 60: the error is “rsua” not “rsau”<lb/>
p. 482 Line 5 <hi rend="i">should read</hi> Line 6<lb/>
p. 487 <hi rend="i">After</hi> Line 32 <hi rend="i">insert</hi> t <hi rend="i">in the margin</hi><lb/>
p. 489 <hi rend="i">should read</hi> [“The Crystal Cabinet”] Line 27 [etc.]<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> p. 51, after entry for p. 845 add:<lb/>
p. 850 Line 2 (from bottom): insert 32 Envy is free <hi rend="i">1st rdg del.</hi><lb/>
p. 986 Line 5 (from bottom): 466 <hi rend="i">should read</hi> 446<lb/>
p. 990 Line 3: 488 <hi rend="i">should read</hi> 448
</q></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <pb id="p20-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">CALL FOR PLAYS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Actors Theatre of Louisville is now conducting a nationwide search for unpublished translations and adaptations of plays for next season’s (1987-88) Classics in Context Festival—“The Romantics,” which will celebrate the ideals and influence of Romanticism on the stage. Though plays by any dramatist whose work is associated with Romanticism will be considered, plays by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, Friedrich Schiller, Ludwig Tieck, Alexander Pushkin, and Michael Lermontov are of particular interest. New plays (either original or adaptations of novels) that deal with the people, ideas, and events connected with Romanticism will also be considered. Please submit plays by 1 November 1987 to Actors Theatre of Louisville, Literary Department, 316 West Main Street, Louisville, KY 40202.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <pb id="p20-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">ENERGY AND THE IMAGINATION</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Morton D. Paley would like to purchase a clean, unmarked copy of his <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination.</hi> If you have a copy and would like to sell it, please write to him at the Department of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
